in spite of the steady accumulation of detailed knowledge
how the human brain works is still profoundly mysterious
[music] the ultimate goal of neuroscience is to learn how the brain gives rise to human intelligence
and what it means to be intelligent
understanding how the brain works is considered one of humanity's greatest challenges
i got into this field because i just was curious as to who i am
you know how you know
how do i think what's going on in my head when i'm what i'm thinking
what does it mean to know something
you know
i can ask what it means for me to know something independent of how i learned it from you
or from someone else or from society
what does it mean for me to know that i have a model of you in my head
what does it mean to know
i know what this microphone does and how it works physically
even when i can't see it right now
how do i know that
what does it mean
how do the neurons do that at the fundamental level of neurons and synapses
and so on
those are really fascinating questions
the neuroscientist francis crick observed that scientists have been collecting data on the brain for decades
they knew a lot about the workings of the brain
but they hadn't converged on any meaningful theory of how the brain worked
how intelligence emerges from low level cells in your head is still a profound mystery
to be intelligent
the brain has to learn a great many things about the world
to understand how the brain creates intelligence
we need to figure out how the brain learns a model of the world and everything in it
jeff hawkins thinks that the reality we perceive is a kind of simulation
a hallucination
a confabulation
he thinks
that our brains are a model of reality based on thousands of information streams originating in the senses in our body
critically
hawkins doesn't think that there's only one model
but rather thousands
jeff has just released his new book
a thousand brains
a theory of intelligence
it's an inspiring and well written book
and i really hope after watching this show
you'll be inspired to read it too
now
jeff is a sub symbolist
he thinks that our knowledge is sliced and distributed over the substrate of synapses in our brain
but similarly that our simulated models of the world are also distributed over hundreds and thousands of cortical columns
this means that when we recognize a dog
there's a society of cortical columns
all independently predicting that the dog is there and mutually calibrating after a consensus is reached
now jeff hawkins is a materialist
he thinks that despite appearances to the contrary
mental states are just physical states and that the latter emerges from the former
there's no inception
no ghost in the machine
no cartesian theater
if i had to summarize into one
big idea is that we think of the the brain
the neocortex is learning this model of the world
but what we learned is actually there's tens of thousands of independent modeling systems going on
and so each
what we call a column in the cortex is about 150
000 of them is a complete modeling system
so it's a collective intelligence in your head in some sense
so the thousand brains theory says
well
where do i have knowledge about you know this coffee cup
where is the model of this cell phone
it's not in one place
it's in thousands of separate models that are complementary and they communicate with each other through voting
hawkins says that the neocortex is the outermost and most recently evolved layer of the mammalian brain
a bit like a wrinkly napkin
which wraps around the old brain
it occupies about 70 percent of the volume of your brain
and it's responsible for all aspects of your intelligence
that is to say your sense of vision
touch
hearing
language
in all its forms and even abstract thinking
such as mathematics and philosophy
the neocortex is surprisingly different to other parts of the brain
it has no visually obvious divisions
the anatomical organization is strikingly similar
nevertheless
different parts of the neocortex still perform different functions like vision or hearing
for example
the complex circuitry of the neocortex looks remarkably alike in visual regions and language regions and even touch regions
it looks similar across species such as rats
cats and humans
the variations between regions are relatively small compared to their similarities
now
hawkins argues that the complexity of the brain is in the content of its connections and its wiring
which is an emergent property of a simple learning algorithm
i mean
look at the openai microscope
their tool for visualizing trained convolutional neural networks
as an example
the learning algorithm is simple
but all of this beautiful complexity emerges as a result of training
even after this type of visualization
it's not really understandable by us humans
it's possible that any successful knowledge
representational substrate for some domains of data may never be understandable by humans
now the neocortex is arguably one of the main organs of intelligence
it gives us sensory perception
motor control and abstract thought
the key attributes it has are its ability to learn continuously learn rapidly
its power efficiency and its flexibility
which is to say its ability to learn diverse and novel tasks
now hawkins argues that the neocortex learns a model of the world
that each cortical column is a complete sensory motor modeling system
he thinks that cortical columns use reference frames to store knowledge and generate behavior
our brains learn about the outside world by processing our sensory inputs and movements
the neocortex anticipates the sensory results of movement when we touch objects or observe the world around us
our brain receives a sensory motor sequence of information
when moving our fingers over familiar objects
we quickly notice discrepancies suggesting we make tactile predictions that are specific to particular objects
hawkins believes that the prediction of sensory stimuli after movements is the fundamental primitive of cognition
the brain does not just memorize the sensory information as this would become quickly intractable
instead
hawkins claims that evolution repurposed the ancient systems that evolved to model spatial relationships
such as grid and place cells
it generalized those systems to model abstract concepts in abstract spaces
in this system
thinking and reasoning becomes a kind of traversal through a complex topology of relationships in the brain
analogous to the traversal of a physical space
the whole cortical sheet is made of collections of primitive columnar units called mini columns
each cortical area is a collection of millions of cortical mini columns
these mini columns are organized in about six layers with specific types of neurons
and connection patterns in each layer
neighboring mini columns have the same receptive field
so they have the same inputs from other cortical areas
and these mini columns form complete fundamental and primitive units known as macro columns
or as hawkins calls them cortical
columns
now pyramidal neurons are the typical excitatory neurons in the neocortex
their name comes from the triangular shape of their cell body
the dendrites of each pyramidal neuron connect to tens of thousands of excitatory synapses equally split from local
and remote sources
the neurons can look significantly different in their connection arrangements
depending on which neocortex layer
they're situated in the thalamus is the main input and output subcortical structure to the neocortex
it could be viewed as the seventh layer of the neocortex
it primarily sends sensory or pre-processed information into layer four of the neocortex
moreover
columns in the neocortex learn to model whatever systems are wired to them
columns wired to the ear
for example
learn to process sound
columns
wired to the retina
rods and cones
learn to process images
the neocortex can retain remarkable plasticity even later into life
perhaps the most striking examples are those of post post-injury plasticity where the brains overcome injury
by rewiring remaining neurons to regain some or even full functionality
the cortical regions are densely interconnected with many feedback and feed-forward skip connections across the hierarchy
and all functional areas in the neocortex are bi-directionally connected with other brain structures
but their main inputs and outputs come from other cortical areas via long-distance connections
all cortical regions are densely connected
but there's some apparent asymmetry and even hierarchy
detectable in the overall structure
sensory areas tend to be lower in the hierarchy than associative or motor areas
for example
and bottom-up information flows are known as feed-forward and top-down connections are known as feedback connections
what should be pretty clear from looking at this structure is that there's no blank slate
there's a very clear cognitive architecture
and much of this high-level structure is there from birth
there are many skip connections
a high level of recurrence
with many feedback loops and the process is highly distributed at this point
i want to draw your attention to a paper published last year by psychologist joseph cesario
it was titled your brain is not a tiny onion with a reptile inside
joseph pointed out several misunderstandings of nervous system evolution
which he says stems from the work of paul mclean
who in the 1940s began to study the brain region
which he called the limbic
system
mclean later proposed that humans possess a so-called triune brain consisting of three large divisions that evolved sequentially
the oldest
the reptilian brain controls basic functions such as movement and breathing
next
the limbic system
which controls emotional responses
and finally
the cerebral cortex
which pretty much means the neocortex
but you know
he thought that that controlled language and reasoning
joseph said that mclean's ideas were already understood to be incorrect by the time he published his 1990 book
i mean
since the 1970s
many in developmental neuroscience thought that the uh
the ideas from mclean were a myth
you know due to its longevity
the triune brain idea has been called by uh
neuroscientist
lisa feldman barrett
as one of the most successful and widespread errors in all of science
joseph pointed out
that the problem with this view is a simple conception of evolution being arranged sequentially from the simplest to the most complex organisms
this view implies that anatomical evolution proceeds in the same fashion as geological strata
with new layers adding on top of existing ones
instead
most evolutionary change consists of transforming existing parts
joseph says that the neocortex is not an evolutionary novelty unique to humans or primates or mammals
all vertebrates possess structures evolutionarily related to our cortex joseph concluded
that these ideas are consistent with traditional views of human nature as rationality
battling emotion
the tripartite
platonic
soul
freudian psychodynamics and religious approaches to humanity
it's also a simple idea that can be distilled and communicated to a lay audience
look
i'm not suggesting for a second that hawkins subscribes to the idea of a tree in brain
but i think it's possible to get this impression
reading his book
which is why i wanted to bring this up
it turns out it's very tricky to get neurons to do this
to build a map of an environment
it's just and so we now know there's this
these famous studies that's still very active about place cells
and grid cells
and other types of cells in the older parts of the brain
and how they build these maps of the world
it's really clever
it's obviously been under a lot of evolutionary pressure over a long period of time
they get good at this
so animals not know where they are
what we think has happened
uh
and there's a lot of evidence to justice
is that that mechanism we learned to map like a space is was repackaged
the same type of neurons was repackaged into a more compact form
and that became the cortical column
in 1972
john o'keefe discovered the first component of an internal gps system in the brain
he discovered place cells in the hippocampus which activate
when a rat is situated in specific locations in a room
more than three decades later
in 2005
mae britt and edward moser
discovered another key component of the brain's positioning system
grid
cells
which represented a coordinate system
which allowed for precise positioning and pathfinding
these discoveries solved the problem that has occupied philosophers and scientists for centuries
how the brain creates a map of the complex world around us
and how we navigate our way through it
what's intriguing about the brain solution is that it seems to create multiple hexagonal grids with slightly different orientations
and scales
because these grids are orientated and scaled differently
each point in space activates a unique combination of grid cells
in other words
the brain encodes locations using bits in a sparse distributed representation
jeff thinks that sparse representations are crucial to the success of the human brain
and should guide our construction of artificial intelligence
what's intriguing about the brain solution is that it seems to create multiple hexagonal grids with slightly different orientations
and scales
because these grids are orientated and scaled differently
each point in space becomes a unique combination of grid cells
in other words the brain encodes these cells using a sparse distributed representation
jeff thinks that such sparse representations are crucial to the success of the human brain
and should guide our construction of artificial intelligence
if you're going to build a model of a house
in a computer
they have a reference name
and you can then reference them like cartesian coordinates
like x y and z axes
so i could say
oh
i'm going to design a house
i can say
well
the
the front door is at this location
xyz
and the roof is at this location
and so on
that's a type of reference frame
so it turns out for you to make a prediction
and i walk you through the thought experiment in the book
where i was predicting what my finger was going to feel
when i touched the coffee cup
it was a ceramic coffee cup
but this one will do
and what i realized is
that to make a prediction with my finger's going to feel like it's going to feel different than this
which would feel different if i touch the hole or the thing on the bottom
make that prediction
the cortex needs to know where the finger is
the tip of the finger relative to the coffee cup and exactly relative to the coffee cup
and to do that
i have to have a reference frame for the coffee
jeff says that after many years of thinking about the function of the neocortex
he deduced that it must store everything that we know
all of our knowledge
right
using something called a reference frame
but what exactly does jeff mean by a reference frame
well
consider a paper map as an analogy
a map is a type of model
right
so a map of a town is a model of a town and the grid lines
such as the
the latitude and longitude lines are a type of reference frame
a maps
gridlines is its reference frame
so they provide a structure of the map
a reference frame tells you where things are located relative to everything else
and it can tell you how to achieve goals such as how to go from one location to another location
now
jeff realized that the brain's model of the world is built using map-like reference frames
not one reference frame but hundreds of thousands of them
jeff thinks that most of the cells in your neocortex are dedicated to creating
and manipulating reference frames which the brain uses to plan and think
our brain's knowledge representation is a simulation of reality
and this applies in concept space as well as physical space
as was the case with grid and place cells in other parts of your brain
so jeff now thinks that the way we think is analogous to how we navigate spaces
he says
that the similarity of circuitry observed in all cortical regions is strong evidence
that even high-level cognitive tasks are learned
and represented in a location-based framework
to be an expert in any domain requires having a good reference frame
a good map
two people observing the same physical object will likely end up with similar maps
for example
it's hard to imagine how the brains of two people observing the same chair would arrange its features differently
jeff said in his book that being an expert is mostly about finding the reference frame to arrange facts
and observations
i mean albert einstein
for example
started with the same facts as his contemporaries
however he found a better way to arrange them
a better reference frame that permitted him to see analogies and make predictions that were surprising
what's most fascinating about einstein's discoveries relating to special relativity is
that the reference frame he used to make them were everyday objects
right
he thought about trains and people and flashlights
he started with the empirical observations of scientists such as the absolute speed of light
and then used everyday reference frames to deduce the equations of special relativity
because of this
almost anyone can follow his logic and understand how he made the discoveries
in contrast
einstein's general theory of relativity required reference frames based on mathematical concepts called field equations
which are not easily related to everyday objects einstein found this much harder to understand
as does pretty much everyone else
jeff hawkins is one of the ultimate gentlemen scientists of our age
his first major project was palm computing
which is a company that he founded
he invented the palm pilot in the mid-1990s and despite his incredible success in the nascent mobile computing industry
his heart was never in it
his passion was always for theoretical neuroscience
he knew the biggest prize was understanding human intelligence
and then using that knowledge to create human level machine intelligence
so in 2005 he co-founded numenta in redwood city in california
nomenta
is a machine intelligence company that has developed a cohesive
theory
core software technology
and applications based on the principles of the neocortex
its dual mission is to understand how the brain works
and to apply those principles of real intelligence to create intelligent machines
neuroscientists were publishing thousands of papers a year
covering every single detail of the brain
but there was a lack of systemic theories that tied all of those details together
nimenta decided to first focus on understanding a single cortical
column
right
they knew that cortical columns were doing something physically complex and therefore must be doing something complex
now
last week
we had ben gertzel on the show
and he is convinced that artificial general intelligence must be a hybrid of many underlying algorithms
not a single learning algorithm
jeff hawkins doesn't agree
hawkins thinks that all the magic of intelligence could emerge from a single cortical learning algorithm
andrew ng said that as a young professor and after he read hawkins first book on intelligence
he also became convinced that a simple scaled-up learning algorithm could reach artificial general intelligence
now
what does seem to really distinguish hawkins ideas is that intelligence must emerge from diverse and strongly multi-modal inputs
perhaps that intelligence is somehow emerging from the nature of physical embodiment
now
jeff argues that we're the first species on earth to know the age and the size of the universe
he thinks that humans are the first species to be known by their knowledge and not by their genes
that's the beauty of this discovery that this guy
vernon
mount castle made many many years ago
which is that there's
there's a single cortical algorithm underlying everything we're doing
the mindful brain is a small book
it's about 100 pages long
and published in 1978 and it contains two essays about the brain from two prominent scientists
one was written by vernon
mel castle
a neuroscientist at john hopkins university
now
jeff hawkins
cites mount castle as being one of his biggest inspirations
jeff says that it remains one of the most iconic and important essays ever written about the brain
mount castle proposed a new way of thinking about the brain
that is elegant
a hallmark of great theories
but it's also kind of surprising and it continues to polarize the neuroscience community
now mount castle noted that the brain grew really large
by adding new brain parts on top of old brain parts
the older parts control more primitive behaviors
while the newer parts create more sophisticated ones
however mount castle goes on to say that while much of the brain got bigger
by adding new parts on top of old parts
that's not how the neocortex grew to occupy 70 percent of our brain
the neocortex got big by making copies of the same basic thing
the same circuit
he says that every single part of the neocortex is the same basic circuit
different parts of the neocortex are different not in their intrinsic function but rather in what they are connected
to
the implications of this are huge
if we understand how one part of the neocortex works
we understand how it all works and how all aspects of intelligence can emerge from a single cortical
algorithm
mount castle pointed out that the neocortex grew really quickly given the short evolutionary time
now darwin's big idea is that the diversity of life emerged from a single algorithm
similarly mount castle proposed that the diversity of intelligence also emerged from a single basic algorithm
the difference is that darwin knew what the algorithm was
random variation and natural selection
darwin didn't know where the algorithm was in the body
the discovery of dna came
much later
mount castle knew where the algorithm resided
but not what it did
mount castle said that there's about 150 000 cortical columns in the neocortex
a bit like 150 000 little pieces of spaghetti stacked next to each other
scientists knew that these columns existed because they all respond to different sensory inputs
be it from a patch of skin or a signal from the retina
but the columns are wired to different sensory inputs from the body
there's a wonderful anecdote in jeff's book about the last time he met mount castle
jeff gave a speech at john hopkins university
and at the end of the day he met with mount castle and the dean of the department
the time had come for him to leave
and you know jeff had a flight to catch
so they said their goodbyes and the car was waiting for jeff
outside
as jeff walked through the office door
mount castle intercepted him
put his hand on jeff's shoulder and said in here is some advice for you
kind of tone of voice
you should stop talking about hierarchy
it doesn't really exist
jeff was stunned
mount castle was one of the foremost experts on the neocortex
and he was telling jeff that one of its largest and most well-documented features didn't exist
jeff was surprised
right
it was as if francis crick had said to him
oh
that dna molecule doesn't really encode your genes
so jeff didn't know how to respond
he just said nothing
as jeff sat in the car on his way to the airport
he tried to make sense of those parting words
today
jeff's understanding of hierarchy in the neocortex has changed dramatically
it's much less hierarchical than he previously thought
did vernon mount castle know this back then
did he have a theoretical basis for saying that hierarchy didn't really exist
was he thinking about the experimental results that jeff didn't know about
he died in 2015
and jeff will never be able to ask him after his death
jeff took it upon himself to re-read many of his books and papers
his thinking and writing always
very insightful
his 1998 perceptual neuroscience
the cerebral cortex is a physically beautiful book and remains one of jeff's favorites about the brain
when jeff thinks back on that day
he really laments
and he kind of wished
that he would have chanced missing his flight for that last opportunity to talk of mount castle further
even now he wishes he could talk to mount castle about his current ideas
he'd like to believe that mount castle would have enjoyed the thousand brands theory of intelligence
so if you have many brains
who are you
then
so it's interesting
we have a singular perception
right
you know
we think
oh
i'm just here
i'm looking at you
but it's
it's composed of all these things
there's sounds and there's and there's
uh
there's vision and there's touch and all kinds of inputs
yeah
we have the singular perception and what the thousand brain theory says
we have these models that are visual models
we have a lot models of auditory models
models
matters of tactile models
and so on
but they vote
and so
um
they send in the cortex
you can think about these columns as that
like little grains of rice
150 000 stacked next to each other
and
um
each one is its own little modeling system
but they have these long-range connections that go between them
and we call those voting connections or voting neurons
um
and so the different columns try to reach the consensus
like what am i looking at
okay
you know
each one has some ambiguity
but they come to a consensus
oh
there's a water bottle
i'm looking at um
we are only consciously able to perceive the voting today
the most common way of thinking about the neocortex is a bit like a flow chart
right
information from the senses is just processed sequentially step
by step as it passes from one region to the next
in this notion
every step of neural processing refines a representation from the low level to the high level
incrementally
scientists refer to this as a hierarchy of feature detectors
but as jeff points
out
even basic study of how the brain works will tell you that cognition is a interactive process
right
depending on movement
for example
to learn what a new object looks like
we hold it in our hand
and we rotate it this way and that way and we see what it looks like from different angles
and once learned
we're able to recognize entire objects from the touch of a single finger
or a fleeting glimpse of a small part of the object
jeff's proposal of reference frames in cortical columns
suggests a different way of thinking about how the neocortex works
thinking of cortical columns as cognitive primitives
even in low-level sensory regions that are capable of learning and recognizing complete objects
jeff's theory explains how a mouse with a mostly one-level visual system can see
and recognize objects in the world
but where is the knowledge stored in the brain
jeff thinks that our knowledge of objects are distributed over many cortical
columns
so when i pick up a pen there isn't a single model of this pen but rather thousands
i have visual models
i have sensory models
i have auditory models and everything created in between
right from a rich topology of reference frames
binding them all together and every cortical column models
hundreds if not thousands of complete objects at multiple scales
the long-range connections between the columns and the regions of the neocortex communicate at the level of classified objects
not features
jeff thinks that his theory solves the age-old binding problem in artificial intelligence
which is the challenge of mapping sensory input to discrete mental categories
and how these discrete categories can be combined into a single lived experience
jeff thinks
that the binding problem is a side effect of a flawed assumption
that the connection topology of the brain is convergent rather than divergent
the solution to the binding problem is that your cortical columns vote
your perception is the consensus
which is reached from the columns
voting on what they recognize
the voting works across sensory modalities
when you grasp an object in your hand
jeff believes that the tactile columns representing your fingers share another piece of information
their relative position to each other
which makes it even easier to figure out what they're touching
the brain wants to reach a consensus
now in jeff's book he shows an example of an image which can appear as either a vars
or two faces
in examples like this
the columns can't decide which is the correct object
because it's ambiguous
as if it's as if they have two maps for two different towns
but the maps at least in some areas are identical
vars
town and faces town
they're just too similar
so the voting layer wants to reach a consensus
but it doesn't permit two objects to be the same simultaneously
so you have to pick one possibility
you can perceive faces or of ours
but not both at the same time
and the process of cognition allows us to move between the alternatives to reason interactively over time
in his book
jeff makes the powerful argument that thinking is simply traversing a topology of reference
and displacement frames in your brain
jeff thinks that this reasoning is movement evolved to extend the physical world of spaces
and time to our worlds of abstract thought
the succession of thoughts that we experience
when thinking is analogous to the succession of sensations we experience
when moving our finger over an object or walking around a town
perhaps the reason why albert einstein was so smart was
because of the unique topology of reference frames in his brain his information architecture
if you will
must have been arranged as a function of his life experiences as well as his biology
traversing his brain
topology allowed him to make powerful abstract inferences that other people couldn't make for him
it must have felt a bit like the borg traversing their wormhole network in the delta quadrant
for those of you who are fans of star trek voyager
jeff says that learning conceptual knowledge can be difficult if i give you 10 historical events related to democracy
how should you arrange them in your brain
one teacher might show you the events arranged on a timeline
you know
in a one-dimensional reference frame
it's useful for assigning the temporal order of the events and which events might be causally related
by temporal proximity
but another teacher might arrange the same historical events geographically on a map of the world
timelines and geography are both valid ways of organizing historical events
yet they lead to different ways of thinking about history
they might lead to different conclusions and different predictions
the best structure for learning about democracy
might even require an entirely different map
a map with multiple abstract dimensions that correspond to fairness or rights
for example
so what does the thousand brains theory tell us about machine intelligence
intelligent machines need to learn a model of the world
inference
prediction
planning and motor behavior are all based on this model
the model is distributed among many
nearly identical units that vote to reach consensus
this gives us robust prediction
it scales well and it works with any kind of sensor array and modality
and voting solves the binding problem in each unit
knowledge is stored in a reference frame and is learned via sensory motor interaction
this means that we can learn unsupervised fast and the motor behavior is integrated
this is matthew taylor from numenta
this place looks really familiar
but i can't remember how i got here
it's almost like someone severed all of the distal connections between the pyramidal neurons and my neocortex
many years ago
nomenta used to refer to their overarching theory as htm theory
but now they use the terminology thousand brains
the htm
or hierarchical temporal memory algorithm was a particular implementation of the early ideas of the thousand brains theory
the original guiding principles of htm were that it was a sequence memory algorithm
numenta
thinks that every neuron in your brain is learning a pattern of sequences
it's needed to support continual learning
and critically
it wasn't an artificial neural network
which they argued were not biologically inspired
or at least not in their popular configuration
at the time
the core data structure of the algorithm was called an sdr or a sparse distributed representation
this was a large bit
mask
think of it as a large ordered collection of ones and zeros
the representation is sparse
which means that it typically only contains about one percent of ones instead of zeros
and the values represented the state of neurons in different regions of your neocortex
so nomenta really leans into this idea of sparsity in the brain
and its necessity to build any intelligent system
the reason why sparsity is so powerful is that there are factorially
many permutations of values
i mean
for example
there are about 175 million values
if you had four on bits in an sdr of length 256
right
because it's 256 choose 4.
so this means that the possibility of getting false positives is negligibly small
it's also space efficient
because those four bits which could represent 175 million things could be stored in a 32-bit array
right
which is four times eight bits
the notion of similarity between these sdrs is their intersection or their hamming distance
and again
the really clever thing is just how robust these representations are to noise
you could add about 33 percent of random noise to both of the sdrs
and it would barely affect the overlap metric
you can also union the sdrs together
and not much information about the patterns would be lost in the mix so the htm algorithm needed encoders to take any data structure
and represent it as a sparse distributed representation
encoding the information into an sdr
is an important consideration for htm
much as it is with any other machine learning model
but i was really excited
you know when i learned about htm
because it seems so audacious
and each column has a connection to this input space and it has a receptive field
so each column is connected to different bits in the input space and these are proximal
dendritic
connections feed forward input into the system
and each one of the cells within the column shares that receptive field through its proximal
connection
we also have these other connections between cells within the structure
and here's a third cell
with another four synapses on its segment
these are distal connections
so the cell body or the soma has got
uh
different areas of receptivity
the feed forward proximal input comes from below
and the contextual information or the distal connections come laterally from other cells within the structure
we're comparing a biological neuron to the htm
you know
neuron in software that we're creating
we have the feed forward input
which is the proximal dendritic input from the input space in in both sides
and then the distal input
from lateral connections to other cells within the space for context
now this htm neuron is showing that there's feed forward input
but it's also showing that it can have one or many distal connections
these are distal segments
each one of these segments could potentially have one
or many synapses or connections to other cells within the htm structure
each one of those cells may be in an on and off state
so at any time
if a cell wants to decide whether it's going to go into a predictive state or not
it can look at all of its segments
and its connections across all of their synapses
and if any one of those summed across all the synapses breach some threshold
which is configurable
then that cell goes into a predictive state based upon its connections
its contextual connections to the other cells within the structure
so what i'm doing is i'm feeding in a four note sequence
and then resetting and restarting the sequence over
so every time it sees f-sharp the first note in the sequence
it's seeing it for
without any context
nothing came before it
so the algorithm goes and looks into every cell in in every active column
only cells within active columns become activated
because these activations are completely driven by the proximal segments to the input space
there's only one segment on the cell
because it's one color
it's magenta color
and all of the cells that it's connected to are active in the current time step
that's why it's predictive
because it looked at its segment and it looked
it summed up all the synapses and they were all one apparently
and that breached its threshold to become predictive
so it is in a predictive state
i've never seen another machine learning algorithm quite like it
you know
almost all of them are continuous rather than discrete
and even the discrete ones like decision
trees they still assume an ordinal value on the dimensions
hdm takes it one step further
its representations are also distributed over the features
the only encoding rules of sdrs were that semantically similar data should have a significant overlap on the sdrs
the encoder should be deterministic and the output should have a fixed dimensionality
and the sparsity level should be similar across the input domain
now the thing that was missing to some extent from htm was the notion of representation learning
like we have in neural networks
you have to do it all yourself in the encoder
which is probably the main reason why htm never took off for unstructured data problems
the reason why cnn's dominated computer vision was because it learned representations that were better than any hand-crafted representations
the locality prior
and the weight sharing and the stochastic gradient descent made it computationally tractable
the htm neuron was inspired by pyramidal neurons in the neocortex
a neuron is receiving sdrs from distilled apical dendrites higher up in the hierarchy
and from basal dendrites from the same region of the hierarchy
and also from proximal dendrites from lower level of the hierarchy
or some sensory input
which represented the classical receptive field of a neuron
now all of these neurons are receiving a stream of sdrs and they're figuring out
when to fire and turn on their on bit
or you know when they should go into a predictive state
which can tell other neurons when to fire
right from the very beginning
numenta knew that real neurons are not simple point neurons
the synapses on active dendrites detect dozens of sparse contextual patterns and can learn complex temporal sequences
active dendrites enable flexible context
integration in the layers of neurons
there are two primary phases of the temporal memory algorithm
the first is to identify which cells within active columns will become active on this time step
the second phase
once those activations have been identified is to choose a set of cells to put into a predictive
state
this means that these cells will be primed to fire on the next time step
htm implemented dendrite branch specific plasticity
so if a cell becomes active and there's a prediction
it reinforces that dendritic segment
if there is no prediction
it grows the connections by sub-sampling the previously active cells
and if the cell is not active and there was a prediction
it weakens the dendritic segments
now i learned all about the htm algorithm from watching the htm school series of videos from matthew taylor
who worked at nomenta
matt tragically passed away last year and i wanted to personally pay tribute to him here
his passion and enthusiasm was infectious and he'll be greatly missed by the entire machine learning community
well
sparsity is something that doesn't run really well on existing hardware
it doesn't really run really well
um
on gpus
and on cpus
and so that would be a way of sort of bringing more
and more brain principles into the existing system on a commercially valuable basis
there's a large body of work on training dense networks to yield sparse networks for inference
but this limits the size of the largest trainable
sparse model to that of the largest trainable dense model
this was the case actually
until relatively recently
now
since the 1980s
we've known that it's possible to eliminate a significant number of parameters from the neural network without affecting accuracy
or inference time
pruning can substantially reduce the computational demands of inference
when the appropriate hardware is utilized to do so
when the goal is to reduce inference costs
pruning often occurs late in training
now
in 1995
researchers discovered that retrospectively pruning low magnitude connections worked impressively well
later researchers found that retraining the prune connections produced even better results or even better
still rinsing repeating the process with multiple rounds of pruning and retraining
other approaches explored adding connections back in at random
or even focusing on non-uniform sparsity
which is to say adding the connections in where they are most needed in the network
jonathan frankl
who was on the show last year
by the way
released his lottery ticket hypothesis in 2019
which demonstrated that if we can find a sparse neural network with iterative magnitude pruning
then we can train that sparse network from scratch to the same level of accuracy
however
as the demands of training have exploded
researchers have begun to investigate the possibility that networks can be pruned early in training or even before training
the benefit of doing so could reduce the cost of training existing models
and make it possible to continue exploring the phenomena that emerge at larger scales
recently
several methods have been proposed specifically for pruning at initialization
snip
aims to prune weights that are least salient for the loss
grasp
aims to prune weights that most harm or least benefit gradient flow and sin flow
which janet made a video about
by the way
aims to iteratively prune weights with the lowest synaptic strengths in a data independent manner with the goal of avoiding layer collapse
where pruning concentrates on certain layers
now
um frankel pointed out in his recent summary paper
that magnitude pruning after training outperforms all of these pre-initialization methods
most of these methods effectively prune the layers
not the weights
which to say you can perform similarly well
even if you randomly shuffle the weights that they prune in each layer
now interestingly sin flow and magnitude pruning work quite well at initialization time without seeing any data
now frankel didn't identify a single cause for why these methods struggled to prune in a specific fashion
initialization time
and thought that this is an important question for future investigation
perhaps there are properties of optimization that make pruning specific weights difficult or impossible
initialization perhaps because the training occurs in multiple phases
now combining gradient descent training with an optimal sparse topology can lead to state-of-the-art results with smaller networks in the brain
numenta argues that sparsity is key for how information is stored and processed
they also believe it to be one of the most important missing ingredients in modern deep learning
we reached out to the mentor after the show and they're vps of machine learning
architecture and research and engineering
so lawrence bracklund and subtite
ahmed told us that at a high level
the biggest difference is
that they view sparse networks as a unique stand-alone class of artificial neural networks
that mirror the sparsity exhibited in the brain versus being a derivative of dense networks created
by pruning
so not really removing redundant connections but creating networks that are designed to be sparse
in 2019
the mentor released a paper called sparsity enables 50 times performance acceleration in deep learning networks
in that paper
they pointed to the scaling challenges faced by the current state-of-the-art neural networks
they said that the brain is highly efficient
right
requiring a mere 20 watts to operate
which is less power than a light bulb
contrast that to gpt3 which costs millions of dollars to train
numenta
believe that by studying the brain and understanding what makes it so efficient
they can create new algorithms that approach the efficiency of the brain
they think that the core reason the brain is so efficient is the notion of sparsity
a sparse network is one
where all of the neurons are not densely connected to every other in the same cortical
area
the brain stores and processes information as sparse representations
you know
at any given time
only a small percentage of the neurons in the brain are active
disparity
may vary
you know
from less than one percent to a few percent of neurons being active
but it's always sparse
sparsity will lead to a massively smaller memory footprint
because only the non-zero elements are stored
enabling the hardware to run more networks
simultaneously
gpus and tensor processing units
so tpus
they are dense execution engines
they perform the same computation task on an entire vector or matrix of data
this is a wise approach
when the vector or matrix is dense
which is to say it's all non-zero but in the dense environment
we gain efficiency by executing a single instruction to be applied to all of the data
this is an approach called simd
but when the data is predominantly zeros
then a prodigious amount of computation is wasted
so if you're keeping up to date on ai hardware
you might have heard of graphcorp or cerebros cerebrus
in particular
actually
they've developed this epic microprocessor with 850 000 cores and 40 gigabytes of memory on board
it's absolutely insane
not only that the chip has been designed to support sparsity from the ground up
these cerebros cores never multiply by zero
the scheduling operates at the granularity of a single data value
so all of the zeros are filtered out
and this in turn provides a performance advantage
by doing useful work during those cycles which otherwise would have been wasted
not to mention the power and efficiency savings
now
recently
in a presentation
they showed this graphic claiming to achieve near linear speed up in respective sparsity
about 84
speed up for 94
sparsity
numenta released this paper a couple of years ago before the current sparse hardware was released
and at the time they chose an fpga which is a field programmable gate array as the platform to run their performance tests
because of the flexibility it provided and handling sparse data efficiently
in addition
random access to memory is far more granular and efficient on an fpga
enabling fpga implementations to efficiently handle the unstructured access patterns in sparse networks
now in their paper
as well as confirming the previous results in the literature about the robustness of sparse networks to noise
and variance error
they also realized a significant performance gain from using the specialized fpga hardware
now my intuition is
that there's no difference at all between the representational power of a discrete htm type model which they used in their previous generation of algorithmic approaches versus an artificial neural network
the obvious difference is that feed forward monolithic vector space models are more amenable to training
given today's hardware
pretty much
everyone agrees that sparse networks are better
but is there something fundamentally special about sparsity
numenta certainly seem to think
so they anecdotally point to the brain as being sparse
but the brain is probably sparse for the same reason that i don't decide to get up every morning
and travel to every city in the uk doesn't seem like a profound insight
to be honest
we can take it as a given that sparse networks suffer less from overfitting
because they're not going to be using their precious representational power
memorizing individual challenging or non-representative examples in the training data
it remains unknown if the performance of the best pruning algorithms is an upper bound on the quality of sparse models
there's actually some really interesting papers out there now like momentum resnet which allow us to train huge neural networks with a small memory footprint
but the key question is are sparse networks functionally better than huge
densely connected neural networks
researchers from google released the paper rigging the lottery
making all tickets winners back in 2019
the rigging the lottery algorithm starts with a randomly initialized connection topology and then layer
by layer adds and removes connections
densifying the layer and then specifying again using a traditional weight magnitude heuristic
the algorithm achieves higher accuracy than all previous techniques for a given computational cost at all levels of sparsity
and then scored higher accuracy than the dense to sparse algorithms
now nimenta say that they've also produced a similar algorithm
although
as far as i know
it's not been made public yet
so i assume it's pretty similar to google's approach
as they pointed us in this direction
but unlike traditional dense to sparse
iterative magnitude
pruning google's algorithm allows the topology to grow
also during the optimization
which can apparently help overcome some of the local minima
obviously the most accurate sparsity algorithms required
at a minimum
the cost of training a large dense network in terms of memory and computational horsepower
but that approach has serious limitations
right
the size of the sparse model you can learn is strongly bounded on the size of the larger dense model
which you're specifying from as a starting point
it's simply too inefficient to waste computation on so many parameters
which would end up being zero
anyway
google's algorithm seems unequivocally better than dense
iterative magnitude
pruning
which is somewhat surprising to be honest
given that it's
uh
it seems to be doing the same thing
but only one layer at a time
now training mobile net one and two on imagenet
with this form of sparse training was instructive
it was possible to train a sparse network with nearly the same accuracy in about 30 percent of the compute time
it was also possible to train a large sparse network
which was five percent better
accuracy in roughly double the flops of training
the original dense uh version
today's neural networks have something called the point neuron
which is a very simple model of a neuron
and uh
by adding dendrites to them
just one more level of complexity
that's in biological systems
you can solve problems in continuous learning
um
and rapid learning
so we're trying to take
we're trying to bring the existing uh field and we'll see if we can do it
we're trying to bring the existing field of machine learning commercially
along with us
you brought up this idea of keeping
you know
paying for it commercially
along with us
as we move towards the ultimate goal of the true ai system
now nimente is working on some really cool stuff behind the scenes
unfortunately there's very little information about it in the public domain
yet jeff's main aim is to realize the vision of the thousand brains theory in an efficient computational algorithm
sparse networks are just a tiny part of this vision
the next step is implementing continual learning with active dendrites
and this essentially means that they need to be able to add new synapses
and train them independently of the existing ones
this is going to require a specified version of backprop
which will also require specialized hardware and algorithms to implement
they also mentioned to us that they want to exploit activation and weight sparsity
simultaneously mirroring the neocortex
anyway
next week
on street talk
[music] another book that i read around the same time that had a big impact on me
uh
and and there was actually a little bit of overlap with john pierre as well
and i read it around the same time
is jeff hawkins on intelligence
which is a classic
and he has this vision of the people of the main championship
i hope you enjoyed it
a multiscale hierarchy of temple prediction modules
and these ideas really resonated with me
like the the notion of a modular hierarchy
um
of you know
potentially
um of compression functions or prediction functions
i thought it was really really interesting and it reshaped
uh
the way it started thinking about how to build minds
let's kick off with the main show
hope you enjoy it
folks
well
i fell in love with brains actually
when i read an article by francis crick
who was one of the co-discoverers of dna
and francis had later in his life turned his interest to neuroscience
and he wrote this essay
that appeared in scientific american
where soon the emperor has no closed type of essay
he said
you know what
we have all this data about the brain and it's really wonderful
we collected all this data and we've got decades and decades
but no one has a clue what the hell is going on
and um
and he says
you know
we need new ways of thinking about the brain
we don't really necessarily need more data
and
and that just struck me
i was 22 and i was like holy crap
you know
that's just a puzzle
we have this
we have these pieces and someone has to put the pieces together
and that seemed like something i would be good at
or at least i would enjoy
and that's got me going
that was
that was the thing that just i said i'm going to make a career out of this
and then
very quickly
i realized that
well
you know
this is the long thing
it's going to take a long time
and
uh
but if we do this
um
then
if we really figure out how the brain works and what it does
then we will have real big insights into how to make intelligent machines
and so i said
oh my god
the implications are here to not just from a neuroscience but from an ai point of view
and so that got me going
uh
on this on this journey
and at that point i decided to change careers from engineering to neuroscience
uh
computer engineering
computer science and neuroscience and start all over
i just got my
my degree from the university
so i was like
yup
starting again
here
we are
40 years later
it's been a long journey though
as you probably probably know
there's been a lot of twists and turns
too
absolutely
well
we really enjoyed reading your book
but
um
i wanted to talk a little bit about some of the tribalism in the machine learning community
so i've been doing a bit of research online
and your mission right now is to try and convince other people of of your ideas
you've got this incredibly exciting idea of the brain
and as you just said that in in some level of abstraction
the brain is infinitely complicated
but actually
if you think about it in terms of simple rules that can produce a lot of complexity
it's not that complicated
but you know
i've noticed that when you speak to some of the machine learning folks
they are very quick to dismiss your ideas and they say
well
there's there's no material difference with monolithic neural networks with point neurons and back props and back prop
and you know
it's good that people are so passionate about what they believe in
but by the same token
it means that science only advances one funeral at a time
yeah
um
it's a very complex issue you bring up here
and um
uh
i i think our mission isn't to convince people
our first
our mission was to figure out what the hell is going on in our heads
that was the first thing we had to do
and we made a lot of progress on that
now we have to sell those ideas
we have to sell them to neuroscientists
so we publish papers
up speaker conferences
people cite our work
they test it
and so on
that has to happen
it takes time
um
then
uh
then we now have a road map we can see
we can now
uh
from the position i'm in and some of the people work with me
we can see where the shortcomings are in current ai techniques
uh
we can
we can see
oh
the brain's doing it differently
it's doing it this way
and and we have
we can have two approaches to go forward
we could say
well
we need to convince everybody else
which is not really a fun thing to do
um
or we can
we can just put our ideas out there
document them
show people them and then work at doing this ourselves like
just demonstrate it
start building things
um
making things that work
making things to solve problems that other people have been struggling with
so we're doing a bit of all these things
we're promoting the neuroscience theory
we're promoting um
these ideas in the machine learning community
and we're also implementing this stuff
uh
because in the end
you
if you don't
if you
you know
you can't implement it unless you understand it
so it's a good test for us too
um
and you would wish you know
everyone wish like
oh
i wish everyone
just you know
agreed with us
where everyone you know got what we understand
but the reality is it's a big world of lots of big little
um
and there's a lot of um people who want to dismiss new ideas
but that's just the nature of the of the beast
right
we just have to accept that
um
science is not just science
you have to promote your ideas as well as discover them
and the same is true
uh
in the machine learning world
well
one thing that's kind of interesting about that
you know
philosophical aspect that you have of look
it's a big world
there's lots of people doing a lot of different things
that's kind of the heart of evolution
right
is that there's variation
people taking different approaches and natural selection will kind of sort out
you know which ones work and don't work
and that's one thing i've always thought about
a lot of the folks that don't want to pay attention to what the brain does is
they don't have a sufficient appreciation for how much you know
uh
let's say
work has gone into designing the human brain right
i mean a billion years of life
however many
hundreds of millions of years of intelligent evolution
so certainly we can learn things from the neuroscience
right
i mean
and
and of course that was the original inspiration for the artificial neuron
but that was just one tiny
simplest possible abstraction of a neuron
that happened
what fit
yeah
i don't know what
50 years ago
right
six years
there's got to be more we can learn right
but yeah
but you know
the way i look at it is
we're all trying to reach the same end goal
we're all trying to figure out how to build intelligent machines
they're truly intelligent
we all
we're either intelligent
uh
we can talk about the implications of that
um
and i don't think there will be multiple ways of doing this
there's like in the end
there aren't multiple ways of building computers
they're all some sense of universal turing machines and we have variations on that
um
and so i think that's what's gonna happen here too now
a priori
how would i know that engineers couldn't figure this all out
just by thinking about and doing engineering stuff
um
you know
my guess was that we'd have to figure out how the brain works first
uh
and who knows i could have been wrong
that was a bet
maybe people would figure it out
but here we are 67 years later in the field of ai
and i still
i think today's ai systems are still incredibly limited
they don't really do much at all with
it's intelligent
that's my opinion
um
they're very very restricted
they don't generalize
they don't create behaviors
they don't
it's just so many things that we're so far away and now we took a long time
but now we figured out a lot about how the brain works
so now we have a roadmap
so
um
i think it's going to be a lot easier
it's now it's not just like
oh
i think it's going to be quicker to study the brain and other people say
no
i don't think we'll be
i said
well
we now have some things we can we really understand about the brain
we don't have to worry about that anymore
so
um
the approach we took has been fruitful
and um
and i should also say
just be clear
today's ai is really useful
so i have nothing against it
yeah
it's great
um
it's just not intelligent and i want to build soldier machines
yeah
it's quite a
it's really fascinating to get to talk to you
uh
your book on intelligence is actually one of the very first books of it about ai
i ever read it
so
uh
edward is your fault
that part of this field
now i always feel bad when people tell me
i hope it worked out
okay
for you
it's been
it's been a wonderful journey
and i'm really glad that it was one of my first exposures to the field
in a way it was so full of like
really interesting ideas especially for the at the time seemed very revolutionary
um
and a very well shaped my picking
so i want to ask you a little bit
um
appears to me as you know
someone who works
sorry
i work with deep learning
you know a lot
of course
nowadays
it feels to me that a lot of your ideas seem
uh
validated in a lot of dealery practices
um
a
like a
currently kind of like emerging trend is how
um
with
like these me
furtive societies transfer models that have become very popular
recently that scaling these larger is just stacking these transformer layers
seems to currently at least increase performance in
like a
you know in a pretty consistent manner
and i wonder
well
it feels like that
it kind of validates in a way
it's like a different proposal to what you say
but like accordingly before we
do
you think there's any kind of connection
ah
you know
i don't think about
i'll answer your question
but let's just say i'm always forward thinking
i never look back
and so i don't worry about
hey
what the hell
was i right about this or not
or just
you know
somebody get credit for with this or that
i don't really care
oh so it's like let's go forward
what's the best thing you can do right now
and um
and so you know
i think there's you can
obviously
as i said
really
we're all going to converge on the same thing right eventually
i think so ideas become
you know
i got ideas from other people other than people
get ideas
for me
the history of how that milieu of ideas travels
it's very difficult to point to
um
so i i
i'm very reluctant to claim precedent than anything
i just feel like
hey
you know
if we're all moving towards the same idea
that's great
i don't think transformers are an implementation of the cortical
column or the cortical um algorithm idea that we're not there yet
because we know we now know what that
the core of that algorithm is
it has to do with movement and reference frames
and
uh
transformers don't have that
in some sense
they have a very primitive sort of um
attentional movement
if you want to think of it that way
um
but nothing like kind of moving and referencing we talk about
so
um
so it's a little bit in the right direction
and of course they're really impressive
um
but it's
it's not
it's not close to what i think we need to get to yeah it's really fascinating
though
because transformers are strange beasts
they perform a kind of information rooting
and it's quite esoteric exactly how they work
and i think in some sense they're similar to capsules
i know capsules have equated to some of your work
but i wanted to talk a little bit more deeper than that
though
so a lot of um
your ideas from a machine learning point of view
come down to the fundamental dichotomy of discrete representations versus continuous representations
which is what we use in deep learning
we use vectors
and there are some advantages to using these continuous vector spaces
namely that you get for free
some spatial priors
so you can encode semantic similarity as a function of how close they are
and yeah
and also you have gradients
which are useful for stochastic gradient descent and
and interestingly
the manifold hypothesis states that most natural data falls on very smooth and low dimensional manifolds
so all of the human faces could be projected onto a low dimensional manifold
but um
i i know that a lot of your work has has been really solely focused on on these um
sparse distributed representations and then um
building on top in in the encoding
for example
so if i'm encoding a date representation
i would do it such
that this sparse distributed representation would have a significant overlap for date times that are in the vicinity
yeah
and so semantically similar things should intersect each other
and spatial relations between bits can be encoded using a receptive field similar to
you know how it works in in cnn
so
um
but nimenta has asserted that intelligence wouldn't be possible without these sdrs and they're the primitive of of intelligence
so what do you think about the kind of comparison between vectors
and and these um discrete representations that that you were never
yeah
well
let's just start
you know
the whole idea of these sparse representations comes because that's how brains work
i mean that's
there's no compression about it
uh
if you look in the brain
you look at any population of cells that are representing something at any point in time
most of the cells are inactive
uh
it can be anywhere from
um
you know
90 percent to 99 percent of the cells interact
you just don't see of the information carrying neurons or some neurons that fire all the time
we're not talking about those
but the ones like information
you just do not see any kind of dense representations
that is a
when you
when that happens
you're having a seizure
um
and we also see that in in in real neurons that they're not very high fidelity
they don't carry individual spiking rates are very crude
um
there's many instances where even the single
the first spike is actually the most important thing recovering information
so we're not like
this isn't so
on a high resolution
you know
four bits or three bits
or even
even often
one bit of precision and firing of a nerve
all right
so this doesn't exist in the brain
um
so we just take that okay
well
we need to understand why that is
and it's not just
it's like more efficient
from an energy point of view
that's not what it is
um
it turns out that um
sparse representations have a lot of really desirable and interesting properties that you don't get with dense representations
um
we can talk about those
it's not like everything is
um
there's a spectrum here
right there are some parts of the brain where you have representations
which are a little bit less dense
maybe of the tempest are firing and there
the activity rates really do matter
um
they're still not high precision
but they really do matter
and then we believe there's other parts where they're very
very sparse
so i might have five thousand neurons and let's say two percent are active
so i have 100 active neurons and all the information is encoded
almost all the information is coding in the population code
not in the fire rate
and we can talk about that
if you want to dive into the details with the advantage of sparse distributed representations
um
but it is an empirical observation of the brain
so you know we're gonna start with that
it's okay
well
why is it that way
you know
well
one thing i wanted to understand
because you made the comment before that
um
they could improve generalization
but intuitively they're the opposite of improving generalization
because they have such an incredible specificity
so
for example
when i was reading through some of your literature when you use boosting
for example in your algorithm it increases the specificity to such an extent
but then the way we generalize in our cognition isn't necessarily through the representation
it's through the abstractness of of the concept we're learning
would you argue
yeah
so i'll be honest with you
i've changed my opinion about this
um
i used to believe exactly what you're saying
which is like
oh
these overlaps between these sdrs are really how you're going to get generalization
we now realize it is a much more powerful form of generalization
um
i talked about it briefly in uh
my new book
um
a thousand brains
i don't know
if we really discussed it in any of our papers yet
um
and this is the idea that you're so i can switch into that
so i'm admitting right
yeah
i don't think it's what i said before
okay
all right
we learn
um
but there's a much more powerful form of generalization
if you want
i can delve into that right now
um
uh
it's not okay
so so we have
this is what we've learned is that each core of a column where you say the brain in general
um
it's building this sort of
uh
the model of the world you can think of as a graph
but it's
you can literally think of it as like
where are things relative to other things
it's like a computer-aided design
model
right
cad model
it's literally doing that
you have a model of something like a computer or your house
or room or bird
or ideas that they're structured
using reference frames and data
populating
reference locations and reference frames
and um
so you can imagine
uh
my knowledge of something again
as you know
in the book
i use the coffee cup example
quite a bit
but you can use anything
um
a knowledge of say a stapler is
is it has a certain set of parts
uh
which are then arranged in certain
relative positions of each other and they have certain movements related to each other
and um
and that structure is
is that graph
if you will
is the uh
is the definition of that object
and that's your
that's your model of it
that's how you
that's how you represent it in your brain
now
when you
when you learn it
the way you do this is you attend individual components one at a time
so if i
if i were to look at a new object i haven't seen before
like a stapler
i would just attend to one end or look at what's what's this thing look like
then
what's that thing look like
and as you attend to these different parts
you're essentially building this graph
you're essentially building the model
you're saying
okay
this component
i recognize
that's like a hinge
this component over here looks like maybe a button
this component here looks a rubber pad
and i and i just start building this model in my head
but it looks my phone right thumb up there
um
i started building this mod
okay
so you got this
i'm trying to paint a picture in your head
how you you're doing this every moment of your life
as you look around
even like you're looking at the screen right now you're looking to see different things
you see where they are relative to each other
i think most generalization in the world comes about from a different from the process
of
if i see something new that i haven't seen before or i'm experiencing something new
doesn't matter revision
but just imagine you're seeing something new
you don't recognize it
you don't see this arrangement as a familiar arrangement
then you look at a subset of the components and you say
okay
let's just focus over here
and you say
well
these three components every year look like something i've seen before
these look like it might be a button that i pushed down and this thing over here looks
it might be a hinge
um
and then you
then you say
well
if it's a hinge
then a button with this thing
even i've never seen it before
maybe if i push on this button
the hinge will look
and and so you
you
basically your
your generalization comes about
because subsets of these graphs
that you build of the structure in the world are similar to subsets in other graphs you've learned
and you can say
well
these subsets are similar
therefore the behavior behaviors associated with those substances are similar
the performance of the substance is similar
so i now can ascribe to the stapler
some things i've learned about other things
um
and we keep
and if i see something really new
we just keep going down into small and smaller pieces until we find something i recognize
this next
okay
well
i thought i recognized
and and so that i believe
uh
is actually the primary way we generalize in the world
um
we can talk about how str's do that
do that too
but anyway
what you're talking about
it sounds a lot like sort of some of the graph isomorphism you know
work that that people talk about where
if you
if you've got this new thing and it has all these parts
and they're in a graph
you know
certain subsets of that graph may be isomorphic to previous
you know graphs that you've seen
and then therefore you can learn about it
um
and you said something really interesting
which is when you see something new
you know
you attend to kind of different parts of that and you're doing kind of a remapping there
and there's a lot of research on on grid cells
right that they remap
so when a rodent goes into a new
a new environment
it remaps the grid cells
can you talk some
i mean
is this related to the remapping
and i'm really curious about how does that remap
and happen in the neurons and how quickly does it take place
you know
yeah
well
so one of the the
the hypothesis
we have a thousand range theory is that
well
first of all
we deduce the idea that you need some that there is any in the cortex
there are these reference frames and these structures
these graphs
right
we can deduce that it's like okay
well
i know this is happening
i walked through the logic behind that
and then it was
at first to me
it was very odd
like
how could neurons build these graphs
right
how and how do they structure them i mean it
what with the way i used to focus is like my cortex knows
where my finger is relative to the thing it's touching
like relative to the thing
it's tilting
not relative to my body
and and so i use the example of coffee cup and the coffee cup blows around
so the reference brand has to move the coffee up
i was like holy crap
how does that happen
it's really hard for neurons to do this
and then
of course we looked into the literature of the hippocampal complex
which is grid cells in the anterional cortex
and place cells in the hippocampus and there's a whole bunch of stuff
and there's
there's a 20 year or 30 year history of research in this field
it's not in the neocortex
but it's it's something that's very related to the neurocortex
um
and and so
and that's what they
it's clear that grid cells and place cells and these other types
these vector cells that exist
there are building maps just like this
um
and so we said
okay
well
it's likely then that the the same mechanisms that are used
by grid cells are probably going to be used in the cortex
and the time we made that that was a purely evolutionary argument
it was like saying
it seems unlikely evolution is going to discover something like this twice
it's really hard to do right
it's really really hard to do this
so
and animals have to know where they were in the world a long time ago
so they probably evolved this complex mechanism from knowing where they are
and now the brain's gonna use that same mechanism for knowing where
like your eyes are or your fingers are
or you know
it's gonna be the same mechanism for everything else
and so we just said
hey
it's probably likely that the same basic mechanism that uses good cells
and place cells and vector cells is going on cortex
at the time we made that that prediction
we were not aware of any evidence of that was the case
um
and now there's a lot of evidence for it
now people are finding fit cells throughout the cortex
um
so so the general idea i'll keep get into your details in a moment
but the general idea that
hey
the same mechanisms are work in both places
seems to be right
and and now we don't understand those mechanisms completely
even though there are 30 years of research on grid cells and place cells
it's there's still some mysteries about them
um
but there's still a lot
but there's a lot that's known
and so
um
we can map on the concepts i was talking about like
okay
um
where am i
where am i in this graph
what's what do i place in that graph
you can think of that a little bit like place cells
um
in grid cells
you can think of remapping
is
um
there's two types of remapping like this is a whole new thing
so let's just start with a new graph
or versus
let's fix the graph i already got
you know
and uh
and that's that's very much related
as you said to remapping of grid cells
not that we understand that completely
we don't
no one does
um
but we know a lot about it
it's a very
very technical field in the neuroscience solution
right
i've been fascinated by douglas hofstadter
he has a really um interesting idea on cognition
and he says that cognition is a little bit like the interstate freeway
um
in the sense that we we have this ability to make analogies
and this is something that current ai systems cannot do
and a lot of the symbolic folks are saying
well
of course
deep learning models can't do it
you're just interpolating on a manifold
for goodness sake
but um
your conception of reference
frames i i found fascinating because they're not just on your sensory inputs
there's you actually said that thinking is a little bit like traversing through concept space through these reference frames
and that's absolutely fascinating
so
but the thing is
when we learn information
many of us learn information differently
but we learn the same knowledge and the same facts
you know
we
we all know how to speak
um
the same language
and you did allude to this in your book
that there are some interesting differences in the topology of how you learn information
but we still seem to be able to reconcile it in the same way
yeah
well
sometimes you know it's it's like the way i view it
uh
again
we're telling stuff that some
some of this hasn't been published anywhere yet
um
but the way i view it is
if i think of myself as this part of the cortex says the cortical call
um
i don't know what come my input represents
and i don't know where i am in the world
i don't
i just don't know anything
i'm just a bunch of neurons right
and so i have to discover what i'm getting
i get two pieces of information
i get some sensory data and i also get information about how my sensor is moving in the world
yeah
we can talk about how that happens
but i get
i get some knowledge
and so i have to figure out on my own
what is the dimensionality of the space
what kind of space is it
i i don't have a preconceived
it's not like
oh
the world is three-dimensional i don't know that
um
i don't know if it's two-dimensional three-dimensional or in-dimensional i just kind of figure out
i have to figure out what is the structure of which i'm going to to place this information
and when you and i look at a chair we both see it as three-dimensional we
it is a three-dimensional object
we're going to build three-dimensional reference frames for that chair
they're going to be pretty similar
it's going to be hard for you to have a representation of the chairs
it's significantly different than mine
um
but when we look at things that we might not sense directly
something that someone tells me about or i'm reading about
in a book
the kind of reference frames you and i might create for the same facts could be very different
and and so we can arrange the same data in different reference frames
because we can't directly sense it we're basically relying on information coming from other people
and so we can end up with
like the same facts represented differently and reach to different conclusions
and this is why we have different beliefs about the world
it's almost always about things we can't sense directly
if we can sense them directly
then we generally have the same belief about it
you know
but numb the same kind of structure
so i think this is a fascinating idea
um
and um
uh
but it's
it's really fascinating to me
is
that there is no pre a notion about the dimensionality of the world that a column is looking at
and and the data
so it can represent almost any kind of data
as long as you can
could figure out from a movement vector
in a sense
lumen data and sense data
they can say
can i build a map of this thing that makes sense
the predictive map and um
uh
and if i can
i said
okay
that's my
that's my understanding of it
another
another beautiful thing about it is is the fact that your brain is
is creating these binary encodings at all
like i
when i was researching this
i found it very interesting that for grid cells
there is some some topography
at least in the visual cortex or in the visual layer
i'm sorry
so you know
grid cells that are nearby each other will have like a similar orientation
but maybe a different scale
but once you go up a level higher
so those things create the sdr
you know
they create these bits that are very sparsely populated
and then the place cells correspond to combinations of those
those bits to indicate a certain location
and once you're at that layer
there is no more topography
it's like now they've become truly digital encodings of information
right
well
i'm not sure
i'm not sure i understand that
because i
it's my
from my understanding
there's always going to be a topology
you're never going to lose it
uh
you may not see that topology in the place else
right
um
all right
that's that
i mean this
the neuroscientists who listen to white
listen to this
i don't
i don't want to insult them
because i'm going to make this very simple
i say you can think of like place cells are like what
and grit cells are like
right
okay
so
um
and you can say
well
this thing
the what thing is at this location
type of stuff
and so if you just look at the place cells
you don't
this isn't because they actually do uniquely encode places
so this is
it gets a little confusing here
but um
uh
but you can think of it just generally like that
um
if we're going to go deeper about this
we're going to start getting into all the unknowns about grid sales and play cells and they're very interesting
the unknown and weird properties
um
we actually think now that
this is work that one of our employees marcus
um
is doing is we think
actually
the
the better way to think about a coding is not
the location is not actually through the grid cells
but through these vector cells
things are things like optic vector cells
and so on
um
it's
it's in the
the grid cells actually might just play a very interesting singular role
they might play the role of what we call path integration
which is like
if i'm moving in a certain direction
i have to be able to predict where i'll be
uh
as i move
that's called path integration
i'm going to predict something i have to know where i'm going to be when i get there
um
and that most of the max
the graph itself is not built up of grid cells
it's built up these objects
these
more like these polar coordinate cells called vector cells
um
so again
this is an evolving field and you know
and even stuff
we wrote
a couple years ago
we're like
oh
maybe that's not right
it's like this
but the overall principles are the same
it's still a graph
it's still
you know data at locations in this graph
um
that hasn't changed
uh
it's just like
how's the graph actually constructed
that's a little tricky
right
i mean it's like it's fascinatingly deep
it's just a fascinatingly deep feel
but if i can just tie this back to sdrs
because i know there's
there's always a lot of really confusion or uncertainty about the value of sdrs
and just for our listeners sake
i wanted to share one intuition and get your take on it
which is if we are representing
let's say
location
uh
in some space
if all we need is 20 bits to do that
so we really only need 20 bits of information to represent a space location
to the resolution that we need
then
if you go further than that
if you have 10 000 bits and you decide i'm not going to use 20
i'm going to use all 10
000 put
like you know
little. 01 values kind of all throughout there
really
you're just creating noise and that other space that you could have been using for other purposes
right
and so i think that's one advantage of the sdrs
like
what do you think about that intuition
that's that's a little bit correct
i i
i
i haven't thought of it that way
um
let me give you some
let me just give you my take on some of the advantages of seos
so let's say i'm going to represent
uh
something
i have 5 000 neurons
i'm going to represent
so
all right
so let's talk about the capacity and let's say i'm going to use a 2 sparsities
so i have 100 active neurons and five four thousand
nine
hundred
um
they act if not
and
um
first thing
you say
what is the capacity of the system
how many different representations you can represent
so that's
that's just five thousand choose
you know 100
and it's
you know
gazillion because i'm in gaza
so then you can say okay
so there's no representational capacity
you
then you see if i randomly chose these sdrs
um
what is their overlap
well
they'll overlap by about two neurons each
because each neuron is going to participate in every 50 patterns
um
but not by a lot more
you won't find two patterns randomly overlapping by 50 bits or 30 bits
it's all statistically impossible
so you can
now you have all these these patterns
you can pick randomly all day long and they're not going to overlap
so they're very unique
each one is going to be extremely robust to noise
so you can add 50 noise to any of these patterns and they're still going to be recognized correctly
okay
so very noise
robust is another um thing
so high capacity
uh representation is very noisable
there's another property that
uh
we think is being used everywhere
which is really interesting
i don't know if there's any equivalent to it
other types of networks is what we call the union property
where i could invoke
um
not one pattern
but two
three
five
ten poundings at once
and so now
instead of having a hundred neurons active
i say i vote ten patterns
i'm gonna have a thousand neurons active
thousand out of five thousand
well
it turns out that all the processing that you do still works on all those
you can process them in parallel
there's you get
even though you're
you're mixing these things together
the other ends
the neurons that are that are detecting these patterns
don't get confused
and you can show this mathematically
so
instead of representing probabilities like a probability distribution
you might think about the brain often relies on this union property
which is
you know
there are multiple possibilities right now
it's not really a probability distribution
it's just like these are all possible things that could be happening right now
let's process them all in parallel and see which one works out a superposition
that's the kind of property that
yeah
i guess you could call that
um
and you only get the sparser
you are
the more of those you can do and the whole things become
so you got this huge capacity
super noise
robustness
um
it only takes
you know
if i want to recognize one of these patterns of 100 neurons
i only have to recognize i only have to connect to 20 of them
so so neurons typically don't really detect mana
they look for
maybe up to about 20 or 30 synapses at maximum
um at a time
so so all these
these are other properties
all these properties come about
yeah
since you did mention capacity
though i would like to
because i did see
you know some variable statements
sometimes i've seen no problem whatsoever with capacity
mathematically
we've got tons of it
but i was listening to one of your research calls
i guess
and you started to question
you know capacity
i think
at least in the
maybe the the grid cell
you know
the inter rhino cortex
or or some such
so i guess i have two questions
yeah
one is
is capacity a concern or not a concern
and also
uh
in order to make best use of the capacity
i'm sure the brain must have some type of entanglement
so you know
machine learned artificial networks
we know that they entangle representations
so the
you know
there's like weight sharing between different representations
do you think something similar is happening in
uh
biological networks
well
i i don't know
uh
the
the machine learning
uh
field that you're talking about
and so i can't really comment on this idea of entitlement of weights in machine learning
um
i'm not familiar with it there
i do
i
i want to maybe correct something about sdrs
which relates to the question you're asking
uh
we think in some parts of the brain
some parts of the neocortex
these very sparse representations worked
as i just said
there are other places where there are less sparse
maybe 10 percent sparsity
grid cells is a great example
if i actually look at a population of grid cells
you know it's not like one percent sparsity
it's more like ten percent sparse
and and even and there the activation levels actually do matter
it's not like they matter
like three digits of precision
but maybe one digit of precision
and um
and they
and so that doesn't have all the properties
i was just talking about
um
when you get to like 10
you can't really do a lot of superposition patterns
so it looks like
in some parts of these algorithms
there are sparse patterns that work on some principles
and you know
and in other parts
they're very
very sparse
i work on other principles
it's not everything is super sgrs
you know
i used to think that
but i don't think that anymore
um
i just became enamored with seoul and i said
oh my god
this is really cool
you know how these things work
um
but i now we now know that there are in some parts of these algorithms
you need to have
um
still sparse
but more dense and activation of level matter
and then some of the capacity issues
uh
you don't have those
the capacity advantages
and so
um
and that's clearly true with with grid cell representations
but i i imagine it's true at other things too
i know it's true in other rares
too
so it's
it isn't one size fits all here
um
i do
i do say we could say for certainty that you don't find anywhere in the braid
where anything is represented by full active
you know
uh
fully dense
networks where all the neurons are fire
developed that this does not exist
doesn't mean this couldn't be useful
and it doesn't mean that we could in the future do something like that
it just seems very unlikely to me
uh
i know that's how most
you know
convolutional nora
that works with networks work today
um
but
right
but you probably know there's a lot of
there's a lot of effort going on in sparsity
right now
in the classic machine learning community
uh
people try to do it and we're working on that too
um
so so i i think there's something fundamental about the representations we use when we build ai algorithms
there's a dichotomy between
you know
the good old-fashioned ai people
they
they work at a level of abstraction higher
they try to implement the mind and us connectionists
we're trying to implement the brain
i think there's something fundamental about that level of abstraction that we work at
so there's a discussion between people like scott harrison
who think that computation is raw and should happen at the lowest possible level
so just think of how neural networks work
they distribute knowledge
don't they across lots and lots of different neurons
and then there's um
uh
people like krishna swami
and he's a computer scientist
and and he thinks that we should be dealing with much higher level computational primitives like functions and types
so
um
i i guess
from your perspective
because i i feel that all of this is strongly emergent
i feel that we could work at the very lowest primitive level of computation
and all of the magic emerges
do you think we should be doing that
or do you think we should be working higher up the stack
no
i
well
i think we have to working higher up the stack
um
i mean
of course you can break any system down and say it's just a bunch of atoms
it's just a bunch of molecules
right
it's just a bunch of cells
um
and that's true
and you can
theory
should be able to understand that
but just like thermodynamics says
it's not very useful to think about liquids as a bunch of atoms
right
you
you need to have something at a higher level than that
and and so you know what
i guess
the principle we
that we'd assume that we just we have
now
in some sense discovered that the brain uses this representation scheme using reference frames and movement
now i think that's the right level to think about it
i don't
i
you could try to extract it less than that
but why bother
that is the unit that we're talking about here
we use models that are
but okay
that's
that's the thing
though
but
um
the brain was evolvable
it evolved within biological and environmental limitations
and and go
five people say
well
you know what scrap that
let's just implement the mind directly
you know
and they think that functions and types
um
they're not an imaginary concept that have been invented by humans
they think that mathematical knowledge has
it's universal and it's been discovered
by us and we would be silly not to implement it directly in this higher level language
because if you think about it
even
um
the knowledge that we have
you write about this in your book
it's fascinating that now there's a separation between our genes and the knowledge we've created as the human race
and all of this stuff now is
is
is emergent
our society is emergent
so why not implement it directly
but why trust
because
because you're gonna
you're gonna guess wrong
right
you know
you're gonna say
okay
well
i will figure out what that structure is
what you know
what is that mind structure that we're gonna
you know
and and so
for example
most of the
you know
the good old-fashioned ai never considered movement in their
in their
in their fundamental aspects of representation space
right
um
and you know
or even
do you look for what dr lanatt did was psych
you know
same idea
right
um
yeah
and so
but but now i know
okay
the brain builds these structures using movement
so it it's not like it was a wrong idea of the old ai people
it just they just didn't pick the right schema
it was the wrong schema
well
could you expand on that
because the thing is
um
because we've got a go-fi person
we're very
we're very good friends with
and he is convinced that there is
you know
like the knowledge engineering bottleneck and yeah
it
it's very
very brittle and it didn't work very well
but um
but you're reading your chapter on knowledge representation
i think you were saying our brain is
it's like lots of models
when we model a stapler
it's actually lots of little models in our brain and it's it learns a kind of
um
it analogizes the knowledge in a really sophisticated and distributed way
so when we want to know what happens when we press down on the stapler
we run a simulation in our mind
you know what
what happens if i press down on it
what happens if i stretch it
and our models seem to um generalize to any version of a stapler we might ever find
so that almost convinced me that we do need to have a lower level representation of knowledge
lower than what
lower than the the reference frames i was talking about
well
lo
so the go five people say that we should use um functions and types and relations to describe knowledge
but do you think that's possible
i
i i don't want to misrepresent go fight because i haven't looked at that stuff in a long time
um
i i think you can't do this at the level of the neuron
i mean
obviously brains are made of neurons
so
but they're not uniform neurons
we have dozens of different types of neurons hooked up in very complex ways
they do different functions
it's not just one big neural network
uh
that structure is important
um
and so
uh
i think it's now become evident to me
and it wasn't this way five years ago
it's really evident to me now that at least in the brain
knowledge is represented in this structured form
uh
with reference
aims and movement
it's the same inspiration that um
uniting has with with capsules
but he didn't incorporate movement as part of that structure
um
you know
uh
that
with that
you know
but now i
i now i understand
okay
at least from a brain's point of view
these reference frames are constructed
as i mentioned earlier
they're discovered through through movement
observing movement of the of the sensor through the world
and
um
and so now we have this
the
the basic structure of
if you want to call it will fi is
is these
uh
movement related
um
reference frames and placing
you know
and stuff like that
i
i can't
i don't know how i would do it
less than that
i don't know
what how i want to get rid of that
now
what do i do
just ignore that and go back and just put a bunch of neurons together
i don't know
do you mean
could you come up with a genetic algorithm that could have discovered this using just traditional neural networks
sure
maybe you
could
you know
i don't know
which is the fastest way to get there
but now that i know it
why would i want to do something different
i
maybe i'm misunderstanding your questions
right
yeah
well
i
i think the the
the main issue is that we don't understand the representation
you know
if you look at the open ai microscope and you can visualize all the different neurons
and so on
these objects have been distributed in a way which is completely ineffable across all of these different neurons
and is that the most high fidelity possible representation of knowledge
well
i don't
i don't know
but well
i will say now is
i currently believe very strongly that
um
in the future
when we build ai systems
they're going to work more like on these brain structures
and they won't be just highly distributed
mysterious blobs of neurons right there
that's great
by the way
it's
it's great
uh
not only because of what they
how they perform
but it's great
because they'll understand about a whole lot better
this
you know
this touches on the issue of the
the threats of ai
right
you know
the so many of the threats of are based on the idea
that we don't know what's going to happen
well now you actually will know what's gonna happen
it's like
you know
i just like to say it works like this
it's what's it
you know
i can't put it everything
but i
you know
i don't know what it's gonna learn
but i know how it's gonna learn and what it's what it's capable of
um
so i
i just
you know
i i don't want to debate people about this because i
you know there's a lot of smart people out there and they may have things
no things that i don't know and they can pursue things
but from where i see right now
um
it's very clear to me that
okay
this is how brains do this
this explains everything explains again
how we structure all knowledge
um
and how it evolved
that's a big part of this
and how you know how we have this common algorithm
and it's going to be based on these reference frames and movement and so on
and so okay
well
why wouldn't i just just just build that
let's go for that
um
and you know
why build something else
if i understand that
i
i don't
i understand the point of
is it going to be better
you know
in the future
we will certainly take you
let's say i'm right
and we build machines that work on these principles that i outlined in the book
well
of course
we can very well go for that
we don't have to stick to the way biology
maybe we'll come up with a better way of representing things in structures and reference frames
maybe it won't be movement-based maybe something else
i don't know
but i try to do it
do it
build something and get it working
why would i go away from it
you know
yeah
go ahead to try and steal steel man
the go-fi people
it's because they think that knowledge is universal
we discover it
there is only one representation of knowledge
and clearly in the brain
you can learn things in different ways
you can
i can teach you a curriculum and i can teach you it in a different way
and maybe in some weird way
our brain does learn some latent representation of the knowledge
which is the universal knowledge
but they're making the argument that
why don't we just represent it the only way it can possibly
well
obviously
first of all
that's not
you know
it clearly isn't true
i give it
just like you just said
i gave the example in my book about taking a bunch of historical facts
and arranging them along a timeline
and arranging them on a map
and you end up with different inferences and different beliefs about the same set of facts
so whether there is a universal truth
i don't know
but clearly humans don't know that universal truth
um
we
we can't know everything
we can only sense a small part of the world and um
and in in
you know
the vast majority is invisible to us
so who the hell knows what that universal truth is
um
what we can do is build good models and
uh
and the models
there isn't a universal model
there isn't one correct model for for history
right
um
we might like to believe there is my models
writing yours was wrong
that kind of thing
but you know it's really easy to point
out
even non-controversial things like the timeline versus the map will lead to different models
the order in which you train someone will matter
you know
so i think we have to live with this um and i don't think you know
maybe there's some platonic
you know
go five people thinking there's some plot
universal knowledge that's correct all time
i don't know
but certainly i don't think that's accessible to us
if there was
we
just we
just we can't
we can't sense the world both physically and time wise
we
our senses only deal with a teeny part of the world
yeah
it's a good part
but it's not a little teeny part
we don't even know the universal truth about space and time
is
i mean
definitely true
if i could move on to some other questions about the brain
um
so you of course focus very much on new cortex as the
you know
seed fuel intelligence
and i think i think you're definitely on the right path with that
i think most people agree something similar to that
but there's also lots of other parts in the brain that see pretty important and i'm specifically
uh
interested
it's like one thing that machine learning people are interested in is the dopamine circuit
so like the cortical basal ganglia critical
and which seems really
it seems like alerted
it seems like some kind of learning is going on
there
could you maybe say some words about that
yeah
so obviously the neoprojects is connected to the rest of the brain in modern ways
um
myriad ways
uh
it's
it's not in isolation and it's a very complex relationship
so lots of other things
um
that doesn't mean you can't understand what its circuits are doing
but in a human and their cortex is complexly tied to things
and one of those things is that
if you think
if the neocortex is as this sort of map of the world or model of the world
well
it
what should it learn and what goals should it have
the dopamine circuitry is clearly associated with what should we learn
when should we take
when should we take the effort to learn something which is metabolically expensive
um
and um
and so somebody has to decide that
uh
my basic contention is the decision is not the neocortex's decision
right
mostly
it's somebody else's decision and
um
when we build intelligent machines
we'll have to figure out who's making that decision
and
um
it won't be in the neocortical equivalent
it'll be in another part of the intelligent machines equivalent
but uh
there's absolutely no reason we would have to model the goals and um
emotions and other things that other parts of the brain
do
unless you want to create something was human-like right
so you know
i used to joke that our dopamine signal in our models is a switch
i turn it on and turn it off
i can learn
now
stop learning now
right
just manually turn it on
manually turn it off
uh
when we run experiments
um
it doesn't have anything you know
more complicated than that
um
but there's it
you know
the only thing i'm claiming here is when we build intelligent machines
if we build them on the principles in the neocortex
they have to be embodied
i mentioned this
the whole chapter in the book about they have to be embodied in some sort physical or non-physical embodiment
but some embodiment
they have to have
uh
you know
very sort of safeguards built in
they have to have various mechanisms for what to learn
what not to learn
someone has to provide goals
uh
what should the goals of the system be
what are we trying to achieve right now and
um
but so those things have to exist
but they don't have to be modeled on
i don't see any reason at all to model those on the neural circuits
the way the neurons do that that
now we're getting pure biology
we're now getting into what is a biological organism need
including
like keeping your heart going and breathing
and you know
making sure you have sex and all these things
um
yeah
i can ignore that
just if we're going to build intel's machines
just make them a little bit
um
to our purpose
i guess i would say another neuroscience question is that i know
um
you know
a lot of people are skeptical that the brain can do anything remotely like bat propagation
right
i mean there's sort of good arguments for why that's just not possible
but on the other hand
i don't know if you've seen kind of a lot of the recent work by blake richards
at mcgill university
where he talks about
you can do something that performs in a very similar way to back propagation
because
and especially in the neocortex
the
uh
the neurons there had these very long apical dendrites
and they had these sections with these calcium channels
that can do these very long lasting activations that trigger like spike trains
and he's saying that there are
there is evidence that you know
if you have feedback from a higher or downstream layer back into this
the
uh
the apical dendrite
you know
connections that that can have an effect of creating something like back propagation
it's like stochastic back propagation
uh
what are your thoughts on that
well
i'm
i'm a little bit familiar with that work and blood breakthroughs work a little bit
um
i viewed a little bit of a distraction because you know backpropagation's a cool idea
uh
it works on classic neural networks pretty well
um
i don't think the end result is like kind of nerf what you see in the brain at all
i don't think the kind of learning
that that back propagation does is the kind of learning we see in the brain
um
and and so
uh
and there's lots of other theories
what those apical dendrites are doing and why you have that stuff so
um
i'm not going to say that back propagation isn't occurring anywhere in the brain
i don't know
maybe it is
um
but it hasn't played a role in our theories about the brain
and i think a lot of people spend time trying to shoot her in there
like i'm going to prove it to you
see the brain really is doing this
it's like well
but the paintings look like anything else
none of this stuff
the brain doesn't look like anything like you're talking about here
you're just trying to put this
you know
one little piece back prop into this thing
i mean for example just take away learning
we know that learning in a neuron
lauren taught these dendritic branches and and the synapses are distributed on these branches
uh
well
this is
this is key
this is critical
you can't
you can't get around this
this is this
there's an important information
theoretic
reason for this
it's
it's not just some other reasons
it's doing something important from an information point of view
and and so the whole idea of backprop working with learning on individual dendritic segments is
i don't know what that means
right
it's like
it's like hard to fit in
so right to my mind
it's like noise
i kind of like tuning it out
saying
well
if they figure out something really important
they'll let you know
well
i mean i'll pay attention to it
yeah
i think i think more his his motivation
and i quite agree with this
it's about taking inspiration from the brain
so this algorithm that they discovered by kind of looking for things that could you know
at least enable
you know
feedback mechanisms for the training
is it
but are they
are they taking information from the brain
are they taking inspiration from the neural networks and trying to figure out what the brain could do
what they're trying to do is they're trying to figure out how can the brain do deep training
how can the brain do deeply
and they like assuming that that's what
that
assuming back prop is what they want
no
i just want to know
can it do
how can it do deep learning
and so then they look very carefully at the biology and they find this this alternative mechanism
which can produce results that are very similar to back propagation
but actually it's slightly better in some ways
and so it's leading to inspiration for how to improve ml
and i guess that's the question i really wanted to ask you
which is i always ask this what's missing question
okay
so we have artificial neural networks
clearly
they're a very stripped down
you know
micro abstraction of what happens in the brain
if you could add in a few things like just one
two
three kind of abstract properties to neural networks today
what would you suggest should be added to get the biggest bang for the buck like
how can we incrementally improve them
okay
well
so so that's what we're doing at nemesis right now
so
um
my colleague
subatomi
ahmad
who's really the machine learning expert
i'm more of the neuroscience guy
um
he put together a road map
well
we did it
together but he's implementing it
uh
a road map
the idea is like
hey
we have these grand theories about the neocortex and so on again
maybe the right
maybe they're not
but we think they're right
um
well
what do we do next
like what do we do right
so the answer question was well
how we incrementally get from where we are today
uh
machine learning to where we want
where we think we need to be some number of years from now
and so we literally have a roadmap and we started off by saying okay
uh
first i'm going to focus on sparsity
and so we've been doing that and we've been at
uh
we've been making really interesting progress
some of it
which we published and some
we haven't yet
uh
about introducing sparsity to
first we did it for the convolution neural networks and we did for other types of nerves
now we're doing it for transformers
um
and showing that we can speed these things up and make them more robust
and and i'm talking speeding things up by a lot
not a little bit
but a lot
uh
depends on the network
depends on the world through all these different things
but uh
how do
and then how do you implement that on heart
so we start with sparsity
the next thing we're working on is the dendritic computation
because what the dendrites get you
and we haven't really talked about this much at all so far
but with the dendrites
each individual section of a dendrites like its own little complete computational pattern recognizer
um
they allow you to represent information in different contexts
and so um
uh
this is
we think it's going to make
it's far far less training data to train existing networks
um
and so and allow us to do continuous well
because when you train a neuron you don't train all the synapses
you only
you only modify a few on on one of these dendritic branches
and so you can
you can learn without forgetting things
um
so we're working on that
so okay
take existing networks make them so that they're going to be continually learning or they
they don't forget things
um
and make them so you can train them for fewer data points
and then so we're
we're well into that now
um
and then the third thing with the next big one
which is sort of biting off the whole concept of reference frames
and um
we're just starting that
um
and it probably will take several years
but and then finally we do the whole the whole thousand brains theory
we have lots of these columns and so on
so at least we put together
we have a road map
we're working to it
i think i i'll be honest with you
i think this
the progress we've made is actually far better than i thought it would be
i thought it would take us longer to achieve the things we're achieving
uh
the performance gains we're getting are really really something dramatic
and
uh
without losing accuracy
um
so
uh
that's
that's what nomento is working on
and i don't think we've talked about this road map
um
but we haven't given all the details of it
yeah
so it's not public yet
the roadmap
well
the rare map
because i've talked about it in like you know talks
i just i just spoke about it here
right
so i have pictures of that stuff
um
but the details how we're doing it
like we've created
we've discovered
like you talk about sparsity
the problem is you want to run sparse networks
you want to run them on some hardware
right
what kind of heart
are you going to run mods
is it gpus
cpus
fpgas
well
we're doing all of those
um
but they all have their problems and issues and because gpus don't like sparse networks
at least you don't get any benefit from them
and um
and fpgas are hard to use
but they're pretty
they're good
but they're really hard to use
um
and
and so that will be discovered and including
very recently we've discovered tricks
um
engineering tricks that allow you to map sparse networks onto some of these existing architectures
uh
better than we think anyone else has been able to do by pretty large margin
and so
um
that you know these are very engineering problems
uh
they're not pure
you know they're not pure theoretical problems
they're very big engineering problems and we have to be able to solve those
because it's no good to say
hey
spartan is great if you can't run it faster on something
you know
it's gotta really work in the real world
so it's exciting and we'll see how far we go
but right at the moment it's going great
i'm really thrilled about it
uh
we've actually decided to invest more in it
because
uh
we're hiring more people because it seems to be working so well
so we've been talking a lot about intelligence
uh
you know
however
that might exactly be defined
i think rural on campus pitch what we need when we talk about intelligence
the video cortex is this map
this ability
you know
however you might exactly want to define it
but we've also talked
you know
we
we've
um
a little bit moved
you talked about motivations about
you know
which may you know
relate more to dopamine or whatever you know in the brain there you just run on your cortical intelligence
so in your book use you
and of course dedicate a good chunk of it to these questions of motivations
risks of benefits
yeah
and you describe yourself as someone who is pretty skeptical about
like severe risks
um
so one of your
one of the things which i fully agree with
by the way
is you very phenomenally describe how intelligence is kind of like having a map
either
the map itself has no immunizations
it's not good or evil
it's
you know
it's just a tool it could be used to do something nice or something good
or it could be used to do something bad
um
the map itself is
you know
it's orthogonal to these kind of questions of motivations and you know
good or bad
it kind of feel the human idea of you
we can't get it out from the news
but
at some point
of course
when we actually build these systems
we don't want a lot to be in there
right
you know
we do want our system to actually do things
at some point
we'd only grow about sitting there and know everything
but never take the actions
and the book
you
for example
gives you the example of
you know
we want them
you know to go to mars and then
you know
build a colony and not just sit around the sun all day
thinking about the universe or whatever
so at some point we have to introduce some kind of motivational system
the brain seems to solve this
according to this
which called the old breed
and um
i'm not sure exactly which parts you found of the oval prey and versus the newborn
but some of perfect obvious
you know we have circuits that give us hunger
or you know you have other motivations or whatever
but it's and
but it seems like these parts are will be very important that
okay
let's assume your project goes fantastically here
20 years in a mentor
is the biggest ai company in the world
yeah
you figured out the neocortex
you've created a wonderful algorithm on
at some point
we have to inject motivation
i'm sure you agree with
yeah
and we have to assure that those motivations aligned here in like what we want
and that seems like a hard problem
maybe if you talk a little bit about that
well
i don't know if it's a heart problem
i think the concern that people have about this is that these machines will evolve their own motivations
that that
or somehow they
they are some sort of
you know
epiphenomena disappears
um
and
i i don't think that's right
um
i think we will have to work hard to put them in there
like i mentioned earlier
um
it will not be easy
uh
we'll have to design what how these systems work
um
unless we put this machine in some sort of evolutionary um structure
whether it's a self-replicating machine or it just uses evolutionary algorithms
genetic algorithms to decide what its motivations are
um
they won't modify themselves
they won't change on their own
you know
um
i i gave the very simplistic example of a self-driving car
but i think it's a correct example
you know
i tell the car where i want it to go
it's not going to decide to go someplace else
because today it feels different
you know it's
i could make a call that does that
but why would i do that
i'm not going to design a car to do that
so if we send roll rods to mars to build uh machines
i'll have to be motivated to solve the tasks they've been given
um
and
but we will also build in all kinds of safeguards
just like we built in safeguards into cars
and we won't allow the machines to
you know
it won't be a mysterious process
it'll be like a self-driving car
it's not going to be something we don't understand that happens and runs away from us
it will be difficult to do
we can make mistakes
we can put in bad things and machines will do bad
things
but it's not like the machines on their own are going to do this
it's not like we've just enabled this beast
that's just going to take over and decide on its own what its motivations are
so i make it very clear in the book that there are a lot of risks with ai
and a lot of bad things can happen with it
but i
my only contention is that the fears of existential risk
uh
are overblown
i don't think it's true at all
and that the arguments don't really hold up
um
because there are more arguments based on ignorance
as opposed to some detailed knowledge of how these things are going to work
so did i answer
i absolutely agree with you
uh
i
i happily agree with you that these
like epiphenomenal explorations or naive
you know
a lot of like sci-fi depictions are like
the robot becomes conscious
it wakes up and it decides to rebel against its master
of course that's a pretty silly person
not everyone thinks that's silly
by the way
so i
i
i know i i
and i'm well aware that
on everything facility
but i feel there is a stronger
a similar argument
that's
i don't consider the same argument but has similar consequences
and in a way it's kind of like
in your book
you have a chapter titled how the new tortex can thwart the old brain
and you yourself describe the old brain as the motivational system
and now you're describing the neocortex
the new brain plotting to thwart the goals put in by
you know the
you know
our creator
you know evolution or whatever
so it seems like our
why
wouldn't our machines maybe have similar capability interests to like modify their own old brain
quote
unquote
that's interesting
um
uh
yeah
i can see your point there
um
let me see
i
no one's ever asked me that before so let me just think about a second
um
well
the way i view that with the
you know
the old brain's trying to sort something okay
so
first of all
then
yeah
the new bridge is going to like overtake the open
so the new
the neocortex
that's
it has a model of the world
and the model is very consistent and it strives to have consistent models
it wants
it wants to make its model correct
that's one motivation it has if it sees something wrong
it tries to correct it in this model
so he has this model of the world and says
okay
the world ought to work like this
if a happens a b happens and c happens
and that's good
uh
but then you know
the old break comes along and says
nope
we
don't
we're not going to do that
we see a and b
we're going to go x and uh
and so it violates the model in some sense
right
it's like
while it's the model and so
um
generally
the new neocortex uh
is not able to overcome the older brain things
it just we just give in to our desires and emotions
uh
but we just struggled with it
um
so i guess you're saying
where does the motivation for the from the neocortex come
how does it decide that its model is more important than the old branch model
um
and i
i don't
it's a good question
i'll have to think about it some more
but i think that the root of it will be that the motivation
the true
and only motivations the neocortex has is to make its model the world correct and to fix errors
um
and um
that is
it says this isn't right
my model says this isn't right
uh
we
you know
i want to correct my model
but i'm being told not to
or i'm being told to do things that are violating the model
um
and so that is its motivation
now you could take that to some extreme
let's get a little sci-fi here right
you could take this to some extreme and
uh
say
well
um
the neocortex really figures out how the world works
the future brain ai and neophytes really figure out how the world works and humans got it all wrong
you know
uh
let's let's bring it to an example
we could
we can relate to
there is no god
all right
i know i figured this out
there's no god
you guys all believe in this
but it's not true
so
uh
what do we do
about that is
is this ai system
uh
put up with it
or is it
or does it do something about it
or does it just keep trying to prod humans to do something differently
um
i don't know
it's a good question
i think you bring up
that's a very interesting philosophical question
um
i will say this
i don't think this is something that's going to happen fast quickly overnight
you know it's
it's
it's not
this is something we don't have time to think about this quite a bit
um
but it does bring up a question
what if
the the world as as a smarter machine unknows
it violates the world
as we'd like to believe it
and that's really the the
the friction you're talking about
and
um
what should we do about that
there's an even more direct like kind of physical assault on this
that doesn't require much philosophy
it's just what about the traditional mechanisms that created life
which is variation
and you know random variation and natural selection
so for example
if we send robots to mars to build a colony
they're going to get damaged and destroyed
a boulder is going to fall on them
so they're going to need to be programmed to replicate themselves they're going to have to be programmed to build replacements of themselves
and they're not going to be able to do that with absolute 100 fidelity
so errors will creep into the
the neurons or the silicon neurons or the programming or whatever
and so you've already got in place
the requirements for evolution
which is information transfer or self-replication oh
i'll push
i'll push back on that
first of all
uh
hanging
robots
self-replicate is really really hard
are they gonna build their own semiconductor chips
you know
are they gonna
mind their own
you know
titanium
i mean i don't know
but
but but even if they do
evolution requires a very complex structure for
um
how information is represented and and requires that information be changed constantly in our offspring
right
you know
so when we build
we build
you know
computer chips of nvidia builds index chip
they
they're all pretty much going to be identical
um
so i i push back on the idea
that there's inherent evolution built in any kind of self-replication i don't think that's true
i think we're if it
if there's some variation
it would be very
very minor
and and and it's not going to be passed on genetically to somebody else
you know
there's going to be some blueprint
how to build this ship
which is the neocortex
the blueprint itself isn't changing
so if i
if
i
if i build a neocortex from the blueprint that slightly got an error in it
that's not going to be propagated to its children
um
so i think there's a lot of ways you
there's a lot of things you have to do to create evolution
it's not easy
um
and i don't think that's going to happen accidentally
so i'm pushing back
keith
i don't think that's going to happen
you know it's good
it's good to think about it
ask that question
right
but you know
i don't think
so
i think
in reality
if you're sending robots to mars
but you know
in the chapter in the book i mentioned this point that we could send robots across the universe
and then they would have to self-replicate right
and after i wrote it
i said
oh damn
i don't know how to do that
i just don't know how you know
a fleet of robots
you know
ai systems appear on another planet in some distant part of the galaxy
and they have to replicate themselves
what would be the physical form
of those ai systems that they would be able to do that in any reasonable amount of time
and effort
because you know
just think about again
i mentioned
like semiconductor factories
right
you know
it's like they're gonna build those things
how do they do this
so it made me it
it was a hole in my argument that we could send ai systems across the universe
and i didn't put out
pull out the whole
i said to myself
well
i
i excuse myself in this regard by saying
well
you know what
if we're going to send ai systems to other parts of the universe
they're not going to be built of silicon chips there may have to be some other manifestation that
like biology is able to replicate
uh
on its own without the use of
um
these complex
uh
other systems like semiconductor factories and
um
but we're so far from knowing how to do anything like that today that
i don't know
and then maybe we'd be in trouble
right
we send these things over there
they evolved and they come back
and yes
i don't know
but we're talking a long time from now
yeah
that's for sure
there is a kind of failure mode of thinking
you know too far ahead into the sci-fi future and you're just kind
of generalizing your fictional evidence
yeah
you know
i guess what i
um
so what i have taken from
like your
your obsession
your book didn't for now
kind of about like motivations and essential risk is that i think
actually
uh
at least except essential risk
people that i personally find interesting
they agree with you in like a lot of ways
actually
in that
i think a lot of them are very reasonable in the sense of saying
like
you know whether it's fast or short
it's kind of like
you know
it's kind of beside the point and you try to see
humans already
kind of you know
hard to control and like you know it's like
if you actually try to think about
how would we write a motivation system
because you know it can't really be a learning system because you know
like in your book
you give an example
where if the brain comes up with two ways to get to food
and one of the path has a tiger on it
the old brain will say you know kind of like
oh no
don't go there
but you know the whole brain
how does it know that a tiger is bad
that's like also like
not obvious to me
how we would necessarily learn that
so i guess it just it feels to me that
um
as you so say you're focused on the neocortex
which i think is an important thing to be working on
but maybe we can agree on that
some work on these motivational systems and control problems might also be justified
oh yeah
sure
i'll totally agree with that
um
i
i think it's justified and necessary
but i'm not scared of it
and you know the the conversation
sometimes people we shouldn't be doing this research because it's going to get out of control
aren't you kidding me
it's gonna be so hard to do this at all
you know nothing's gonna get out of control
um
so we need to do that
we should do it
the conversation we're having today is great about that kind of stuff
but i guess it's just not
you know this
there are quite a few people feel this existential risk is
you know
upon us
and
and in any day now
you know it'll be too late
therefore
you know we have to stop all this stuff
and i
it's just i can't see that in any possible scenario
but yeah
we have to think about these things right
we have to figure out
not because i'm
it's scary or dangerous
because we have to figure out
because we have to do it and and i use the example of the book about
you know
we put in safeguards
my car doesn't always listen to me when i
if i'm about to hit something
my car puts the brakes on
even if i put the accelerator down
ignores me
well
we have to put in some some fail-safe systems too
um
in these systems
so they don't
you know
end up damaging things
but it all has to be done
i had a question on on intelligence
i'm fascinated on the nature of intelligence
and you were saying in your in your book that you know the traditional go-fi people had a task
specific skill conception of intelligence
and then it moved towards more of a flexibility model
so being able to learn
and there's also a really interesting tradition in cognitive science about embodiment
which i think is fascinating
and you know
my favorite person is francois chorley
he says that intelligence is the infamous
well
i think he says it's the task acquisition efficiency and generalization
but but also
quite
you know
now we've been talking about this a lot
and there's this interesting idea that you can think of intelligence as the ability to um acquire knowledge
so almost all of the knowledge that humans acquire in their lifetime is
is not empirical in trial and error
it's given through instruction or reasoning and deduction and some
some magic happens with these intelligent systems
you know
why
why can we deduce so much knowledge
is that a question to me
yes
uh
why why i mean mechanistically
well
how do we do that
i mean i
i think i've
i thought i answered this earlier
so maybe i'm
i don't want to repeat myself too much
um
and maybe i don't understand the question
well
for example
you know
you knock the beer bottle off the table
you can now reason that the floor is wet
someone might slip up on on the floor
yeah
so almost all of the the knowledge that we that we have around the world is deduced
or well
it's it's
it's deduced that knowledge that you had to learn that
through observation
if you had never experienced liquids and you never started slipping on liquids
you never experienced knocking a cup over
you wouldn't know what's going to happen
i mean that's what kids do
little babies do this
right
they're like
oh
look what happens that we could live in a world where liquids fall up
and that would be a perfectly good world
and that's what we learn
um
so i won't think we deduce
this
we observe it and and then by analogy
we we predict
uh
how other things that are similar would behave similarly
but i think you know
to me
the way i look at it is you're born with this with this structure in your head
that is designed to learn the world through eyes
and ears and touch
um
but it really in the neocortex knows almost nothing about what it's going to learn
the old parts of the brain
that's not true
right refining refining questionnaire because i'm
i'm also fascinated
by this concept
that i learned it from the first time in your book
that the neocortex now i was going to say blank slate
but keith would kill me for saying that it's not a blank slate
it's a template
because there's actually there's a lot of evolutionary knowledge that's gone into there
yeah
because you
because you can think
you know
it's just learning all these signals
but just the way the ear has evolved over time
that the information gets encoded in a certain way
the cochlear has the logarithmically spaced bands and so on
so it's learnable because it's been encoded in in a certain way
but people like chomsky
they say that we have a kind of universal grammar or language built into our brains
and it was endowed
by evolution
so where do you kind of draw
that
does he say that about all knowledge about the actual language
i thought he just said that about language about language
yeah
so i don't know
i mean
but we're
we're talking about all knowledge now
right
so like it's so you know
so i think
look
there
is
there's all these assumptions about the how how the cortex is connected to things right
and how it's internally connected
that have been evolutionary advantageous
and so you know
we
we only see certain spectrum of light
because that's a good spectrum to look at
and we only certain types of you know sensory inputs
because those are things that we process them before they get to the near cortex
so that they're in the right form for the neocortex to work
um
we allocate a certain amount of our neocortex to these different sensory modalities
because that seemed to be the right thing to do from an evolutionary point of view
um
and so there's a good good example to say
it's like a template that's right
but the in the ins
what's actually learned in that template is is
um
is unknown in terms of language
i i hated it this
when i talked about language in the chapter about high level thought in the book
and i don't consider myself an expert in language at all
um
but it occurs to me that if vernon melcaster is right
that there is a single cortical algorithm that's basically running everywhere
the language has to be somehow fundamentally mapped on to this algorithm for century
motor modeling through reference frames
and i made the analogy about a big part of languages
it has to do with um recursion and a recursive structures
and and the algorithms in the in the column are really good at that
um
and so to me i would say that you know if i would take
this isn't it
i never thought of this
but if i would say
take the idea that there's a universal language
i would extend it beyond what we call language
i would say there's a universal
uh structure to everything in the world
that we can learn
not everything in the world but everything in the world that we can learn
and
um
that universal structure
is this this
uh reference frame
central motor idea
and um
that universal structure can learn any language
whether it's spoken language or computer language or written language
it can learn any structure that fits into that algorithm
and that could be
you know how staples work and how birds fly and how evolution occurs
these are all everything we know has to fit into that structure
so in some sense i would
i would agree with chomsky
i just think he only focuses on quote language
um
where i would say the universal algorithm is
language is a subset of the universal algorithm that chomsky talks about
that's an interesting idea
i never
i never said that before stuff man
we'll see how it feels about tomorrow
but but there's
there's a fascinating dichotomy
though
isn't that because it's similar to the um bias variance trade-off in machine learning
so you know
evolution has has given us a certain prior and a certain default encoding
and then we have this learnability algorithm
and then what fascinates me is how externalized so much of this stuff is
so there's embodiment
there's all the knowledge in in society that we
we learn language
we're brought up by our parents and and we we acquire the language around us
so how much of it is being pushed down from society
and how much of it is being pushed up from the prior knowledge that we've evolved and inherited
well
i would
i would say there's three things
there is the our knowledge we inherited
there is what we learn on our own just to exploratory behavior
and then what is passed down
which is always always through language
but it could be also through by observation of other humans
um
and um
and what's the balance between those two
well
i think in terms of the neocortex
it's not a lot from the biology and the evolution
in terms of the other parts of the brain
it's very much
so
you know
there's a
if there's evidence that says the prayer collectors is like the old visual system
um
it
it detects snakes and spiders
so people were scared of snakes or spiders
it's not the neocortex is the old by going
ah start a snake
it looks like a snake
and so you know that's not learned
it's there
it's hard to get rid of
um
so there's some of that
but you know
our ability to walk
we don't learn to walk
we actually are programmed to walk
it's just that we did
we haven't finished developing yet
until when we learn to walk
we're really just our nervous system is finished being growing
you don't really learn to walk
so these are these old priors
lots of them
um
and as a human
they're very
very important
you know eating and sex and
and
uh
body functions
and you know
survival
all these things and all there
uh
but from the neocortex point of view
i'd say there's very little
um
it's more just assumptions about the
the
the sensory types of sensory data you're going to get
i mean it's what you know
what strikes me
tim is
it's incredibly
we are so incredibly versatile on what we can learn
i mean just you know
think of all things we learned and i'm sure you know this
you thought about
i'm sure yourself that all the things we learned
we had no evolutionary pressure to do like running these
this kind of podcast and you know
broken computerism and talking about brains
it was incredible
it just just cries out that there's a universal method here that's being applied to any anything
that
not to everything
you know
brains can't learn everything
but they can learn a hell of a lot
and it seems to be
we haven't really discovered the extent of it yet
so this
this says
you know
there's
there is this sort of blank slatish um system
if you want to call it that way
with these assumptions about our bodies built into it
well
the only thing about the the blank slate thing is it's such a dichotomy
because i was reading your book and it seems to be so strongly determined
by the embodiment and the multi modality
you know
the way that we're wired
because you said yourself that ai will actually evolve towards
you know
robotics
basically
it's not just the brain
yeah
it's
it's how it acts in the environment and how it gets with those senses
but i wanted to ask one one final thing
so i went to a yoga retreat at the weekend
and after the physical components of the practice were concluded
matters of a philosophical nature
uh
were investigated
and the basic case that the yoga teacher was making is that we have two selves
right
we have the emergent social self and then we have the inner self
which i'm sure sam harris probably might spoke to about
you know the sense of being and the sense of being is
when you kind of ignore the virtual social program on the top
and you know a society
it is an emergent virtual program and it does many of the things that the cortical columns are doing
it has the error correction it had
you know
it's the externalization and distribution
so
even though we're programmed to care a lot about our social selves
um
we are very stressed when we lose control of our own narrative
because someone might be saying something bad about us on twitter
so anyway
this yoga teacher was saying
well
there's something deeply fulfilling
um
spiritually about just kind of um going into your mind and and just just that raw conscious experience
but then i felt like saying to him
well
you should read jeff hawkins book
because your mind is just a load of prediction models and all you're doing is traversing your reference frames
so what do you
what do you think i don't
i
well
i again asked me to talk about things i'm not too familiar with
but i'll tell you
i'll tell you a personal experience
i have
okay
i don't do meditation
and and sam didn't bring that up
but but i thought about it a bit
i do something equivalent to meditation
um
is that when i find things in the world
stressful
um
i just sort of shut out the world
and i think about interesting problems like the future of humanity or the future of intelligence
what's the nature of life and things like this
and so now i'm living in this world that is sort of
um
is in some sense
uh
pure
right
it's not
it's not being messed up with
like i'm hungry
or this person's being nasty to me or just like tuning it all out
like
oh my god
i'm not in trouble again
and then
so i think that's my own personal meditation
and i don't think i think it's useful actually
because
uh
i think it helps when you
when you think like that
you
you're
you're sometimes able to get to deeper truths
um
that you separate the body functions and the day-to-day stuff
and and i often do my best thinking when there are no distractions either on that
sometimes while i'm driving or sometimes i'm just awake at night lying in bed
um
but where there's like
i don't i don't have to deal with anything else
so that's kind of like meditation
and i find
i don't think it's useful
i think it's very useful because you
it allows the brain to sort of separate out from the old brain stuff
and um
and just have run a bit
sometimes it comes up some good ideas
you know exactly
i couldn't attest to that
well
um
jeff hawkins
thank you so much for joining us today
it's been an absolute honor
well
it's been a pleasure
you guys are great
i really
i enjoy all your questions
you're really fun and i think this is one of the
one of the more meaningful conversations i've had in a long time
i'm serious
you know
because hey
you know what you're talking about
you know what i'm talking about
you ask great questions
you're really deep thinking about all this stuff
so i think that's wonderful
thank you so much appreciate that
thank you so much
all right
well
i hope it helped
it was good for you guys
so that was a wrap
how was that guys
it's pretty great
um
and honestly
yeah
i'm really pressed
it was really nice to talk to them
it's just clearly
you know
it was like so much more than was in the book
uh
it
building
the book was really just scratching the surface
and
uh
i wish we had
like
you know
like just taking off for a beer and like really dig into some of the degrees
yeah
what i i love
uh
i love people like him because he's so smart and and smart and a very
um
he has such great common sense right
so
when you
when you ask him questions
he comes back with these really informative answers that are very
uh
concrete
and you understand what he's talking about
so it's really fun to talk to him
i mean
a very
very
great learning experience
yeah
i got the impression that his research focus has changed a little bit
so when we were doing some preparation for this
we were looking a lot into the htm algorithm
which i understand is now
um
they're pivoting away from that a little bit
so he was talking about some stuff that they're doing with transformers models and sparsity
and quite a few things i haven't heard about
and also he was really focused on
um
the particular way of thinking about cognition using these reference frames
which he spoke about in his book
which i think is actually a slight departure from from um
some of the stuff the mentor has had out about five years ago
yeah
but i definitely got the feeling that he had like so much interesting stuff
that's just not quite ready yet for public consumption
but
um
hopefully
in the book
i often have this feeling like
ah
the city
just you know
it feels like there's more to this than there is in the book
maybe
or maybe just needs more time
and i think i remember reading the book
it took like a year and a half to write
or so
so
maybe
even right here
you know
lots of things been happening
um
so i do look forward to whatever he's gonna publish in the future
well
what i love too is you know he's more than willing to admit
look
i've changed my views
you know
i think
yeah
lots of people run into are not able to do that
and if you agree with chalet's
you know
measure of intelligence
the mark of intelligence is the ability to assimilate new information and to learn from it
and most of the people we talk to just want to stay adamantly entrenched
you know
no
look
this thing that i called xyz back
you know
30 years ago
you're wrong that it was limited to this little area
it actually encompasses everything
you know
that that works now
like nobody ever wants to admit that they've learned or changed or that science has evolved
i want to push back on that a little bit because there is something really special
i know we were joking that science advances one funeral at a time
but there is something really special about people who have an idea and they see it through
just like yan lacoon and the deep learning pioneers
everyone was asking them why the hell are you doing this in the 1990s
and they and they hung on and it was worth hanging on
and it's a similar thing with
with some of the approaches from nomento
they've been at this for such a long time now
and there is some really really kind of biologically inspired
and plausible reasons why this might lead to something interesting in the future
but clearly they've been at this for a long time and and they've been sticking at it
well
nothing
nothing's wrong with perseverance
but perseverance without adaptation is wrong
it's just perseverance when you're right
is right
and prince raised when you're wrong
is bad
you're never 100
right
and you're right
you're never 100.
so that's the whole point is
you've got to be able to learn
you have to be able to
well
the learning rate needs to be about 0. 01
sure
and the party centers
3 e minus 4
i think is the correct learning rate for all matters in life
yeah
all the matters specifically
and i agree
like also
i
i'm really glad i got to talk to jeff about essential risk or something
because of course
you know
i take some songs pretty seriously
yeah
it's a very common experience to hear people dismiss and extensively
because they've heard the bad versions of the arguments
if there are some heroin encouragements of these arguments
that it's even from some very smart people like
yeah
some smart people i feel do the field a great justice than i just can't feel bad
they're against
um
and it was really nice to see you know him
say like
yeah
you know what something we're thinking about
and
um
i
i think
honestly
a lot of the disagreement comes down to that
yeah
like
i agree with him and almost everything really
so they're not those relationships
i was really impressed with with his response
and as you say
you can see it from so many different perspectives
so you can cover it from a grand perspective
talking about paper clips and um
oh my god
but
um
i lost my train of thought
yeah
so he
i read the
uh
the less wrong article which you linked to me was that steve burns
yeah
secrets
so that was fascinating
so so he was saying that
um
at the end of the day
you've got a robot rover on mars or something like that
and at some point you need to actually give it something to do
and you might give it an instruction
and then it might really want to complete that instruction
so it might predict that you're about to give it another instruction
it says
oh my god
he's about to give me another instruction
i've not done the first thing yet
so i need to kill him
and that's not completely beyond the realms of possibility
now i i agree with charlotte that i think intelligence is externalized
it is embodied and there are many like natural environmental
limiting steps to intelligence
and you could talk about all the replication stuff as hawkins did
but that's just a simple example
i'm just an intelligent agent on on mars and i i need to have motivation
because i need to be told what to do
what am i doing
am i building a base and then i can plausibly see how that could be
um
you know
misdirected
yeah
i feel like it's it the intelligence explosion
arguments
i'll get mixed up with these
like motivational
uh
concerns
which i think is unfortunate because they really aren't blocking all like you could like these
these concerns about
you
know
alignment and about motivation will crop up
whether you know
it takes 10 years or a thousand years for ai to come to be
at some point
s hawkins
i think
gonna pick
so when we put
the work needs to be done at some point
you just have to build a safety mechanism
at some point
you have to write a motivation system
so that's why i think this
you know
kind of research
even if intelligence blows
it doesn't happen is still something needs to get done
yeah
and and there is this thing
um
i mean you can explain this better than me
but instrumental convergence
which is the idea that
um
you know
many seemingly innocuous goals incidentally lead to dangerous motivations like self-preservation and self-replication and goal preservation
and um
i i can sign on to that
that seems very plausible
yeah
exactly
i mean you give a perfect example
but like you know
you give the rover and the the the job
will
you know
build a thing
but actually it's like
oh
actually
i wanted to build something different
you know
still was motivated
but i went to the first thing
so unless we have
like some really sophisticated
you know
system inside of it allows to like
you could equally value
doing this or do with another human
self-encourageability and which we don't currently really love
but implement formally
um
it's very likely that it will
you know
having instrumental goals like keeping itself alive
so
and where you're stopping you from giving it your orders
like it maybe will damage its entirement or something
so you can't give it orders
or maybe
if you
if you're now
if you try to destroy the broker because this malfunctioning
maybe they'll retaliate
because if it's destroyed it can't build habitat
no
can it
so so yeah
there's a lot of ghouls like this
also also like delayed power seeking goals to sleep obviously
yeah
if you don't know how to achieve a goal
and gaining your power is probably like always a good move
you know
getting more money
more social capital
you know
controlling for people
the driver resources
like almost always a good thing
like almost
no matter how innocuous
the goal might seem
yeah
but see
like
on the other hand
i don't care if a rover on mars tries to retaliate
it has like no capability to retaliate on us at all
and so the only kinds of like artificial intelligence i worry about are ones
that are capable of expanding in some capacity
like they have to be able to build things
and they actually have to be able to build intelligent things
so that's why i brought up the point of
you know
if we have a robot
we're gonna need one that can build
you know
somehow
or another
replicas of other robots to expand
conduct more work
replace ones that were broken
whatever
and it's not so infeasible to believe that
at some point in the next few hundred years
you know we'll have 3d printing technology more than sufficient to build silicon chips and you know whatever else
and as soon as you have a system that's self-replicating
and we don't live in a perfect world and we have random variation
right
and they have sets of instructions
and also we're going to need them to adapt to new environments
like it's going to be diff
difficult
different
building it on the plains of mars versus deep down in the valleys and mining water or whatever
so they're going to have to have some capability to allow variation
you know
then you have the mixture for evolution
and once you have evolution
even if you had no goals
like
think of it this way
the ultimate thing which has no motivations whatsoever was inanimate matter
and that's what the earth was four billion years ago
and we wound up with animate objects that have goals
so despite philosophers
and this is kind of an interesting thing
philosophers are always like
you can never get ought from is
but interestingly enough
ought arose from just stuff
right
yeah
the very elegantly said
there's this weird kind of symmetry breaking that happens somewhere
i mean in evolution
the symmetry breaking happened is because of physics
because things that don't want to replicate
don't replicate
so we don't see them
so we found the first one from
is comes from just the fact that if there is a possibility of replicator and the possibility non-replicator eventually
you will only see replicators
and that's your first symmetry breaking
and corporate occurs
that hopefully be
you know
when we build intelligent systems is that maybe we can break the symmetry in a more
in a less dystopian you know than a malthusian way and build systems that aren't more motivated
but i think to be considered better than just for your replication
but it's very non-obvious to me
you know how to do that safely
it's hard
it's a hard trouble
but hawkins did say though that he was more worried about the immediate threat of um humans
controlling the kind of ai that we have now
or the kind of ai we have now being used for bad purposes or or even things like
um
the spread of false beliefs
that's incredibly dangerous as well
and that that replicates like a virus
that's why that
um
you know that social dilemma documentary
like
i thought this was a very brilliant quote that was in there
and a lot of other people think it's like not an interesting quote
but to me it was beautiful when
uh
you know
undermining
exactly
he said we've always been worried about when ai would overcome our strengths
when we should have been worried about when it would overcome our weaknesses
right and that
and it's already
you know
even though we don't have
maybe we forget
if we have real intelligence or not
or whatever
clearly
these machine systems have overcome lots of our weaknesses
and they've created things that are more addictive than they've ever been found
ways to waste more of our time than now
of course there's offsetting things like
yeah
we also get greater productivity here
etc
but we should be worried about
when it overcomes our weaknesses and what that's doing to us and our children
and you know
one of my favorite examples is it's called the food optimizer
so this comes from
and yeah
called roku
and he makes this example that
so
the way he describes it is
that in like the 19th century we collectively summoned a weak super intelligence to feed all humans
i think the deal was kind of this
this capitalist
you know
market system will produce really cheap food for us
but the system was optimizing a reward signal based on profit
of course
let's see how these things work
so it's kind of like a weak
it's not sent huge
it was obviously not intelligent
the weight you know humans are
but a weed is option
rising system
it optimized for more and more food
and now we're at the point that you know what
60 of adults in the western world are obese
something
we are literally eating ourselves to death
and this is a very
very weak intelligence quote and this is already powerful enough in a way to you know
get people to basically kill themselves voluntarily
so imagine if you gave such a motivation
you know
biggest
food corporation in the world
you know
build their big
their big agi
you know
using hawkins
thousand brandon algorithm
of course
uh
and give you the motivation of
you know
smith roth
yeah
but this
this gets to utility and similarly hawkins said
oh
you should never clone yourself
because you're not cloning
you're forking
i thought that was a bit of a contradiction
though
because he was talking about
um
you know
sending clones of yourself to mars or seeding mars
that's right
and that's the same thing
isn't it
you're actually forking the human race when you have a population of humans on on mars
i don't think
um
who doesn't like forking what's wrong with that
well
no
but the thing is because you
we
we're doing it because we want to leave a legacy
you know
i
i like doing this youtube channel because you know
after i'm dead
people can see who is that tim scarf guy
but um
but you know you might say i'm going to create a clone of myself
because i want to have a legacy
but it's not a legacy
because after
after the next day it becomes a
you know
it's a different person
it's not connor anymore
and similarly
when you were talking about
um
you know
why don't we restructure society because let's take away social media
let's let's fork and take away facebook and everything else
but what's your utility function
how could you
how could you justify that ourselves in that parallel universe would be better off than we are now
well
first of all
i mean i think it would be a legacy
so you
and i both think that that the pixels on youtube are going to be a legacy
and those are a pale pale shadow of a
you know
projection of us right
so i would
totally
you know
a clone of you or a robot programmed with your mind state or something that then can go off
and live its own life
that's exactly what a legacy is like that
that is a legacy
it's not me
it's a legacy
yeah
like i described to even more extreme crazy
uh
versions of this kind of thing is like i
i fundamentally believe
i'm like you know a non-dual identity
and like that
most of the kinds of identity is kind of incoherent
it's just it's just a convenient abstraction in humans
like humans tend to be discreet
that's just a convenient property that humans have to have happen to have
there's no reason that identity or minds in the sense have to be discrete like this
it just happens to be the case that humans come in packages
it looks like they become in
you know
one intelligence please one unit of intelligence
but there's everything you should study
they have it
they have a mark
they have to have a markov blanket exactly exactly
but there's no reason you can't have systems that don't really
there's not like a clear separation between them like the
the only reason i think really me and tim aren't the same person
it's because the bandwidth between our brains is really low is interbreed
it's lower that it is intraprey
like
why is the right heart for memory
maybe that's the person in the left hand
also a different person
depending on your definition
like you know
there's like split brain patients
where like the brain has to actually disagree and like take different actions and like fight with each other
so like really different people
i don't think
so i think
what makes identity a synchronization in a sense or like alignment
so you see is that identity
the best way to define identity is alignment with agua
is that
like
does the
the system coherently act without
you know
like shooting itself from the foot
so to speak
or like you know
doing at all
so like
that's why i think it's a really great argument that
for example
ant colonies
for one animal that happens to have
like
you know
very big individual parts
because in a way it is aligned
you know not all the parts were produced
you have a reproducing part
you have
you know
fighting for death
eating parts or whatever
food
getting parts or whatever
and they happen to not all be one body that's just an implication detail
you were also just colonies of cells
you know
it's
it's just
it's just implementation details and matters
is the coherency with the synchronization
of
you know
knowledge and goals in life
yeah
but again
a lot of that is is emergent
but you were saying as well that
um
there's a kind of there's a
there's an i o bottleneck when we communicate
and this is
um
a lot of people talk about neural link in this context as well
but i don't think there is
because when we communicate
there's common knowledge that we both have
so it's a fairly efficient communication mechanism
and we're invoking lots and lots of very complex knowledge that we've reconciled
so when we read a book or when we
when we take on board information
the bottleneck is comprehension
i don't think it's the
the bandwidth
sure
as it depends on how like
and by bandwidth
i also meant comprehension back
it's like if i could
literally
i imagine we
could
you know
take
two human brain would put them in the same skull
and could like to connect them through some super cleopas closeum or whatever
and you know
let the whole thing synchronize and you're not diet seizures immediately or whatever
i think there's an arsenal argument to be made
that is one entity
but you could also make an argument's two connected entities and simply just becomes continuous
like a classic play open when something seems confusing
if there's a discrete quantity
evolved
try try continualizing the quantity and see if the confusion disappears
very cool
well
gentlemen
it's been a pleasure
so see you next week
folks see you next week