so,
i don't know if you know, but i
i was on a twitter spaces with you like four months ago,
and we were we were talking about micro strategy, and it was pretty cool.
we were just talking about your thoughts on bitcoin,
but
i've been i've
been a fan
for a while,
and
i'm,
you
know, happy
you're
joining
the stream.
awesome, man.
yeah.
thanks.
nice to hook up with you.
all right.
so, bunch of how much time?
what?
30 minutes?
you got 30 minutes?
whatever you want.
yeah.
okay, cool.
here we go.
uh, first of all, big fan of goodell.
i actually paid for it, so oh, thank you.
great.
yeah.
i i got into that $60 a month tier a while ago.
now i have to be nice to you.
now you have to be nice to me.
good.
i i have your bloomberg competitor right here.
i i can't i i can't i can't say anything nasty at this point.
you're a customer, so i i work for you.
there we go.
um
okay,
so
my audience
has really been interested in your thoughts in a variety of different areas.
pounder, nvidia, bitcoin, quantum.
so i think we can take those one by one, but
i think we'll start off with the elephant in the room.
everyone has been wondering
why you are short quantum
and how quantum is going up four 5x.
is it just retail hype momentum or do you
the guy who has done pretty well for himself in life in terms of managing money
not understand the quantum thesis?
so i'll just lay it out there.
are you right or are the shorts going to get burned on quantum?
yeah.
so i mean i think this is going to be one of the biggest
trades in my in my career.
i think that
um
and and my career is is not as you know is it's it's not in trading.
my career is in in being an entrepreneur.
i built drug companies.
i'm building a software company now.
so, it's not really one of these things where i,
you know, have wanted to or or i'm going to,
you know, be a hedge fund manager.
i've never really wanted to do that.
and,
um, you know, nevertheless, i find myself compelled
because this is this is one of the craziest things i've ever seen.
it it's, uh, you know, there really hasn't been anything like this.
i don't know if ever is the right term,
but it's it's it's
really a remarkable thing that's going on in the market.
and it's it's it's wrapping a lot of
people who are new to the market into it.
and i think it's it's,
you know, there's there's something like this happens, you know, every few years.
we had the cannabis rally, we had nftts,
we had, you know, 3d printing,
we had there's a lot of little mini bubbles, but this one's pretty preposterous.
i mean, 3d printing could have been a thing.
cannabis could have been a thing,
you know, and you just have to sort of wait and see.
and then when all the cannabis companies reported earnings, they were really bad.
gross margins were negative.
you can't build a business on negative gross margins.
and
um you know, you sort of watch and and kind of like decide that okay,
you know,
this is a cool and exciting idea, but the business just isn't there.
quantum is sort of like that.
there's just no possible way that these companies could be successful.
um my girlfriend, there's no way they could be successful.
no way.
yeah.
so, so my girlfriend's a,
you know, we're
a lot of people are experts
and we we
talk to all the same experts
everyone else does.
you know, all the big names in the field,
but the big names in the field are telling you that it's not possible.
scott aronson, again, my girlfriend worked with him at mit and at openai.
and in essence, you know, scott just doesn't believe that quantum's coming anytime soon.
worse than that, there's four quantum stocks.
regetti, d-wave, ion q, and quantum computing inc., correct?
two of those are frauds.
so, ion q and regetti are actually trying to build a quantum computer.
now, i think that's 30 years away.
even if you do build it, there's nothing there.
but d-wave and quantum computing inc., in my opinion,
you know, and i know other people disagree,
they are complete scams.
so d-wave has been around 20 years.
they've never they made six computers, six generations of their computers.
they've never worked.
you can't find a customer who says they work.
you can't find a customer who
actually
uses the machines in production in software we call production
live setting, the real deal.
not just, you know, trying it out, see if this thing could work someday,
but actually like
no, this is a part of our business,
right?
no one, not a single one that i'm aware of.
and again, if the company could could show one,
i i i challenge them to do so.
but, you know, so i'm shorting these stocks.
qci was a beverage company.
they're under investigation by the sec.
not that i love the sec,
but you know, i think that,
you know, this is a company that basically didn't exist before.
they had $30,000 of revenue last quarter.
30,000. you know, your stream and my stream do more than that.
and i think that, you know, for this to be a two billion dollar
publicly traded company
that has a, you know, a quantum is is just silly.
again,
why in your in your professional opinion,
how did we get to two billion off 30,000
in revenue?
liquidity.
so, it's it's it's liquidity.
i i love you, your stream, your viewers.
i love my viewers.
not all of our viewers are the sharpest tools in the shed.
there are a few of amongst us who are not great at investing.
you're you're excited,
you want to buy the next nvidia,
so do i, but you have to look through thousands of stocks to find the one
gem.
and that's not what people do.
people are lazy.
they they don't want to do that.
they want to read reddit.
they want to watch a youtube.
they see one thing that sounds exciting.
oh, that sounds like the future.
i'm going to buy that.
and you know, that's typically what happens.
nftts were the same way.
cannabis was the same way.
how could you deny the sexiness of cannabis?
you got a hundred-y old tobacco industry in the us, hundred billion dollar companies,
and now you have weed.
oh my god, this is going to be huge.
well, it turns out the business fundamentals just weren't that good.
and the till raise went down 95%, aurora cannabis down 95%,
etc. and the reality just hits you sometimes.
and we all want to buy growth stocks.
we all want to buy exciting stocks that could be the future.
but you also have to do do your homework.
and and you know the ceo of ionq, former ceo and founder
had this very esoteric podcast
a physics podcast.
i thought he was tweeting about it yesterday.
yeah.
629 nanometer.
it's it's like the nerdiest thing you can imagine, but this is where you find alpha.
and he went on there and he said quantum computing is not going to be around
for another 30 years and
there's no application.
we don't know what they're good for literally.
and even nsa.
so, the one thing i can see in quantum is that they would be extremely
good for
for
hacking and and encryption
breaking, you know, and this is like a hobby of mine on the side,
specifically with bitcoin.
and so, i've played with quantum computers.
i've bought every single commercial quantum computer.
i'm a major user of their cloud cloud time.
spent thousands of dollars of my own money on quantum computing.
and i can tell you these machines don't work.
you know, they they can't factor
even the number like a million,
which a child could factor
with a pen and paper,
right?
these quantum computers can't do that.
and it doesn't look like, oh, we're just around the corner.
we're going to get a breakthrough.
in fact, if anything, it looks like we may be at a log jam.
now, technology does progress.
and sometimes you get these discontinuous
jumps where it's like, oh, wow, okay, it didn't work before.
it didn't work before.
and all of a sudden, boom, it works.
kind of like ai.
but the problem is, what are we going for?
what is it that we're going to do when the magic machine shows up?
and nobody can answer this question.
and factoring numbers is fun.
i like doing it.
but the only thing it's good for is encryption.
we've already have postquantum encryption.
in fact, the this the former the guy whose name is chris monroe.
he's a genius.
he's an idol of mine.
yep.
he's probably going to win the nobel prize.
chris said that even the nsa doesn't want a quantum computer, which shocked me actually.
that's way more bearish than i ever was.
um he said that they just want to know when quantum
quantum computers are coming so they could prepare for it.
and i thought that was fascinating
because a lot of people think the nsa has a quantum computer or they're they're they're
really interested in it.
but that impression from the from the founder of ionq was really surprising to me.
i i i wouldn't have characterized it that way.
and again, he's sort of explaining that even the big companies like google and ibm
don't have quantum computers that will work.
he thinks they're wasting their money.
i i want to talk about google and ibm, but here's the question.
if you were the biggest quantum bull on the planet,
what is the use case that you are the most excited about because of quantum?
i think it's people who are these people are confused.
they they don't understand what these computers can or can't do.
so, if you think about computing in general, nvidia is the biggest computing company, right?
and xai,
openai,
these are the companies that buy these machines
and they want to train
models
and run inference.
these are hard to do computationally, right?
quantum could never do those.
it can't do those.
why?
there's no memory.
there's no ram.
there's no way to load the data into the machine.
the machine has 100 cubits.
you could you could how much can you can store your name
in 100 cubits maybe, but you can't store the corpus of the internet at 100 cubits.
it doesn't do that.
i think there's this confusion that like these are normal computers.
you can the the lady i just watched this interview with john presc.
prescll is one of the fathers of quantum computing.
worked with richard fineman at caltech.
he who invented quantum computers, the idea of them at least.
prescll said the interview said, "prescll, can can this make me post on instagram faster?"
and this is like this is not what these machines do.
these are scientific machines and the only people really interested in them are scientists.
you know,
if you had to come up with a use case that is uber bullish,
what would it be?
i mean, there is this idea that you could and listen, i have a vivid imagination.
you know, i can i can try to come up with one
and the best i could give you maybe would be
simulating physics.
so like a really good physics engine.
but this gets back to the to to one really interesting point that jensen wong said.
he said
he had the 10 quantum ceos up on the stage and he said
we don't need a better solution to the traveling salesman problem.
so anybody who knows computing in the house
knows is the np hard problem that traditional computers struggle with.
you cannot if i give you 70 cities to,
you know, 70 blocks of a city
where you have to drop off, you know, mail
all 70 blocks.
what is the optimal route?
that's a really hard question.
combinatorally, it kind of explodes on you.
it's like two to the 70th power or something crazy like that.
but what's funny is that a regular old computer,
a stupid ass laptop can do this equation
close enough.
it gets like a 99% approximate of the perfect answer.
and in fact, quantum computers, it's proven that they don't have a complexity speed up for
for traveling salesmen.
they probably could do it faster.
but the point is
getting a shaving a,
you know, a millionth of a second to get the optimal
mathematical
answer.
this is something scientists are interested in.
this isn't something uber is interested in or or they would be investing.
fedex would be investing in quantum computing.
ups would be investing in quantum computing.
these guys have a lot of money.
they would be doing it.
they're not.
why did jensen why did jensen have them on stage?
so it's interesting you know you know this is really fascinating.
my girlfriend's dad was a senior guy at nvidia
and one of the funny things here
not that that gives me any insight but
you know i've been following
nvidia
my whole life
and
you know it's
the greatest
company in the world.
the the question is
you know so he goes on stage before that and he says quantum's 30 years away.
it doesn't work.
it's not interesting right and the quantum stocks you know fall.
i made like $2 million that day and i
am
sitting
there watching
this
like
oh this is great
you know
and
he shits
on them over and over again and the problem becomes
these quantum
companies call him and say hey man you know you really did a number on
us
you know this is
you know what the hell you know and i think jensen
just in that moment had this flashback
to like
when he
was you know making gpus
and everyone was laughing at him saying ah gpus
don't matter
gpus will never make a difference
and he is obviously right in the long run.
and he basically said, i i can't be that guy, you know?
i can't be the guy [ __ ] on entrepreneurs,
crapping on their dreams, telling them they're never going to work.
i have to at least hear these guys out.
this is the guy who knows the most about computing on planet earth.
and he said in his heart of hearts, he said, "30 years away."
you know, he didn't change his mind.
he didn't say, "ah, you know what?
actually, it's next year." he he still thinks it's 30 years away.
and i feel like again, you know, we all want to be bullish on something.
we all want to get the next 100 bagger.
but just be careful what you wish for because
there's a lot of people that quit the stock market
after they bought wheat stocks and they dropped 90%.
people quit the stock market or or
quit financial life when they bought board apes at a million dollars.
i know a guy who had to sell his private jet,
you know, he bought a ton of board apes and nftts.
this is real life.
you know, he literally was a private jet guy.
jet's gone.
so he still support ape.
i mean be that guy.
there was a guy who bought beles nft for 69 million.
i think it's worth 20,000 from the last projections i saw.
i mean if you want to be that guy,
knock
yourself out,
you know, but i i
feel like
you're paying.
do you think there is so much momentum
in terms of liquidity for re like retail's buying palunteer, tesla, nvidia?
is there
that much free money out there even with more
rates that that money is going into quantum and and these types of stocks?
i think we're in a we're almost in a postmoney
world and i think the way this sounds this is a little philosophical
but
we're we're getting to a point where where money in essence is worthless
you know and things like
um attention is is a new
a new currency
right when you you know it's it's it's kind of anecdotal
here but again
you know hang philosophically for a second
20 years ago in new york city
the average
beautiful
woman
cared about what job you had how much money you had
right
you know nowadays
they might say well how many followers
does he have
you know and it's one of these things that's a really
a shift because what can money buy you?
you know, i had lunch with
peter
teal
like
20 years ago
and he had this iphone
and i'm sitting there saying,
"man,
this guy's worth like hundred
zillion
times
what i'm worth.
i got nothing."
and
you know, i'm just starting my first drug company
and he's got the same phone i do.
there's no luxury.
we're eating the same meal.
you know, what does being rich really get you?
and and the top the inflation's
been the top the highest
the higher the price the asset is.
so sports teams have gone up 20x.
picassos have gone up 10x.
the stuff that you know the bevelin goods have gone up.
the rest of us live the same life as even the wealthiest people.
so money becomes one of these things that's that's really not that important.
when covid happened, our economy didn't go to zero.
everyone kind of threw a party.
you know, it was a very bizarre like, you know, thing.
unemployment's the lowest it's ever been.
i'm not sure.
and then finally, people use real money to chase crazy assets.
a fartcoin,
ethereum,
you know, bitcoin, etc. these are interesting projects, but they're probably not worth trillions of dollars.
and i think the fact that people have disposable income, look, this is a market.
this is a cycle.
you know, at the bottom of the cycle, you know, it'll be different.
and there's always a bottom of the cycle.
and it doesn't feel like if i had to pick,
it feels like we're closer to the top than the bottom.
okay.
so, i have a couple more questions on quantum,
and then i then i want to get into some thoughts around bitcoin,
pounder,
uh, nvidia, broader market.
first of all, martin, we thank you for taking your time, bro.
really appreciate it.
uh, martin's twitter, i'm putting it right here in the chat.
he's doing some awesome stuff building a nice bloomberg competitor.
so you guys can check that out.
there's his twitter right there.
okay.
so here's a question.
are you accusing the quantum ceos of fraud?
um you know, yes and no.
so i think that
i think that
they're,
you know, fra fraud, the definition of fraud is something i'm very familiar with.
um are they knowingly it's a very technical thing.
sometimes i' i've beaten it and i've also lost it.
um yeah, the the technical definition usually is are you knowingly misleading others?
are you knowingly saying false things?
i think the answer to that is unequivocally yes.
um but you know to other people it means other things.
if you have a safe harbor
statement
you wrap yourself
around it and say
well you know these these
are subject
to forward-looking
statements and you know
you know you can kind of do that and say
you know i we may not build a quantum computer tomorrow.
you don't know.
so i think there's like
it's kind it's kind of like you saying not financial
advice
even though you don't believe in saying that right.
yeah.
i don't believe i personally
don't believe in saying that
but but
i do think it's
one of these
disclaimers
where
if you
you know if you really pin down
the
quantum
computing
companies
they would never do an interview with me because i'd say
what date
what date is it coming
and what will it do
and what what's it going to do better and who is going to buy it
and they won't be able to answer these questions because they're hard questions
and the reality is these companies are built on
imaginations
that are wilder than possibility
again like
you know it's okay to have a great imagination
like i have to do that as a business person.
i dream one day that i can bring quantitative
investing to the masses and you can trade like jane street and set it up.
that's my dream.
is it realistic?
maybe, maybe not.
but it's possible.
the quantum stuff is just not possible.
you know, the the laws of physics and computing prohibit what they're talking about.
now, again, could there one day be computers
made by inq or regetti, not by dwaver quantum computing, inc.
because i don't think they have anything at all
and
nobody
even pays those companies
any attention
in the community.
prescll said prescll said that d-wave is a fraud.
u this is a theoretical physics professor.
he doesn't normally go out and call companies fraud.
scott aaron said dwave is a fraud.
um but the real two companies ion q and regetti
you know which are
the also rans these are runs of the litter
right so the big quantum companies are ibm
number one i'd say google number two quantinium number three
sci quantum number four there's six more privates and then ionq and then we're getting
so like these are the runs of the litter these aren't even the good pups
and you know
so
they have a shot at maybe making a quantum computer someday, but there's no obvious
thing they can do.
so to me, fraud means, you know, we know we don't know what the application is.
we know
that we we don't know if we can make these or not,
but we're going to
still stoke
excitement
about it.
now, these companies almost went bankrupt.
so, they've had feast and they've had famine.
they were two years ago, d-wave is this close to bankruptcy
because they couldn't get people excited.
so, as an entrepreneur, i kind of understand it's great when people are excited,
but i do think some of these have been really responsible.
i'll give credit real quick to answer your question definitively.
the regetti ceo has been superb at saying, "don't expect revenue, right?
don't expect us to make a machine anytime soon.
we are a research company.
stop thinking this is a near-term thing." and he's done that.
and i
have to applaud
him for doing that because the other guys are
trying to tell you
quantum
is now.
be excited today.
and look, five
years can a lot can happen in five years, but as of right now, these machines
are completely
useless.
the d-wave came out with some advanced hardware a week ago.
what are your thoughts on that?
yeah, so they won't let anybody try it,
you know, and i think that's very telling
because
iq
lets me use their machine,
you know, despite i'm the biggest, you know, i'm the biggest, you know, skeptic.
ibm lets me use their machine.
uh, brietti lets me use their machine.
new era lets me use their machine.
all of these other companies that have you reached out, did you wave?
i have.
yeah.
and they said, "no,
you you cannot get this machine
without them banging you over the head trying to sell upsell you consulting services."
so many people have published there's a website called archive arxiv.
it's a scientific website.
many many many people who have access to dwave machine have published and showed
that there is no speed up with the dwave machine.
and in fact, you know, friends with a hedge fund called carousel,
they put a short report out.
um carousel does real work.
they're not, you know, you know, uh, scammers.
they they've been in the hedge fun business a really long time.
they don't get everything right.
but in essence, you know, um,
they they they found that
mostly what d-wave
does is they take their quantum computer,
they attach it to a real computer,
they give you the result, and they say, you know,
that that
they're doing something, but really the quantum part is not doing anything.
and a former d-wave employee said that the quantum part's just for show.
so this company's been around 20 years.
they've had six generations of this computer.
they have the latest generation out now.
can't find anybody
that says, "i use this computer and it helps me." can't find a single person.
have you looked into any of the partnerships they have?
any of iota, mastercard, stuff like that?
yeah, we have.
so, so, so all the people we've talked to
have said carisdale and we have talked to almost everybody.
they've pointed out everybody says quietly behind closed doors, it was a research agreement.
it was an attempt.
look, mastercard is a $500 billion company.
it was an attempt to
think about possibly maybe improving
one process at mastercard and it failed.
and there's a reason if if any of these companies
like the d-wave machine, they would have a hundred million in revenue.
they would have a billion in revenue if these machines were useful.
they don't have any revenue.
nobody's buying these [ __ ] things.
well, that's what's been confusing to me.
obviously,
i've got some people that have been excited about quantum
and you know, i saw these stocks at three.
my kind of value investor hat said i can't buy them.
then i see them go to 20
and i'm like, am i the idiot or is yours,
you know, like what's going on here?
and i think you would say,
yeah,
you're
kind of dumb
for
not buying
at
three because it
could have gone
to 20.
but realistically,
chasing it at 20 here is is a little scary.
oh, yeah.
it's nuts, it's nuts to even think about buying them here.
but i would say look at three
you know part part of you know there there was a technology in biotech
um called rnai
and and people were skeptical about rnai including myself and rna rnai
came through it came it happened it really transpired
and it i wouldn't say it changed the face of medicine
but it was a real thing and it worked
um so it doesn't mean that technology can't work but when you're pricing in
the industry become actually not just working but becoming huge right very soon
that that's where the value investor has to say no
there's a chance it doesn't work right and that chance is actually pretty decent
there's a chance that even if it works you're not the company that wins
and then there's a chance commercializing
it's not going to be great and then there's a chance that you know
if you discount all these cash flows nothing's happening it's terrible investment
so i feel like you know lotto tickets are out there fartcoin
is worth a billion
nftts
are are
not really having a comeback but there's meme coins are the new form of nfts
so those have been out a bubble there's other bubbles in
um like some of these aviation stocks, nuclear, you know, a bunch of stuff.
people want the big bull win.
and i get that.
you know, everybody wants the 100x, but
you know, this this is exactly what cannabis felt like.
it's exactly what nftts felt like.
and
every you look, people will literally
tell you to your face, you're stupid for not owning fartcoin,
and you're stupid for not owning board ape at $1 million.
well, board ape's $10,000 now.
and
you know, there there were people that were bamboozled,
basically tricked into buying board apes for millions of dollars.
and you know that that's what this is.
yeah.
could you know it's dazzling when you look at the port ape?
it went from zero to a million.
yeah.
and at a million a bunch of people said i can't take it anymore.
i have to buy it.
you know, and the price action's too good.
what if it goes to 10 million?
this is going to be like a picasso.
picasso's at 100 million.
this might be bigger than picasso.
so it's a it's a steal at a million.
well, just listen to common sense.
that's what's been confusing me because you got amazing
companies like an nvidia
and pounder that fell damn near 40 50% over the past two months,
right?
people went into the most speculative
parts
of the market and that's where i'm like
what
stage of a cycle
is this or is this even
i think i think it's the kappam
frontier.
so the kappam frontier,
you know, it it basically
just says
the more risk you take,
the more reward
you get,
right?
that is true.
so, who looks the best when the when there's high beta?
when the market's going up, the highest risk stuff looks the most attractive.
and you sit there having fomo saying, "oh, i really want that fcoin.
it went up 30% in a day.
imagine if my portfolio went up 30% a day.
i'd be rich."
and then you realize that, wait a second,
no, there
it doesn't make sense to buy something called fcoin.
it doesn't really make sense to buy something in quantum computing.
maybe i should buy coca-cola.
you buy coca-cola, it doesn't move.
in fact, it might go down.
and so, it's it's frustrating being an investor.
it's not easy.
but the answer is not buy the riskiest asset that you can find.
options, for example, a lot of people love to trade options.
they wipe out their account,
they
put
more
money in
their
account
when
they
have
when
they have it, and
they
wipe
it out
again.
and i i just really think there's a better way to invest that is exciting
but not stupid.
and
um you know, of course, there's no easy easy way to do it.
the quant funds are basically just running rough shot over the whole market.
they're making so much money that you know, it's it's sick.
and
um you know if you can't beat them, join them in a way.
and i think that you know trading as a human
is extremely difficult and i i just wouldn't advise it.
and and again i can't believe
i'm saying this but you're it's like playing chess against a machine.
you know not even magnus carlson can beat the chess machine but you want to try?
you know i i don't think you can beat citadel and jane street.
i think the only
way to do it is to sort of play the game on their level which
it's hard.
last question on quantum, then i want to move on.
uh,
how leveraged
are you into these shorts and could you blow up your entire
net worth if this goes against you?
yeah.
so, i've been in this situation a million times.
um, you know, i i am not worried about that.
you know, unlike other people, i do have access to capital outside of just my own.
yeah.
so, i've been making the rounds to various billionaires.
as this trade goes up,
i have more confidence to go to the people i used to work with,
to go to the people i met
in my travels
over the years
and say, "listen,
i i got a deal for you.
this is this is the greatest trade i've ever seen.
do you want to short these stocks?" it's an unbelievable opportunity.
and if they go up higher,
i just raise more capital and find more capital
and and short more of it because and what are these conversations with the billionaires
like?
are they like, "holy crap, this is a bubble.
take as much money as you want." it's pretty exciting.
you know, they they a lot of these guys are long stuff, so
finding
shorts
is is
something they're interested in.
they don't have mark tomarket.
the hedge funds can't short right now, right?
that's why these stocks are popping as well.
gamestop just put a kibos on shorting.
and the hedge funds, if a short goes against them, even 10%, they're out.
they're chicken.
in my day, tiger soros, i worked at a tiger cub.
we had we were fearless.
the fund i was worked for literally was called intrepid.
we had no fear.
we were short of stock if it went up 10x on us.
doesn't matter.
we're short more.
and you know, melvin was was a tiger cup, too.
a lot of people don't know this.
and when our funds interacted a lot and
you know, melvin should have stuck through the gamestop short.
they should have just kept piling in.
and he had the capital.
i think he didn't want to do it for business reasons because he had
um
you know, his firm, he didn't want to sort of continue with that firm
and owe investors more money.
and it was like a technical reason, but he absolutely could have
gotten five billion from here, five billion from there, and said,
"game on.
i raise you.
i re-ra." and i think that, you know, he should have done that.
but, you know, i think that he had his own reasons.
he's still a billionaire.
you know, he's not sitting there crying.
um, and i think, you know, it's the same way.
you know, i'm a professional.
i'm not worried about, you know, uh, these stocks going up.
they could go up more.
they could go up 50x.
you know, anything could happen.
but we will find a way to pop the bubble and make money on the trade.
now, tiger and soros, two of the biggest firms in the world in 2000,
they quit at the top shorting
right at the top.
they said, "i can't take it anymore.
get me out.
cover these shorts." and guess what happened?
it was over.
that was the literal top of the nasdaq.
it took 15 years to come back.
so, you know, you have supreme confidence on this.
what's that?
you have supreme confidence on this trade.
yeah.
i mean, i you know, i i try to be sober,
but if i look at the the history of all the stuff i've shorted over 25
years,
this is up there.
i mean, i remember shorting internet stocks in 2000,
and you know, it was it was hard to fight that narrative.
martin, don't you know, the internet's going to be the biggest thing ever?
of course.
yeah, i use it.
i'm a kid.
and you know, people told me, you know, you're fighting with fire.
the economy is changing.
all the rules are going to be rewritten,
etc., etc. and you know, it didn't bother me.
it didn't phase me.
you know, quantum isn't anything like that.
you know, quantum is not going to change the world like the internet did.
quantum is not going to change the world like ai is is doing as we speak.
it's it's really a farce.
and it's a me tooism.
it's a it's a fomo.
you know, i missed ai.
i missed nvidia.
i need the next thing.
what's the next big thing?
well, look, i mean, you know, there are stocks that are privately held.
i think one of the biggest problems
you and my communities are going to have is that these stocks like spacex
privately held.
you and i can't buy them.
yeah.
you know, you need you need millions of hard spot at least.
and spacex went from five billion to 350 billion.
sucks for you.
sucks for me.
you're saying retail investors
see the big guys make money by getting in early because they're accredited.
and then they flock to fartcoin to make up for that.
but that you're you're you're chasing that.
you you want the spacex, you want the open ai, but guess what?
you're not in that club and you'll never be in that club.
and i really like palmer lucky at anderole.
i'm proud to call a friend.
he wants to take his company public because he doesn't he wants the average joe
to be able to buy his stock and palunteer
did did the same thing and look at how many millionaires palanteer has made you know
retalier my channel my community is heavily focused on it.
what are your thoughts on this name?
it's amazing company.
i mean you know you you you can't deny the unbelievable success they've had.
as i said, i have a somewhat of a conflict of interest, but the the the
the llm
revolution
is is, you know, changing the world.
what palanteer does, which i think a lot of people don't know.
a lot of people say nobody knows what they do, etc., etc.
it's it's not the case.
um, in essence, what they're doing now is they're taking llm
and going to businesses that don't understand how to implement them across enterprises.
so, you and i know how to use lms.
dear chatbot, uh, my girlfriend is mad at me, you know, what should i say?
and you hit enter.
um, you know, or or you ask it something more complicated.
even coders know how to use it to write code.
i i use it every day to write code.
uh, but at an enterprise, it's a little different.
you know, at an enterprise, you might have something like
coca-cola has a a a invoices from around the world that they need to translate.
so what they do is they they hire translators,
send them to the translators, they wait for the response back.
it's a real pain in the neck and you can't do it automated.
so it's done by hand.
so there's people that manage the translators, right?
and you know, all this stuff and
you know, you have controls
and audit
and things like that that have to look over it.
so palunteer comes in and says, you know what,
we can write the software that does all of this.
we already have it.
we just have to implement it.
and basically all this will go from
800 people or 200 people and it doesn't matter what it is.
invoicing, it can be document translation, it could be intake, whatever it is.
and we're going to use lms to offtheshelf lm.
we don't have to use openai.
we can use deepseek or we could use whatever.
and
we're going to make this so it's a bulletproof
business process that just runs with five people
and
you know you you're going to save 100 million bucks a year
and our software is going to be really expensive.
we're going to take like 20 million of that, but you're going to love it.
and
is that why you think they're getting the multiple
because they are the most expensive
software
stock in the market.
well, so you know what's interesting about multiples is
they only make sense if the company's in a steady state,
you know, so
you can pay 18
times
for the market because
on average the market's growing
a small amount,
right?
coca-cola, proctor and gamble, you can kind of eyeball, okay, the growth is like this.
but when a company has sales that are growth that's changing rapidly, everything everything changes.
you know, the the the funny thing about palunteer
that's really bizarre, and this happened to me with google in in
when google ipoed around
2005,
the second derivative of sales can go up.
almost
all of us in normal
life,
we're used to the more you
the faster
you grow and the more money you make,
just
it slows
down.
you know, you can't the it's the law of large numbers.
you can't grow faster.
it doesn't make sense, right?
that's what's happening in palanteer.
and i think it's going to be a situation.
i talk to people who tell me, "pounder's expensive.
isn't it crazy?" i said, "hold on, hold on.
let's do the math.
first of all, you have to look at free cash flow.
everyone looks at revenue or something like that." it's like, "no, no, no, no.
start with the cash.
are they making cash?
how much are they making?" you do the numbers and it's actually quite reasonable.
60% free cash flow margins.
yeah.
i don't i don't my model in front of me, but i think it's around
100 times
free cash flow.
and again, you might say, "martin, that's a lot." well, hold on.
if free cash flow is going to double every year for the next five years,
which they might beat that.
i think that, you know, you're talking about, you know, pretty insane.
you know, two to the fifth is 16 billion.
so, company makes 16 billion.
uh,
you you can put a multiple on that and you get a stock price that's higher.
look, it's not a cheap stock.
it's not for the faint of heart.
it's gone up a lot.
um, would would i rather buy it at 60 or 80?
yeah.
you know, it's it's it's but it is an unbelievably well-run company.
i think revenue is going to growth is going to accelerate.
earnings growth is going to accelerate
and that's what nobody prices in
is that it's growing 40%
okay it's going to go back down to 30 then
then 10.
nobody has in their model
80%
revenue growth
which they very easily could do
and
they're
fighting
hard to
do it and i don't know how you bet
against
that like i mean the execution
is off
off the charts.
okay so last question on pounder alex karp.
how do you feel about him as a ceo?
i think he's really great.
i mean, the individualism is something that in 2015,
you know, i i went through this little business crisis myself and, you know, people said,
the pr people said, "you just got to be quiet.
you're being too individualistic.
people know who you are.
they know your quirks.
just
don't do it." and i ask you, do you know
who the ceo of eli liy is?
do you know by firstname basis and what his quirks are?
do you know the ceo of bristol myers?
do you know the ceo of amjen?
no.
they're all flat suits.
ceo of coca-cola.
i have no idea.
i'm supposed to be a business expert.
i love the markets.
i don't know who these people are, but you know who alex karp is.
you know who palmer lucky is?
you know who elon musk is?
you know who mark zuckerberg is.
you know who sam alman is.
because they're real people.
they're individuals.
they have flaws.
they have great features.
alex, you know, is really interesting individual.
and and
you know, one of the greatest people in business today is this woman named lulu
chang
who's
mostly an adviser to ceos.
proud to call her a friend.
she advises some of these ceos that i just mentioned.
and she's told them like
martin was the first guy to actually stick his neck out and be himself.
and now people like palmer,
well palmer always was, but people
people have said, you know, i'm i'm gonna show everyone the the real me.
and it's better than the fake me.
and alex has flaws.
you know, he's he's weird,
but he's one of these guys that lets it all hang out.
and you know who he is, and you know that you can believe in him.
and that's why he has the cult that he's got.
and i think that, you know,
it's it's sort of a,
you know, a testament to his his success.
he's one of the best hiring,
you know, people in the world, which is what management's all about.
at the end of the day, one of the things i've learned over
time is
your
individual
contribution
is meaningless to most companies.
y, you know, once you get to thousand people, 2,000
people, what are you going to do personally
that lifts,
you know, the world, uh, that lifts your company?
nothing.
the only thing you could do is find really great people
and make those people work really well.
and this guy, i mean, the staff at palunteer,
i mean, i i don't know if there's another company in silicon
valley that's that's as good as them.
i'm
just so happy you said that because
i feel like most
of us have been saying that for the past couple years.
everyone, you know, alex karps
makes these weird
jokes
or he
puts his neck out and says that he does he just doesn't care what
his political beliefs.
he's not censoring himself censoring himself at all about how he thinks about the world.
but in exchange for the sacrifice of being yourself, you might develop an authentic audience.
i think that's one of the things i've done with my youtube channel.
that's one of the things you've done.
and that success.
yeah.
i talked to palmer lucky about this.
i mean, the number one thing
that you need to do at a company is you have to get people to believe.
yes.
and they have to when they believe they're working saturday and sunday.
when they believe they're they'll kill for you.
you know, it's it's that kind of religion at palunteer.
you know, a normal company guy's leaving at 5:00 p.m.
guy's checking out.
oh, another sick day.
oh, another vacation day.
that's not how it works at palanteer.
these guys are hellbent on success and they made each other rich.
every single guy at palanteer is a millionaire,
you know, and that's the kind of company you want to work at.
and it just creates this flywheel of success.
now, again, the numbers have to catch up, right?
but i don't see why they can't be a trillion dollar company.
i mean, you look at openai, which is obviously,
you know, going to be a trillion dollar company.
you
inevitably
have palunteer as the enterprise
kind of version of openai where they they basically are doing these like bespoke
ai applications
which are a bigger arguably
a bigger market than openai
because they go into the fortune 500 the whole their tam is the entire business world.
yeah.
which if you think about is is really nuts like they are actually
just applying ai
to solve
all
bottlenecks
all inefficiencies
of all corporations
and if you think about how big that tam
is like there's no reason they can't be a
10 trillion
dollar company
the the problem is markets
as you know we have to take things one quarter at a time
so
you know
it's it's
one of these
things where it's like when do you buy it you know what if next
quarter
is bad
you're gonna it's going to be down
50%
so, you know, it's a really tough like thing to own,
but that's because markets price in
on a razor's edge, just the right price,
and you have to have this bet that he's going to execute to perfection
and then some, and you will get rewarded if that happens.
if he executes only well, look out below.
it's going to be a rough stock to own.
so, it's one of these stocks where like in during the tariff
tariff nightmare, you know, that's the stock you buy first.
know that's like
you put it on a list and you're like if it ever goes to this price
i'm going to buy it.
but you still have to watch the quarters like a hawk because
if they say, "look, things are slowing down.
we're not able to execute as well as we can, it's accenture
that's somehow competing with them and doing really well in ai implementations,
then you just have to call spade a spade."
but obviously,
you know, they're running
circles around
accenture
and booze allen and all these other like,
you know, old school systems integrators
that just charge you a fortune.
like, this is how ibm is still a $200 billion company.
like, if ibm's a $200 billion company, just do 5x whatever ibm's worth.
that's palanteer's words.
i love it.
no, it's very encouraging to hear someone because you are very valuation heavy.
i watch your streams and you really go through the numbers.
so, everyone
that i hear from the bear side of pound share
been hearing for the past couple years is it's expensive,
expensive,
expensive.
but your thing happened 2006. google google went public.
the tiger cup community, like i said, is very close.
and
there's
this one guy who's
like
a little bit of a leader in the in that community,
steve mandel,
lone pine.
loine became the second largest stockholder of google.
wow.
second largest.
and people said, "steve's crazy." you know, how how people bought like 4% of google.
google, this was like 15 billion market cap or something like that.
and google, you know, had this torrential tear.
and everyone said, "how are you buying this thing?
it's 100 times their earnings.
it's etc." and he said, "you don't get it.
they're they're not they're growing 30% right now.
they're about to grow 50%."
for many years in a row, and cash flow is just going to double every year.
you know, you're messing with the wrong business.
you know, you have to buy this thing.
and he was right.
and every traditional value guy looked at and said, "i can't own this thing." yeah.
but value isn't about a pe multiple.
value isn't about any multiple.
value is about what are the long-term
steady state, you know, when the business is kind of maturing and in a normalized
situation.
when that happens, what are those cash flows like?
is it a billion?
is it five billion?
is it 20 billion?
for google, it's about a hundred billion.
and at the time
cash flow was like pretty meager
but you know you have to envision
what does it look like and palanteer
when you think about it
you say okay if they are in the enterprise at every fortune
fixing
broken systems fixing inefficiency if you've ever worked at a fortune 500
i i have briefly
you know the whole thing is a [ __ ] show
you know the whole thing's a mess with inefficiencies
so they go out there and say you've heard our reputation we're balancer we're like the
you know we're now
they used to be the weird kid four years ago.
now
people
want
to partner
with them and because
they're kind of the poster
child of ai.
so i agree.
i want yeah.
and they do it for the government.
they say if we can do it for the cia,
you know, how can we do it for you?
i think that they're going to just
sort of run everything and it's going to be as everpresent
as ibm was in the 80s and things like that, you know.
so i'd say palanteer
still still,
you know, 3 to 5x at least, you know, but
it's it's one of these things as a value guy.
you're really sticking your neck out, you know, and
you don't want to get disappointed
because one bad quarter and that's all it takes.
but i do think that these these
what they do, how they implement ai, it actually does work.
you know, their customers are not paying them by accident.
you know, they are earning their their value.
yeah.
nvidia, is this the the greatest company in the world?
and can they keep up the growth?
i think so.
you know, i i briefly shorted the stock last night because
i just for a trade,
i think that the quarter was wasn't as good as i thought it would be.
but i think that nvidia has has three kind of major
um advantages that will just propagate it to 10 trillion market cap.
um why i'm shorting it.
again, i i just wanted an instant reaction to the quarter.
very very very small position.
think thousands of dollars, not millions of dollars.
and you know, so just like maybe it'll go down for five minutes kind of thing.
um and we all know that even even cheap stocks will sometimes
like digest a quarter that kind of like is really sloppy.
this is a bit of a sloppy quarter, but the three big things for nvidia
are
you have
agi,
which in essence is going to require huge amounts of compute.
claude was down yesterday.
we're we're big claude users over here.
as
much as i hate to admit it,
i
don't like the people at the company,
but
they
have great software.
we use claude
and the demand was so high for their latest model, the company couldn't serve it.
they crashed.
they have to rate limited it.
you know, there is no limit to the amount of intelligence
people want
that that and that's why palanteer is, you know, such a good long.
there is absolutely no limit to the amount of intelligence that
yeah, i'm almost breaking even here.
um the
um there's no limit.
yeah, still still holding an l, but
um yeah, i shorted at 139. i just thought the market would react negatively
even though they're obviously doing great.
you know, i thought that the market got too,
you know, is the prices just, you know, rel the expectations are very high.
turns out the people thought this would be a bad quarter
and they they put in an okay quarter, especially china.
yeah, that that's sort of, you know, a mess and it's hard to interpret,
you know, are they telling the truth?
is is china really that, you know, big of a business for them?
why can't china just get these chips from somewhere else?
it it's tough to digest, but if you zoom out, forget the shenanigans
of like the minations
of like the near-term quarter stuff,
which is, you know, on wall street, it's it's a it's a game
in essence
um of it's a poker game of whose position where and like is fidelity
going to sell?
is this good?
you're basically asking was this quarter good enough for fidelity?
fidelity is the biggest, you know,
single, it's the biggest mutual fund that actively manages their portfolio.
so, it's like what's fidelity going to do on this quarter?
has nothing to do with what you think.
it's all about what are the big market players going to do.
so, zooming out from that, you know, those near-term shenanigans,
the three big things, i mean, agi
is is
basically
every single person is going to have agi
and it's going to cost
it's going to make nvidia $100,000
per person.
um, it's going to be so productive
that
we you basically every human being is going to have a chip allocated to them practically
for for this new form of intelligence.
and it's going to be, you know, really cost-effective.
you know, you're going to get multiples of that in productivity.
the second big thing is autonomous vehicles.
um this is happening.
you know, the cars are driving themselves and that's not going to stop.
and these things need nvidia.
i i did a tour of whimo.
some whimo engineers were kind enough to give me a tour.
you know, they work great.
they're expanding to every city.
elon's dropping them, too.
these all run on ai.
they are they are ai machines on wheels and they cannot work without ai.
so it's a huge thing for nvidia and you're talking about
saving lives quite frankly and and
changing the face of of
transportation.
so that's not i think in the stock price at all.
and then the third thing is robotics.
you know this is like the beall endall.
elon's betting his life his legacy
basically
on robotics and he's saying there's going to be more robots than humans.
he's not kidding.
you know he really thinks that.
and if you want to have you want to be amazed
and we've seen some cool robot
stuff, but look at figure ai
figure.ai
they're you know they're making really nice humanoid robots.
valuation's 50 billion.
this is the biggest ham as well that exists.
human labor can be automated.
and you know are these machines truly generalizable?
can they really do anything?
we don't know.
but one of the things we could say that sam alman likes to say about ai
for for at least for llms is this is the worst it'll ever be.
right.
and you know that's kind of you know amazing
if you think about it
now
we don't
you know robotics
is one of these crapshoots
but clearly tesla stock
probably about half of it
is robotics
valuation
and we just trust elon
and
you know he'll he'll he'll figure it out.
some people think robotics is a fraud and it's it suffers from too many dimensions
of freedom where the machine just won't be able to be like us.
i disagree.
i think that we have synthetic training data at this point where these machines can actually
do anything.
and i think
um
various
companies including openai and others are going to start betting very heavily and more publicly
that robotics is the future.
when are we going to see machines out in the wild?
when are you going to walk across the street and
look look to your left and it's it's a robot walking across the street with you
or or
you know robots
going to buy groceries
or something.
it's going to happen.
that's the world we're going to live in.
i don't know if it's this year or not or or
five years or 10 years
but it's
definitively
technologically
within our capability.
and you are talking about one of the biggest sea changes in humanity.
take think about this.
um elon musk is on a list serve.
list serves don't exist anymore.
it's a mailing list.
yeah.
for crypto cipher punks.
and if you look through this
um mailing list that's fascinating.
he's sitting there posting about, you know, this stuff 10 years before satoshi.
and okay, cool.
paypal co-founder.
he's talking about digital money, trans sending money around the world before anybody's talking about it.
tesla, first guy to to autonomous vehicles and and electric vehicles.
don't a lot of people forget open ai, he's the co-founder.
yeah, he was there too.
spacex first guy to do to do satellites cheaply.
neuralink, you know, and now robotics.
he's telling you this is going to be the biggest thing tesla's ever done.
do you do you do you think tesla's overvalued?
what's that?
you think tesla's overvalued?
no.
it's like just like palunteer.
it's the the tread value guy says, "oh my god, it's such a short.
it's so obvious.
look at the cash flow deteriorating, etc., etc." and it's like, "okay, value the car business.
put it aside.
now, value the cyber taxi business.
put that aside." you know, basically, it's it's old shitty stodgy company.
that's all it is.
sorry, elon.
um, that's that's kind of there.
and maybe that's worth 200 billion.
toyota's worth 200 billion, right?
cool.
and maybe he can make that grow.
i don't know.
but that's the conservative assumption.
what would the best cyber taxi startup be worth?
well, whimo is worth 50, but whimo doesn't have elon.
so maybe, and they're not a car company at all, right?
so maybe that's 100. so that's robo taxis.
now, how about autonomous?
it's slightly different
um from robo taxis.
how about
um some of the new cars they're going to make?
you have to value each of these as a sort of a separate business.
and then finally, robotics you have to value.
and robotics, you know, would i pay 500 billion for a robot startup?
probably not.
but the market is sort of as a sum of parts.
i forget the all the parts
quite frankly right now,
but i did a sum of parts analysis
and
it's sort of fairly valued to me unless robots
is even bigger than we think.
yeah.
which it might be.
i mean, that's that's what you're betting on.
and if the greatest i mean, i'm t telling you go to 1998.
elon's 20some years old and he's posting about cryptocurrency 10 years before it happens.
this guy can tell the future.
i don't know how, but he can tell the future.
and
the vcs
i talked to, mark andre
or peter shield, they all tell you,
don't bet against elon.
you know, he is the that guy.
he can tell that robots is going to be the future.
then robots are going to be the future.
and you know, how big they're going to get is another question.
but conceivably, we could all have a robot each.
and again, powered by nvidia.
they have to be powered by ai.
and
you know whether tesla uses nvidia or not i don't think is that important because
as
as much as tesla will try they won't have 100%
market share right you know there'll be other companies
probably tesla will still use nvidia
but even if they don't you know the other companies will so you got three huge
things that nvidia
you basically have to use nvidia
to power the future
all of the future is based on intelligence
being digital
and it all has to go through nvidia
which is crazy if you think about it
you know
somebody else should be able to make money on this but
they just have it locked
you locked
in
and
that's why i think nvidia is going to be the first 10 trillion dollar company.
do you think elon's attempt at doge was meaningful or it was a waste of time?
i think you learned what a lot of people learn.
you know, in the hedge fund world, you meet a lot of rich
people
who
get bored.
i i'd even put vake in that category.
i love vake.
consider him a friend.
but like
you sort of, you know, you did your thing in business,
you made a lot of money, and you say, "what's
next?"
and bloomberg did this, etc.
what most of these guys find is they step one day
in
politics
and they say, "oh,
no, no, no, no.
i love this because,
you know, and i i i've
seen this story play out maybe maybe a hundred times.
you know, you make you make however much money,
you decide,
you know, you you
want to see what politics
is like, and you never go back.
and 5%
of those people
like it,
and they figure it out, and they make it work,
you know, the bloombergs
of the world.
but most people say, "this isn't real life.
like, i cannot do this, you know, because
it is mostly people who are, you know, pretty slimy
and they're not telling you the truth.
they're duplicitous.
they're, you know, it's very much an optics game and perception.
and you know, you have these slick people that that are not worried about actually executing,
which business people do.
they're much more worried about, you know, properating their image.
yeah.
getting re-elected.
that's it.
you know, and that and that's and and i think he learned the hard way.
and now it seems like that relationship is fracturing.
he said yesterday he was disappointed in trump's budget that that it was so much spending.
you know, it seems like they're headed for a divorce.
but, you know, i think that,
you know, trump trump also
is such an iconoclass
trying to get into the system and change it and even he can't change it.
it's so hard to to make that system change.
so, business people just get annoyed
at this and they realize
that
you have to think about politics on a 30 40 year time scale.
they're used to changing stuff in three or four day.
elon's three, four minutes.
if you don't respond to me, you're fired, you know.
so, i think that, you know, it's not hard.
it's not a surprise that he's, you know, sort of saying i
i thought i could do x, y, and z.
turns out the court stopped me.
thought i could do x, y, and z.
turns out some republican senator who has a power card to play,
you know, uh, can, you know, kill this whole thing.
uh, robin hood, vlad tennvive.
i bought a lot of call options
on the stock when it was $8.
it was one of the biggest wins i've had in the market from an options
perspective.
60 bucks.
is robin hood the future of finance?
how do you think of this company?
i do.
i do think it's the future of finance.
i compete with them.
i talked to vlad about doing something with with my product.
um, you know, the guy's just a genius.
you know, he he figured out that there's huge untapped potential in brokerage.
um, you know, i can't say i love every single thing he does.
you know, i think he he has gified the market a little bit.
um, but, you know, i think he's going to build the next big financial institution.
you know, i would not be surprised if
he built a two-300 billion company that was bigger than goldman sachs.
wow.
you know, uh, if you look into vlad's history, um, this isn't guy to bet against.
and when you see a guy like this who's
him kind of reminds me a little bit of this, too.
when you see really talented managers, it took me 25 years to to to
of investing and batting beating my head against the wall sometimes
to learn some of these lessons.
so, i i hope
some of you guys will will avoid those 25 years of pain that i had.
you know, when you see a great manager
managing
a business and it's just growing and growing,
i think you just buy and forget about it and and you just let them compound,
especially if they have a big open
vision.
and the big open vision here is
finance
could be more digital, finance could be more inclusive,
finance could look different, and
i'm going to make the next goldman sachs or the next jp morgan.
and he's doing it.
and you just watch and enjoy, you know, like
again, you know, is is he going to be a perfect straight lineup?
probably not.
but, you know, you have to be amazed at this guy.
like, and again, i i consider him a rival, you know.
so, i i feel like, you know, i'm just amazed at at his abilities.
and look at look at his math career if you
actually want to be really impressed that the guy isn't just some dope that
figured it out.
every guy, i mean, thousands of people have tried to make online brokerages and failed.
yeah.
you know, this guy did something right.
like, same thing with him.
every anybody can make like a little tellah health app tomorrow, a little prescription app tomorrow.
like you can spin it on up tonight.
it's a big difference to make it a 10 billion dollar company.
and in in robin hood's case, he's at 60 60 billion now.
i mean, you have to give credit where credit's due.
and and you know, clearly he's he's on to something now.
does that mean the ride lasts forever?
you know, if you look at palanteer,
you look at robin hood and you say, "these guys are so good.
tesla even,
you know, how much can these guys compound
and how when will it stop?"
and look, the reality is it does stop at some point.
ceos get rich.
they decide, you know, maybe i'm bored.
maybe i'm gonna have 65 kids.
maybe.
i'm kidding.
but maybe, you know, maybe i'm not going to be so interested in this.
and one sign
if you want to be vicious,
and i think sometimes you have to be in this business.
vlad started a second company recently.
and i had investors
a long time ago who said, "martin,
if you ever do something like that, we're taking all our money out.
if you ever even get a girlfriend or get married,
we have a problem
because you're supposed to be managing our money,
not
do you think there could be a symbiotic relationship because it's an ai company.
robin is doing ai.
maybe that's looks like a distraction to me.
i mean, he's a mathematician.
he loves math.
so do i.
but,
you know, if i was
seriously ruthless, i'd just be like, what is that [ __ ] yeah.
you know, so that's a, you know, he'll probably be fine.
but when you look at these telltale signs, like, what are you doing?
you know, and you just have to watch it carefully because
e even the best ceos, they fall off the horse.
and
you know, when you that's i guess what i'm saying is
when you trust and believe so much in the carps
and the the musks
and the and the tenants,
you do have to sit there and sort of say,
well,
trust but verify.
you know, i'm gonna i'm gonna i bet on you and i believe in you, but
you know, watch the quarters,
watch the things they do, and if you ever get uncomfortable, just hit the sell button.
you know, it's not that hard.
you know, i think so many the biggest mistake i see individual
investors make is they get married.
they they just can't ever hit the sell button.
we have a guy in our chat, we call named alejandro.
we call him bagahandro because he's a bag holder.
he's up so much on ion q.
he just can't hit sell for some reason.
and it's like, look, man, you doubled your money.
you're right.
you licked me.
i lost two or three million of us.
just hit the sell button.
you know, it's it's but you know, for whatever
reason,
every time it goes up, he invents a new reason to belong.
yeah.
and you know, it's it's a symptom that a lot of people have.
and there's really there's nothing offending about selling.
there's nothing the company doesn't give a [ __ ] about you.
you know, you're not you don't get points in the stock market for being loyal.
you know, do you get loyalty points?
people say they're proud.
they say, "i've owned palunteer since this price.
i've owned palunteer since this year." you don't get extra stock for that.
no.
no, you don't.
alex karp doesn't send you a christmas card for that.
your job is to protect your portfolio.
and if you start to see the
i don't know, karp's acting weird and
the numbers aren't as good as they thought they'd be,
you just sell.
you know, it's it's not going to kill you.
find the next volunteer.
you know, a lot of people spend
all of their energy on the portfolio they have now.
yeah.
you should be spending a lot of energy on the portfolio
of stocks that you don't know about that could be the next
palunteer.
you know, go worry about, you know, just constantly scrutinizing these stocks.
you made your bet.
already you already have palanteer.
why study it?
you know, it doesn't make any sense.
you know, keep on tabs on it, but
you've
got to go find the next one and the next one and the next one because
eventually
palanteer will fall off the horse.
tesla might and investing is ruthless.
you've got to be able to compound and find the next one.
i i want to ask you about him, but real quick, sofi,
this online bank tech platform,
my friend start my friend mike kagy once
i was meeting him in san francisco
and i i said
he was working for paul
gaddy,
one of the wealthy
dynastic families america.
and i said, "what are you interested in?" he said, "online banks." and he started sofi.
and he got kicked out for sexual harassment reasons.
that's a i've never i know they went public.
they kind of did spack and
you know, they seem to have have have gotten things together, but i
but you don't you don't think of them as competitors
to robin hood or anything like that.
you don't know what i always call a spade a spade.
if i don't know a stock inside and out, i just tell you.
got it.
okay.
hims.
you went on the hims house podcast.
i've been on that podcast.
there was a big cold falling on this one.
are you long hims?
i'm not long.
i was long on when i was on the podcast.
then it [ __ ] like doubled or something like that.
i sold it.
i even shorted it briefly and
i shorted hims and bought palanteer as a pair trade
because hims had this like so so quarter and palanteer had this killer quarter.
yeah.
and hims went up 20% on the quarter and palanteer's flat on the quarter.
i was like, "hold on, this this is going to reverse." and it reversed.
um, you know, so i do trade sometimes.
i put the trader hat on,
but when i put the investor
hat on, i mean, this is obviously a management
team that that knows what the hell they're doing.
i mean, this this tam is also kind of infinite.
i mean, healthcare is full of broken [ __ ] to fix.
and
one of the first broken things to fix was, why can't i just get a prescription
for the drug i want?
and the answer is, well, well, doctors have to decide first.
and it's like, well, what the [ __ ] does this doctor know anyway?
and the reality is,
yes,
look, i don't i wouldn't want you to do surgery on me,
brain surgery on me, amit.
but i do think that, you know, i can fill my own prescription for birth control.
if you're a woman and you want birth control, what's the big deal?
everybody knows.
everybody takes these drugs.
like, it's really not that serious.
cholesterol medicine.
i mean, you don't need a doc for every single damn thing.
and i think when you go to the doctor,
it tends to create, oh, well, we have to do a blood draw.
oh, well, you know, blood draw had this.
well, we're going to have to biopsy that.
and it's this constant
back and forth of you overutilizing
health care when the reality is like give me this drug, this drug and this drug
and
that's the way it should be
and i feel like
you know they have a check and balance there
in a tele doctor
checking
and making sure
but the reality is we spend way too much on healthcare.
it's bank bankrupting our country and hims is
odd as it sounds
it's sort of an attempt to sort of fix some of that as well as providing
people
satisfactory
service.
i hate going to the doctor to renew my script.
you know, the doctor
says,
you know, i'm not going to renew the script unless you come in and
i want to make sure that,
you know, these are the drugs i still want to prescribe.
and there's a reason he's doing that.
it's not not for, you know, fun or safety.
it's because he gets money doing that and he can build his practice up.
and,
you know, hims is kind of a
a challenge to health care system of saying, "yeah, let's do let's do things differently."
do you think they have a moat?
i don't think you need one.
you know, i think that, you know, moat is a funny word.
um, i had a bunch of friends at american express who were investors with me that
um, buffett was a big investor in american express and buffett visited amx
and this is like an offthecuff
un
unrecorded
kind of like chat and
there buffett's
done a lot of these and if you collect little tidbits you hear from people
it's kind of fascinating
what he's not said publicly.
and for for moes he said you guys have a mode but what's a mode?
he said moat is when the customer
uses a different part of their brain to buy the product, right?
what does that mean?
you know, well, the part of my brain that buys the product when i look at,
i don't know, a software
service,
i look at the price and i sort of say, oh,
is this
worth it to me?
do i want to pay $9.99 a month for this [ __ ] oh, maybe.
when when you see the gucci hat and you say, i need that.
yeah.
i don't care what the price.
what's the price?
you're already at the checkout and you look at the price.
you know, you you need it.
you know, i i i
don't care about fashion myself, but you know, the point is, you know,
there's a different part of your brain that's that's operating.
and i think him it's tricky.
you know, on one hand,
it's kind of a different part of your brain, but on the other hand,
it's not.
i think that their brand name is is very valuable.
people know him, they trust it.
but on the other hand, yeah, i mean, somebody else could erode it over time.
um, their job is to build it and build it and build it and and and
get it to a point where
nobody can do that and they make a fortress.
so far they've done well.
there's thousands of these [ __ ] things, right?
and we know him.
there's row.
but like we don't like it at 55. this is i think it's okay.
yeah, i think it's okay.
i i
think it's actually kind of cheap, too, because
they're
actually growing
cash flow really
fast.
but all of wall street's really pessimistic because no moat,
uh, you know, what's going to happen after glps,
uh, etc. but if you just take a step back and say, does this management,
they've grown sales.
so what's amazing about these kids because they're really really young.
look at revenue five, six years ago.
they barely had any.
they have two billion in revenue now.
yeah.
they went from like 50 in revenue to two billion.
who does that?
can you do that?
can i do i i've never done that.
you know, i i made a $2 billion company.
we never we never went from starting start to two billion in revenue.
holy moly.
you know, who does that?
you can.
it just shows you that this these people know what they're doing.
now, again, you got to watch it like a hawk.
unlike palunteer and and tesla and and and
even robin hood maybe the valuation on him is quite reasonable.
um the price to cash flow is like 20 times.
it's really not, you know, some wild number.
now, wall street,
the bears on wall street think that cash flow is about to collapse,
right?
you know, glp and so forth.
you know, i i don't know for sure.
it does
it i i would argue it's just as likely it doubles,
but it's one of these stocks that's like i it's tricky.
you know, i wish everything were were cut clear,
you know, you know, very very clear longs.
i mean, it could be rocky if the deal they have with novo
is a little complicated.
you know, selling glps
kind of under the table isn't exactly great business to be in,
you know, but they will figure out the next thing
and the next thing and the next thing because they're hims.
they always seem to figure it out.
and healthcare is such a big space that, you know, he's literally told you by 2030
we're going to be billion six billion.
and
it's it's not cuz he's guessing, you know, he's got a plan,
you know, and and
look at the plan.
imagine being the series a investor.
kid comes to you and says, "yeah, 50 million valuation.
how much business do you have?" "well, a couple million in pharmacy sales."
and you're like, "okay,
well, we'll see." and then six billion revenue.
i mean, unbelievable success.
you know, i think he's probably going to beat the six billion.
but again, you know, is now the time?
is today the time?
you know, your strategy wise,
it's it's probably a long, you know, i think it probably belongs in most portfolios,
but
it's not to say it's riskless.
you know, nothing's risk riskless.
martin, is tlt the most obvious trade in the market as rates
probably have to come down?
i'm not a i'm not a macro guy.
um, i've never been good at it.
you know, it's just not what i do.
cool.
that's fair.
um, okay.
rapid fire questions.
we really appreciate the time, martin.
uh, audience loving you.
we got 6,000 people here that really
appreciate your thoughts, even if they may disagree with you, but
you know how to communicate
very well about the stock market, and that's because obviously you understand the markets really well.
archer, any thoughts on them?
not really.
okay.
seems like seems bubbleicious.
rocket lab, any thoughts on them?
seems bubbleicious.
i i know a lot of people like this one, but man.
okay.
not for me.
have you looked at grab ever by any chance?
not really.
okay.
um, micro strategy, bitcoin, general thoughts.
does this explode?
yeah, i i so one of my big habies is cracking bitcoin, trying to
um it's led me to down a lot of really interesting roads.
um i have a github repo on on some of my work.
i'll update later today.
i think satoshi's
tokens
on the p this is very technical
p2pk
script the original p2pk not p2pkh
or taproot or segwit
those tokens which are about 9% of bitcoin they will be hacked
now whether it's me that does it or not we'll see but wait
why why are you so confident that they're going to be hacked the public key
is
is shown on those tokens
you need to calculate which is impossible most people okay.
and normally 99% of me agrees.
1% we're going to try.
the public key of the ecc curve 256 bits.
so it's 256 ones and zeros or about 77 digits.
that public key matches a 77digit private key.
if you guess this private key, you win.
every other bitcoin, the other 91%, they don't show you the private key.
so you don't even know what the number is to guess.
but you have the number here.
you just don't know how to go from one way to the other.
now, it's very hard.
but quantum computers can do this very easily.
there's no such thing as a quantum computer yet that can do it.
but,
you know, in 10 years when we can do this magic number trick, we can
we can
turn this one number to this other number.
that's the one thing i do concede quantum computers could do.
again, don't know if it's 10 years.
don't know if it's 20 or 30. but no matter what,
the people at the bitcoin foundation
and who control the the github repo,
no matter what they do, they cannot
stop these tokens unless they blacklist them, which they can do, right?
that's the only saving grace.
they can say, "we're deleting satoshi's tokens.
he's dead."
the problem with that is that
what does it say to the rest of the bitcoin market?
yeah.
you know, it's like maybe you could delete your tokens, too.
and i don't think that's good.
so, if they leave satoshi's tokens there, it's nine nine% of the supply.
that's inevitably going somewhere.
probably the the first guy with a quantum computer that figures it out.
maybe the guy that's using all the quantum computer time on the clouds right now.
but regardless, you know, it'll be
um it'll be cracked someday.
i think that is is very obvious.
even the people kneede in this on the bitcoin board or bitcoin community acknowledge this.
and
i don't know what you do about imagine
you had you knew you had a stock where you knew 9%
of the stock was going to be sold,
right?
it could be one of these things where you say, "well, if they sell it,
they sell it in an orderly
way
or maybe they burn it, right?"
you know, they
could do it in a,
you know, if they burned it, they'd
be burning
hundred
billion
dollars.
who wants do you think bitcoin is a hedge against money printing?
do you believe in that?
yeah.
yeah, it is.
you know, it's and i hate to say it because
i thought trump was going to be
a bearish thing for bitcoin
because trump was supposed to
um basically bitcoin is an asset that was born in crisis in the blockchain.
inscribed in it is the financial crisis, right?
it's a it's the newspaper of the banks failing, right?
and satoshi was clearly telling you in in only so many words that
how do you trust people to organize the monetary system?
you can't.
they're going to print money.
they're going to do political things.
we need something that we that is beyond the aocc's
and even the quite frankly sometimes the trumps of the world.
if they're going to print all this money, we need something something else.
so he told you that.
so trump was supposed to come in, cut the deficit,
cut the spending, cut the [ __ ]
and
also
bitcoin was born in crisis in a time of invasion of privacy and censorship and anti-moneylaundering
laws and know your client laws and all this stuff that gums the financial system.
bitcoin doesn't have any of that.
so trump was supposed to cut that, stop the surveillance state.
none of that's happening, you know.
so bitcoin is still needed.
you know, you're still being censored.
people are still being kicked out of bank accounts.
inflation is rampant.
the need for bitcoin still exists.
i thought trump would come in and people would say, "well, why do we need cryptocurrency?
what good is it for?
i the government's not spying on me anymore.
inflation's been tamed.
we've tamed that beast, right?
budgets budget's going back to normal." but no, actually things seem like they're worse.
you know, it seems like the us is going to go bankrupt.
it seems like inflation isn't going anywhere.
it seems like civil liberties, look, i'm a republican, but
you know, you have to throw spade
a spade.
trump's not exactly, you know, mr.
civil liberties.
i mean, he is taking people and chucking them out of the country.
so, you know, whether what team you're on depends,
but right now the democrats
are looking at it saying, "we feel he's a fascist." now, i don't agree.
but when the democrats were in charge, i said, "well, i think they're a fascist."
you know, so we're none of nobody's tamping it down and saying, "all right, let's all
kind of calm down."
you
know,
it's the country is sort of a [ __ ] show.
so
that's the kind of time where you want bitcoin because if we have to reorder
the entire financial system of the world,
as as much as i think bitcoin's
kind of silly,
it's a good place to start
if you are going to reorder
the financial
system of the world, it is widely distributed
already.
you know,
again, it's just a it's just a little crappy database,
and i could spin one up now right on my terminal.
would you want to buy a piece of my little crappy database?
no.
uh, did you own a decent chunk of bitcoin or no [music] comment?
uh, amd thoughts on amd?
don't know.
well, don't know.
well, okay.
um, here's an interesting one that i think is is is really a funny one.
uh, apple, it's a tough one.
you know, it, you know, he's a very different kind of manager, cook.
um, he's sort of this like ruthless executor, but the company's lost its magic, obviously.
um, it's also, it's probably one of these stocks where there's nothing to do, you know?
i could they make something big work?
yes.
you know, is ai going to lift their boat just because?
yeah.
they're really good at chips.
you know, that's the one thing that's super impressive about them.
you know, it's shocking.
you never would have thought, you know, they'd be this good at at chips.
and that's kind of one of the things that could save them.
but it does feel like apple's tired.
it's just as tired as microsoft was at the microsoft peak where it was like
people didn't like
the evil empire microsoft and,
you know, at least on the consumer side.
and do you think apple could be a healthcare play in a real way?
no.
they don't have the focus.
you know, they, you know, to be really good at this,
you need somebody who's just a killer executive that's going to be really well compensated
and is going to smash through the smash everything.
and these bigger companies, they they're just too deeified
and like you can't make something like that work at apple.
i think it has to come from outside,
you know, and you can see they
what have they innovated
on,
you know, they they
flopped
on vision
pro,
airpods
is okay,
but, you know, in general, this company hasn't done something new in 20 years almost.
do do you think xrp is a scam?
i do.
why?
doesn't do anything.
nobody is, you know.
i think that bitcoin is a lot like that too, but it's more lindy for one.
you know, there's a greater, you know, it's a widely distributed thing.
i i have a friend who owns over a billion dollars of bitcoin,
and he's a famous entrepreneur.
you actually mentioned his name in this podcast at one point,
and you know, he said, "martin, i know bitcoin's [ __ ]
but it it's [ __ ] enough people believe.
and i don't disagree.
you know, i i love bitcoin in one part of my mind.
in the other part of my mind, i agree with warren buffett.
i mean, what the [ __ ] is it?
it's nothing.
it's like old crappy database, hard to update, hard to maintain.
and i think one of the bearish
things for bitcoin,
just just
to put a bone on this is interesting,
is when people figure out
that those satoshi
tokens are gone, it's a big bearish catalyst because
it's not so much that the tokens get sold.
yes, they might cause a panic sale or whatever.
it'll bounce back from that.
you know, even
even if they sell it to a dollar,
they're going to walk it right back up.
the bigger problem is that satoshi is the mythology.
the mythos of bitcoin is a big part of it.
here's this mystery man that drops money, the new money on us and disappears.
he doesn't even sell his own tokens.
he just drops a hundred billion too and says, "i don't need it." right?
maybe he's dead.
maybe he's not.
point is when
elliptic curve cryptography and shor's algorithm that cracks it that existed at the time.
satoshi wrote bitcoin.
shor's algorithm comes go back back to 90s.
he should have known this was a problem and he he left these bitcoin there anyway.
so the more we crack the satoshi myth
that he was this mythological god
and more realize that he was just a dude he was a programmer
who made mistakes
that maybe it becomes one of these things that was like
why are we all kind of like
you know putting
trillions
of dollars in the whole financial
system on this code that we can't update
that has flaws
and
what happens if another
computer
a probabilistic computer a thermodynamic
whatever
kind of computer
we don't even think about what if that cracks
the rest of the 91%
of bitcoin what do we do then yeah you know do we censor
the the bitcoin we don't like.
you know, it's it's not the perfect system at all.
and you know, but it's hard to crack the the the the mythology of it.
you know, the that's what keeps a a bunch of it going.
that's what keeps the people evangelizing it.
the crazy people i think i think sellers nuts.
i mean, i think he's basically manic.
i think he's not sober in terms of his attitude.
i don't know about his personal life.
um but he he just is so drunk on bitcoin.
um he what you call drunk people would call conviction.
no i i mean i have conviction on stuff you know but
i think that
you part of conviction is acknowledging you know the the downside
and
you know there's always there's no perfect investment
you know i think it's really disingenuous
for him
to
tell you tell the people that there's no late time to buy bitcoin.
the 100,000x is over man.
we're never getting that again.
you know, if bitcoin took over the entire financial system, it's maybe a 10x.
so, you know, it's a bit silly to sort of say,
you know, oh, you're, you know, you got to get in bitcoin.
well, you're trying to
get people to mark up your position
is what you're trying to do.
and you don't see him sitting there
saying, let's put bitcoin in payments because it can't be used in payments.
yeah.
you know, he's not, you know, so to me, i think i think sailor's
a bit of a charlatan.
you know, again, i i appreciate his evangelism of bitcoin, but
it seems like
this is more of a pump and dump for him than not and not a dump.
just a pump and pump
um you know, for him more than it is anything else.
all right.
some people are okay with that.
some people want a pump and pump.
well, it's trading at almost 2x now, so i guess so.
absolute
last question for you, martin, and i just want you to give us the goodell pitch.
here's the question.
meta, google, amazon, nvidia, tesla, microsoft, apple.
if you have to pick one mac 7 over the next decade,
what is the one you go long on?
and you can't own the other six.
okay, so definitely not apple.
um, probably not google.
um, i want to put meta and nvidia on the maybe side.
probably not amazon.
do i got them all?
microsoft?
probably not microsoft.
so, it's it's between meta and nvidia.
nvidia.
so, you have a lot of respect for zucks.
i do.
i think he's the beast.
i was talking to baron trump about baron was like glazing elon.
he was like, "ah, you learn the best."
and i said, "don't
don't sleep on zuck."
he's like, "ah,
no, no, we don't." i said, "don't
sleep on zuck."
you know, he's
he's just as good as elon or better.
you know, he is
he's the absolute unit and you know, we don't know what zuck has planned for us
anytime soon, but you know, there's he's got this he's got a bunch of cool stuff.
i know whi- which part of it and what will work i don't know
but he's still young and he's still hungry and
it's clear he's he's one of the best ever
what about tesla is tesla on that list of
no
it's just that okay i'll tell you really quick story so
there was a guy named alman he passed away
he created the the first insulin pump and then the first coclear implant brilliant guy
um made billions.
then he made he was making the first inhaled insulin
and this was like early in my career.
i i i fought him.
he almost actually physically tried to beat me up.
he was 82.
um it was that bad.
the short versus the founder, right?
and al man, he's like, "don't you know who i am?
i'm this guy, that guy." he was the elon musk of medtech.
and his last gasp was to do inhaled insulin.
he was wrong.
i was right.
i took him down.
he forever blamed me for beating his company up and defeating it.
he died having wasted his last few billions on this on this dream.
in the scheme of things, the guy was a brilliant guy and a wonderful guy.
but he also,
you know, for whatever reason decided to put all of his money behind a bad idea.
i can't
for
certain
say if elon's
going to be right or wrong,
and that's the mystery
of the markets.
right.
you know, on one hand, i i think he's probably going to be right,
but on the other hand, nvidia gets paid if he's right,
and nvidia kind of gets paid no matter what.
so, we don't know.
you just don't know if if you're about to be the next alam man.
there are people that
their first company works, the second company works, third company works, fourth company makes them broke.
it happens all the time.
i'm not saying that's going to happen to elon.
i think he's great, but i don't know him.
i don't i don't sit down with him every day.
i don't i don't know what he's doing dayto-day.
i don't know if he's lost his mind or not.
no clue.
do you?
no, we don't know.
so,
we
only
can watch what
he's doing
and
we don't even
there
we just get
imperfect
information,
you know.
so, it it you're betting big.
basically, half a tesla is this leverage bet on robotics.
i don't know if the future is going to be robotics.
he's telling you it's going to be.
but again, al man told me inhaled insulin was going to be the biggest thing ever.
nobody was going to inject insulin ever again, right?
you know, i i said no.
and i was right.
and you know, the guy had billions of dollars, i had millions of dollars.
and you know, some of his money became my money.
and it's one of these things where, you know, i just
it's,
you know, you just because there's a big upside
potential risk doesn't mean you have to take it.
you know, you can still respect.
i mean, he's probably going to do it.
he's probably going to do it.
but i'd like to if i can get my cake and eat it, too.
so, if i can see the robots
coming out,
right, and revenues grow and then i can buy
and if the price,
if the market blesses
me by giving me the opportunity
to
still buy at a good price,
then i'm all in,
right?
but, you know, sometimes the market, mr.
market shouts at you a really good price.
and sometimes he doesn't.
i may never get that chance on tesla,
but the stars just might align where the robots,
like, let's say people start losing faith in us.
the robots aren't coming.
you know,
[ __ ] the robot and tesla revenue
is down for the auto and there's a big crisis.
he's got a margin call,
whatever it is, and you could buy tesla for 10 times earnings in a recession
and then you see that the robots are coming and you see it is real.
then you go all in, right?
so like
now this price at this risk profile,
i i still would be long, but in that paniply
of companies, you know, maybe nvidia
better,
right?
you know, maybe i'd say tesla's number three.
so, i i put nvidia, uh, meta, and then, uh, then tesla,
and then maybe microsoft, um, and then amazon, and then apple,
but yeah, we'll see.
it's hard to tell.
these are the most looked at stocks in the world.
and you can sort of basically assume that their valuations are relatively right, right?
you know,
at the given moment, everyone in the world is analyzing them and markets are
machines that work.
you know,
there may be changes that we don't know about, but once those changes
are made,
we're made aware of them, the markets will adjust.
and i believe in the markets.
you know, i don't think they always work.
otherwise, we wouldn't have jobs, right?
but i think 90% of the time they work.
so, it's it's a little bit difficult to tell the future on those.
martin, we really appreciate your time.
there's martin's twitter.
i mean, my audience has absolutely loved this and enjoyed it.
thanks so much.
if i can plug my thing real quick.
yeah.
so, this is so this is what i'm going to do.
so, goodell.
so, dude, so i'm going to be honest.
i still pay for this every month, but i don't use it.
and that's more of a me thing.
i just like force of habit.
i haven't been using it, but i saw it in january.
it's a bloomberg
terminal competitor and and you know, i've se i've been familiar with your brand.
so, i i i
paid for it and i just need to
start using a lot more.
what is it?
why are you trying to compete against bloomberg
and
you know, you went some you went through some stuff over the past decade,
went to prison,
came back.
why is this the next big idea?
yeah.
so, i've been involved in financial software my whole life.
i i actually was a software guy,
you know, for most of my life before i i did pharma very seriously.
i was a programmer growing up.
i love software.
um, so if you know the bloomberg terminal, it's really efficient.
it is hard to use and hard to learn.
the average person doesn't know how to use a bloomberg terminal, but we made a backwards
compatible version.
so if you know bloomberg, you know god, and if you learn goodell,
you learn bloomberg, right?
so the key to it is pressing the the the
button on top of your tab, the the back tick button.
yeah.
so when you press that button,
we actually made this thing so you're not supposed to use your mouse.
just throw your mouse away.
and now type hit the back tick and type pltr and hit enter.
and and that's sort of how it works.
now type hds and hit enter.
ah, you used your mouse.
oh, you're right.
you're right.
i did those little press escape twice.
wow.
now type n.
that's news, right?
yeah.
and hit enter.
this is the most comprehensive news.
no ads in the news.
no ads anywhere in our platform.
the most comprehensive news.
in fact, there are more stories on our platform than there are on bloomberg,
which is something that we worked really hard to get.
so, it's not quite bloomberg yet, but it is also 95% cheaper than bloomberg.
so, you know, i always wondered why bloomberg was so expensive.
and, you know, i love programming
and
i also think that one of the the biggest things that
that's
problem out there is that nobody
can quantitatively
invest.
and i kind of want to build that for people.
i also have a lot of social features in there.
so, there's chat rooms and all kinds of stuff that's fun.
so, you know, robin just got out of the hood was a funny one.
uh, how are you charge 60 bucks a month for this?
like, that seems pretty cheap.
well, it's also free, so you can actually just mess around with it for free.
and that's something a lot of people don't know.
and we have we have thousands and thousands of users, uh, tens of thousands of users.
and, um, we still haven't even publicly announced it.
so, i haven't tweeted about it yet.
so, it's still kind of like early early days and under apps.
and we're going to hopefully do um, we're adding bonds to it.
we're adding, you know, it's going to be the full feature of bloomberg.
ready to take them down.
i i just honestly hate bloomberg.
they they banned me from their product.
i've been i was a user since i was 17. they're very political organization.
they have a news team that hates me.
it's become personal, you know, for for whatever reason.
this is personal.
mike is one of the rich some people, a lot of people don't know this.
mike bloomberg may be the richest man in the world.
yeah.
and it's it's you know, the the forbes people have finally figured this out.
he's like number seven or something.
but people just don't know how rich he is.
i would guess about 400 500 billion.
so forb says 104, but you think it's even just bloomberg alone is worth 200. yeah.
so
and then the funny thing about bloomberg
is every year he pays himself a dividend of 5 to 10 billion
for the last of it of it
for the last 40 years.
that's probably why they haven't gone public, right?
they enjoy.
and what does he do with the money?
does he just throw it away?
no, he's been investing it and making 20% on that money.
the guy might have a trillion dollars for all we know.
it's kind of nuts.
do you think this
could you could sell this to to
hedge
funds and they could use this over
bloomberg?
yeah, we're mostly going to target, you know, uh, wall street,
but i also think that if you look at aws,
kind of my vision here is like, all right, bloomberg,
you can't even go on bloomberg right now and and
even if you're a billionaire,
you can't slap your amx down and say, "give me that thing." you can't.
and if you're broke, forget it.
you know, if you have less than 10 million, yeah, don't even bother.
um it's it's just not worth it.
it's 30 grand a year.
so
aws,
when you jump on amazon web services,
it doesn't matter if you're netflix and you're paying them five bill a year,
you're our company and maybe you're paying them 100 grand a year or if you're hobbyist
and you're paying them nothing a year.
they want you no matter what because it's the best system.
i'm the same way.
if you you don't want to pay this thing, don't pay it.
you know, it's fine.
i'm not going to show you.
i'm
not going to give you the
stuff that
cost
me a lot of money
and
i'm going to lose
tons
of money on you,
but i'm
give you some stuff and
i'm
probably going to lose a little bit of money on you.
and if you pay me, i'm gonna give you the world.
and that's, you know, kind of the way we we do this.
and it's early days, but you know, i'm excited.
why was this the big idea?
why were you so excited to to start this?
yeah.
i think that financial software hasn't changed.
you know, so bloomberg hasn't changed in 15 years.
and the sad thing is
most people wouldn't know this, but the quantitative world has completely changed wall street.
the average guy in wall street
30 years ago
was a cigar chomping
frat boy with a famous last name like kennedy or something that went to yale.
the average guy on wall street now is a chinese programmer who won a math contest.
and it is a very different world.
and why is that?
well, markets are very technical and efficient.
and the top 10 hedge funds on it,
they used to be all stock pickers and and and
you know, macro pickers.
of the top 10 head 10 head 10 hedge funds now nine are quants
nine out of 10
the the whole market's mathematical
i wouldn't say it's rigged
because that's not the right word
but
if
you're trying to trade
out
trade people
it's
i mean it's
really tricky
i mean these firms are making
20 30 billion
a year
and you're paying them we're paying them when when we trade
and i i want to make systems that
can
at least
show you some of this and compete on it and like
the the best tools right now like bloomberg
they don't have any tools like that and they don't really help you very much.
so, we're going to try to cater to a more modern audience
that knows how to program, that's more technical,
that really wants to make money by any means necessary,
like not gambling
on whether or not a stock might go up, but
really having a system
that that
will make them money.
and it's a group of people that are really smart.
so, if you go into the press back real quick and type in jane
or type in citadel.
okay.
yeah.
so, so yeah, just type in jane real quick.
you had it up for a second.
don't press enter.
yeah.
so, you see all those people there?
those
are all
people that
work at jane street
that
you can if you click on one of them, you get their
personal phone number and email.
what?
yep.
so, holy crap.
type type type blackstone.
this is not available to the average person, right?
jonathan gray.
hit hit it.
hit it real quick.
jonathan gray's worth $10 billion.
it might have popped up somewhere else or something.
yeah.
press yeah.
press enter.
uh, press up arrow.
use your arrows and then hit enter when when it's on the name.
press down down and hit enter.
there it is.
there you go.
there's email.
crap, dude.
yeah.
phone number and email.
so, you want to network,
you really want to be on wall street, you really want to be a player,
you know, you're not going to do it on robin hood.
it's just not not going to happen.
you know, you can't even short on robin hood.
so, yeah.
trying to make a real system that really works.
i'm feel bad for this guy, jason brown.
sorry, dude.
but, uh, you know, the point is, uh,
you know, it just doesn't make a lot of sense to
to if you're an individual investor to play with one hand tied behind your back.
i always say like, would you fight brock lesnar tonight in the cage?
people, are you crazy?
i get my ass kicked.
and it's like, well, why are you trading against citadel and jane street?
you know, we got to fight these guys.
if you're gonna compete and the markets are competition, fight them head-to-head.
you know, fight fire with fire.
and i think that's something that's really hard to do if your tools suck.
and again, great firms.
jane street, some my best friends work there.
but, you know, they're they're killing us.
you know, they're making tons of money.
anyway, i appreciate the plug.
so, so real quick, 80 bucks a month.
that's it.
that's for people if they want to use it.
yeah, it's 80 a month.
i mean, listen, we're we're going after people who have tons of money.
it's it's free.
you know, you're not going to get everything for free.
i think one day we'll we'll have something that's like
like aws where you pay for what you use.
we want everyone to get
access to everything,
but it cost me millions of dollars to get data on bonds and things like that.
it's not
it's not cheap, but i i'm planning to
give you as much as i can for free.
again, just don't like bloomberg.
i'm happy to have a billion dollar company and take them down.
i don't need the 200300 billion dollar company mike has.
but i also know that wall street is
a
place with a lot of money and
they're
willing to pay tons
of money for software.
so i i still want to make individuals happy, but it's, you know,
it's hard to balance that.
yeah, martin, i appreciate it, man.
means a lot.
thank you for three hours.
appreciate it, brother.
thank you.
have a great day.
have a great one.