- The only person who cause you more harm
than a thief with the dagger is a journalist with a pen.
- The following is a conversation with Bill Ackman,
a legendary activist investor
who has been part of some of the biggest
and at times controversial trades in history.
Also, he is fearlessly vocal on X, FKA Twitter
and uses the platform to fight for ideas he believes in.
For example, he was a central figure in the resignation
of the President of Harvard University, Claudine Gay,
the saga of which we discuss in this episode.
This is The Lex Fridman Podcast,
to support it please check out
our sponsors in the description.
And now dear friends, here's Bill Ackman.
In your lecture on the basics of finance and investing,
you mention a book, "Intelligent Investor"
by Benjamin Graham as being formative in your life.
What key lesson do you take away from that book
that informs your own investing?
- Sure. Actually it was the first investment book I read,
and as such, it was kind of the inspiration
for my career and a lot of my life, so important book.
You know bear in mind this is sort of
after the Great Depression,
people lost confidence investing in markets,
World War II and then he writes this book,
it's for like the average man.
And basically he says that
you have to understand the difference
between price and value, right?
Price is what you pay,
value is what you get.
And he said the stock market is here to serve you.
And it's a bit like the neighbor that comes by every day
and makes you an offer for your house.
Makes you a stupid offer you ignore it,
makes you a great offer, you can take it.
And that's the stock market.
And the key is to figure out what something's worth
and you have to kind of weigh it.
He talked about the difference between,
he said the stock market
in the short term is a voting machine.
It represents speculative interests,
supply and demand of people in the short term.
But in the long term the stock market
is a weighing machine, you know, much more accurate.
It's gonna tell you what something's worth.
And so if you can define what something's worth,
then you can really take advantage of the market
'cause it's really here to help you.
And that's kinda the message of the book.
- In that same way, there's a kind of difference
between speculation and investing.
- Yeah, speculation is just,
it's a bit like buying trading crypto, right?
- [Lex] Strong words.
- (laughs) Well, short term trading crypto,
maybe in the long run there's intrinsic value,
but many investors in a bubble
going into the crash were really just pure speculators.
They didn't know what things were worth,
they just knew they were going up,
that's speculation.
And investing is doing your homework,
digging down, understanding a business,
understanding the competitive dynamics of an industry,
understanding what management's gonna do,
understanding what price you're gonna pay,
the value of anything I would say,
other than love let's say,
is the present value of the cash
you can take out of it over its life.
Now some people think about love that way,
but it's not, it's not the right way to think about love,
but it's...
Yeah. So investing is about basically building a model
of what this business is gonna produce over its lifetime.
- So how do you get to that,
this idea of called value investing?
How do you get to the value of a thing,
even like philosophically value of anything really.
But we can just talk about the things
that are on the stock market, companies.
- The value of a security,
the value is the present value of the cash
you can take out of it over its life.
So if you think about a bond,
a bond pays a 5% coupon interest rate,
you get that let's say every year or twice a year,
split in half.
And it's very predictable.
And if it's a US government bond
you know you're gonna get it,
so that's a pretty easy thing to value.
A stock is an interest in a business.
It's like owning a piece of a company,
and a business, a profitable one is like a bond
in that it generates these coupons or these earnings
or cash flow every year.
The difference with a stock and a bond
is that the bond, it's a contract.
You know what you're gonna get
as long as they don't go bankrupt and default.
With the stock you have to make predictions
about the business.
You know how many widgets are gonna sell this year,
how many gonna sell next year?
What are the costs gonna be?
How much of the money that they generate
do they need to reinvest in the business
to keep the business going?
And that's more complicated.
But what we do is we try to find businesses
where with a very high degree of confidence,
we know what those cash flows are gonna be
for a very long time.
And the very few businesses
that you can have a really high degree of certainty about.
And as a result many investments are speculations
'cause it's really very difficult to predict the future.
So what we do for a living,
what I do for a living is find those rare companies
that you can kind of predict what they're gonna look like
over a very long period of time.
- So what are the factors that indicate
that a company is going to be something
that's going to make a lot of money,
it's gonna have a lot of value
and it's going to be reliable over a long period of time.
And what is your process of figuring out
whether a company is or isn't that?
- So every consumer has a view on different brands
and different companies.
And you know, what we look for
are sort of these non-disruptible businesses.
A business where you can kind of close your eyes,
stock market shuts for a decade
and you know that 10 years from now
it's gonna be a more valuable, more profitable company.
So we own a business called Universal Music Group.
It's in the business of helping artists
become global artists,
so recorded music business.
And it's in the business of owning rights
to sort of the music publishing rights of songwriters.
And you know, I think music is forever, right?
Music is a many thousand year old
part of the human experience,
and I think it will be thousands of years from now.
And so that's a pretty good backdrop to invest in a company.
And the company basically owns
a third of the global recorded music,
the most dominant sort of market share in the business.
They're the best at taking an artist who's 18 years old,
who's got a great voice
and has started to get a presence on YouTube and Instagram
and helping that artist become a superstar,
and that's a unique talent.
And the result is the best artists in the world
wanna come work for them,
but they also have this incredible library of the Beatles,
the Rolling Stones, U2, et cetera.
And then if you think about what music has become
used to be about records and CDs
and eight track tapes for those of whom,
and it was about a new format
and that's how they drive sales.
And it's become a business which is like
the podcast business about streaming.
And streaming is a lot more predictable
than selling records, right?
You can sort of say,
okay, how many people have smartphones?
How many people are gonna have smartphones next year?
There's a kind of global penetration
over time of smartphones
and you pay, call it 10, 11 bucks a month
for a subscription or last for a family plan.
And you can kind of build a model
of what the world looks like and predict
the growth of the streaming business,
predict what kind of market share
Universal's gonna have over time.
And you can't get to a precise view of value.
You can get to an approximation.
And the key is to buy at a price
that represents a big discount to that approximation.
And that gets back to Ben Graham.
Ben Graham was about what he called,
invented this concept of margin of safety, right?
You wanna buy a company at a price that if you're wrong
about what you think it's worth
and it turns out to be worth 30% less
you paid a deep enough discount
to your estimate that you're still okay.
It's about investing.
A big part of investing is not losing money.
If you can avoid losing money
and then have a few great hits,
you can do very, very well over time.
- Well, music is interesting
'cause yes, music's been around for a very long time,
but the way to make money from music has been evolving.
Like you mentioned streaming,
there's a big transition initiated by,
I guess Napster then created Spotify
of how you make money on music
with Apple and with all of this.
And the question is,
how well are companies like UMG able to adjust
to such transformations?
One, I could ask you about the future,
which is artificial intelligence
being able to generate music, for example.
There have been a lot of amazing advancements with,
so do you have to also think about that?
Like when you close your eyes,
all the things you think about,
are you imagining the possible ways
that the future's completely different from the present
and how well this company will be able to
surf the wave of that?
- Sure. And they've had to surf a lot of waves.
And actually the music business peaked the last time
in like the late '90s or 2000 timeframe.
And that really innovation,
Napster digitization of music almost killed the industry.
And Universal really led an effort to save the industry
and actually made an early deal with Spotify that enabled
the industry to really recover.
And so by virtue of their market position
and their credibility and their willingness
to kind of adopt new technologies,
they've kept their position.
Now they of course had this huge advantage.
'Cause I think the Beatles are forever.
I think U2 is forever.
I think Rolling Stones are forever.
So they had a nice base of assets that were important
and I think will forever be,
and forever is a long time.
But you know, again, there's enormous,
there are all kinds of risks in every business.
This is one that I think
has a very high degree of persistence.
And I can't envision a world where beyond streaming
in a sense, now you may have a Neuralink chip in your head
instead of a phone,
but the music can come in a digitized kind of format.
You're gonna wanna have an infinite library
that you can walk around in your pocket or in your brain.
It's not gonna matter that much if the form factor,
the device changes, it's not really that important
whether it's Spotify or Apple
or Amazon that are the so-called DSPs
or the providers.
I think the values really gonna reside
in the content owners,
and that's really the artists and the label.
- And I actually think AI is not going to be
the primary creator of music.
I think we're going to actually face the reality
that it's not that music has been around
for a thousands of years,
but musicians and music has been around.
Like we actually care to know
who's the musician that created it.
Just like we wanna know that who's the artist,
human artists that created a piece of art.
- I totally agree.
And I think if you think about it
there's other lots of other technologies
and computers that have been used
to generate music over time,
but no one falls in love
with a computer generated track, right?
And you know, Taylor Swift,
you know incredible music,
but it's also about the artist and her story
and her physical presence and the live experience.
I don't think you're gonna sit there
and someone's gonna put a computer up on stage
and it's gonna play
and people are gonna get excited around it.
So I think AI is really gonna be a tool
to make artists better artists
and I think like a synthesizer, right?
Really created the opportunity for
one man to have an orchestra.
Maybe a bit of a threat to a percussionist,
but maybe not, maybe it drove even more demand
for the live experience.
- Unless that computer has human-like sentience,
which I believe is a real possibility.
But then it's really from a business perspective
no different than a human.
If it has an identity that's basically fame and an influence
and there'll be a robot Taylor Swift
and it doesn't really matter--
- That's a copyrightable asset I would think.
- [Lex] And then there'll be--
- I'm not sure that's the world I'm excited about.
- Well, that's a different discussion.
The world is not gonna ask your permission
to become what it's becoming
but you could still make money on it.
Presumably there'd be a capital system
and there'd be some laws under which,
which I believe AI systems will have
rights that are akin to human rights
and we're gonna have to contend with what that means.
- Well there's sort of name and likeness rights
that have to be protected now.
Can a name be attributed to a Tesla robot?
I don't know.
- I think so.
I think it's quite obvious to me.
- Okay, so those are more potential artists for us
to represent at Universal.
- Exactly. Exactly.
- That's sort of one example.
Another example could be just the restaurant industry.
If you can look at businesses like a McDonald's, right?
It's a whatever the company's like a 1950 vintage business
and here we are 75 years later
and you can kind of predict
what it's gonna look like over time
and the menu's gonna adjust over time
to consumer tastes but I think the hamburger
and fries is probably forever.
- The Beetles, the Rolling Stones,
the hamburger and fries are forever.
I was eating at Chipotle last night
as I was preparing these notes (laughs)
- Thank you.
- And yeah, it is one of my favorite places to eat.
You said it is a place that you eat,
well, you obviously also invest in it.
What do you get at Chipotle?
- I tend to get a double chicken.
- Bowl or burrito?
- I like the burrito,
but I generally try to order the bowl, cut the carb.
- [Lex] For health reasons. Alright.
- And double chicken, guac, lettuce, black beans.
- And I'm more of a steak guy.
Just putting that on the record.
What's the actual process you go through?
Like literally like the process of figuring out
what the value of a company is?
Like how do you do the research?
Is it reading documents?
Is it talking to people?
How do you do it?
- It's all the above.
So Chipotle, what attracted us initially
is the stock price dropped by about 50%.
Great company, great concept,
you know athletes love it.
Consumers love it.
Healthy, sustainable fresh food
made in front of your eyes.
And great Steve Ells, the founder did an amazing job,
but ultimately the company's lacking some of the systems
and had a food safety issue.
Consumers got sick, almost killed the rent.
But the reality of the fast food quick service industry
is almost every fast food company
has had a food safety issue over time,
and the vast majority have survived.
And we said, look, it's such a great concept,
but their approach was not,
it was far from my deal,
but we start with usually reading the SEC filing.
So companies file a 10 k or an annual report,
they file these quarterly reports called 10 Qs.
They have a proxy statement
which describes kinda the governance,
the board structure,
conference call transcripts are publicly available.
It's kind of very helpful to go back five years
and kinda learn the story.
You know here's how management describes their business,
here's what they say they're gonna do,
and you can follow along to see what they do.
It's like a historical record
of how competent and truthful they are.
It's a very useful device.
And then of course looking at competitors
and thinking about what could dislodge this company?
And then we'll talk to,
if it's an industry we don't know well
we know the restaurant industry really well,
music industry, we'll talk to people in the industry.
We'll try to understand
the difference between publishing and recorded music.
We'll look at the competitors, we'll talk to...
We'll read books.
I read a book about the music industry
or a couple books about the industry.
So it's a bit like a big research project.
And there are these so-called expert networks now
and you can get pretty much anyone on the phone
and they'll talk to you about an aspect of the industry
that you don't understand, wanna learn more about,
try to get a sense.
Public filings of companies
generally give you a lot of information
but not everything you wanna know.
And you can learn more by talking to experts
about some of the industry dynamics, the personalities.
You wanna get a sense of management.
I like watching podcasts.
If a CEO were to do a podcast
or a YouTube interview,
you get a sense of the people.
- So in the case of Chipotle, for example,
by the way, I could talk about Chipotle all day.
I just love it. I love it.
I wish there was a sponsor.
(both chuckling)
- I'll mention it to the CEO.
- Don't make promises you can't keep Bill.
- I'm not making, I can't.
Brian Nichols a fantastic CEO,
he's not gonna spend $1
that he doesn't think its the company's best interest.
- All right. All I want is free Chipotle, come on now.
What was I saying?
Oh, and so you look at a company like Chipotle
and then you see there's a difficult moment in its history
like you said that there was a food safety issue.
And then you say,
okay, well I see a path where we can fix this
and therefore even though the price is low,
we can get it to where the price goes up to its value.
- So the kind of business we're looking for
is sort of the kind of business
everyone should be looking for, right?
A great business.
It's got a long-term trajectory of growth
out into you know even beyond the foreseeable distance.
Those are the kinda businesses you wanna own.
You want businesses that generate a lot of cash.
You want businesses you can easily understand.
You want businesses with these sort of
huge barriers to entry
where it's difficult for others to compete.
You want companies that don't have
to constantly raise capital.
And these are some of the great business of the world,
but people have figured out
that those are the great businesses.
So the problem is those companies
tend to have very high stock prices
and the value is generally built into
the price you have to pay for the business.
So we can't earn the kind of returns we wanna earn
for investors by paying a really high price.
Price matters a lot.
You can buy the best business in the world
and if you overpay,
you're not gonna earn particularly attractive returns.
So we get involved in cases where
a great business has kind of made a big mistake
or you've a company that's kinda lost its way,
but it's recoverable.
And we buy from shareholders who are disappointed,
who've lost confidence selling at a low price
relative to what it's worth if fixed
and then we try to be helpful in fixing the company.
- You said that barriers to entry,
you said a lot of really interesting qualities
of companies very quickly in a sequence of statements
that took like less than 10 seconds to say,
but some of them were fascinating,
all of them were fascinating.
So you said barriers to entry.
How do you know if there's a type of moat
protecting the competitors from stepping up to the play?
- The most difficult analysis to do as an investor
is kind of figuring out how wide is the moat,
how much at risk is the business to disruption?
And we're in, I would say
the greatest period of disruptive ability in history, right?
Technology, you know, a couple of 19 year olds
can leave whatever university
or maybe they didn't even go in the first place.
They can raise millions of dollars.
They can get access to infinite bandwidth storage.
They can contract with engineers
in low cost markets around the world.
They could build a virtual company
and they can disrupt businesses
that seem super established over time.
And then on top of that,
you have major companies
with multi-trillion dollar market caps
working to find profits wherever they can.
And so that's a dangerous world
in a way to be an investor.
And so you wanna, you have to find businesses
that it's hard to foresee a world
in which they get disrupted.
And the beauty of the restaurant business,
and we've actually, our best track record is in restaurants.
We've never lost money.
We've only made a fortune interestingly,
investing restaurants.
A big part of, it's a really simple business.
And if you get Chipotle right
and you're at a hundred stores
it's not so hard to envision getting to 200 stores
and then getting to 500 stores, right?
And the key is maintaining the brand image,
growing intelligently,
having the right systems
and when you go from 100 stores to 3,500 stores,
you have to know what you're doing.
And there's a lot of complexity, right?
If you think about your local restaurant,
the family's working in the business,
they're watching the cash register
and you can probably open another restaurant across town.
But there are very few restaurant operators
that own more than a few restaurants
and operate them successfully.
And the quick service business is about systems
and building a model
that a stranger who doesn't know the restaurant industry
can come in and enter the business
and build a successful franchise.
Now, Chipotle's not a franchise company,
they actually own all their own stores,
but many of the most successful restaurant companies
are franchise models like a Burger King, a McDonald's,
Tim Horton's, you know, all these various brands, Popeye's.
And there it's about systems,
but the same systems apply
whether you own all the stores
and it's run by a big corporation
or whether the owners of the restaurants
are sort of franchisees, you know, local entrepreneurs.
- So if the restaurant has scaled to a certain number
that means they've figured out
some kind of system that works
and it's very difficult to develop that kind of system,
so that's a moat.
- A moat is you get to a certain scale
and you do it successfully.
And the brand is now understood by the consumer.
And what's interesting about Chipotle is
what they've achieved is difficult, right?
They're not buying frozen hamburgers getting shipped in.
They're buying fresh
sustainably sourced ingredients,
preparing food in the store.
That was a first, right?
The quality of the product at Chipotle is incredible,
it's the highest quality food you can get for,
you can get a serious dinner for under 20 bucks
and eat really healthfully
and very high quality ingredients,
and that's just not available anywhere else.
And it's very hard to replicate
and to build those relationships
with farmers around the country.
It's a lot easier to make a deal with
one of the big massive food producers
and buy your pork from them
than to buy from a whole bunch of farmers
around the country.
And so that is a big moat for Chipotle.
Very difficult to replicate.
- And by the way, another company
I think you have a steak is McDonald's?
- No, we own a company called Restaurant Brands.
Restaurant Brands owns a number of quick service companies,
one of which is Burger King.
- Burger King?
- Yeah.
- Okay, well it's been a meme for a while,
but burger King is great too, Wendy's whatever,
but usually I go McDonald's,
I'll just eat burger patties.
I don't know if you knew you could do this
but a burger patty at Burger King can do this,
McDonald's, it's actually way cheaper.
- They'll just sell you the patty.
- The patty and it's cheap.
It's like a $1.50 or $2 for per patty
and it's about 250 calories and it's just meat.
And despite like the criticism of memes out there, that's--
- [Bill] Pretty healthy stuff.
- It's healthy stuff.
And so when I go...
The healthiest I feel is when I do carnivore,
it doesn't sound healthy,
but if I eat only meat, I feel really good.
I lose weight, I have all this energy. It's crazy.
And when I'm traveling
the easiest way to get meat is that.
- Is you go to McDonald's, you order six patties.
- Exactly. So there's this sad meme
of me just sitting alone in a car when I'm traveling,
just eating beef patties at McDonald's.
But I love it.
And you gotta do what you love,
what makes you happy,
and that's what makes me happy.
- I think we should maybe
we'll have Burger King feature in it.
What about Flame World?
What's with these fried burgers?
We gotta get you to Burger King grilled burgers.
- Wait, is this like fast food trash?
I didn't know.
I don't know the details of how they're made.
I don't have allegiance.
- I think we got a chance
to switch you to Burger King.
- Great. We'll see.
I'm making so many deals today, it's wonderful.
Okay, you were talking about moats
and this kind of remind me of Alphabet, the parent company.
- Sure. It's a big position for us.
- So it's interesting that you think that
maybe Alphabet fits some of these characteristics.
It's tricky to know with everything
that's happening in AI,
and I'm interviewing Sundar Pichai soon.
It's interesting that you think that there's a moat.
And it's also interesting to analyze that,
'cause the consumer is just a fan of technology.
Why is Google still around like they've been,
it's not just a search engine,
it's doing it all the basics
of the business of search really well
but they're doing all these other stuff.
So what's your analysis of Alphabet?
Why are you still positive about it?
- Sure. So it's a business we've admired as a firm
for whatever, 15 years,
but rarely got to a price that we felt we could own it.
Because again, the expectations were so high
and price really matters.
And really the sort of AI scare I would call it.
You know Microsoft comes out with Chat GPT,
they do an amazing demonstration.
People like this most incredible product.
And Google, which had been working on AI even earlier,
obviously the Microsoft was behind an AI.
It was really their chat GPT deal that gave them
a kind of a market presence.
And then Google does this
fairly disastrous demonstration of Bard and the world says,
oh my god, Google's fallen behind an AI.
AI is the future.
Stock gets crushed.
Google gets to a price around 15 times earnings,
which for a business of this quality
is an extremely low price.
And our view on Google,
one way to think about it when a business becomes a verb,
that's usually pretty good sign about
the mode around the business.
So you'd open your computer
and you open your search
and very high percentage of the world
starts with a Google page
and a one line where you type in your search.
You know the Google advertising search,
YouTube franchise is one of the most
dominant franchises in the world.
Very difficult to disrupt,
extremely profitable.
The world is moving from offline advertising
to online advertising
and that trend I think continues. Why?
Because you can actually see whether your ads work.
They used to say about advertising
spend a fortune and you just don't know
which 50% of it's works,
but you just sort of spend the money
'cause you know, ultimately
that's gonna bring in the customer.
And now with online advertising,
you can see with granularity which dollars I'm spending.
You know when people click on the search term
and end up buying something
and I pay, it's a very high return
on investment for the advertiser
and they really dominate that business.
Now AI of course is a risk
if all of a sudden people start searching
or asking questions of Chat GPT
and don't start with the Google search bar,
that's a risk to the company.
And so our view based on work we had done
and talked to industry experts
is that Google if anything had a,
by virtue of the investment they've made,
the time, the energy that people put into it,
we felt their AI capabilities were
if anything potentially greater than Microsoft Chat GPT
and that the market had overreacted.
And because Google is a big company
global business regulators
scrutinized it incredibly carefully.
They couldn't take some of the same liberties
a startup like OpenAI did in releasing a product.
And I think Google took a more cautious approach
in releasing an early version of Bard
in terms of its capabilities.
And that led the world to believe that they were behind.
And we ultimately concluded,
if any they're tied or ahead
and you're paying nothing for that potential business.
And they also have huge advantages by virtue.
If you think of all the data Google has,
like the search data, all the various applications,
you know, email and otherwise
the kinda the Google suite of products,
it's an incredible data set.
So they have more training data
than pretty much any company in the world.
They have incredible engineers,
they have enormous financial resources
so that was kind of the bet.
And we still think it's probably the cheapest
of the big seven companies
in terms of price you're paying for the business
relative to its current earnings.
It also is a business
that has a lot of potential for efficiency.
Sometimes when you have this
enormously profitable dominant company,
all of the technology companies in the post March 20 world
grew enormously in terms of their teams
and they probably overhired.
And so you've seen some,
the Facebooks of the world and now even Google
starting to get a little more efficient
in terms of their operation.
So we bet a low multiple for the business.
One way to think about the value
of the business is the price you pay for the earnings
or alternatively what's the yield.
If you flip over the price over the earnings,
it gives you kind of the yield of the business.
So a 15 multiple is about
almost a seven and a half percent yield
and that earnings yield is growing over time
as the business grows
compare to what you can earn
lending your money to the government,
4%, that's a very attractive going in yield.
And then there's all kinds of
what we call optionality
in all the various businesses
and investments they've made that are losing money.
They've got a cloud business that's growing very rapidly,
but they're investing basically 100% of the profits
from that business and growth.
So you're in that earnings number,
you're not seeing any earnings from the cloud business
and you know, they're one of the top cloud players.
So very interesting,
generally well-managed company
with incredible assets and resources and dominance,
and it has no debt.
It's got a ton of cash.
And so pretty good story.
- Is there something fundamentally different
about AI that makes all of this more complicated,
which is the sort of the exponential possibilities
of the kinds of products
and impact that AI could create
when you're looking at Meta,
Microsoft, Alphabet, Google, all these companies,
xAI or maybe startups,
is there some more risk introduced
by the possibilities of AI?
- Absolutely. That's a great question.
You know business investing is about finding companies
that can't be disrupted.
AI is the ultimate disruptable asset or technology.
And that's what makes investing treacherous
is that you own a business that's enormously profitable.
Management gets, if you will, fat and happy
and then a new technology emerges
that just takes away all their profitability.
And AI is this incredibly powerful tool,
which is why every business is saying,
how can I use AI in my business
to make us more profitable, more successful,
grow faster and also disrupt
or protect ourself from the incomings,
It's a bit like, you know,
Buffett talks about a great business like a castle
surrounded by this really wide moat,
but you have all these barbarians
trying to get in and steal the princess
and it happens.
You know, Kodak for example,
was an amazing, incredibly dominant company
until it disappeared.
Polaroid, this incredible technology
and that's why we have tended to stay away
from companies that are technology companies.
'Cause technology companies generally
the world is such a dynamic place.
It's one's always working on a better version.
And you know, Kodak was caught up
in the analog film world
and then the world changed.
- Well, Google was pretty fat and happy
until Chat GPT came out.
How would you rate their ability to wake up,
lose weight, and be less happy
and aggressively rediscover their search for happiness?
- I think you've seen a lot of that in the last year
and I would say some combination of embarrassment
and pride are huge motivators
for everyone from Sergey Brin,
to the management of the company.
- And Demis Hassabis has thrown 'em into the picture
and all of DeepMind teams and the unification teams
and like all the shakeups.
It was interesting to watch the chaos, I love it.
I love it when everybody freaks out,
like you said, partly embarrassment
and partly that competitive drive that drives engineers
it was great, I can't wait to see
what there've been just a lot of improvement in the product
let's see where it goes.
You mentioned management,
how do you analyze the governance structure
and the individual humans
that are the managers of a company?
- So as I like to say, incentives drive all human behavior
and that certainly applies in the business world.
So understanding the people and what drives them
and what the actual financial
and other incentives of a business
are very important part of the analysis
for investing in a company.
And you can learn a lot.
You know I mentioned before
one great way to learn about a business is go back a decade
and read everything that management has written
about the business and see what they've done over time.
See what they've said.
Conference calls are actually relatively recent.
When I started in the business,
there weren't conference call transcripts.
Now you have a written record
of everything management has said
in response to questions from analysts
at conferences and otherwise.
You learn a lot about people by listening
to what they say, how they answer questions
and ultimately their track record
for doing what they say they're gonna do.
Do they under promise and over deliver?
Do they over promise and under deliver?
Do they say what they're gonna do?
Do they admit mistakes?
Do they build great teams?
Do people wanna come work for them
or are they able to retain their talent?
And then part of the is do they,
how much are they running the business
for the benefit of the business?
How much are they running the business
for the benefit of themselves?
And that's kind of the analysis you do.
- Are we talking about CEO, COO?
What does management mean?
Oh, how deep does it go?
- Sure. So this very senior management matters enormously.
We used the Chipotle example,
Steve Ell's great entrepreneur,
business got to a scale
he really couldn't run it.
We recruited a guy named Brian,
helped a company recruit a guy named Brian Nichol.
And he was considered the best person
in the quick service industry.
He came in and completely rebuild the company.
Actually we moved the company,
Chipotle was moved to California.
And sometimes one way to redo the culture
of a company is just to move it geographically
and then you can kind of reboot the business.
But a great leader has great followership,
well over the course of their career
they'll have a team they've built
that will come follow them into the next opportunity.
But the key is,
really the top person matters enormously
and then it's who they recruit.
You know you recruit an A+ leader
and they're gonna recruit other A type people.
You recruit a B leader,
you're not gonna recruit any great talent beneath them.
- You mentioned Warren Buffett,
you said you admire him as an investor.
What do you find most interesting
and powerful about his approach?
What aspects of his approach
to investing do you also practice?
- Sure. So most of what I've learned
in the investment business, I learned from Warren Buffett.
He's been my great professor of this business.
My first book I read in the business
was the Ben Graham "Intelligent Investor".
But fairly quickly you get to learn about Warren Buffett
and I started by reading
the Berkshire Hathaway and reports.
And then I eventually got the buffet partnership letters
that you can see, which are an amazing read
to go back to the mid 1950s
and read what he wrote to his limited partners
when he first started out
and just follow that trajectory over a long period of time.
So what's remarkable about him is one, duration, right?
He still added it at '93,
two, you know, it takes a very long-term view.
But a big thing that you learn from him,
investing requires this incredible
dispassionate on emotional quality.
You have to be extremely economically rational,
which is not a basic,
it's not something you learn in the jungle.
I don't think it's something that, you know,
if you think about
surviving the jungle the lion shows up
and everyone starts running, you run with them.
That does not work well in markets.
In fact, you generally have to do the opposite, right?
When the lemmings are running over the cliff,
that's the time where you're facing the other direction
and you're running the other direction,
i.e you're stepping in,
you're buying stocks at really low prices.
Buffet's been great at that
and great at teaching about what he calls temperament,
which is this sort of emotional kind of
or unemotional quality that you need
to be able to dispassionately look at the world
and say, okay, is this a real risk,
are people overreacting?
People tend to get excited about investments
when stocks are going up
and they get depressed when they're going down.
And I think that's just inherently human.
You have to reverse that.
You have to get excited when things get cheaper
and you gotta get concerned when things get more expensive.
- You've been a part of some big battles,
some big losses, some big wins.
So it's been a rollercoaster.
So in terms of temperament psychologically,
how do you not let that break you?
How do you maintain a calm demeanor
and avoid running with the lemmings?
- I think it's something you kind of learn over time.
A key success factor is
you wanna have enough money in the bank
that you're gonna survive
regardless of what's going on with volatility in markets.
One, you shouldn't borrow money.
So if you borrow money,
you own stocks on margin,
markets are going down
and you have your livelihood at risk,
it's very difficult to be rational.
So key is getting yourself to a place
where you're financially secure,
you're not gonna lose your house, right?
That's a kind of a key thing.
And then also doing your homework, stock prices.
Stocks can trade at any price in the short term.
And if you know what a business is worth
and you understand the management,
you know it extremely well,
it doesn't bother you when a stock price goes down
or it has much less impact on you
because you know, again, as Mr. Graham said,
you know, the short term, the market's a voting machine,
you have a bunch of lemmings
voting one direction that's concerning.
But if it's a great business doesn't have a lot of debt
and people are gonna just listen
to more music next year than this year,
you know you're gonna do well.
So it's a bit some combination of being personally secure
and also just knowing what you own
and over time you build calluses, I would say.
- So psychologically, just as a human being
speaking of lions and gazelle and all this kind of stuff.
Is it as simple as just being financially secure?
Is there some just human qualities
that you have to be born with/develop?
- I think so. I think
I'm a pretty emotional person I would say.
Or I feel pretty strong emotions, but not in investing.
I'm remarkably immune to kind of volatility
and that's a big advantage
and it took some time for me to develop that.
- So you weren't born with that, you think?
- [Bill] No.
- So being emotional, do you want to respond to volatility?
- Yeah. And you just, it's a bit...
Again, you can learn a lot from other people's experience.
It's one of the few businesses
where you can learn an enormous amount
by reading about other periods in history.
Following Buffet's career, the mistakes he made.
If you're investing a lot of capital,
every one of your mistakes can be big.
So we've made big mistakes.
The good news is that the vast majority
of things we've done have worked out really well.
And so that also gives you confidence over time.
But because we make very few investments,
we own eight things today
or seven companies of that matter,
if we get one wrong, it's gonna be big news.
And so the other nature of our business
you have to be comfortable with a lot of public scrutiny,
a lot of public criticism
and that requires some experience.
I call it that.
- I think we'll talk about some of that.
Financially secure is something
I believe also recommend
for even just to everyday investors.
Is there some general advice
from the things you've been talking about
that applies to everyday investors?
- Sure. So never invest money you can't afford to lose
where it would if you'd lost this money
and you lose your house, et cetera.
Being in a place where you're investing money
that you don't care about the price in the short term,
you know it's money for your retirement
and you take a really long term view, I think that's key.
Never investing, you borrow money against your securities?
You know the markets offer you the opportunity
to leverage your investment
and in most worlds you'll be okay,
except if there's a financial crisis
or a nuclear device gets detonated,
God forbid somewhere in the world,
or there's a unexpected war
or someone kills a leader unexpectedly.
Things happen that can change the course of history
and markets react very negatively to those kinds of events.
And you can own the greatest business in the world,
trading for $100 a share
and next moment it could be 50.
So as long as you don't borrow against securities,
you own really high quality businesses
and it's not money that you need in the short term,
then you can actually be thoughtful about it
and that is a huge advantage.
The vast majority of investors it seems
tend to be the ones that panic
and the downturns get over elated
when markets are doing well.
- So be able to think long-term
and be sufficiently financially secure
such that you can afford to think long-term.
- Yeah, Buffett is the ultimate long-term thinker
and just the decisions he makes,
the consistency of the decisions he's made over time
and fitting into that sort of long-term framework
is a very, very educational,
let's put it that way for learning about this business.
- So you mentioned eight companies,
but what do you think about mutual funds
for everyday investors that diversify
across a larger number of companies?
- I think there are very few mutual funds.
There are thousands and thousands of mutual funds.
There are very few that earn their keep
in terms of the fees they charge.
They tend to be too diversified
and too short term.
And you're often much better off
just buying an index fund.
And many of them perform,
if you look carefully their portfolios
are not so different from the underlying index itself
and you tend to pay a much higher fee.
Now, all of that being said,
there's some very talented mutual fund managers,
a guy named Will Danoff at Fidelity's
had a great record over a long period of time.
You know, the famous Peter Lynch, Ron Baron,
another great long-term growth stock investor.
So there's some great mutual funds,
but I put them in the handful versus the thousands.
And if you're in the thousands
I'd rather someone bought just an index fund basically,
- Yeah, index funds.
But what would be the leap for an everyday investor
to go to investing in a small number of companies
like two, three, four, five companies?
- I even recommend for individual investors
to invest in a dozen companies.
You don't get that much more benefit
of diversification going from a dozen to 25 or even 50.
Most of the benefits diversification
come in the first, you know, call it 10 or 12.
And if you're investing in businesses
that don't have a lot of debt,
they're businesses that you can understand yourself.
You understand, you know,
actually individual investors did a much better job
analyzing Tesla than the so-called professional investors
or analysts, the vast majority of them.
So if it's a business, you understand
if you bought a Tesla, you understand the product
and its appeal to consumers.
It's a good place to start when you're analyzing a company.
So I would invest in things you can understand
that's kind of a key.
You know you like Chipotle,
you understand why they're successful.
You can go there every week and you can monitor
is anything changing?
You know, how these new kind of,
how's chicken el pastor is that a good upgrade
from the basic chicken,
The drink offerings improving, the store is clean.
I think you should invest
in companies you really understand.
Simple businesses where you can predict
with a high degree of confidence
what it's gonna look like over time.
And if you do that
in a not particularly concentrated fashion
and you don't borrow money against your securities,
you're probably do much better
than your typical mutual fund.
- Yeah, it's interesting.
Consumers that love a thing
are actually good analysts of that thing,
or I guess a good starting point.
- And by the way,
there's much more information available today.
When I was first investing,
literally we had people faxing us documents
from the SEC filings in Washington DC.
Now everything's available online,
conference call transcripts are free.
You have AI, you have unlimited data
and all kinds of message boards and Reddit forums
and things where people are sharing advice.
And everyone has their own,
you know, by virtue of their career or experience
they'll know about an industry or a business
and that gives them...
I would take advantage of your own competitive advantages.
- I'm just afraid if I invest in Chipotle,
I'll be like analyzing every little change of menu
from a financial perspective
and just be very critical.
- If it's gonna affect your experience
I wouldn't buy the stock.
- Yeah, I mean I should also say that
I am somebody that emotionally does respond to volatility,
which is why I've never bought index funds
and I just notice myself psychologically
being affected by the ups and downs of the market.
I want to tune out because if I'm at all tuned in
and has a negative impact on my life.
- Yeah, that's really important.
- Can you explain what activist investing is?
You've been talking about investing
and then looking at companies when they're struggling,
stepping in and reconfiguring things within that company
and helping it become great.
So that's part of it,
but let's just sum out,
what's this idea of activist investing?
- I think recently in the last couple of days
I read an article saying that
more than 50% of the capital in the world today
that's invest in the stock markets,
passive indexed money.
And that's the most passive form, right?
So if you think about an index fund,
a machine buys a fixed set of securities
in certain proportion.
There's no human judgment at all.
And there's no real person behind it in a way.
They never take steps to improve a business.
They just quietly own securities.
What we do is we invest our capital in a handful of things.
We get to know them really, really well.
'Cause you're gonna put 20%
of your assets in something you need to know it really well.
But once you become a big holder
and if you've got some thoughts
on how to make a business more valuable,
you can do more than just be a passive investor.
So our strategy is built upon
finding great companies in some cases
that have lost their way and then helping them succeed.
And we can do that with ideas from outside the boardroom.
Sometimes we take a seat on a board
or more than one,
and we work with the best management teams in the world
to help these businesses succeed.
So when I first went into this business
no one knew who we were
and we didn't have that much money.
And so to influence what was to us a big company,
we had to make a fair bit more noise, right?
So we would buy a stake,
we'd announced it publicly,
we'd attempt to engage with management.
The first activist investment we made
at Persian Square was Wendy's.
I couldn't get the CEO to ever return my call.
He didn't even return my call.
So we actually, in that case,
our idea was Wendy's owned a company called Tim Horton's,
which was this coffee donut chain.
And you could buy Wendy's for basically $5 billion
and they owned a hundred percent of Tim Horton's,
which itself was worth more than 5 billion.
So you could literally buy Wendy's,
separate Tim Horton's and get Wendy's for negative value.
That seemed like a pretty good opportunity
even though the business wasn't doing that well.
So we bought the stake called the CEO,
couldn't get a meeting, nothing.
So we hired actually Blackstone,
which was at that time an investment bank.
And we hired them to do what's called a fairness opinion
of what Wendy's would be worth
if they followed our advice
and they agreed to do it, paid 'em a fee for it.
And then we mailed in a letter
with a copy of the fairness opinion
saying Wendy's would basically be worth 80% more
if they did what we said.
And six weeks later they did what we said.
So that's activism, at least an early form of activism.
With that kind of under our belt,
we had a little more credibility
and now we started to take things
and stakes in companies.
The media would pay attention.
So the media became a kind of an important partner
and some combination of shame, embarrassment
and opportunity motivated
management teams to do the right thing.
And then beyond that
there's certain steps you can take
if management's recalcitrant
and the shareholders are on your side.
But it's a bit like running for office.
You've gotta get all the constituents
to support you and your ideas.
And if they support you and your ideas,
you can overthrow, if you will, the board of a company.
You bring in new talent
and then take over the management of a business.
And that's the most extreme form of activism.
So that's kind of the early days.
And what we did, and a lot of the early things
that we did were
we call it sort of like investment banking activism
where we'd go in and recommend something,
a good investment bank would've recommended.
And if they do it, we make a bunch of money
and then we moved on to the next one.
And then we realized an investment,
a company called General Growth
was the first time we took a board seat on a company.
And there it was some financial restructuring
and also an opportunity to improve the operations
of the business, sit on the board of a company.
And that was one of the best investments we ever made.
And we said, okay, we can do more
than just be an outside the boardroom investor
and we can get involved in
helping select the right management teams
and helping guide the right management teams.
And then we've done that over years.
And then I would say the last seven years
we haven't had to be an activist.
An activist is generally someone
who's outside banging on the door, trying to get in.
We've sort of built enough credibility
that they open the door
and they say, "Hey Bill, what ideas do you have?
"So welcome. Would you like to join the board?"
We're treated differently today
than we were in the beginning.
And that is,
I would say some people might just call it
being an engaged owner.
And that by the way,
that's the way investing was done in the Andrew Carnegie,
JP Morgan days, 150 years ago, right?
You had these iconic business leaders
that would own 20% of US steel,
and when things would go wrong,
they'd replaced the board and the management and fix them.
And over time we went to a world where mutual funds
were created like in the 1920s, '30s,
index funds with Vanguard and others.
And that all these controlling shareholders
would kind of gave their stock to society
or their children and multiple generations
and there were no longer kind of controlling
owners of businesses were very few.
And that led to underperformance
and the opportunity for activists over time.
And what activism has done,
and I think we've helped lead this movement,
is it restored kind of the balance of power
between the owners of the business
and the managements of the company.
And that's been a very good thing for the performance
of the US stock market actually.
- So the owners meaning the shareholders?
- [Bill] Yes.
- And so there's a more direct channel of communication
with activists investing between the shareholders
and the people running the company.
- Yes. So activists generally never own more than
five or 10% of a business.
So they don't have control.
So the way they get influence
is they have to convince the other
but they have to get to sort of a majority
of the other shareholders to support them.
And if they can get that kind of support,
they can behave almost like a controlling shareholder,
and that's how it works.
- So the running of a company's
according to Bill Ackman is more democratic now?
- It is, it is.
But you need some thought leaders.
So activists are kind of thought leaders
'cause they can spend the time and the money.
You know, a retail investor that owns a thousand shares
doesn't have the resources or the time, they got a day job.
Whereas an activist day job
is finding the handful of things
where there are opportunities.
- So on average, is it good to have such an engaged,
powerful, influential investor
helping control the direction of a company?
- It depends who that investor is,
but generally I think it's a good thing.
And that's why one of the problems
with being CEO of a company today
and having a very diversified shareholder base
is the kind of short term, long term balance.
And you have investors who have all different interests
in terms of what they want achieve
and when they wanted it achieved.
And CEO of a new company hasn't had...
A new CEO of an old company, let's say,
hasn't had the chance to develop the credibility
to make the kinda longer term decisions
and can be stuck in a cycle
of being judged on a quarterly basis.
And a business, the best businesses are forever assets
and decisions you make now have impact three,
four or five years from now.
And sometimes there are decisions we make
that have the effect of reducing
the earnings of a company in the short term
because in the long term
it's gonna make the business much more valuable.
But it's sometimes it's hard
to have that kind of credibility
when you're a new CEO of a company.
So when you have a major owner that's respected
by other shareholders sitting on the board saying,
hey, the CEO's doing the right thing
and making this expensive investment in a new factory,
we're spending more money on R&D
because we're developing something
that's gonna pay off over time.
That large owner on the board
can help buy the time necessary
for management to behave in a longer term way.
And that's, I think, good for all the shareholders.
- So that's the good story.
But can it get bad?
Can you have a CEO who is a visionary
and sees the long-term future of a company
and an investor come in
and have very selfish interest
in just making more money in the short term
and therefore destroy
and manipulate the opinions of the shareholders
and other people on the board in order to sink the company,
maybe increase the price,
but destroy the possibility of long-term value?
- It could theoretically happen,
but again, the activist in your example,
generally doesn't own a lot of stock.
The shareholder bases today,
the biggest shareholders are these index funds
that are forever, right?
The BlackRock, Vanguard, State Street,
their ownership stakes are just at this point
only growing 'cause of the inflows of capital
they have from shareholders.
So they have to think or they should think very long term
and they're gonna be very skeptical
of someone coming in with a short term idea
that drives the stock price up
in the next six months.
But impairs the company's long-term ability to compete.
And basically that ownership group
prevents this kind of activity from really happening.
- So people are generally skeptical,
short-term activist investors?
- Yes, and they're very few.
I don't really know any short-term activist investors.
Not ones with credibility.
- You mentioned General Growth.
I read somewhere called arguably
one of the best hedge fund trades of all time.
So I guess it went from $60 million to over 3 billion.
- It was a good one.
But it wasn't a trade,
I wouldn't describe it as a trade.
A trade is something you buy and you flip.
This is something where we made the investment initially
in November of 2008,
and then we still own a company
we spun off of General Growth
and it's now 15 years later.
- Can you describe what went into making that decision
to actually increasing the value of the company?
- Sure. So this was at the time of the financial crisis
circa November, 2008.
What real estate's always been a kind of sector
that I've been interested in.
I began my career in the real estate business
working for my dad actually
ranging mortgages for real estate developers.
So I have kind of deep ties
and interest in the business
and General Growth was the second largest
shopping mall company in the country.
Simon Properties, many people have heard of,
General Growth was number two.
They owned some of the best malls in the country.
And at that time people thought of shopping malls
as these non-disruptively things.
Again, we talk about disruption.
Malls have been disrupted in many ways.
And General Growth, the company,
the CFO in particular was very aggressive
in the way that he borrowed money,
and he borrowed money from a kind of Wall Street,
not long-term mortgages
but generally relatively short-term mortgages.
It was pretty aggressive as the value went up,
he would borrow more and more against the assets
and that helped the short-term results of the business.
The problem was during the financial crisis,
the market for what's called CMBS,
commercial mortgage backed securities basically shut
and the company 'cause its debt was relatively short term,
had a lot of big maturities coming up
that they had no ability to refinance.
And the market said, oh my god,
the lenders are gonna foreclose
and the shareholders are gonna get wiped.
The company's gonna go bankrupt,
they're gonna get wiped out.
The stock went from $63 a share to 34 cents.
There was a family, the bucks bound family owned
I think about 25% of the company
and they had 5 billion of stock
that was worth 25 million or something by the time
we bought a stake in the business.
And what interested me was
I thought the assets were worth
substantially more than the liabilities.
The company had 27 billion of debt
and had a hundred million dollars value
of the equity down from like 20 billion.
And one that, you know,
sort of an interesting place to start with a stock down 99%.
But the fundamental drivers,
the mall business are occupancy.
How occupied are the malls.
Occupancy was up year on year between '07 and '08.
Interestingly, net operating income,
which is kind of of a measure of cash flow from the malls,
that was up year on year.
So kind of the underlying fundamentals were doing fine.
The only problem they had is they had
billions of dollars of debt that they had to repay,
they couldn't repay.
And if you kind of examine the bankruptcy code
that it's precisely designed for a situation like this
where it's kind of this resting place you can go
to kind of restructure your business.
Now the problem was that every other company
that had gone bankrupt, the shareholders got wiped out.
And so the market's seeing every previous example,
the shareholders get wiped out
the assumptions is this stocks gonna go to zero.
But that's not what the bankruptcy code says.
What the bankruptcy code says is that
the value gets apportioned based on value.
And if you could prove to a judge
that there was the assets worth more than the liabilities,
then the shareholders actually get to keep
their investment in the company.
And that was the bet we made.
And so we stepped into the market
and we bought 25% of the company in the open market.
We had to pay up.
It started out at 34 cents,
I think there were 300 million shares.
So it was at a hundred million dollars value.
By the time we were done
we paid an average of,
we paid 60 million for 25% of the business.
So about $240 million for the equity of the company.
And then we had to get on the board
to convince the directors the right thing to do.
And the board was in complete panic,
didn't know what to do,
spending a ton of money on advisors.
And you know, I was a shareholder activist,
four years into Pershing Square
and no one had any idea what we were doing.
They thought we were crazy every day stock.
Every day we'd go into the market
and we'd buy this penny stock
and we'd file what's called a 13 D,
every 1% increase in our stake.
And people just thought we were crazy.
We're buying stock in a company that's gonna go bankrupt.
Bill, you're gonna lose all your money, you know, run.
And I said, well wait, you know, bankruptcy code says
that it was more asset value than liabilities.
We should be fine.
And the key moment if you're looking for fun moments
is there's a woman named Maddie Buxbaum
who was from the Bucksbaum family
and her cousin John was chairman of the board,
CEO of the company.
And I said, as she calls me
after we disclose our stake in the company,
she's like, "Billy Ackman, I'm really glad to see you here".
And I met her like, I don't think it was a date,
but I kind of met her in a social context
when I was like 25 or something.
And she said, "Look, I'm really glad to see you here
"and if there's anything I can do to help you call me".
I said sure.
We kept trying to get on the board of the company,
they wouldn't invite us on,
couldn't really run a proxy contest
not with a company going bankrupt.
And their advisors actually were Goldman Sachs
and they're like, you don't want the fox in the hen house.
And they were listening to their advisors.
So I called Maddie up
and I said, "Maddie, I need to get on the board
"of the company to help".
And she says, "You know what, I will call my cousin
"and I'll get it done".
Like, you know, she calls back a few hours later,
you'll be going onto the board.
I don't know what she said to the cousin.
- Well, she was convincing.
- Next thing you know, I'm invited to on the board
of the company and the board is talking about
the old equity of General Growth.
Old equity is what you talk about
the shareholders are getting wiped out.
I said, no, no, no, this board represents
the current equity of the company
and I'm a major shareholder.
John's a major shareholder.
There's plenty of asset value here.
This company should be able to be restructured
for the benefit of shareholders.
And we led a restructuring for the benefit of shareholders
and it took, let's say eight months
and the company emerged from chapter 11.
We made an incremental investment into the company
and the shareholders kept
the vast majority of their investment.
All the creditors got their face amount of their investment
par plus accruede interest.
And it was a great outcome.
All the employees kept their jobs.
The mall stayed open, there's no liquidation.
The bankruptcy system worked the way it should.
You know, I was in court all the time.
And the first meeting with the judge,
the judge was like,
"Look, this would never have happened
"were it not for a financial crisis".
And once the judge said that I knew we were gonna be fine
because the company really not done
anything fundamentally wrong,
maybe a little too aggressive in how they borrowed money.
And stock went from 34 cents to $31 a share.
And actually fun little anecdote,
we made a lot of people
a lot of money who followed us into it.
I got a lot of nice thank you notes,
which you get on occasion in this business,
believe it or not.
And then one day I get a voicemail,
this is when there was something called voicemail
probably a few years later.
And it's a guy with a very thick Jamaican accent
leaving a message for Bill Ackman.
So you know, I return all my calls.
Call the guy back, I said,
"Hi, it's Bill Ackman, I'm just returning your call".
He says, "Oh Mr. Ackman, thank you so much for calling me".
And I said, "Oh, how can I help?"
He says, "I wanted to thank you".
I said, "What do you mean?"
He said, "I saw you on CNBC a couple years ago
"and you were talking about
"this General Growth and the stock".
I said, "Where was the stock at the time?"
He said, "It's 60 cents or something like this.
"And I bought a lot of stock".
And I'm like, "Well how much did you invest?"
"Oh, I invest all of my money in the company".
And he was a New York City taxi driver
and he invested like $50,000
or something like this at 60 cents a share.
And he was still holding it.
And he went into retirement
and he made, you know, 50 times as money.
And you know, those are the moments
that you feel pretty good about investing.
- What gave you confidence through that.
Went to penny stock and I'm sure
you were getting a lot of naysayers
and people saying that this is crazy.
- It's the same thing. You just do the work.
Like we got a lot of pushback from our investors actually.
'Cause we had never invested in a bankrupt company before.
It's a field called distressed investing
and they're dedicated distressed investors
and we weren't considered one of them.
So Bill, what are are you doing?
You don't know anything about distressed investing.
You don't know anything about bankruptcy investing.
But I can read.
- And you learned.
- And I learned and it sometimes it's very helpful
not to be a practitioner, an expert in something,
'cause you get used to the conventional wisdom.
And so we just, you know, abstractly read
the step back and looked at the facts
and it was just a really interesting setup
for one of the best investments we ever made.
- How hard is it to learn some of the legal aspects of this?
Like you mentioned bankruptcy code.
Like I imagine is very sort of dense language
and dense ideas and the loopholes
and all that kind of stuff.
Like if you're just stepping in
and you've never done distressed investing,
how hard is it to figure out?
- It's not that hard.
No, it's not that hard.
I mean, I literally read a book on distressed investing.
Ben Branch or something,
something on distressed investing.
- So you were able to pick up the intuition from that.
Just all the basic skills involved,
the basic facts to know all that kind of stuff.
- Most of the world's knowledge
is already been written somewhere.
You just gotta read the right books.
And also had great lawyers,
built up some great relationships.
We worked with Sullivan and Cromwell
and the lawyer there named Joe Schenker,
who I met earlier in my career.
Pershing Score is actually my second act
in the hedge fund business.
I started a fund called Gotham Partners when I was 26.
One of my early investments
was a company called Rockefeller Center Properties
that was heading for bankruptcy.
And the lawyer on the other side representing Goldman Sachs
was a guy named Joe Schenker.
So he was like an obvious phone call
'cause we had yet another real estate bankruptcy.
And that one we did very well.
But I missed the big opportunity
and I suffered severe psychological torture
every time I walked by Rockefeller Center
because we could've made,
we knew more about that property than anyone else,
but I knew less about deal making
and didn't have the resources.
And I was 28 years old or 27,
and they hired a better lawyer than we did
and they outsmarted us on that one in a way.
So I said, okay, I'm gonna go hire this guy
the next time around.
- Okay, we'll probably talk about Rockefeller Center
and some failures,
but first you said Fox in the henhouse.
Something that the board
and the chairman were worried about.
Why would they call you a fox?
So you keep saying activist investing is,
there's nothing to worry about.
It's always good, mostly good.
But you know, that expression applied in this context,
they were still worried about that.
And so, I mean, there's a million questions here,
but first of all, what is the process
of getting on the board look like?
- So a board can always admit a member at any time
in their discretion for a US company
that maybe there's some jurisdiction
where you need a shareholder vote.
But in most cases a board can vote on
any director that they want.
If the board doesn't invite you to the party,
you have to apply to be a member in effect.
And that process is called,
basically it's the process
of ultimately running a slate for a meeting
where you propose a number.
Any shareholder can propose
to be on a board of a company
if they own a one share of stock in the business.
And getting your name in the company's,
you know, in the materials they sent to shareholders
those rules were written in a way that were very unfavorable
and very difficult to get in the door.
And those rules have been changed very recently
where the company now has to include a candidate,
really all the candidates
and the materials they sent to shareholders,
so the shareholders pick the best ones.
When we applied or when we applied,
when we ran proxy contests in the past
that was not the case.
And so you have to spend a lot of money,
mostly mailing fees and all kinds of other legal
and other expenses to let everyone know you're running,
like running a political campaign.
And then you gotta run around
and meet with the big shareholders,
you know, fly around the country,
explain your case to them,
and then there's a shareholder meeting.
And if you get a majority of the votes you get on.
- What's this proxy contest/battle idea?
What's--
- The battle comes when they don't want you to get on.
And a lot of that has to do with, I would say pride,
normal human kind of stuff.
You know, a lot of times a board
of an underperforming company doesn't wanna admit
that they've underperformed
and boards of directors,
20 years ago when we started Pershing Square,
were pretty cushy jobs.
Sit on a board of a company,
you play golf with a CEO at nice golf courses,
you make a few hundred thousand dollars a year
to go to four meetings.
It was kind of a rubber stamp world where boards, you know,
at the end of the day the CEO really ran the show.
Once shareholders could actually dislodge board members
and they could lose their seats,
and that's really the rise of shareholder activism.
Boards started taking their responsibilities
much more seriously,
because directors are typically,
you know, there are many cases they're retired CEOs,
this is kind of how they're making a living
in the later part of their career.
They'll sit on four boards,
they collect a million half dollars a year
in director's fees
if they get thrown off the board by the shareholders,
that's embarrassing, obviously
and it affects their ability to get on other boards.
So again, incentives, as I said earlier,
drive all human behavior.
The incentives directors,
they wanna preserve their board seats.
Now the directors on board serve in various roles.
The most vulnerable ones are ones who, for example,
chair a compensation committee.
And if they put in a bad plan
or they overpaid management,
they're subject to attack by shareholders.
But you know, these contests are not dissimilar
to political contests.
Whereas Mudslinging
and other side puts out false information about you
and you have to respond and they're
spending the shareholders' money.
So they have sort of unlimited resources.
And you're spending your
and your investors' money, you know,
when you're a small firm, finite resources.
So they can outspend you, they can sue you, they can try to,
you know, jigger the mechanics in such a way
that you're gonna lose,
there's some unfortunate stuff that's happened in the past,
you know manipulative stuff.
- So also some stuff that's public,
like in the press and all this kind of stuff.
- Oh, of course. You know, there'll be articles about
the dirty days where they would go
through your trash and make sure that
you're not sleeping around and things like this.
But that's okay.
I'm subject, I can survive extreme scrutiny
'cause I've been through this for a long time.
- So you're saying the fat
and happy hens can get very wolf like
when the fox is trying to break in,
is this how do we extend this metaphor?
- Well, the fox is a threat to the hens.
- Yeah. But the charismatic fox
just explain to me why the fox
is good for everybody in the henhouse.
- At the end of the day,
it's actually very good on a board to have someone,
you know, there are many examples over time
and some handful of high profile ones
where the board fought tooth and nail
to keep the activists off the board.
And then once the activists got on the board
and they said the guy's not so bad after all
the shareholders voted them on,
it's got some decent ideas
and let's all work together to have this work out.
And so there are very few cases
where after the contest,
and by the way, sometimes
you have to replace the entire board.
We've done that.
But in most cases you got a couple of seats on the board
and it's just you wanna build a board
comprised of diverse points of view.
And that's how you get to the truth.
- What was the most dramatic battle for the board
that you have been a part of?
- The Canadian Pacific Proxy contest.
So Canadian Pacific was like considered
the most iconic company in Canada.
It literally built the country
because the rail that got built over Canada
is what united the various provinces into a country.
And then over time,
'cause the railroad business is pretty good business,
they built a ton of hotels,
they owned a lot of real estate
and it became this massive conglomerate,
but it was horribly mismanaged for decades.
By the time we got involved,
it was by far the worst run railroad in North America.
They had the lowest profit margins,
they had the lowest growth rate.
The every quarter management would make excuses generally
about the weather as to why they underperform versus,
and there there's a direct competitor,
a company called Canadian National
has a rail goes right across the country
and Canadian Pacific would constantly
be complaining about the weather.
And basically same country, same regions,
tracks weren't that far apart.
But it was a really important company
and being on this board was like an honorary thing.
And everyone on the board was an icon of Canada,
the chairman of the Royal Bank of Canada,
the head of the most important grain,
privately held grain company.
The sort of an important collection of
big time Canadian executives.
Here we were, you know, this is probably about 13 years ago
and still maybe 44-year-old from New York, not a Canadian
basically saying this is the worst run
railroad in North America.
And we bought 12% of the railroad at a really low price.
And we brought with us to our first meeting
the greatest railroader ever,
a guy named Hunter Harrison
who had turned around Canadian national.
So we'd like, okay, we've got a great asset,
we've got the greatest railroad CEO of all time.
He's come outta retirement to step in and run the railroad.
And we brought him to the first meeting
and they wouldn't even meet with him.
And they wouldn't certainly
weren't gonna consider hiring him
and that led us to a proxy contest.
- And this is where the engine starts churning
to figure out how this contest can be won.
So what's involved in a--
- Well the key is we had to one, come up with a group
of directors who would be willing to step into a battle.
And we didn't want a bunch of New York directors
or even American directors, we wanted Canadians.
The problem was this was the most iconic company in Canada,
and we wanted high profile people.
So we talked to all the high profile people in Canada.
Every one of them would say,
Bill, you're entirely right.
This thing is the worst run railroad, it needs to be fixed.
But you know, I see John at the club,
I see him at the Toronto Club,
I can't do this, but you're totally right.
And we had to, and that was the concern
you have to file your materials by a certain day,
you gotta put together a slate.
We needed a big slate 'cause we knew
that we had to replace basically all the directors.
And then one, I spoke to a guy
who was one of the wealthiest guys in Canada
who was on the board at one point in time.
And he said, "Bill, I have an idea for you.
"There's this woman, Rebecca McDonald's,
"why don't you give her a call?"
And I called Rebecca and she was the first woman
to take a company public in Canada as CEO.
And she was a kind of anti-establishment,
not afraid to take on anything kind of person.
And I called her, we had a great conversation
and she was in the Dominican Republic at her house.
And I flew down to see her and she said, "Yeah, I'm all in".
And actually, once we got her,
that enabled us to get others.
And then we put together our slate
and we had some pretty
interesting dialogue with the company.
They tried to embarrass us all the time.
- In the press publicly, what are we talking about?
- Press publicly.
You know, at one point I wrote an email saying,
look, let's come to peace on this thing,
but if we don't you're really forcing my hand
and we're gonna have to rent the largest hall in Toronto
and invite all the shareholders
and it's gonna be embarrassing for management.
And I made reference to some nuclear winter,
let's not have it be a nuclear winter.
And they thought they'd embarrass me by releasing the email,
but it only inspired us.
And we rented the largest hall in Canada
and we put up a presentation walking through,
here's Canadian National, here's Canadian Pacific,
here's what they said, here's what they did.
And then we had Hunter get up,
who's this incredibly charismatic guy from Tennessee,
an amazing, he's like a lion, okay.
Incredibly deep voice,
unbelievable track record,
incredibly respected guy.
It's like getting Michael Jordan to come out of retirement
and come and run the company.
And Hunter was incredible.
And other Paul Ell,
other members of my team were super engaged.
And the board, Canadians are known to be nice.
So one of the problems we had is shareholders
would never tell management or the board
that they were losing.
It was not until the night before the meeting
when the vote came in,
that management realized that they lost,
we got 99% of the vote.
And they offered us a deal
when they begged us to take a deal.
They said, look, we'll resign tonight
so that we don't have to come to the meeting tomorrow.
That's how embarrassed they were.
But that was kind of a interesting one.
- So for in both this proxy battle
and the company itself,
this was a one of your more successful investments?
- It was.
I mean the stock's up about 10 times
and it's an industrial company.
It's a railroad, it's not like a growth.
Like, it's not Google.
So it's a great story.
And the company's now run by a guy named Keith Creel.
And Keith, it was Hunter's protege.
And in some many ways he's actually better than Hunter.
He's doing an incredible job.
The sad part here is we made it, we did very well.
We tripled our money over several years.
And then I went through a very challenging period
because of a couple of bad investments
and we had to sell our Canadian Pacific
to raise capital to pay for investors who were leaving.
But we had another opportunity to buy it back
in the last couple of years.
And so we're now again a major owner of the company,
but had we held onto original stock,
it would've been epic, if you will.
- So on this one, you were right.
- [Bill] Yes.
- And I read an article about you
and there's many articles about you.
I read an article that said Bill is often right,
but you approach it with a scorched earth approach
that can often do more sort of damage.
- I haven't read the often right article,
but the good news is we are often right
and I say we because we're a team,
small team, but a fortunately very successful one.
You know, so our batting average
as investors is extremely high.
And the good news is our record's totally public.
You can see everything we've ever done.
But the press doesn't generally write
about the success stories, they write about the failures.
And so we've had some epic failures, big losses.
Good news is they've been a tiny minority of the cases.
Now, no one likes to lose money.
It's even worse to lose other people's money.
And I've done that occasionally.
The good news is, if you've stuck with us,
you've done very well over a long time.
- On a small tangent since we were talking about boards,
did you get a chance to see
what happened with the Open AI board?
Because I'm talking to Sam Waltman soon.
Is there any insight you have,
just maybe lessons you draw from these kinds of events,
especially with an AI technology company,
such dramatic things happening.
- Yeah, that was an incredible story.
Look, governance really matters.
And the governance structure of open AI
I think leaves something to be desired.
You know, I think Sam's point was this and maybe Musk,
Elon Musk point originally set up as a nonprofit.
And it reminds me actually,
I invested in a nonprofit run by a former Facebook founder
where he was gonna create a Facebook-like entity
for nonprofits to promote goodness in the world.
And the problem was he couldn't hire the talent he wanted
'cause he couldn't grant stock options,
he couldn't pay market salaries.
And ultimately he ended up selling the business
to a for-profit.
So it taught me for-profit solutions to problems
are much better than nonprofits.
And here you had kind of a blend, right?
It was set up as a nonprofit,
but I think they found the same thing.
They couldn't hire the talent they wanted
without having a for-profit subsidiary.
But the nonprofit entity, as I understand it,
owns or a big chunk of Open AI
and the investors own sort of a capped interest
where their upside is capped
and they don't have representation on the board.
And I think that was a setup for a problem
and that's clearly what happened here.
- And there's I guess some kind of
complexity in the governance.
I mean, because of this nonprofit and cap profit thing,
it seems like there's a bunch of complexity
and non-standard aspects to it
that perhaps also contributed to the problem.
- Yeah, governance really matters.
Boards of directors really matter.
Giving the shareholders the right to have input
at least once a year on the structure of the governance
of companies is really important.
And private venture backed boards
are also not ideal.
You know, I'm an active investor in ventures
and there are some complicated issues that emerge
in private as sort of venture stage companies
where board members have somewhat divergent incentives from
the long-term owners of a business.
And what you see a lot in venture boards is
they're presided over generally by
venture capital investors
who are big investors in the company.
And oftentimes it's more important to them to give the,
to have the public perception
that they're good directors
so they get the next best deal, right?
If they have a reputation for kind of taking
on management too aggressively
word will get out in the small community of founders
and they'll miss the next Google.
And so their interests are not just
in that particular company,
that's also, you know, one of the problems.
Again, it all comes back to incentives.
- Can you explain to me the difference
a venture backed like VCs and shareholders?
So this means before the company goes public.
- Yeah. So private venture backed companies,
the boards tend to be very small,
could be a handful of the venture investors and management.
They're often very rarely independent directors.
It's just not an ideal structure.
- Oh, I see. You want independent.
- It's beneficial to have people
who have an economic interest in the business
and they care only about the success of that company
as opposed to someone who
if you think about the venture business,
getting into the best deals
is more important than any one deal.
And you see cases where the boards go along with,
in some sense cases bad behavior on the part of management
because they want a reputation for being kind of
a founder friendly director.
You know that's kind of problematic.
You don't have the same issue in public company boards.
- So we talked about some of the big wins
and you're a track record,
but you said there were some big losses.
So what's the biggest loss of your career?
- Biggest loss in my career
is a company called Vion Pharmaceuticals.
We made an investment in business
that didn't meet our core principles,
problem in the pharmaceutical industry
and there are many problems, as I've learned,
is it's a very volatile business, right?
It's based on drug discovery,
it's based on predicting kinda the future revenues
of a drug before it goes off patent.
You know lots of complexities.
And we thought we had found
a pharmaceutical company we could own
'cause of a very unusual founder
in the way he approached this business.
It was a company where another activist
was on the board of directors of the company
and kind of governing
and overseeing the day-to-day decisions.
And we ended up making a passive investment in the company.
And up until this point in time,
we really didn't make passive investments.
And the company made a series of decisions
that were disastrous
and then we stepped in to try to solve the problem.
It was the first time I ever joined a board
and the mess was much larger
than I realized from the outside.
And then I was kind of stuck.
And it was very much a confidence sensitive strategy,
'cause they built their business
by acquiring pharmaceutical assets
and they often issued stock
when they acquired targets.
And so once the market lost confidence in management,
the stock price got crushed
and it impaired their ability
to continue to acquire low costs drugs.
And we lost $4 billion.
- $4 billion?
- Yeah. How's that for a big loss?
- [Lex] That's--
- It's up there.
- I'm sweating this whole conversation,
both the wins and the losses and the stakes involved.
- And by the way, that loss catalyzed other,
what I call market to market losses.
So very high profile, huge number, disastrous press.
Then people said, okay, Bill's gonna go outta business,
so we're gonna bet against everything he's doing
and we know his entire
portfolio 'cause we only own 10 things.
And we were short a company called Herbalife.
Very famously, we've only really shorted two companies.
The first one, there's a book,
the second one there's a movie.
Okay, we no longer short companies,
so people pushed up the price of Herbalife,
which is when you're a short seller, that's catastrophic.
I can explain that.
And then they also shorted the other stocks that we owned.
And so that valiant loss
led to an overall more than 30% loss
in the value of our portfolio.
The valiant loss was real and was crystallized.
We ended up selling the position taking that loss.
Most of the other losses were what I would call
market to market losses that were temporary.
But many people go outta business
because as I mentioned before, large move in a price.
If investors are redeeming or you have leverage,
you know, can put you outta business.
And people assumed if we got put outta business,
we'd have to sell everything
or cover our short position
and that would make the losses even worse,
so Wall Street is kind of ruthless.
- So they can make money off of that whole thing?
- [Bill] Absolutely.
- So they use the opportunity of Valiant
to try to destroy you, reputation,
financially, and then capitalize on,
make money off of that?
- [Bill] Yes.
- Well, that's a terrifying spot to be in.
What was it like going through that?
- I was pretty grim.
It's actually much worse than that
because I had a lot of stuff going on personally as well
and these things tend to be correlated.
The valiant mistake came at a time
where I was contemplating my marriage
and I was also...
The problem with the hedge fund business
is when you get to a certain scale,
the CEO becomes like
the chief marketing officer of the business.
And I'm really an investor as opposed to a marketing guy.
But when you have investors who give you
a few hundred million dollars,
they wanna see you, you know,
once a year bill, I'd love to see you for an hour.
But if you've got a couple hundred of those,
you find yourself on a plane to the Middle East to Asia,
flying around the country.
This is pre Zoom
and that takes you away from the investment process.
You have to delegate more.
That was a contributor to the valiant mistake.
So now we lose a ton of money on valiant.
My ex-wife and I were talking about separating,
getting divorced, I put that on hold.
So I didn't wanna make a decision
in the middle of this crisis.
And things just kept getting worse.
We were also sued when you lose a lot of money.
We didn't get sued by our investors,
but we got sued by a shareholder
because when the stock price goes down, shareholders sue,
we'd done nothing wrong other than make a big mistake.
So you have litigation,
your investors are taking their money out.
I'm in the middle of a divorce,
the divorce starts to proceed.
My ex-wife's lawyer's expectations
of what my net worth was about
three times what it actually was
and it was going lower right in the middle of this.
And I remember the lawyer saying,
"Look Bill, estimate your net worth at X,
"but don't worry, we only want a third".
But X was 3X so a third was a hundred percent (laughs)
And then I had litigation and actually never
before publicly disclosed,
and I'll share it with you now.
We had a public company that owned
about a third of our portfolio
that was called our version of Berkshire Hathaway.
I tried to learn from Mr. Buffett over time,
and it was, so to speak, permanent capital.
The problem with hedge funds
is people can take their money out every quarter.
What Buffet has is a company
where people wanna take their money out,
they sell the stock, but the money stays.
So we set up a similar structure in October of 2014,
and then a year later Valiant happens,
and then a year later we're in the middle
of the mess and we're still in the mess.
You know, like by kind of mid 2017,
we've got litigation underway
and another activist investor,
a firm called Elliot Associates,
which is run by a guy named Paul Singer,
took a big position in our public company
that was the bulk of our capital
and they shorted all the stocks that we owned.
And they went long.
The short probably went long, the short
that we were short
and they were making a bet that we'd be forced to liquidate
and then they would make money on, you know,
our public company was trading at a discount
to what all the securities worth.
So they bought the public company,
they shorted the securities,
and then they came to see us
and to try to be activists
and force us to liquidate and that sort of...
So I thought this was gonna be...
I envisioned an end where
the divorce takes all of my resources.
The permanent capital vehicle ends up getting liquidated.
And another activist in my industry puts me outta business.
And I had met Neri Oxman right around this time,
and I'd fallen completely in love with her.
And I was envisioning a world where I was bankrupt.
A judge found me guilty of whatever,
he sends me off to jail or not that judge
'cause he was a civil judge,
but another judge sues the SEC Department of Justice.
And I find myself in this incredible mess.
And I decided I didn't want things to end that way.
So I did something I'd never done before.
I talked to all before about you don't borrow money,
I borrowed money and I borrowed
$300 million from JP Morgan in the middle of this mess.
And I gave JP Morgan enormous credit in seeing through it.
And also I had been a good client
over a long period of time
and it's like it's a handshake bank
and they bet that I would succeed.
And I took that money to buy enough stock
in my public company that I could prevent
an activist from taking over
and effectively buy control
of our little public company.
And I got that done.
And that I knew was the moment, the turning point.
And I resolved my divorce
and divorces get easier to resolve
when things are going badly.
I was able to resolve that.
We settled the litigation.
I was buying blocks of our stock in the market.
I remember a day I bought a big block of stock in the market
and I get a call from Gordon Singer,
who's Paul Singer's son
who runs their London part of their business.
And he's like, "Bill, was that you buying that block?"
I said, yes. And he's like, "Fuck".
(both laughing)
- So he knew--
- He knew that once I got that
they were not gonna be able to succeed and they went away.
And that was the bottom.
And that we've had an incredible run since then.
- And there you were able to protect your reputation
from the valiant failure still?
- I mean this is a business
where you're gonna make some mistakes.
It was a big one.
It was very reputationally damaging
the press was a total disaster.
But I'm not a quitter.
And actually the key moments for us,
we'd never taken our core investment principles
and actually really written them down
something we talked about at meetings,
kind of our investment team meetings.
I had a member of the team, I said,
"Look, go find a big piece of granite and a chisel
"and let's take those core principles.
"I want them like Moses' 10 commandments".
We're gonna chisel em
and then we're gonna put it up on the wall.
And once we produce those,
we put one on everyone's desk.
I said, look, if we ever again veer
from the core principles,
hit me with a baseball bat.
And that was the bottom.
And ever since then,
we've had the best six years in the history of the firm.
- So refocus on the fundamentals--
- And love helps. - Hell of a story.
- Love helps. I literally met Neri at the absolute bottom.
Our first date was September 7th, 2017.
That was very close to the bottom.
Actually, there's one other element to the story.
So this went on for a few months after I met her.
The other element is that one day I get a call from Neri
and she's like, 'Bill, guess what?"
I'm like, "What?"
Brad Pitt is coming to the media lab.
He wants to see my work.
I'm like, that's beautiful sweetheart.
I didn't know Brad Pitt
was interested in your work.
- As a man that's a difficult phone call to take.
- And apparently he's really interested in architecture.
I'm like, okay, now Neri and I were like,
we would WhatsApp all day every day,
we talk throughout the day.
Brad Pitt shows up at the media lab at 10 o'clock.
I talk to her in the morning.
I kind of text her to see how things are going.
Don't hear back.
And on WhatsApp you can see like
whether the other person's read it or not.
- Yeah, yeah. Okay.
- No response.
A couple hours later, send her another text, no response.
Six o'clock, no response.
Eight o'clock, no response.
10 o'clock, no response.
And you know she finally calls me at 10:30
and tells me how great Brad Pitt is.
So I had this scenario, okay,
a judge is gonna find me,
we're gonna lose to the judge.
All my assets will disappear.
And then Brad Pitt's gonna take my girlfriend.
- Brad Pitt's your competition. This is great.
- So it was like a moment.
That was sort of the bottom.
And then sort of the motivational thing.
I didn't wanna lose to an activist,
didn't wanna lose my girl to some other guy.
- Brad Pitt and you emerged from all that,
the winner on all fronts.
- I'm a very fortunate guy, very fortunate and lucky.
- You talked about some of the technical aspects of that.
But psychologically is there a,
like what are you doing at night by yourself?
- That was a hard time.
Hard time 'cause I was separated from my wife and my kids.
I was living in not the greatest apartment,
I had a beautiful home
and so I had to go find like a bachelor place
and I didn't wanna be away from my kids.
I moved like 10 blocks away
and I wasn't seeing them and they didn't like it.
So I ended up buying an apartment I didn't like
in the same building as my kids,
like, with a different entrance.
So I could be near them.
But I was home alone.
I got a dog that was a bar
We call 'em a bar that, not the elephant.
He's a black Labradoodle.
He was supposed to be a mini,
but he's not so as mini.
But I got him at six weeks old
and he would keep me company.
And I started meditating actually.
And a friend recommended TM.
And I would meditate 20 minutes in the morning,
20 minutes in the evening.
And I also a big believer in exercise
and weightlifting and I played tennis
and I had been, this is not my first,
proximity to disaster.
I had another moment in my career like, you know, 2002.
And I learned this method
for dealing with these kind of moments,
which is you just make a little progress every day.
So today I'm gonna wake up,
I'm gonna make progress,
I'll make progress on the litigation,
I'll make progress on the portfolio,
I'll make progress with my life.
And progress compounds a bit like money compounds.
You don't see a lot of progress in the first few weeks,
but like 30 days in you're like, oh, okay.
Like you can't look up at the mountaintop
where you used to be
'cause then you'll give up, right?
But you just, okay, just make step by step by step
and then 90 days in you're like,
okay, I was way down there.
I'm okay. I don't look up.
Just keep making progress, progress, progress
and progress really does compound.
And one day you wake up
and like, wow, it's amazing how far I've come.
And if you look at a chart of Pershing Square, our company,
you can see the absolute bottom,
you can see where we were,
you can see the drop and you can see where we are now.
And that huge drop that felt like
a complete unbelievable disaster
looks like a little bump on the curve
and it really gives you perspective on these things.
You just have to power through.
And I think the key is,
I've always been fortunate,
like from a mental health point of view
and nutrition, sleep, exercise,
and a little progress every day, that's it.
And you know, good friends and family,
I had, you know, go take a walk
with a friend every night,
and a sister who loves me
and parents who were supportive,
but they were all worried about their son, their brother.
It was a moment.
And also, by the way, the other thing to think about
is when you recover from something like this,
you really appreciate it (laughs)
And also as much of the media loves,
okay, when some successful person falls,
they love writing the story of success.
They love even more the story of failure
but when you recover from that,
it's kinda like the American story.
America, you know, you think of the great entrepreneurs
and how many failures they had before they succeeded.
How many rocket launches
did SpaceX have explode on the pad?
And then you look at success.
I mean, that's why Musk is so admired.
- You mentioned Herbalife.
Can you take me through the saga of that?
It's historic.
- So we at Pershing Square, short of very few stocks.
And the reason for that is short selling
is just inherently treacherous.
So if you buy a stock,
it's called going long, right?
You're buying something,
your worst case scenario is you lose your whole investment.
You buy a stock for a hundred, it goes to zero,
you loose a hundred dollars, right?
Per share. You buy one share of a hundred.
You shortest stock at a hundred
what it means is you borrow the security from someone else.
The analogy I gave that made it easy for people
to understand, it's a bit like you think,
silver coins are gonna go down in value
and you have a friend who's got a whole pile of these
1880 silver US dollars,
and you think they're gonna go down in value
and you say, hey, can I borrow
10 of those dollars from you?
He's like, sure, but what are you gonna pay me to borrow?
I'll pay you interest
on the value of the dollars today.
So you borrow the dollars
that are worth a hundred dollars each today.
You pay 'em interest while you're borrowing them.
And then you go sell 'em
in the market for a hundred dollars.
That's what they're worth.
And then they go down in price to 50.
You go back in, you buy the silver dollars back at $50
and you give 'em back to your friend.
Your friend is complete fine.
You borrowed 10, you gave him the 10 back
and he got interest in the meantime,
he's happy he made money on his coin collection.
You however made $50 times the 10 coins, you made 500 bucks.
That's pretty good.
The problem with that is,
what if you sell them
and they go from a hundred to a thousand,
now you're gonna have to go buy them back
and you gotta pay whatever, $10,000 to buy back coins.
You know that you sold for 500,
you're gonna lose $9,500.
And there's no limit, right?
To how high a stock price can go.
Companies go to $3 trillion in value, right?
Tesla, a lot of people shorted Tesla saying,
oh, it's overvalued,
he's never gonna be able to make a successful electric car.
Well, I'm sure they're people went bankrupt shorting Tesla.
That's why we didn't short stocks.
But I was presented with this actual reporter
that covered the other short investment
we made early in the career.
A company called MBIA came to me and said,
"Bill, I found this incredible company.
"You gotta take a look at it.
"It's a total fraud
"and they're scamming poor people".
- And we should say that NBIA was a very successful short.
- It was, big part of it was
that we used a different kind of instrument to short it
where we reversed that sort of,
we made the investment asymmetric in our favor,
meaning put up a small amount of money
if it works and make a fortune.
Whereas short selling is you kind of sell something
and you have to buy it back at a higher price.
Herbalife didn't have the,
what's called credit default swaps that you could purchase.
Not a big enough company.
You didn't have enough debt outstanding
to be able to implement it.
You had to short the stock
in order to make it as successful
to bet against the company.
And the more work I did in the company,
the more I was like, oh my God,
this thing's an incredible scam.
You know, that they purport to sell weight loss shakes,
but in reality they're selling
kind of a fake business plan.
And the people that adopt it lose money.
And they go after poor people.
They go after actually in many cases,
undocumented immigrants
who are pitched on the American Dream opportunity.
And because they have few other options
because they can't get legal employment,
they become Herbalife distributors.
And it's a business where you,
so-called multi-level marketing
or multi-level marketing, sort of
the name for a legitimate company like this
or it's a pyramid scheme
where basically your sales
are really only coming from people who
you convinced to buy the product
by getting them into the business.
That's precisely what this company is.
And like, okay, shorting a pyramid scheme seems like one,
we'll make a bunch of money,
but two, the world will be behind us
because they're harming poor people.
You know, regulators will get interested
in a company like this.
And we thought the FTC is gonna shut this thing down.
And we did a ton of work
and I gave this sort of epic presentation
laying out all the facts.
Stock got completely crushed
and we were on our way.
And the government actually got interested early on,
launched an investigation pretty early,
SEC and otherwise,
but then a guy named Carl Icahn showed up
and we have a little bit of a backstory,
but his motivations here were not really principally driven
by thinking HerbalLife was a good company,
he thought it was a good way to hurt me.
So he basically bought a bunch of stock
and said it was a really great company.
And you know, Carl at least at the time,
threw his weight around a bit.
I was a credible investor,
had a lot of resources
and that began the saga.
- So he was, we should say,
a legendary investor himself.
- I'd say legendary in a sense.
Yes, for sure.
An iconic Carl icon.
- Oh, that's very well done.
- Yeah. So definitely a iconic investor.
- So what was the backstory between the two of you?
- So I mentioned that I had another period of time
where significant business challenges,
this was my first fund called Gotham Partners.
And we had a court stop a transaction
between a private company we owned in a public company.
It's another long story.
- I would love to hear it as well.
- But it was really my deciding to wind up my former fund.
And we owned a big stake in a company called
Harwood Realty Partners,
which was a company that owned real estate assets
and it was worth a lot more than we was trading,
but it needed an activist to really unlock the value.
And we were in fact going outta business
and didn't have the time or the resources to pursue it.
So I sold it to Carl Icahn,
and I sold it to him at a premium
to where the stock was trading.
I think the stock was like 66,
I sold it to him for 80,
but it was worth about 150.
And I said, look, and part of the deal was Carl's like,
look, I'll give you Schmuck Insurance.
You know I'll make you sure you don't look bad.
And I had another deal at a higher price
without Schmuck Insurance.
When I deal with Carl at a lower price
with Schmuck Insurance
and the way the Schmuck Insurance went,
he said, look, "Bill, if I sell the stock
"in the next three years for a higher price
"I'll give you 50% of my profit".
That's a pretty good deal.
So we made that deal
and 'cause I was dealing with Carl Icahn
who had a reputation for being difficult.
I was very focused on the agreement
and we didn't want him to be able to be cute.
So the agreement said if he sells
or otherwise transfers his shares.
And we came up with a definition
to include every version of sale.
Okay. 'cause you know, it's Carl.
Well, he then buys the stake
and then makes a bid for the company.
And plan is for him to get the company.
And he bids like 120 a share.
And the company hires Morgan Stanley to sell itself
and he raises bid to 125, and then 130,
eventually gets sold, I don't remember the exact price,
let's say $145 a share.
And Carl's not the winning bidder
and he sells his stock,
or he loses or transfers his shares for $145 a share.
So he owes actually our investors
the difference between 145 and 80 times 50%.
And I had like lawyers never like you
to put like a arithmetic example.
I put like a formula
like out of a math book in the document
so there can be no confusion.
It was only an eight page, really simple agreement.
So the deal closes
and he's supposed to pay us
in two business days or three business days.
I wait a few business days, no money comes in.
I called Carl, I'm like,
"Carl, congratulations on her on the Hal Realty".
Thanks Bill.
I said, "Carl, I just wanna remind you,
"I know it's been a few years,
"but you know we have this agreement,
"remember the Schmuck Insurance?"
He's like, yeah.
I said, "Well, you owe us our Schmuck Insurance".
He said, "What do you mean I didn't sell my shares?"
I said, "Do you still have the shares?"
He says, "No".
I said, "What happened to them?"
Well, the company did a merger for cash
and they took away my shares, but I didn't sell them.
Do you understand what happened?
So I said, "Carl, I'm gonna have to sue you".
He said, "Sue me, I'm gonna sue you".
He says, so I sued him
and the legal system in America can take some time.
And what he would do is we sued
and then we won in the whatever New York Supreme Court,
and then he appealed
and you can appeal like six months after the case.
We waited to the 179th day and then he would appeal.
And then we fought it at the next level.
And then he would appeal.
And he appealed all the way to the Supreme Court.
Of course the Supreme Court wouldn't take the case.
It took years.
Now as part of our agreement,
we got 9% interest on the money that he owed us.
So I viewed it as my Carl Icahn money market account
with a much higher interest rate.
And eventually I won.
- What was the amount?
- Just tiny.
Now, it was material to my investors.
So my first fund, I wound it down
but I wanted to maximize
everything from my investors, right?
These are the people backed me at 26 years old.
I was right outta business school,
had no experience and they supported me.
So I'm gonna go to the end of the earth for them.
And four and a half million relative to our fund at the end
was maybe 400 million so it wasn't a huge number,
but it was a big percentage of what was left
after I sold all our liquid security.
So I was fighting for it.
So we got four and a half million plus interest
for eight years or something.
That's how long the litigation took.
So we got about double.
So he owed me $9 million, which to Carl Icahn,
who had probably a $20 billion net worth at the time
this was nothing.
But to me it was like,
okay, this is my investor's money, I'm gonna get it back.
And so eventually we won.
Eventually he paid
and then he called me,
he said, "Bill, congratulations
"now we can be friends and we can invest,
"do some investing together".
I'm like, "Carl, fuck you".
- You actually said fuck you?
- (laughs) Yes.
And I'm not that kind of person generally,
but you know, he made eight years to pay me,
not me, even me, my investors money they owed.
And so he probably didn't like that.
So he kind of hung around in the weeds
waiting for an opportunity.
And then from there I started Pershing.
We had to kind of straight line up,
we were up the first 12 years
we could do nothing wrong,
then Valiant, Herbalife, right?
He sees an opportunity and he buys the stock.
He figures he is gonna run me off the road.
And so that was the beginning of that.
And kind of the moment,
and I think it's the,
I'm told by CNBC, it's the most watched segment
in business television history.
They're interviewing me
about the Herbalife investment on CNBC.
And then Carl Icahn calls into the show
and we have kind of a interesting conversation
where he calls me all kinds of names and stuff.
So it was a moment, it was a moment in my life.
- It wasn't public information
that he was long on Herbalife.
- He didn't yet disclose he had a stake.
But he was just telling me
how stupid I was to be short this company.
- So for him, it wasn't about
the fundamentals of the company,
it was about, it was just personal.
- [Bill] 100%.
- Is there a part of you that regrets saying
fuck you on that phone call to Carl Icahn?
- No.
(both laughing)
I generally have no regrets
because I'm very happy with where I am now.
And I feel like it's a bit like
you step on the butterfly in the forest
and the world changes because you know,
every action has a reaction.
You know if you're happy with who you are,
where you are in life, every decision you've made,
good or bad over the course of your life
got you to precisely where you are.
I wouldn't change anything.
- He said, you lost money on Herbalife.
So he did the long-term battle.
- What he did is he got on the board of the company
and used the company's financial resources
plus his stake in the business to squeeze us.
And a squeeze in short selling
is where you restrict the supply of the securities
so that there's a scarcity.
And then you encourage people to buy the stock
and you drive the stock up.
And as I explained before,
you short those coins at 10, they go to 100,
you can lose theoretically an unlimited amount of money.
And that's scary.
That's why we don't short stocks.
That's why I didn't short stocks before this.
But this was, unfortunately
I had to have the personal lesson.
- So how much was for him personal
versus part of sort of the game of investing?
- Well, he thought he could make money doing this.
He wouldn't have done it if he did otherwise.
He thought his bully pulpit,
his ability to create a short squeeze,
his control over the company
would enable him to achieve this.
And he made a billion, we lost a billion.
- So you think it was a financial decision outta personal?
- It was a personal decision to pursue it.
But he was waiting for an opportunity
where he could make money at our expense.
And it was kind of a brilliant opportunity for him.
Now the irony is, well first of all,
the FTC found a few interesting facts.
So one, the government launched an investigation,
they ended up settling with the company
and the company paid $220 million in fines.
I met a professor from Berkeley a couple years ago
who told me that he had been hired by the government
as their expert on Herbalife.
And he got access to all their data,
was able to prove that they're a pyramid scheme
but the government ultimately settled with Carl
'cause they were afraid
they could possibly lose in court
so they settled with him.
But if you look at the stock,
if we'd been able to stay short the entire time,
we would've made a bunch of money.
'cause the stock had a $6 billion market cap
and we shorted it today as probably a billion,
a billion and a half.
- So you left the short or whatever that's called--
- Covered. We closed it out.
well we sold Valiant, we covered Herbalife.
That was the resetting moment for the firm.
'Cause it would just psychologically,
and you know, the beauty of investing
is you don't need to make it back the way you lost it
you can just take your loss,
by the way, losses are valuable
and that the government allows you to take a tax loss
and that can shelter other gains.
And we just refocused,
- Can you say one thing you really like about Carl Icahn
and one thing you really don't like about him?
- Sure. So he's a very charming guy.
So in the midst of all this at the Hall Wood one,
he took me out for dinner
to his favorite Italian restaurant.
- [Lex] Really?
- Yeah. We were in the middle of the litigation
to see if he could resolve it.
And he offered 10 million in my favorite charity.
The problem was that it wasn't my money,
it was my investors' money
so I couldn't settle with him on that basis.
But I had the chance to spend real time with him at dinner.
He's funny, he's charismatic,
he's got incredible stories.
And you know, actually I made peace with him over time.
We had a little hug out on CNBC
even had him to my house, believe it or not.
I hosted something called the Finance Cup,
which is a tennis tournament between people in finance
and Europe and the US and we had the event at my house
and one guy thought to invite Carl Icahn.
And so we had Carl Icahn on there to present awards.
And again, I have to say I kinda liked the guy,
but I didn't like him much during this.
- Because at least from the outsider perspective,
there's a bit of a personal vengeance here
or anger can build up.
Do you ever worry the personal attacks
between powerful investors can cloud your judgment
of what is the right financial decision?
- I think it's possible, but again,
I try to be extremely economically rational.
And actually the last seven years have been quite peaceful.
I really have not been an activist
in the old form for many years.
And the vast majority
of even our activist investments historically
were very polite, respectful cases.
The press of course focuses on the more interesting ones.
Like Chipotle was one of the best investments we ever made.
We got four of eight board seats
and we worked with management
and it was a great outcome.
I don't think there's ever ever been a story about it.
And the stock's up
almost 10 times from the time we hired Brian Nichols, CEO.
But it's not interesting because there was no battle.
Whereas Herbalife, of course, was like an epic battle,
even Canadian Pacific.
So for a period there, you most people,
when they meet me in person,
they're like, wow, Bill, you seem like a really nice guy.
But I thought, you know, so,
but things have been pretty calm
for the last seven years.
- Of course there's more than just investing
that your life is about, especially recently.
Lemme just ask you about what's going on in the world.
First, what was your reaction
and what is your reaction
and thoughts with respect
to the October 7th attacks by Hamas on Israel?
- You know, it's a sad world that we live in.
That one we have terrorists
and two that we can have such barbaric terrorism
and yeah, just a reminder of that.
- So there's several things I can ask here.
First on the, your views on the prospects
of the Middle East, but also on the reaction to
this war and in the United States,
especially on university campuses.
So first lemme just ask,
you've said that you're pro-Palestinian.
Can you explain what you mean by that?
- You know, with all of my posts about Israel,
I'm obviously very supportive of the country of Israel.
Israel's right to exist,
Israel's right to defend itself.
My Arab friends, my Palestinian friends
were kind of saying, "Hey Bill, where are you?"
You know, what about Palestinian lives?
And I was pretty early in my life,
a guy named Marty Parrott, who's been important to me
over the course of my life, a professor,
or first investor in my fund introduced me to Neri,
asked me when I right outta school
to join this nonprofit called the Jerusalem Foundation,
which was a charitable foundation
that supported Teddy Collick when he was mayor of Jerusalem.
I ended up becoming the youngest chairman
of the Jerusalem Foundation in my 30s
and I spent some time in Israel.
And the early philanthropic stuff I did
with the Jerusalem Foundation,
I thing I was most interested in was kind of
the Palestinian, the plight of the Palestinians
and kind of peaceful coexistence.
And so I had kind of an early kind of perspective,
as chairman of the Jerusalem Foundation
I would go into Arab communities
and I would meet the families in their homes.
You know, you get a sense of the humanity
of a people and I care about humanity.
I generally take the side of people
who've been disadvantaged.
Almost all of our philanthropic work
has been in that capacity,
so that's sort of my natural perspective.
But I don't take the side of terrorists ever, obviously.
And the whole thing is just a tragedy.
- So to you, this is about Hamas, not about Palestine?
- Yes. I mean the problem of course is when Hamas controls
for the last almost 20 years, has controlled Gaza
including the education system,
they're educating, you know, you see these
training videos of kindergartners indoctrinating them
into hating Jews and Israel.
And of course you don't like to see
Palestinians celebrating some of those early videos
of October 7th with dead buddies in the back of trucks
and people cheering.
So it's a really unfortunate situation.
But I think about a Palestinian life is important
and as valuable as a Jewish life, as a American life.
And you know, what do people really want?
They want a place, they want a home.
They wanna be able to feed their family.
They want a job that generates
the resources to feed their family.
They want their kids to have a better life than they've had.
They want peace.
I think these are basic human things.
I'm sure the vast majority
of Palestinians share these views,
but it's such an embedded situation with hatred
and as I say, indoctrination.
And then, you know, going back to incentives
terrorists generate their resources by committing terrorism,
and that's how they get funding.
And there's a lot of graft.
You know, it's a plutocracy, right?
The top of the terrorist pyramid
if you accept the numbers that are in the press,
the top leaders have billions of dollars.
You know, 40 billion or so has gone into Gaza
and the West Bank over the last 30 years,
a number like that.
And a lot of it's disappeared
into some combination of corruption or tunnels or weapons.
And the tragedy is
you look at what Singapore has achieved
in the last 30 years, right?
- Do you think that's still possible
if we look into the future of 10, 20, 50 years from now?
- Absolutely.
- [Lex] So not just peace but--
- Peace comes with prosperity.
You know, people are under the leadership of terrorists,
you're not gonna have prosperity
and you're not gonna have peace.
And I think the Israelis withdrew in 2005
and fairly quickly Hamas took control of the situation
that should never have been allowed to happen.
If you think about I have the opportunity to spend
call it an hour with Henry Kissinger,
a few months before he passed away,
we were talking about Gaza
or in the early stage of the war.
He said, look, you know, this is not,
you could think about Gaza as a test
of a two state solution.
It's not looking good.
These were his words.
So the next time round
the Palestinian people should have their own state,
but it can't be a state where 40 billion resources goes in
and is spent on weaponry and missiles
and rockets going into Israel.
And I do think a consortium of the Gulf States,
the Saudis and others have to ultimately
oversee the governance of this region.
I think if that can happen,
I think you can have peace,
you can have prosperity.
And I'm fundamentally an optimist.
- So a coalition of governance.
- [Bill] Governance matters, you know,
going back to what we talked about before.
- And you know that kind of approach
can give the people a chance to--
- a hundred percent - Flourish.
- A hundred percent.
I mean, look at what Dubai has accomplished
with nomads in the desert, right?
And that's become a major,
it's a tourist destination.
Gaza could have been a tourist destination.
- Take me through the saga of university presidents
testifying on the topic of protests on college campuses,
protests that call for the genocide of Jewish people
and the university presidents,
maybe you could describe it more precisely,
but they fail to denounce the calls for genocide.
- So it begins on October 8th, probably.
And you can do a compare and contrast with
how Dartmouth managed the events of October 7th
and the aftermath and how Harvard did.
And on October 8th or shortly thereafter,
the Dartmouth president,
who had been in her job for precisely
the same number of months
that the Harvard president had been in her job,
the first thing she did is she got
the most important professors of Middle East studies
who were Arab and who were Jews.
And they convened them
and held an open session Q&A for students
to talk about what's going on in the Middle East,
and began an opportunity for common understanding
among the student body.
And Dartmouth has been a relatively benign environment
on this issue, and students are able to do work.
And there aren't disruptive protests
with people with bullhorns walking into classrooms
interfering with, you know, people pay today $82,000 a year,
which itself is crazy to go to Harvard.
But imagine your family borrows the money
or you borrow the money as a student,
and your learning is disrupted by constant protest
and the university does nothing.
You know, when George Floyd died
the Harvard president wrote a very strong letter
denouncing what had taken place
and calling this an important moment in American history
and took it incredibly seriously.
Her first letter about October 7th was not that,
let's put it that way.
And then her second letter was not that.
And then ultimately she was sort of forced
by the board or the pressure
to make a more public statement,
but it was clear that it was hard for her
to come to an understanding of this terrorist act.
And then the protests erupted on campus
and they started out recently benign.
And then the protesters
got more and more aggressive in terms of
violating university rules on things like bullying
and the university did nothing.
And that obviously for the Jewish students,
the Israeli students, the Israeli faculty, Jewish faculty,
created an incredibly uncomfortable environment.
And the President seemed indifferent.
And I went up to campus
and I met with hundreds of students
in small groups, in larger groups.
And they're like,
"Bill, why is the president doing nothing?
"Why is the administration doing nothing?"
And that was really the beginning.
And I reached out to the president,
reached out to the board of Harvard,
I said, look, this thing is headed in the wrong direction
and you need to fix it.
And I have some ideas, love to share.
And I got the Heisman, as they say,
they just kept pushing off the opportunity for me
to meet with the president and meet with the board.
And a certain point in time I pushed,
you know, I'm kind of an activist when you push me,
it reminded me of early days of activism
where I couldn't get the CEO of Wendy's
to return my call.
I couldn't get the CEO of Harvard to take a meeting.
And then finally I spoke to the chairman of the board,
a woman by the name of Penny Pritzker,
who I knew from on a business school, a board with her.
And it was, as I described,
one of the more disappointing conversations in my life.
And it did not seem, she seemed a bit like,
if you will, deer in the headlights.
They couldn't do this, they couldn't do that.
The law was preventing them from doing various things.
And that led to my first letter to the university.
And I sort of ended the letter,
sort of giving this president of Harvard
a dared to be great speech.
This is your opportunity
you can fix this, this could be your legacy.
I emailed it to the president
and the board members whose email addresses I had,
I posted it on Twitter.
I got no response, no acknowledgement, nothing.
And in fact the open dialogue I had
with a couple of people on the board
basically got shut down after that.
And that led to letter number two,
and then when the Congress led by Elise Stefanik
announced an investigation of antisemitism on campus
and concern about violations of law.
The president was called to testify along with two other,
the president of MIT,
the president of University of Pennsylvania
were having similar issues on campus.
I reached out to the president of Harvard
and said, well, one, the Israeli government
had gotten in touch
and offered the opportunity for me to see the Hamas,
if you will, GoPro film.
And I said, you know what, I'd love to show it at Harvard.
And they thought that would be a great idea.
And so I partnered with the head of Harvard Habad,
a guy named Rabbi Hershey,
and we were putting the film up on campus
and I thought if the president were to see this
it would give her a lot of perspective on what happened,
and she should see it before her testimony.
And so I reached out to her,
or actually Rabbi Hershey did.
And he was told she'd be out of town
and couldn't see it.
And then I reached out to her again,
said, look, I'll facilitate your attendance in the Congress,
come see the film, I'll fly you down.
That was rejected.
And then she testified.
And I watched a good percentage,
80% of the testimony of all three presidents
and it was an embarrassment to the country,
embarrassment to the universities,
they were evasive,
they didn't answer questions,
they were rude, they smirked,
you know, they looked very disrespectful to our Congress.
And then of course there was that several minutes
where finally at least Stefanik
was not getting answers to her questions.
And she said, you know, let me be kind of clear,
what if protestors are calling for genocide for the Jews
does that violate your rules on bullying and harassment?
And the three of them basically gave the same answer.
You know, it depends on the context
and not until they actually executed on the genocide
to the university have the right to intervene.
And the thing that perhaps bothered me the most
was the incredible hypocrisy,
Harvard was, you know, each of these universities
are ranked by this entity called FIRE,
which is a nonprofit that focuses on free speech on campus.
And Harvard, it's been in the bottom quartile
for the last five years and dropped to last
before October 7th, out of like 250.
- I should mention briefly
that I've interviewed on this podcast,
the founder of FIRE and the current Head of FIRE.
We discussed this at length,
including running for the board of Harvard
and the whole procedure of all that,
it's quite a fascinating investigation of free speech
for people who care about free speech absolutism,
that's a good episode to listen to
because those folks kind of fight for this idea.
It's a difficult idea actually to internalize
what does free speech in college campuses look like.
- Harvard has become a place where
free speech is not tolerated on campus,
or at least free speech
that's not part of the accepted dialogue.
Or, you know, this whole notion of speech codes
and microaggressions really emerged on the elite,
the Harvard, Yale campuses of the world
and the president of Harvard's,
then president of Harvard's explanation for why
you could call for the genocide
of the Jewish people on campus
was Harvard's commitment to free expression.
And you know, one of the more hypocritical statements
of all time, and you really can't have it both ways either.
Harvard has to be a place where it's a free speech.
She basically said, we're a free speech absolutist place,
which is why we have to allow this.
And Harvard could not be further from that.
And so that was a big part of it.
And I was in the barber chair, if you will,
getting haircut.
And I had a guy on my team
send me the three minute section.
I said, cut that line of questioning.
And I put out a little tweet on that
and I call it my greatest hits of posts.
It's got something 110 million views.
And everyone looked at this and said,
what is wrong with university campuses
and their leadership and their governance by the way.
You know, in a way this whole conversation's
been about governance.
Harvard has disastrous governance structure,
which is why we have the problem we have.
- And just to linger on the testimony
and you mentioned smirks and this kind of stuff
and you mentioned dare to be great,
I myself am kind of a sucker for great leadership.
And those moments, you mentioned Churchill or so on,
even great speeches,
people talk down on speeches like it's maybe just words,
but I think speeches can define a culture
and define a place, define a people that can inspire.
And I think actually the testimony before Congress
could have been an opportunity to redefine what Harvard is,
dare to be great for,
dare to be a great leader.
- President of Harvard had a huge opportunity
'cause she went third, right?
The first two gave the world's most disastrous answers
to the question and she literally just copied their answer,
which is itself kind of ironic
in light of ultimately what happened.
- It's tough because you can get busy as a president,
as a leader and so on.
There's these meetings.
And so you think congress,
maybe you're smirking at the ridiculousness of the meeting.
You need to remember that many of these are opportunities
to like give a speech of a lifetime.
If there is principles which you want to see
an institution become and embody
in the next several decades,
there's opportunities to do that.
And you as a great leader also need to have a sense
of when is the opportunity to do that.
And October 7th really woke up the world
on all sides, honestly.
Like there is serious issue going on here.
And then the protests woke up the university,
there's a serious issue going on here.
It's an opportunity to speak on free speech
and on genocide, both.
Do you see the criticism that you are a billionaire donor
and you sort of used your power
and financial influence unfairly to affect
the governing structure of Harvard in this case?
- First of all I never threatened
to use financial other resources.
The only thing I did here was wrote.
I wrote public letters,
I spoke privately to a couple members of the board.
I spoke for 45 minutes to the chairman.
None of those conversations were effective
or went anywhere as far as I could tell.
I think my public letters
and then some of the posts, I did tweets.
That little three minute video excerpt had an impact,
but it wasn't about, I mean you can criticize me
for being a billionaire, but that had,
you know, it was really the words.
It's a bit like, again, going back to the corporate analogy,
it's not the fact that you own 5% of the company
that causes people to vote in your favor,
it's the fact that your ideas are right.
And I think I was disappointed
after the congressional testimony.
The board of Harvard said that
they were 100% behind unanimously,
100% behind President Gay.
And so clearly I was ineffective.
And ultimately what took her down was other,
I would say activists who identified issues
with academic integrity.
And then she lost the confidence of the faculty.
And once that happens, it's hard to stay.
And I wanted her to be fired basically,
or be forced to resign because of failures of leadership.
'Cause that would've sent a message about the importance
of leadership, you know, failure to stop a emergence
of antisemitism on campus.
And you know, there's some news today
the protests are getting worse.
- Is there some tension
between free speech on college campuses
and disciplining students for calls of genocide?
- Yes, there's certainly a tension.
And I think first of all,
I think free speech is incredibly important.
I'm a lot closer to absolutism
on free speech than otherwise.
The issue I had was the hypocrisy, right?
They were restricting other kinds of speech on campus,
principally conservative speech, conservative views.
So it wasn't a free speech absolutist campus
and the protests were actually
quite threatening to students.
And there are limits to even absolutist free speech.
And they begin where people feel intimidation,
harassment and threat to bodily harm, et cetera.
You know, that kind of speech is generally,
and again, it's pretty technical,
but as people feel like they're in imminent harm
by virtue of the protest, that speech is at risk
of not meeting the standards for free speech.
But Harvard is a private corporation
and as a private corporation,
they can put on what restrictions they want.
And Harvard had introduced only a few months before
bullying and harassment policies.
And that's why Representative Stefanik focused on
it's not like she said
this calling for genocide against the Jews
violate your free speech policies,
she says it's calling for genocide against the Jews,
violate your policies on bullying harassment.
And I think everyone looked at this
when they said it depends on the context.
And they said, look, if you replaced Jews
with some other ethnic group,
students have been, who've used the N word, for example,
have been thrown off campus, were suspended.
Students who've hate speech directed at LGBTQ people
has led to disciplinary action.
But attacking, spitting on Jewish students
or you know, kind of roughing them up a bit,
seemed like we're calling for their elimination
didn't seem to violate the policy.
I think a university should be a place
where you have broad views and open viewpoints
and broad discussion,
but it should also be a place
where students don't feel threatened going to class,
where their learning is not interrupted,
when final exams are not interrupted
by people coming in and with loud protests.
Students asked me when I went up there,
what would you do if you're a Harvard president?
I said, and this was before I knew
what was happening on the Dartmouth campus.
I said, I would convene everyone together.
This is Harvard.
We have access to the best minds in the world.
Let's have a better understanding of the history.
Let's understand the backdrop, let's focus on solutions.
Let's bring Arab and Jewish
and Israeli students together.
Let's form groups to create communication.
That's how you solve this kind of problem.
And none of this stuff has been done.
It's not that hard.
- Do you think this reveals a deeper problem
in terms of ideology
and the governance of Harvard
maybe the culture of Harvard?
- Yes. So on governance,
the governance structure is a disaster.
So the way it works today
is Harvard has two principal boards.
There's the board of the corporation,
the so-called fellows of Harvard.
It's a board of I think 12 independent directors.
And the president, there's no shareholder vote,
there's no proxy system.
It's really a self perpetuating board that
its effectively elects its own members.
So once the balance tips politically one way or another,
it can be kept that way forever.
There's no kind of rebalancing system.
You know, if a US corporation goes off the rails
so to speak, the shareholders can get together
and vote off the directors.
There's no ability to vote off the directors.
Then there's the board of Overseers,
which is I think 32 directors.
And there a few years ago
if you could put together 600 signatures,
you could run for that board
and put up a bunch of candidates
and about five or six get elected each year.
And a group did exactly that.
And it was an oil and gas kind of disinvestment group.
They got the signatures,
a couple of 'em got elected
and Harvard then changed the rules
and they said, now we need 3,200 signatures.
And by the way if there are these
dissident directors on the board,
we're only gonna allow,
we're gonna cap them at five.
So if three were elected in the oil and gas thing,
now they're only two seats available.
And then a group of former students, kind of younger alums,
one of whom I knew, approached me
and said, look Bill, we should run for the board.
And they decided this pretty late,
only a few weeks before the signatures were due.
And love your support.
I took a look at their platform,
I thought it looked great.
I said, look, happy to support.
And I posted about them,
you know, did a Zoom with them
and they got thousands of signatures,
collectively the four got whatever,
12,000 signatures or something like this.
And they missed by about 10% the threshold.
And what did Harvard do in the middle of the election?
They made it very, very difficult to sign up for a vote.
And it just makes them look terrible.
And they've got now thousands of alums upset
and again, this wasn't an election,
this was just to put the names on the slate.
So the only candidates on the slate
are the ones selected by the existing members.
And so it's businesses fail
because of governance failures.
Universities fail because of governance failures.
It's not really the president's fault
because the job of the board
is to hire and fire the president
and help guide the institution academically, otherwise.
So that's governance.
And ideology, I was like, how can this be.
October 7th, the event that woke me up
was 30 student organizations came out
with a public letter on October 8th,
literally the morning after this letter was created
and said, Israel is solely responsible
for Hamas' violent acts.
Again, Israel had not even mounted a defense at this point
and there were still terrorists running around
in the southern part of Israel.
And I'm like, Harvard students,
34 Harvard student organizations signed this letter.
And I'm like, what is going on?
You know, WTF, right?
And that's when I went up on campus
and I started talking to the faculty.
And that's when I started hearing about actually Bill,
it's this DEI ideology.
I'm like, what like diversity, equity, inclusion.
Obviously I'm familiar with these words
and you know, I see this in the corporate context
and they say, yeah.
And they started talking to me about
this oppressor oppressed framework,
which is effectively taught on campus
and represents the backdrop
for many of the courses that are offered
and the various, some of the studies
and other degree offerings.
I'm like, I had not even heard of this.
And you know, I'm a pretty aware person,
but I was completely unaware.
And basically they're like,
look, Israel is deemed an oppressor
and the Palestinians are deemed the oppressed.
And you take the side of the oppressed
and any acts of the oppressed
to dislodge the oppressor
regardless of how vile or barbaric parquet.
I'm like, okay, this is a super dangerous ideology.
And so I wrote like, questioning post about this,
like, here's what I'm hearing,
is this right?
Then I had someone, a friend of mine sent me
a Christopher Rufos book, "America's Cultural Revolution"
which is sort of a sociological study
of the origins of the DEI movement
and critical race theory.
And I found it actually
one of the more important books I've read
and also found it quite concerning
and really it's sort of ultimately DEI
comes out of a kind of a Marxist
socialist backdrop way to look at the world.
And so I think there are a lot of issues with it,
but it unfortunately it's advancing.
I ultimately concluded racism
as opposed to fighting it,
which is what I thought it was ultimately about.
- So maybe you can speak to that book a little bit.
So there's a history that traces back across decades
and then that infiltrated college campuses.
- So basically what Rufo argues
is that the black power movement of the '60s really failed.
It was a very violent movement
and many of the protagonists ended up in jail
and out of that movement,
a number of kind of thought leaders,
this guy named Mark Esques
and others built this framework kind of an approach,
look, if we're gonna be successful
can't be a violent movement, number one.
Number two, we need to infiltrate, if you will,
the universities and we need to become part of the faculty
and we need to teach the students.
And then once we take over the universities
with this ideology, then we can go into government
and then we can go into corporations
and we can change the world.
So, and I thought important book,
and the more I dug in
the more I felt there was credibility to this,
not just the kind of sociological backdrop,
but to what it meant on campus and faculty,
Harvard faculty were telling me that
there's really is no such thing as free speech on campus.
And that there was a survey done,
I dunno, a year or so ago of the Harvard faculty
and only 2% of the faculty admitted,
even in an anonymous survey admitted to being,
having a conservative point of view.
So we have a campus that's 98% non-conservative,
liberal progressive
that's adopted this DEI construct and this,
and then I learned from a member of the search committee
for the Harvard president
that they were restricted in looking at candidates
only those who met the DEI offices criteria.
And I shared this in one of my postings
and I was accused of being a racist,
and that's someone who believes in a diversity
is a very good thing for organizations
and that equity fairness isn't really important.
And having an inclusive culture is critical
for a functioning of organization.
So here I was someone who was like,
okay, DEI, sounds good to me,
at least in the small D, small EI version of events.
But this DEIO ideology is really problematic.
- So what's a way to fix this in the next few years?
The infiltration of DEI with the uppercase version
of universities and the things that have troubled you,
the things you saw at Harvard and elsewhere,
- The same way this was an eye-opening event for me
it has been for a very broad range of other people.
I've never gotten...
I mentioned general growth,
I got a lot of nice letters from people
for making money on a stock that went up a hundred times.
But I literally get hundreds of emails, letters,
texts, handwritten letters,
type letters from people the ages of 25 to 85 saying,
Bill, this is so important.
Thanks for speaking out on this.
You were saying what so many of us believe
but have been afraid to say.
I described it as almost a McCarthy esque kind of movement
and that if you challenge the DEI construct
people accuse you of being racist.
It's happened to me already.
I'm much less vulnerable than a university professor
who can get shouted off campus, canceled.
I'm sort of difficult to cancel.
But that doesn't mean people aren't gonna try.
I've been the victim of a couple of
interesting articles in the last few days,
or at least one in particular in the Washington Post
written by what I thought was a well-meaning reporter.
But it's just clear that
I've taken on some big parts
of at least the progressive establishment,
DEI I'm also a believer that Biden
should have stepped aside a long time ago.
And it's only getting worse.
You know, so I'm attacking the president, DEI,
elite universities and you make some enemies doing that.
- But I should say,
I'm still at MIT and I love MIT
and I believe in the power of great universities
to explore ideas, to inspire young people to think,
to inspire young people to lead.
- Let me ask, okay, how can you explore
how to think when you're only shared
a certain point of view, right?
How can you learn about leadership
when the governance and leadership of the institution
is broken and exposure to ideas if you're limited
in the ideas that you're exposed to.
So I think university is at risk.
I mean, the concerning thing
is if 34 student organizations that each have,
I don't know, 30 members or maybe more, right?
That's a thousand, okay?
That's a meaningful percentage of the campus perhaps
that ultimately respond.
Now, a 10 or so of the 30 withdrew the statement
once many of the members realized what they had written.
So I don't think it seems like the statement
was signed by the leadership
and not necessarily supported
by all the various students that were members.
But if the university teaches people these precepts,
this is the next generation of leader.
You know, normally if you think about,
I wrote my college thesis on university admissions.
The reason why controlling
the gates of the Harvard Institution,
the admissions office is important isn't
that many of these people who graduate end up with,
you know, the top jobs in government
and ultimately become judges,
they permeate through society.
And so it really matters what they learn.
And if they're limited to one side
of the political aisle
and they're not open to a broad array of views
and this represents some of the most
elite institutions in our country,
I think it's very problematic for the country long term.
- Yeah, I 100% agree.
And I also felt like the leadership wasn't even
part of the problem as much as they were almost out
of touch, like unaware
that this is an important moment,
it is an important crisis.
It's an important opportunity to step up as a leader
and define the future of an institution.
So I don't even know where the source of the problem is.
It could be literally governance structure
as we've been talking about.
- Well, it's two things.
I think it's governance structure.
I also think universities they're not selecting leaders.
You know, it's not clear to me that
universities should necessarily be run by academics.
The dean of a university,
the person who helps,
there's sort of the business of the university
and then there's the academics of the university
and having I would argue having a business leader
run these institutions
and then having a board
that has itself diverse viewpoints
and by the way, permanently structured
to have diverse viewpoints
is a much better way to run a university
than picking an academic that the faculty supports.
'Cause you know, one of the things I learned about
how faculty get hired at universities,
ultimately it's signed off by the board,
but the new faculty are chosen
by each of the various departments.
And once the departments tip,
there's sort of a tipping point politically
where if once they tip in one direction,
the faculty recruit more people like themselves.
And so the departments come more and more progressive,
if you will, with the passage of time
and they only advance candidates
that meet their political objectives.
It's not a great way
to build an institution which allows for--
- Small D diversity
- Allows for, yeah, diversity.
And diversity by the way, is not just race and gender.
And that's also something I feel very strongly about.
- Well, luckily engineering robotics
is touched last by this.
It is touched, but you know,
when I am at the computing building
starter and the new one
politics doesn't infiltrate
or I haven't seen it infiltrate quite
as deep place elsewhere.
- It's in the biology department at Harvard.
'Cause the biology is controversial now.
- [Lex] Yes, yes,
- 'Cause biology and gender there are faculty,
there's a woman at Harvard
who was literally canceled from the faculty as a member.
I think she was at the med school
and she made the argument that there are basically
two genders determined by biology.
She wasn't allowed to stay.
That's another topic for another time.
- That's another topic.
- You should do a show on that one.
That'd be an interesting one.
- So as you said, technically Claudine Gay,
the president of Harvard resigned over plagiarism,
not over the thing that you were initially troubled by.
- It's hard to really know, right?
It's not like provable fact,
I would say at a certain point in time
she lost the confidence of the faculty
and that was ultimately the catalyst.
And whether that was,
how much of that was the plagiarism issue
and how much of that was
some of the things that preceded it,
or was it all of these issues in their entirety?
There's no way to do a calculus.
- Can you explain the nature of this
plagiarism from what you remember?
- So Aaron Sibarium and Christopher Rufo,
one from the free beacon and Chris,
surfaced some allegations
or identified some plagiarism in the issues
that I would say the initial examples were,
use of the same words with proper attribution,
some missing footnotes.
And then over time with I guess more digging,
they released I think ultimately something like
76 examples of what they call plagiarism
in I think eight of 11 of her articles.
And one of the other things that came forth here
is as president of university,
she had sort of the thinnest transcript academically
of any previous president.
You know, very small, relatively small body of work.
And then when you couple that
with the amount of plagiarism that was pervasive.
And then I guess some of the other examples
that surfaced were not missing quotation marks
where the authors of the work felt
that their ideas had been stolen.
And really plagiarism is academic fraud.
One indicia plagiarism is a missing footnote
that could also be a clerical error.
And so when a professor's accused of plagiarism
university does sort of a deep dive.
They have these administrative boards
and it can take six months,
nine months, a year to evaluate
intent matters with this intentional theft
of another person's idea that's academic fraud.
Or was this sloppy,
you missed, or just humanity, right?
You miss a footnote here or there.
And I think once it got to a place where people felt
it was theft of someone else's intellectual property,
that's when it became intolerable
for her to stay as president of Harvard.
- So is there a spectrum for you between
different kinds of plagiarism,
maybe plagiarizing words and plagiarizing ideas
and plagiarizing novel ideas?
- Of course, the common understanding of plagiarism,
if you look in the dictionary, it's about theft.
Theft requires a intent.
Did the person intentionally
take someone else's ideas or words?
Now if you're writing a novel,
words matter more, right?
If you're taking Shakespeare
and presenting it as your own words,
if you're writing about ideas,
ideas matter, but you're not supposed
to take someone else's words
without properly acknowledging them,
whether it's quotation marks or otherwise.
But in the context of academic's life's work
before AI, everyone's gonna have
missing quotation marks and footnotes.
I remember writing my own thesis,
there were books you couldn't take out a Widener library.
So I'd have index cards and I'd write stuff on index cards
and I'd put a little citation to make sure
I remember to cite it properly.
And you know, scrambling to do your thesis,
get it in on time, what's the chances you forget
at what point what are your words versus the author's words
and you forget to put quotation marks.
Just the humanity, you know, the human fallibility of it.
So it's not academic fraud
to have human fail ability,
but it's academic fraud
if you take someone else's ideas
that are an integral part of your work.
- Is there a part of you that regrets that,
at least from the perception of it
the president Harvard stepped on over plagiarism
versus over refusing to say that
the calls for genocide are wrong?
- Again, I think it would've sent a better message
if a leader fails as a leader
and that's the reason for their resignation or dismissal,
then she gets, if you will,
caught on a technical violation
that had nothing to do with failed leadership.
Because I don't know
what's lesson that teaches the board
about selecting the next candidate.
I mean the future of Harvard
a lot of it's gonna depend on who they pick
as the next leader.
Here's an interesting anecdote
that I think is not surfaced publicly.
So a guy named Larry Backhoe
was the previous president of Harvard.
Larry Backhoe was on the search committee
and they were looking for a new president.
And what was strange was they picked an old white guy
to be president of Harvard when there was
a call for a more diverse president.
And what I learned was Harvard actually ran a process,
had a diverse new president of Harvard.
And in the due diligence on that candidate,
shortly before the announcement of the new president,
they found out that that presidential candidate
had a plagiarism problem.
And the search had gone on long enough,
they couldn't restart a search to find another candidate.
So they pick Larry Backhoe off the board,
off the search committee to the next president of Harvard
as kind of an interim solution.
And then there was that much more pressure
to have a more diverse candidate this time around.
'Cause there was a big disappointment to the DEI office,
if you will, and I would say to the community at large
that the Harvard of all places couldn't have
a racially diverse president,
it sent an important message.
So the strange thing is that they didn't do due diligence
on President Gay and that it was a relatively quick process.
So the whole thing I think is worthy of further exploration.
- So this goes deeper than just the president.
- Yeah, for sure.
When a company fails,
most people blame the CEO,
I generally blame the board, right?
'Cause the board's job is to make sure
the right person's running the company
and if they're failing, help the person.
If they can't help the person make a change.
That's not what's happened here.
The board's hand was sort of forced from the outside,
whereas they should have made
their own decision from the inside.
- Do you still love Harvard?
- Sure, it's a 400 odd year institution.
It enormously helpful to me in my life I'm sure.
My sister also went to Harvard
and the experiences, learnings,
friendships, relationships.
Again, I'm very happy with my life.
Harvard was an important part of my life.
I went there for both undergrad and business school.
I learned a ton, met a lot of faculty,
a lot from number of my closest friends
who I still really keep in touch with, I met them.
So yeah, it's a great place,
but it needs a reboot.
- Yeah, I still have hope.
I think universities are really important institutions.
- You know, when I went to Harvard
there were 1600 people in my class.
I think today's class is about the same size
and their online education really has not sort of taken off.
So I heard Peter Thiel speak at one point in time
and he is like, what great institution do you know
that's truly great that hasn't grown in a hundred years.
And you know, the incentives in some sense
of the alums are for it.
It's a bit like a club.
If you're proud of the elitism of the club,
you don't want many new members.
But the fact that the population has grown
of the country significantly
since certainly I was a student in 1984.
And the fact that Harvard recruits people
from all over the world,
it's really serving a smaller and smaller percentage
of the population today.
And some were most talented
and successful entrepreneurs anyway.
You know it's a token of success
that they didn't make it through their undergraduate years.
You know, they left as a freshman
or they didn't attend at all.
- For entrepreneurs, yes.
But it's still a place--
- Very important for research,
very important for advancing ideas
and shaping dialogue
and the next generation of Supreme Court justices.
The members of government politicians.
So yes, it's critically important,
but it's not doing the job it should be doing.
- Neri Oxman, somebody you mentioned several times
throughout this podcast,
somebody I had a wonderful conversation with,
a friendship with I've known, looked up to her,
admired her, I've been a fan of hers for a long time
for work and of her as a human being.
Looks like you're a fan of hers as well.
- Yes.
- What do you love about Neri?
What do you admire about her
as a scientist, artist, human being?
- I think she's the most beautiful person I've ever met.
And I mean that from like the center of her soul.
She's the most caring, warm, considerate,
thoughtful person I've ever met.
And she couples those remarkable qualities
with brilliance, incredible creativity,
beauty, elegance, grace.
Yeah, I'm talking about my wife,
but I'm talking incredibly dispassionately.
But I mean, what I say,
she's the most remarkable person I've ever met.
And I've met a lot of remarkable people
and I'm incredibly fortunate to spend
a very high percentage of my life time
with her ever since I met her six years ago.
- So she's been a help to you
through some of the rough moments you described.
- For sure. I mean, I met her at the bottom,
which is not a bad place to meet someone if it works out.
- Is there some degree of ying and yang
with the two personalities you have,
you have described yourself as emotional and so on,
but it does seem the two of you
have slightly different styles
about how you approach the world.
- Well, interestingly, we have a lot of like,
we come from very similar places in the world.
You know, there are times where we feel like
we've known each other for centuries.
You know, I met her parents for the first time
a long time ago, almost six years ago as well.
And I knew her parents were from Eastern Europe originally.
So I asked her father like, what, you know,
what city did her family come from originally?
And I called my father
and asked him, dad, what's grandpa Abraham?
What's the name of the city?
And then I put the two cities into Google Maps
and they were 52 miles apart,
which I thought was pretty cool.
Then of course, at some point we did genetic testing
to make sure we weren't related.
Which we were not.
But we share incredible commonality on values.
We are attracted to the same kind of people,
she loves my friends, I love hers.
We love doing the same kind of things,
we're attracted to like spending time the same ways.
And she has, yes, more emotion, more elegance.
She doesn't like battles,
but she's very strong.
But she's more sensitive than I am.
- Yeah, you are constantly in multiple battles
at the same time.
And there's often the media, social media
is just fire everywhere.
- You know, that hasn't really been the case for a while.
I've had relative peace for a long time
as I haven't had to be the kind of activist I was
earlier in my career,
I think since October 7th, yes,
I do feel like I've been in a war.
- Can you tell me the saga of the accusations against Neri?
- So I did not actually surface the plagiarism allegations
against President Gay that surfaced by Aaron
and maybe Christopher Rufo as well,
or maybe Chris helped promote
what Aaron and some anonymous person identified.
But I certainly, it was a point in time
where the board had said we're a hundred percent behind her
and unanimously, and I really felt she had to go.
So it didn't bother me at all
that they had identified problems with her work.
So I shared, I reposted those posts
and then when the board...
She ultimately resigned and she got a $900,000 a year
professorship continuing at Harvard.
I said, look, in light of her limited academic record
and these plagiarism allegations she had to go.
I knew when I did so I assumed,
I was actually a bit paranoid
about that thesis I had written.
I only had one academic work,
but I hadn't checked it for plagiarism.
And I thought, that's gonna happen.
I did not have a copy on hand.
So I got a copy of my thesis
and I remember writing it.
Harvard at the time was pretty,
they kind of gave you a lecture about
making sure you have all your footnotes and quotation marks.
I learned later that apparently
they had a copy of my thesis at the New York Public Library.
And a member of the media told me he was there online
with a dozen other members of the media
all trying to get a copy of my thesis
to run it through some AI.
They had to first do optical character recognition
to convert the paper document into digital.
But fortunately, through a miracle
I didn't have an issue.
I didn't think about Neri of course,
who has whatever, 130 academic works.
And so we were just at the end of a vacation
for Christmas break
and I was early in the morning for a vacation time
and all of a sudden I hear my phone ringing
in the other room
or vibrating in the other room multiple times.
I'm like, hmm.
I pick up the phone.
It's our communication guy, Fran McGill.
And he's like, Bill Business Insider
has apparently identified a number of instances
of plagiarism in Neri's dissertation.
Let me send you this email.
He sent me the email
and they had identified four paragraphs
in her 330 page dissertation
where she had cited the author,
but she had used the vast majority of the words,
and that those paragraphs were from the author
and she should have used quotation mark.
And then there was one case
where she paraphrased correctly an author,
but did not footnote that it was from his work.
And so we were presented with this
and told they're gonna publish in a few hours.
And we're like, well, can we get to the next day?
We're just about to head home.
And they're like, no, we're publishing by noon.
We need an answer by noon.
And so we downloaded the copy of her thesis
on like the slow internet.
And you know, Neri checked it out
and she said, you know what?
Looks like they're right.
And I said, look, you should just admit your mistake.
And she wrote a very simple, gracious,
yes, I should have used quotation marks.
And on the author I failed to cite,
she pointed out that she cited them many other times
and wrote her several paragraph section
of her thesis acknowledging his work.
And none of these were like important parts of her thesis.
But she acknowledged her mistake
and she said, you know, apologize for my mistake.
And I apologize to the author who I failed to cite
and I stand on the shoulders of
all the people came before me
and looking to advance work.
We sort of thought it was over,
we head home.
In flight on the way home, although we didn't realize this
till we got back the following day,
Business Insider published another article
and said, Neri Oxman admits to plagiarism.
Plagiarism of course is academic fraud.
And this thing goes crazy viral.
Oh, the title is Bill Ackman's wife,
celebrity Academic Neri Oxman.
And they use the term celebrity
because there are limits
to what legitimate media can go after.
But you know, celebrities,
there's a lot more leeway in the media
and what they can say.
So that's why they call her a celebrity.
First time ever she'd been called a celebrity
and they basically, she's admitting to academic fraud.
And then the next day at 5:19 PM
I remember the timeline pretty well.
An email was sent to Fran McGill saying,
we've identified two dozen other instances
of plagiarism in her work.
15 of which are Wikipedia entries
where she copied definitions
and the others were mostly software hardware manuals
for various devices or software she used in her work,
most of which were in footnotes
where she described a nozzle for a 3D printer
or something like this.
And they said, we're publishing tonight.
The email they sent to us was 6,900 words.
It was 12 pages, it was practically indecipherable.
You couldn't even read it in an hour.
And we didn't have some of the documents
that were referring to.
And I'm like, now you know what?
I'm gonna do it.
I think it'll be useful to provide context here.
I'm gonna do a review
of every MIT professor's dissertations,
every published paper AI has enabled this.
I put out a tweet basically saying that,
and we're doing a test run now
because we have to get it right
and I think it'll be a useful exercise,
provide some context if you will.
And then this thing goes crazy viral.
And you know, Neri is a pretty sensitive person,
pretty emotional person,
and someone who's a perfectionist
and having everyone in the world thinking
you committed academic fraud is a pretty damning thing.
Now, they did say, they did a thorough review
of all of her work and this is what they found.
I'm like, sweetheart, that's remarkable.
I did 130 works, 73 of which were peer reviewed,
blah blah blah.
And she's published in Nature Science
and all these different publications.
That's actually, that's a pretty good batting average.
But you know, they can't, this is wrong, right?
This is not academic fraud.
These are inadvertent mistakes.
And the Wikipedia entries,
Neri actually used Wikipedia as a dictionary.
This is the early days of Wikipedia.
And they also referred to the MIT handbook,
which has a whole section on plagiarism academic handbook.
And if you read it, which I ultimately did,
they make clear a few things.
Number one, there's plagiarism, academic fraud,
and there's what they call inadvertent plagiarism,
which is clerical errors where you make a mistake
and it depends on intent.
And there's a link that you can go to,
which is a section on, if you get investigated, MIT,
what happens, what's the procedure,
what's the initial stage,
what's the investigative stage,
what's the procedure if they identify it
and they make very clear that academic fraud is,
and they list plagiarism, research theft,
a few other things, but it does not include honest errors.
Honest errors are not plagiarism under MIT's own policies.
And in the handbook they also have a big section
on what they call common knowledge.
And common knowledge depends on
who you're writing your thesis for.
And so if it's a fact that is known by your audience,
you're not required to quote or cite.
And so all those Wikipedia entries
were for things like sustainable design,
computer aided design.
She just took a definition from Wikipedia,
common knowledge to her readers,
no obligation under the handbook,
totally exempt on the,
using the same words she referred to
like an whatever, some kind of 3D printer.
She was the Stratasys 3D printer
and she quoted from the manual right away.
Stratasys is a company you consulted for.
You don't need to...
That's not something, you're not stealing your ideas,
you're describing a nozzle for a device
you use in your work in a footnote.
That's not a theft of idea, right?
And so I'm like, this is crazy.
And so this has gotta stop.
And so I reach out to a guy I knew
who was on the board of Business Insider, the chairman,
and his name is gonna come public shortly.
I committed to that time to keep his name confidential.
It's now surfaced publicly in the press.
- Can I just pause real quick here?
- Sure.
- I don't know, there's a lot of things I wanna say,
but you made it pretty clear.
But just as a member of the community,
there's also like a common sense test.
I think you're more precisely
like legal and looking at,
but there's just like a bullshit test.
And like nothing that Neri did is plagiarism
in the bad meaning of the word.
Plagiarism right now is becoming another ism, like racism
or so on using as an attack word.
I don't care what the meaning of it is,
but there's the bad academic fraud like theft.
Theft of an idea.
And maybe you can say a lot of definitions
and this kind of stuff.
But then there's just a basic bullshit test
where everyone knows this is a thief
and this is definitely not a thief.
And there's nothing about anything that Neri did
anything in her thesis or in her life.
Everyone that knows her, she's a rock star, right?
I just wanna make it clear,
it really hurt me that the internet,
whatever's happening, could go after a great scientist.
'Cause I love science and I love celebrating
great scientists and it's just really messed up
that whatever the machine,
we could talk about Business Inside or whatever,
social media, mass hysteria, whatever is happening.
Like we need the great scientists of the world.
'Cause that's like the future depends on them.
And so we need to celebrate them and protect them
and let them flourish and let their do their thing
and like keep them out of this whatever shit storm
that we're doing to get clicks and advertisements and drama
and all this kind, we need to protect them.
So I just wanna say
there's nobody I know
and I'm a million friends that are scientists,
world class scientists, Nobel Prize winners,
they all love Neri, they all respect Neri
she did zero wrong.
And then the rest of the conversation we can have about
how broken journalism is and so on.
But like, I just wanna say that there's nothing
that Neri did wrong.
It's not a gray area or so on.
I also personally don't love that Claudine Gay
is a discussion about plagiarism
'cause it distracts from the fundamentals that is broken.
It's becomes like some weird technical discussion.
But in case of Neri did nothing wrong,
great scientist, great engineer at MIT
and beyond, she's doing a cool thing now so anyway.
- Could not have said it better myself.
Now obviously I'm focused on the technical part, right?
- [Lex] Because you wanna be precise.
- Well, it's not even that.
I mean, yes, I have said
that we're gonna sue Business Insider
and in 35 years of my career
of someone who has not every article
has been a favorable one.
Not every article has been an accurate one.
I've never threatened to sue the media
and I've never sued the media.
But this is so egregious.
It's not just that she did nothing wrong,
but they accused her of academic fraud.
They did it knowing they make reference
to MIT's own handbook.
So they had to read all the same stuff
that I read in the handbook.
They did that work.
Then after escalated this thing to
Henry Blot, the Chairman of Business Insider,
to the CEO of Axle Springer,
I even reached out to Henry Kravis
at a certain point in time.
One of the controlling shareholders
of the company through KKR.
Laying out the factual errors in the article,
Business Center went public
after they said Neri committed academic fraud and plagiarism
and said, we didn't challenge any,
the facts remain undisputed in the article.
So it's basically Neri committed plagiarism that story won,
Neri admits to plagiarism.
She admits to plagiarism.
She admitted to making a few clerical errors.
That's the only thing she admitted to.
And she graciously apologized.
So they said, Neri admits to plagiarism,
apologizes for plagiarism.
That's incredibly damning.
And by the way, we're doing an investigation
'cause we're concerned that there might have been
inappropriate process,
but the facts of the story
have not been disputed by Neri Oxman or Bill Ackman.
And that was totally false.
I had done it privately,
I'd done it publicly on Twitter on X,
I laid out, I have a whole tech stream,
a WhatsApp stream with the CEO of the company.
And they doubled down and they doubled down again.
And so I don't sue people lightly.
And you stay tuned.
- So you are, at least for now, moving forward with--
- It's a certainty we're moving forward.
There's this step we can take prior to suing them
where we basically send them a letter
demanding they make a series of corrections
that if they don't make those corrections,
the next step is litigation.
I hope we can avoid the next step.
And I'm just making sure that
when we present the demand to Business Insider
and ultimately to Axel Springer,
that it's incredibly clear
how they defamed her,
the factual mistakes in her stories
and what they need to do to fix it.
And if we can fix it there,
we can move on from this episode
and hopefully avoid litigation,
so that's where we're.
- I don't know, you're smarter than me.
There's technical stuff, there's legal stuff,
there's journalistic stuff.
But just fuck you Business Insider for doing this.
I don't know much in this world,
but journalists aren't supposed to do that.
- Now we're gonna surface all this stuff publicly ultimately
the email was not to Neri
saying there was plagiarism in her work.
The email came from a reporter named Katherine Long,
and the headline was, your wife committed plagiarism,
shouldn't she be fired from MIT
just like you caused Claudine Gay to be fired from Harvard.
It was a political agenda.
She doesn't like me, okay.
And she was trying to hurt me
and they couldn't find plagiarism in my thesis.
And being a short seller,
the Herbalife battle went on for years,
they tried to do everything to destroy my reputation.
So they're already gone through my trash.
They already done all that work.
So anything they could possibly find,
and I've always lived a very clean life, okay?
Thankfully. And if you're gonna be an activist,
short sell, you better
'cause they're gonna find out dirt on if it exists.
And so they were like, how can we really hurt Bill?
And by the way Neri had left MIT years earlier.
When the reporter found out
she was no longer a member of the MIT faculty,
they were enraged.
They didn't believe us.
They made us like prove to us
she's no longer on the MIT faculty
'cause they wanted to get her fired.
And by the way, malice is one of the
important factors in determining
whether defamation is taking place.
And this was a malice driven,
this was not about news.
And the unfortunate thing about journalism,
this businesses made a fortune from this.
This story was published and republished
by thousands of media organizations around the world.
It was the number one trending thing on Twitter
for like two days.
Every newspaper, it was on the front page
of every Israeli newspaper.
It was on the front page of the Financial Times.
Okay, so this, and she's building a business
and you know if you're CEO of a science company
and you committed academic fraud,
that's incredibly damaging.
But I ultimately convinced her that this was good.
I said, sweetheart, you're amazing.
You're incredible.
You're incredibly talented,
but you're mostly known in the design world.
Now everyone in the universe, has heard of Neri Oxman.
Okay, we're gonna get this thing cleared up.
You're gonna be doing an event in six months
where you're gonna tell the world
you're gonna go outta stealth mode,
you're gonna tell the world about all the incredible things
that you're building and you're designing
and you're creating
and it's gonna be like the iPhone launch.
'Cause everyone's gonna be paying attention
and they're gonna wanna see your work.
And you know, that's how I try to cheer up.
But I think it's true.
- It is true, and you're doing
your job as a good partner
in seeing the silver lining of all this.
Just from observing her, how did she
stay strong through all of this psychologically?
'Cause at least I know she's pushing ahead with the work.
- Oh, she's full speed ahead in her work.
She's built an amazing team.
She's hired 30 scientists, roboticists,
people who, biologists, plant specialists,
material scientists, engineers,
really incredible crew.
She's built this 36,000 square foot lab in New York City.
That's a one of a kind.
It's still, they're working out of it.
It's still under construction
while they're working out of it.
And so she's gonna do amazing things.
But as I said, she's an extremely sensitive person.
She's a perfectionist. Okay?
Imagine thinking that the entire world
thinks you committed academic fraud.
And so that was very hard for her.
She's a very positive person.
But I saw her, and I would say her darkest emotional period
for sure, she's doing much better now.
But you can kill someone,
you can kill someone with by destroying their reputation.
People commit suicide.
People go into these deep dark depression.
- Well, my worry primarily when I saw
what Business Insider was doing,
is that they might dim the light
of a truly special scientist and creator.
- It's not gonna happen.
- But I also worry about others like Neri,
young Neris that this sends a signal to
that might scare them.
And you know, journalism
shouldn't scare aspiring young scientists.
- The problem is the defamation law in the US
is so favorable to the publisher, to the media,
and so unfavorable to the victim.
And the incentives are all wrong.
You know when you went from
a paper version of journalism to digital
and you could track how many people click,
and it's a medium that advertising drives the economics.
And if you can show an advertiser more clicks,
you can make more money.
So a journalist is incentivized to write a story
that will generate more clicks.
How do you write a story that'll generate more clicks?
You get a billionaire guy
and then you go after his wife
and you make a sensationalist story,
and you give them no time to respond.
Look at the timing here.
On the first story they gave us three hours
on the second one the following day,
5:19 PM the email comes in, not to Neri,
not to her firm, but to my communications person
who tracks us down by 5:30, you know, 10 minutes later.
And they published their story 92 minutes after.
And they sent us, we're gonna surface all these documents
in our demand, read the email they sent,
whether you could even decipher it.
And by the way there's a reason why academic institutions,
when a professors accused of plagiarism,
why they have these very careful processes
with multiple stages and they take,
they can take a year or more because it depends on intent.
Was this intentional?
In order to be a crime, an academic crime,
you gotta prove that they intentionally stole.
Look, in some cases it's obvious.
In some cases it's very subtle
and they take this stuff super seriously.
But they basically accused Neri of academic crime.
And then 92 minutes later
they said she committed an academic crime
and that should be a crime
and that should be punishable with litigation.
And there should be a real cost
and we're gonna make sure there's a real cost
and reputationally and otherwise to Business Insider
and to Axel Springer
'cause ultimately you gotta look to the controlling owner,
you know, they're responsible.
- I'll just say that you in this regard
are inspiring to me for facing
basically an institution
that whole purpose is to write articles.
So you're like going into the fire.
- My kid's school, the epithet of the school,
or the saying is go forth unafraid.
I think it's a good way to live.
And again, the words can't harm me.
You know the power of X
and we do owe Elon enormous thanks for this is now...
So for example, the Washington Post
wrote a story about me a couple days ago,
and I didn't think the story was a fair story.
So within a few hours of the story being written,
I'm able to put out a response to the story
and send it to 1,000,200 thousand people.
And it gets read and reread.
I haven't checked, but probably
5 million people saw my response.
Now those are the people on X.
It's not everyone in the world.
There's a disconnection between the X world
and the offline world.
But reputation in my business is basically all you have.
And as they say, you can take a lifetime
to build a reputation
and take five minutes to have it disappear.
And the media plays a very important role
and they can destroy people.
At least we now have some ability to fight back.
We have a platform, we can surface our views.
The typical old days
they write an incredibly deming article
and you point out factual errors
and then like two months later
they bury a little correction on page whatever
by then the person was fired
or their life was destroyed
or the reputation's damaged.
You know, it was with Warren Buffet talking about media.
And it's something he, a business he really loves.
He says, you know what Bill?
He said, a thief with a dagger.
The only person who cause you more harm
than a thief with a dagger is a journalist with a pen.
And those were very powerful words.
- So you think X formerly known as Twitter, is a kind
of neutralizing force to that,
to the power of centralized journalistic institutions?
- A hundred percent.
And I think it's a really important one,
and it's really been eye-opening for me
to see how stories get covered in mainstream media.
And then you actually...
What I do on X is I follow people
on multiple sides of an issue.
Or I post on a topic and I get to hear the other side.
I read the replies.
And the truth is something that people
have had a lot of question about,
particularly in the last,
I would say five years.
You know, beginning with
Trump's talking about fake news
and a lot of what Trump said about fake news is true.
You know the world, a big part of the world hated Trump
and did everything they could to discredit him, destroy him.
And he did a lot of things perhaps deserving
of being discredited,
used by a very imperfect, in some cases harmful leader.
But you know, everything from pre-election,
the Hunter Biden laptop story in the New York Post
that then Twitter made difficult
for people to share and to read.
COVID, you know, the Jay Bhattacharya of the world
questioning the government's response,
questioning long-term lockdowns,
questioning keeping kids outta school,
questions about masks, about vaccines,
which are still not definitively answered.
No counterbalance to the power
of the government when the government can shut down
avenues for free speech.
And where the mainstream media has kind of
towed the line in many extents to the government's action.
So having a independently owned
powerful platform is very important for truth,
for free speech, for hearing the other side of the story,
for counterbalancing the power of the government.
Elon is getting a lot of pushback.
You know, the SpaceXs and Teslas of the world
are experiencing a lot of
government questions and investigations.
And even the president of the United States came out
and said, look, he needs to be investigated.
I'm getting my own version of that in terms of
some negative media articles.
I don't know what's next.
But yeah, if you stick your neck out in today's world
and you go against the establishment,
or at least the existing administration,
you can find yourself in a very challenged place.
And that discourages people from sharing stuff.
And that's why anonymous speech is important.
Some of what you find on Twitter.
- You mentioned Trump, I have to talk to you about politics.
Amongst all the other battles,
you've also been a part of that one.
Maybe you can correct me on this,
but you've been a big supporter
of various democratic candidates over the years,
but you did say a lot of nice things
about Donald Trump in 2016, I believe.
- So I was interviewed by Andrew Sorkin
a week after Trump won the election.
And I made my case for why I thought
he could be a good president.
- So what was the case back then?
To which degree did that turn out to be true
and to which degree did it not?
To which degree was he a good president,
to which degree was he not a good president?
- I think what I said at the time was
the United States is actually a huge business.
And it reminds me a bit of
the type of activist investments we've taken on over time,
where this really, really great business
has kinda lost its way.
And with the right leadership, we can fix it.
And if you think about the business
of the United States today
you've got $32 trillion worth of debt.
So it's over leveraged or it's highly leveraged.
And the leverage is only increasing.
We're losing money i.e revenues aren't covering expenses.
The cost of our debt is going up
as interest rates have gone up
and the debt has to be rolled over.
We have enormous administrative bloat in the country.
The regulatory regime is incredibly complicated
and burdensome and impeding growth.
Our relations with our competitor nations
and our friendly nations are far from ideal.
And those conditions were present in 2020 as well.
They're just, I would say worse now.
And I said, look, it's a great thing that we have
a businessman as president.
And in my lifetime was really the first businessman
as opposed to, I mean, maybe Bush
to some degree was a business person,
but I thought, okay, I always wanted the CEO to be
CEO of America and now we have Trump.
I said, look, he's got some personal qualities
that seem less ideal,
but he's gonna be president of the United States.
He's gonna rise to the occasion.
This is gonna be his legacy and he knows how to make deals
and he's gonna recruit some great people
into his administration. I hoped.
And growth can solve a lot of our problems.
So if we can get rid of a bunch of regulations
that are holding back the country,
we can have a President Obama was a,
I would say not a pro business president.
He did not love the business community.
He did not love successful people.
And having a president who just changed the tone
on being a pro-business president,
I thought would be good for the country.
And that's basically what I said.
And I would say Trump did a lot of good things
and a lot of people you can get criticized
for acknowledging that.
But you know, I think the country's economy
accelerated dramatically.
And that, by the way, you know,
the capitalist system helps the people at the bottom
best when the system does well
and when the economy does well.
You know, the black unemployment rate was lowest in history
when Trump was president,
and that's true for other minority groups.
So he was good for the economy
and he recognized some of the challenges
and issues and threats of China early.
He kind of woke up NATO.
Now again, the way he did all this stuff
you can object to, but you know,
NATO actually started spending more money on defense
in the early part of Trump's presidency
because of his threats,
which turned out to be a good thing
in light of the ultimately the Russia, Ukraine war.
And I think if you analyze Trump objectively
based on policies, he did a lot of good for the country.
I think what's bad is he did some harm as well.
I do think civility disappeared in America
with Trump as president.
A lot of that's his personal style.
And how important is civility?
I do think it's important.
I do think, you know, he was attacked very aggressively
by the left, by the media that made him paranoid.
It probably interfered with his ability to be successful.
He had the Russian collusion investigation overhang.
And when someone's attacked,
they're not gonna be at their best,
particularly if they're paranoid.
I think there's some degree of that.
But I'm giving kind of the best
of defense of Trump.
You know, just you look at how he managed his team, right?
Very few people made it through the Trump administration
without getting fired or quitting.
And he would say they're the greatest person in the world
when he hired them
and they're total disaster when he fired them.
It's not an inspiring way to be a leader
and to attract really talented people.
I think the events surrounding the election,
I think January 6th, he could have done a lot more
to stop a riot.
I don't consider it an insurrection,
but a riot that takes place in our capitol.
And where police officers are killed or die, commit suicide
'cause for failure to, as they sought to do their job.
He stepped in way too late to stop that.
He could have stopped it early.
You know, many of his words I think inspired people,
Some of whom with mal intent
to go in there and cause harm
and literally to shut down the government.
There were some evil people unfortunately there.
So he's been a very imperfect president
and also I think contributed to the
extreme amount of divisiveness in our country.
So I was ultimately disappointed
by the note of optimism.
And again, I always support the president.
I trust the people ultimately to select our next leader.
You know, it's a bit like
who wants to be a millionaire.
When you go to the crowd
and the crowd says a certain thing,
you gotta trust the crowd.
But usually in who wants to be a millionaire,
it's a landslide in one direction.
So, you know which letter to pick.
Here we had an incredibly close election
which itself is a problem.
So my dream and what I've tried a little bit,
played politics in the last little period
to support some alternatives to Trump
so that we have a president.
I use the example, imagine you woke up in the morning,
it's election day, whatever it is, this November 4th,
whatever, 2024.
And you still haven't figured out who to vote for.
'Cause the candidates are so appealing that
you don't know which lever to pull
because it's a tough call.
That's the choice we should be making as Americans.
It shouldn't be,
I'm a member of this party
and I'm only gonna vote this way.
I'm a member of that party,
I'm gonna vote the other way
and I hate the other side.
And that's where we've been unfortunately for too long.
- Or you might be torn because both candidates are not good.
So you wanna...
I love a future where I'm torn
because the choices are so amazing.
- The problem is the party system is so screwed up
and the parties are self interested
and there's another governance problem,
an incentive problem.
Michael Porter, who was one of my professors
at Harvard Business School wrote a brilliant piece
on the American political system
and all the incentives and market dynamics
and what he called it competitive analysis.
And it's a must read, I should dig it up
and send it around on X.
But it explains how the parties
and the incentives of these sort of self-sustaining entities
where the people involved are not incentivized
to do what's best for the country, it's a problem.
- You've been a supporter of Dean Phillips
for the 2024 US presidential race?
- Yes.
- What do you like about Dean?
- I think he's a honest, smart, motivated,
capable, proven guy as a business leader.
And I think in six, almost
in his three terms in Congress,
he ran, when Trump was elected,
he said his kids cried,
his daughters cried,
inspired him to run for office.
Ran in a republican district in Minnesota
for the last 60 years, was elected in the landslide,
has been reelected twice,
moved up the ranks in the Congress,
respected by his fellow members of Congress,
advance some important legislation during COVID
on senior roles on various foreign policy committees.
Centrist, you know,
considered I think the second most
bipartisan member of the Congress.
I'd love to have a bipartisan president.
That's the only way to get kind of go forward
but we'd enormously benefit if we had a president
that chose policies on the basis
of what's best for the country
as opposed to what his party wanted.
What I like about him is he's financially independent.
He's not a billionaire,
but he doesn't need the job.
The party hates him now
'cause he challenged the king, right?
And so, but he was willing to give up his political career
'cause what he thought was best for the country.
He tried to get other people to run
who were higher profile,
had more name recognition.
None would, no one wants to challenge Biden.
If they wanna have a chance to stay in office
or run in the future,
but he's very principled.
I think he would be a great president,
but he needs his shot is Michigan,
but he needs to raise money in order to,
he's only got a couple weeks
and he's gotta be on TV there.
That's expensive.
So we'll see.
- So he has to increase name recognition
all that kind of stuff.
Also, as should mention, he's young.
- Yeah, he's 55, but he's a young 55.
You see him play hockey.
- I mean, I guess 55, no matter what
is a pretty young age.
- I'm 57. I feel young,
I can do more pull-ups today than I could as a kid.
So that's a standard.
- You're at the top of your tennis game.
- I'm at the top of my tennis game for sure.
- Maybe there's someone that would disagree with that.
- And by the way, the other thing to point out here is,
and I have been pointing this out as have others,
Biden is I think is done,
I mean, it's embarrassing.
It's embarrassing for the country
having him as a presidential candidate,
let alone the president of the country.
It's crazy. And it's just gonna get worse and worse.
And he should hit the worst of his legacy
is his ego that prevents him from stepping aside
and that's it, it's his ego.
And it is so wrong and so bad and so embarrassing.
You talk to people, I was in Europe,
I was in London a few days ago,
and people are like,
"Bill, how can this guy be a president?"
And it's a bit like,
again, I go back to my business analogy.
Being a CEO is like a full contact sport.
Being president of the United States
is like some combination of wrestling,
marathon, running, you know,
being a triathlete.
I mean, you gotta be at the serious physical shape
and at the top of your game to represent this country.
And he is a far cry from that.
And it's just getting worse and it's embarrassing.
And he cannot be.
And by the way, every day he waits,
he's handing the election to Trump
because it's harder and harder
for an alternative candidate to surface.
Now Dean is the only candidate left
on the Democratic side that can still win delegates.
He's on the ballot in 42 states.
And the best way for Biden to step aside
is for Dean to show well in Michigan.
- And so you think there is a path
with the delegates and all that kind of stuff?
- A hundred percent.
So what has to happen is,
New Hampshire, he went from zero to 20% of the vote
and 10 weeks with no name recognition.
I helped a little bit.
Elon helped, we did a spaces for him.
We had 350,000 people on the spaces.
Some originally 40,000 live or something
and then the rest after.
And then he was on the ground in New Hampshire.
And New Hampshire is one of the states where
you don't need to be registered
to a party to vote for the candidate.
So it's like jump ball and he got 20%.
And that's with a lot of independence.
And Democrats voting for Haley.
Haley who I like and who I've supported,
does not look like she's gonna make it.
Trump is really kind of running the table.
And so vote for Haley as an independent Michigan,
maybe throw away your vote.
I think it increases the likelihood
that Dean can get those independent votes
if he could theoretically, again, he needs money.
He could beat Biden in Michigan.
Biden's doing very poorly in Michigan.
His polls are terrible.
The Muslim community is not happy with him
and he really has spent no time there.
And so if he's embarrassed in Michigan,
it could be a catalyst for him withdrawing.
Then Dean will get funding.
If he wins Michigan or shows well in Michigan
and people say he's viable
or he's the only choice we have.
He'll attract from the center,
he'll attract from Republicans who won't vote for Trump,
in which they're a big percentage.
Could be 60% or more.
It could be 70% won't vote for Trump
and also from the Democrats.
So I think he's a really interesting candidate,
but we gotta get the word out.
- I gotten a chance to chat with Dean.
I really like him.
And I think the next president of the United States
is gonna have to meet
and speak regularly with Zelensky, Putin
and Netanyahu, with world leaders
and have some of the most historic conversations,
agreements, negotiations.
And I just don't see Biden doing that.
And not for any reason, but sadly age.
- Yeah, I mean, think about it this way.
When Biden's in present now you saw his recent
impromptu press conference,
which he did after the special prosecutor report
basically saying the guy was way past his prime
and then he confused the president of Mexico
and the president of Egypt.
So they're very careful when they roll him out
and he's scripted and he's always reading from a lectern.
Imagine the care they have in exposing him
and when they expose him, it's terrible.
Imagine how bad it is for real.
- It's not good.
- Really bad for America.
And I'm upset with him and upset with his family.
I'm upset with his wife.
You know, this is the time where the people closest to you
have to put their arms around you
and say, dad, honey, you've done your thing.
This is gonna be your legacy
and it's not gonna be a good one.
- Great leaders should also know when to step down.
- Yeah. One of the best tests of a leader
is succession planning.
This is a massive failure of succession planning.
- Outside of politics
let me look to the future first,
in terms of the financial world,
what are you looking forward to in the next couple of years?
You have a new fund,
like what are you thinking about in terms of investment,
your own and the entire economy
and maybe even the economy of the world?
- Sure. So the SEC doesn't like us
to talk about new funds that we're launching
that we filed with the SEC.
But I would say I do...
And by the way, if anyone's ever interested in a fund,
they should always read the prospectus carefully,
including the risk factors.
That's very, very important.
But I like the idea of democratizing
access to good investors.
And I think that's an interesting trend.
So we wanna be part of that trend.
In terms of financial markets,
generally, the economy a lot of it's gonna depend
upon the next leader of the country.
So we're kind of right back there.
You know the leadership of the United States
is important for the US economy,
it's important for the global economy,
it's important for global peace.
And we've gone through a really
difficult period and it's time.
We need a break.
But look, I think the United States
is an incredibly resilient country.
We have some incredible moats among them.
We have the Atlantic and the Pacific,
and we have peaceful neighbors to the north and the south.
We're an enormously rich country.
Capitalism still works effectively here.
I get optimistic about the world
when I talk to my friends
who are either venture capitalists
or my hobby of backing these young entrepreneurs.
I talk to a founder of a startup,
if you wanna get optimistic about the world.
So I think technology is gonna save us.
I think AI, of course, has its frightening
terminator like scenarios.
But I'm gonna take the opposite view
that this is gonna be a huge enabler of productivity,
scientific discovery, drug discovery,
and it's gonna make us healthier,
happier and better.
So I do think the internet revolution
had a lot of good, obviously some bad.
I think the AI revolution's gonna be similar,
but we're at this other really interesting juncture
in the world with technology.
And we're gonna have to use it for our good.
On the media front, I'm happy about X
and I think Elon's gonna be successful here.
I think advertisers will realize
it's a really good platform.
The best way to reach me,
if you wanna sell something to me is post.
I've actually bought stuff on some ads in X.
I don't remember the last time I responded
to a direct response advertising.
You know, in terms of my business,
I have an incredible team.
It's tiny. We're one of the smallest firms
relative to the assets we manage.
It's a bit like the Navy Seals,
you know, not the US Army.
We have only 40 people at Persian Square.
So it's a tight team.
I think we'll do great things.
I think we're early on.
My ambitions investment wise,
I've always said I'd like to have a record
as good as Warren Buffet's.
The problem is, each year he adds on another year.
He's now in his 93rd year.
So I've got 36 more years to just get where he is.
And I think he's gonna add a lot more years.
I'm excited about seeing what Neri's gonna produce.
You know, she's building an incredible company.
They're trying to solve a lot of problems
with respect to products and buildings
and their impact on the environment.
Her vision is how do we design products
that by virtue of the product's existence,
the world is a better place.
You know, today you make,
her world is a world where the existence of the new car
actually is better for the environment
than if the new car hadn't existed.
And think about that in every product scale,
that's what she's working on.
I don't wanna give away too much.
But you're gonna see some early examples
of what she's working on.
So again, I get excited about the future
and crises are sort of a terrible thing to waste.
And we've had a number of these here.
I think this disaster in the Middle East.
My prediction is the next few months,
this war will largely be over
in terms of getting rid of Hamas.
I think I can envision a world in which Saudi Arabia,
some of the other Gulf states come together,
take over the governance
and reconstruction of Gaza
security guarantees are put in place.
The Abraham Accords continue to grow.
A deal is made, terrorists are ostracized.
That this October 7th experience on the Harvard,
Penn, MIT, Columbia,
unfortunately other campuses
is a wake up call for universities generally.
You know people see the problems with DEI,
but understand the importance of diversity
and inclusion, but not as a political movement,
but as a way that we return to a meritocratic world
where someone's background is relevant
in understanding their contribution.
But it's not, we don't have race quotas
and things that were made illegal years ago
actually being implemented in organizations on campus.
So I think there's, if we can go through a corrective phase,
and I'm an optimist and I hope we get there.
- So you have hope for the entirety of it.
Even for Harvard.
- I have hope, even for Harvard,
it's generally hard
to break 400 year old things.
- Well, I share your hope
and you are a fascinating mind, a brilliant mind,
persistent as you like to say.
And fearless, the fearless part is truly inspiring.
And this was an incredible conversation. Thank you.
Thank you for talking today Bill.
- Thank you Lex.
- Thanks for listening
to this conversation with Bill Ackman.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you some words from Jonathan Swift.
A wise person should have money in their head
but not in their heart.
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.