in terms of your mistakes society
tells you don't make them because
we will judge you and we will look down on you
and i think the really successful people realize that actually no
it's the cycle time of mistakes that gets you to success
because your error rate will diminish the more mistakes that you make you
observe them you
figure out where it's coming from is it a psychological
thing is it a you
know cognitive
thing and
then you fix it
following is a conversation with your mouth a
venture capitalist and engineer founder
and ceo of social capital previously
in early senior executive at facebook and
is
the co-host of the all in podcast a
podcast that i highly recommend for the wisdom and the camaraderie of the four co-hosts also
known as besties
this
is the lux friedman podcast to
support it please check out our sponsors in the description and
now dear friends here's
chamath balajapatia
you grew up in a dysfunctional household on welfare you've talked about this before what
war for you personally psychologically some difficult moments in your childhood
i'll answer that question in a slightly different way which is that
i think when you grow up
in a household that's defined by physical abuse and psychological abuse
you're
hyper vigilant all the time
and so it's actually easier for me to point to moments where
i was happy
or i felt compassion or i felt safe
otherwise every moment i'll give you a couple of examples like
you know i was thinking about this a while ago
there was a tree outside of my apartment where we lived when i was growing up
and my father would sometimes would make me go outside to take the tree branch
that he would hit me with
um and so you can imagine if
you're a 10 11 year old kid and you have to deal with that what
do you do well
a hyper vigilant child learns
how to basically estimate the strength of these branches
right how far
can he go before it breaks
you have to estimate his anger and estimate the effective
strength of you
know branches
and bring back something because you know i
remember these
moments where if it was
he
would look at it and then he would make me go out again and
get it right
get a different one
um or
you know there was a certain belt that he wore that had this kind of
um belt buckle that stuck out
and
you just wanted to make sure if that if
that was the thing that you were going to get hit by
that it wasn't the buckle facing out because that really hurt
and so you became hyper aware of
which part of the buckle was facing out versus facing in in those moments
and there are like hundreds of these little examples
which
essentially i would i would say the through line is that you're just so on edge
right and you walk into this
house and you're just basically
trying
to get to the point where you leave the house
um and so in that microcosm of growing up
any moment that's not like that is
seared in my memory in a way that i just can't
describe to a person i'll give you an example
i
volunteered
when i was in grade five or six i can't remember which it was
in the kindergarten
of my school
and i would just go and the teacher would you know ask
you to clean things up
and at the end of that great five year
she took me and two other kids to dairy queen
and i'd never been i've never i'd never gone to a restaurant literally because
we just we didn't have the money
and i remember the first time i tasted
this you know this dairy queen meal
it was like a hamburger
fries a coconut
a blizzard and i was like what is this and i felt
so
special you know because you're getting something that most
people would take for granted oh it's a sunday or
it's a you know or i'm really busy
let me go take my kid to
to fast
food i
think that you know until i left high school
i think and this is not just specific
to me but a lot of other people it's
you're in this hyper vigilant loop
punctuated with these incredibly visceral moments of compassion by other people you know a different example
um we had such a strict budget
and we didn't have a car
and so you know i was responsible with my mom to always go shopping
and so i learned very early on how to you
know look for coupons how
to buy things that were on sale or special
and we had a very basic diet because you have to budget this thing really precisely
but the end of every year
where i lived there was a large grocery chain called loblaws and loblaws would discount
a cheesecake from 7.99 to 4.99
and my
parents would buy that once a year and we probably did that six or seven times
and you can't imagine how special we felt myself my two sisters we
would sit there we would watch the you know the new
year's eve celebration
on tv we would cut
this cheesecake into you know five pieces
it felt like everything
um so that's sort of how you know my
my existence when i was at that age is
for better or for worse that's how i remember it
the hyper vigilance loop is that still with you today what
are the echoes of that that's told you today the good and the bad if
you put yourself
in the mind of a young child
the thing that that does to you
is at a very core basic level it says you're worthless
right because if
you can
step outside of that and you think about any child in the world
they
don't deserve to go through that
and at some point by the way i should tell you like i don't blame
my parents anymore it
was a process to get there but
i
feel like they did the best they could
and they suffered their own issues and enormous pressures and stresses
and so you know i've
really for the most part forgiven them
how did you start to interrupt let go of that blame
that was a really long process where
i would say the first 35 years of my life
i compartmentalized and i avoided all of those memories
and i saw external validation
right going back to this self-worth
idea if you're taught as a child that you're worthless
because why would somebody do these things to you
it's not because you're worth something you think to yourself very
viscerally you're worth nothing
and so then you go out and you seek external
validation
maybe
you try to go and get into a
great college you try to get a good job you
try to make a lot of money you
try to you know demonstrate
in superficial ways with the car you drive or the clothes you wear
that you deserve people to care about you
to try to make up for that really deep hole
but at some point you it doesn't get filled in and so you have a choice
and
so for me what happened was in in the course of a six-month
period i lost my best friend and
i lost my father
and
it was really like the dam broke loose because i the compartmentalization
stopped working because the reminder
of why i was compartmentalizing was gone
and so i had to go through this period of disharmony to really understand
and steel man his perspective
and can you imagine trying
to do that to go through all of the things where
you
have to now look at it from his perspective and
find compassion and empathy
for what he went through
and then i shift you know the focus to my mom and i said well
you were not
the victim actually you were somewhat complicit as well because you
were of sound mind and body and you were in the room when it happened
so then i had to go through that process with her and steal man her perspective
and
at the end of it i never justified what they did but
i've been able to forgive what they did
um i think they did the best they could and
at the end of the day they
did the most important thing which is they gave me and my sisters a shot by
emigrating by
giving up everything by
staying in canada and
doing whatever it took between the two of them
to sort of claw and scrape together enough money to live so that my
sisters and i could have a shot and
i'm very thankful for them could they have done better obviously
but i'm okay with what
has taken place but it's it's been a long process
of of
that steel manning
so that you can develop some empathy
and compassion
and
forgive
do you think if you talk to your dad
shortly
after he died and you went to that process or today you'll be able to have
the same strength
to forgive him
i think it would be a very complicated journey
i think i've learned to be incredibly open about what has happened
and all of the mistakes i've made
i think it's it would require him to be pretty radically honest about confirming
what i think he went through
because otherwise it just wouldn't work otherwise
i would say let's keep things where they are which is i did the work
you know with with people that have helped me obviously but you know it's
better for him to just you know kind of hopefully he's looking from
some place and he's thinking
it
was worth it i think he deserves to think that all of this because
you know i
think the immigrant
challenge we're not even the immigrant challenge the
lower middle class challenge anybody who really wants better for their kids and
doesn't have a good toolkit to give it to them
some of them
just they choke up on the bat they just get so
agitated
about this idea that all this sacrifice will not be worth it
that it spills out in really unproductive ways
and i would put him in that category
and
their self
evaluation
introspection
they have tunnel vision so they're not
able
to often see the damage they did i mean i've i know like
yourself
a few successful people that had very difficult relationships
with their dad and you take the perspective of the dad
they're completely in denial about any of it so if you actually have a conversation there
would not be a deep honesty there
and that i think that's maybe in part the way of life
yeah and you know i remember pretty
distinctly after i left and in this you know in my middle 30s where
you know by all measure i had roughly become reasonably successful
and my dad didn't particularly care about that which was so odd
because i had to confront the fact that you know
whether it was a title or money or press clippings he
never really cared he
moved on to a different set of goals which was more about my
character and you know being a good person to my family and really preparing
me to lead our family when he wasn't there
and that bothered me
because
i thought i thought i got to the finish line and
i thought there was going to be a
metal
you
know meaning like i can tell you lex you
know he never told me that he loved me
i'm not sure if that's normal or not it
was my normality and i thought there's going to be something some gold star which
never appeared
and so that's like a hard thing to
kind of confront because you're like well now what is this what is this all about
um was this all just kind of a a ruse
but then i realized well hold on a second there were these moments
where in his way again putting yourself in his shoes
i think he was trying to say he was sorry he would hold my hand
you know and he would interlock
the fingers which i felt is that's a really intimate way of holding somebody's
hand i think
um so i remember those things so
you
know these are the things that are just etched in at least in my mind and
at the end of it you know i think
i've
done a decent job in repairing
my relationship with him even
though you
know it was posthumous
it does make me wonder in which way you
and i or we might be broken and not see it it
might be hurting others and not see it well i think that when you grow
up in those kinds of environments and they're all different kinds of this kind of dysfunction
but if
what you get from that is that you're not worthwhile you're
not you're less than many many other people
when you enter adulthood or you know semi-adulthood
in your early 20s
you
will be in a cycle where you are hurting other people
you may not know it
hopefully
you find somebody who holds you accountable and tells you and loves you enough through that
but
you are going to take all of that disharmony
in your childhood and you're going to inject that disharmony
into
whether it's your professional relationships or your personal relationships or both until
you get to some form of rock bottom and you start to repair
and i think there's a lot of people that resonate with that because they
have each suffered their own things that
at some point in their lives have told them that they're less than
and
um and then they go and cope and when you cope
eventually
those coping mechanisms escalate
and
at some point it'll be unhealthy either for you but
oftentimes it's for the people around you
well from those humble beginnings you are now a billionaire
how has money changed your life or maybe the landscape of experience in your life
does it buy happiness it
doesn't buy happiness but
it buys you a level of comfort for
you to really amplify what happiness is
i kind of think about it in the following way let's
just say that there's a a hundred things on a table
and the table says find happiness here
and there are different prices
the way that the world works
is that many of these experiences are cordoned off a little bit behind the velvet rope
where
you think that there's more happiness as the prices of things escalate right
if you live in an apartment you admire the person with the house
if you live in a house you admire the person with the bigger house
that person admires the person with you know
um an island right
um
some person drives their car admires
the person who flies who admires
a person who flies business class who admires
a person who flies first
you know to private there's all of these escalations on this table
and most people get to the first five or six
and so they just naturally assume that items you know seven through a hundred is
really where happiness is found
and
the just to you know tell
you the the finish line i've
tried a hundred and back and then i've tried to 400
to it
and happiness isn't there
um but it does give you a level of comfort i read a study
and i don't know if it's true or not but it said that
um the absolute sort of like maximal link between money and happiness
is around 50 million dollars
and
there was a it was just like a social studies
kind of thing that
i think one of the ivy leagues put out and
underneath it the way that they explained
it was because you could have a home you could have all
kinds of the creature comforts you could take care of your family
um and then you were left to ponder
what it is that you really want
i think the challenge for most people is to realize that
this escalating arms race of you know more things will solve your problems
is not true
more and better is not the solution it's it's this idea that you
are on a very precise journey that's unique to yourself you are playing a game
of which only you are the player
everybody else is an interloper
and you have a responsibility to design the gameplay
and
i think a lot of people don't realize
that because
if they did i think they would make a
lot of different
decisions
about how they live their life
and i still do the same thing i mean revert
to basically running around asking other people what
will make you like me more
you
know what will make me
more popular in your eyes and i try to do it and
it never works
um it is just a complete dead end is there negative aspects to money like
for example it
becoming harder to find people you can trust
i think the most negative aspect is that it amplifies
a 360 degree view of your personality
because there are a lot of people and society tells you that
more money is
actually better you are a better person somehow
and you're factually more worthwhile than some other people that have less money
that's also a lie but
when you're given that kind of attention it's
very easy for you to become a caricature of yourself
um that's probably the single worst thing that happens to you but
i say it in the opposite way i think all i've ever seen in
silicon
valley as an example
um is
that when
somebody gets a hold of a lot of money it
tends to cause them to become exactly who they were meant to be
they're either a kind person they're either a curious person they're
either a jerk you know they're either cheap and
they can use all kinds of masks
but now that there's no expectations
and society
gives you a get out of jail free card you
start to behave the way that's most comfortable to you so you see somebody's innate personality
and
that's a really interesting thing to observe because then you can very quickly bucket sort where
do you want to spend time and who is really you know additive to your gameplay
and who is really a negative detractor to your gameplay you're
an investor but you're also kind of a philosopher
um you analyze the world in
all these different
perspectives on all in podcasts on twitter everywhere
do you worry that money makes puts you out of touch from
being able to truly empathize with the experience of the general population
which
in
part first
of all on a human level that could be limiting but also as an analyst of
human civilization that could be limiting
i think it definitely can for
a lot of people because
it's just a it's an abstraction
for you to stop caring
right
um i also think the other thing is that you can very quickly
um especially in today's world become
the scapegoat
just to use a girardian
like rene gerard if you look if you think about like memetic
theory in a nutshell
you know we're all competing
for these very scarce resources that we are told is worthwhile and
if you view the world through that gerardian lens
what are we really doing we are all fighting for scarce resources whether
that's twitter followers money
acclaim notoriety and we all compete with each other and in that competition
you know gerard writes like the only way you escape that loop is
by scapegoating something or somebody
and i think we are in that loop right now where
just the fact of being successful
is
a thing that one should scapegoat
to
end all of this you know tension
that we have in the world
i
i think that it's a little misguided
because i don't think it solves the fundamental
problem
um and we can talk about the solution to some of these problems are but
um that's i think the loop that we're all living and
so if you become a character caricature
and you feed yourself into it
i mean you're not doing anything to to really advance things
your nickname is the dictator how did you get the nickname since
we're talking about the corrupting nature of money that
came from poker in
a poker game you know when you sit down it's chaos especially
like in in our home game there's
a ton of big egos there's people always watching you know rail birding the game all
kinds of interesting folks
and in that somebody needs to establish hygiene and rules and
i really care about the integrity of the game and
it would just require somebody to just say okay enough
and so and then people were just like okay stop dictating and
that's where that's where that nickname so
who to you speaking of which is the greatest poker of
player of all time and why is it phil hellmuth
exactly
you know mute probably knew this question was coming yeah
here's what i'll say i think helmuth is
the
antidote to computers more than any other player playing today
and when you see him
in a heads up situation so i think like he's played nine
or ten heads up tournaments
in a row
and he's played like basically call it 10 of the top 20 people so far
and he's beaten all but one of them
when you're playing heads up you know 1v1 that is the most
um gto
understandable
spot meaning game theory optimal position that's
where computers can give you an enormous edge the
minute you add even a third player the
value of computers and the value of their recommendations
basically falls off a cliff okay so
one way to think about it is helm youth is forced to play against people that
are essentially trained like ais
and so to be able to beat you
know eight out of nine of them means that you are playing so orthogonally
to
what is considered game theory optimal and your overlaying human reasoning
the
judgment to say well in
this spot i should do x but i'm going to do y it's
not dissimilar
in chess like what makes you know magnus carlson so good you
know sometimes he takes these weird lines he'll sacrifice positions
you know he'll overplay certain positions for certain you know bishops
versus knights and all these spots that are very confusing
and
what it does is it throws
people off their game i
think he just won a recent
online tournament
and it's like by move
six
there is no gto
move
for his opponent to make because it's like out of the rule book maybe
he read some game you
know i read the quote it was like he probably read some game in
some bar in russia in 1954
memorized
it and
all of a sudden by six moves in the
computer ai is worthless so
that's what makes helmuth great
the there is one person that i think is superior
um and i think it's what daniel also
said and i would echo that because i played phil as
well but phil ivey is
um the most well-rounded
cold-blooded bloodthirsty animal
he is he's
just and
he he sees
into your solex in a way where you're just like oh
my god stop
looking at me
have you ever played him yeah yeah we played we've played and you know he crushes
the games crushes
the games so what what is feeling crushed
mean
and feel like in poker is it like that
you just can't read at all you being constantly pressured
you
feel off balance you
try to bluff and the
person reads you perfectly that kind of stuff it's
it's a this is a really really excellent
question because i think this has parallels
to a bunch of other things
okay let's just use poker as a microcosm
to explain a bunch of other systems
or games
maybe it's
um running a company
or
investing okay so let's use those three examples but we use poker to explain it what
does success look like well success looks like you have positive expected value
right in poker the simple way to summarize that is
your opponent
let's just say you and i are playing
are going to make a bunch of mistakes there's
a bunch of it that's going to be absolutely perfect
and then there's a few spots where you make mistakes
and then there's a bunch of places in the poker game where i play perfectly
and i make a few mistakes
basically your mistakes minus my mistakes is the edge right
that's that's pure that's how poker works if
i make fewer
mistakes
than
you make i
will make money and i will win that
is the objective
of the game
translate that into business
you're running a company
you
have a team of employees you have a pool of human capital that's capable of being
productive in the world and creating something
but you are going to make mistakes
in making that
maybe it doesn't completely fit the market maybe it's mispriced maybe
it actually doesn't require all of the people that you need so the margins are wrong
and then there's the competitive set of all the other alternatives that
customer has
their mistakes minus your mistakes is the expected value of google facebook apple
etc okay now take investing
every time you buy something somebody else on the other side is selling it to you
is that their mistake we don't know yet but their mistakes minus your mistakes
is how you make a lot of money over long periods of time as an investor
somebody sold you google at forty dollars a share you bought it and you kept it
huge mistake on their part minimal mistakes on your part
the difference of that is the money that you made
so life can be summarized in many ways in that way so the question is
what can you do about other people's mistakes and the answer is nothing
that is somebody else's game you can try to influence them you could try to subvert
them maybe you plant a spy inside of that other person's company to sabotage
them i guess there are things at the edges that you can do
but my firm belief is that life success really boils down to how do you control
your mistakes
now this is a bit counterintuitive
the way you control your mistakes is by making a lot of mistakes
so taking risks you
have to is somehow you
have to you to
minimize the number of mistakes let's just say you want to find love yeah
you know you want to find something go on deeply connected with yeah
are you do you do that by not going out on dates and yes
sorry sorry the
only person that thinks that's yesterday no
i'm joking
i'm joking no but you know what i mean like
you have to date people you have to open yourself up you have to be authentic
and like you
put you you give yourself a chance to get hurt yes
but
you're a good person so
you know what happens when you get hurt that
is actually their mistake
okay and if you are inauthentic that's your mistake
that's
a controllable thing in you you can tell them the truth who
you are and
say here's
my pluses
and minuses my point is there are very few things in life
that you can't break down i think into that very simple idea
and
in terms of your mistakes society
tells you don't make them because
we will judge you and we will look down on you
and i think the really successful people realize that actually no
it's the cycle time of mistakes that gets you to success
because your error rate will diminish the more mistakes that you make you
observe them you
figure out where it's coming from is it a psychological
thing is it a you
know cognitive
thing and
then you fix it so
the implied thing there is that there's a
in in business and investing in poker and dating in life is
that there's this platonic gto
game theory optimal thing out there and so when you say mistakes you're
always comparing to that optimal path you could have taken i think
slightly different i would say mistake
is maybe a bad proxy but it's the best proxy i have for learning
but i'm using the language of what society tells you sure
got it society
tells you that when you try something and it doesn't work it's a mistake
so
i just use that word because it's the word that resonates
most with most people got
it
the
real thing that it is is learning
yeah
it's like in neural networks it's lost the neural network is lost exactly
yeah all right so you're using the mistake that is most
the the word that is the most understandable
especially
by the way people experience it i guess most of life is
a sequence of mistakes the
problem is when you use the word mistake and you think about mistakes
it
actually has the
counterproductive effect of you becoming conservative in just being risk-averse
so
that if
you folk if you re if you flip it and say try to maximize
the number of successes
somehow
that leads you to take more risk
um mistake scares people i think mistakes scare people because society likes
these very simplified boundaries of who is winning and who is losing
and they want to reward
people who make traditional choices
and succeed but the thing is what's so
corrosive about that
is that they're actually not even being put in a position to
actually make a quote-unquote mistake and fail so i'll give you if
you look at like getting into an elite school
right society rewards you for being in the ivy leagues
in a way that you know in my opinion incorrectly doesn't
reward you for being in a non-ivy league school
there's a certain level of status and
presumption of intellect and capability that comes with being there
um but that system doesn't
really have a counterfactual because it's not as if you both go to mit and
ohio state
and then we can see two versions of lex friedman
so that we can figure out that the jig is up and there was no difference
right
and so instead it reinforces
this idea that there is no truth-seeking
function there is no way to actually make this thing whole
and
so it tells you you
have to get in here and
if you don't your life is over you've
made a huge mistake you
know or you've failed completely
and so you have to find different unique ways of dismantling this this is why you
know part of what i realized
where i got very lucky is
i had no friends in high school i had a few cohort of acquaintances
but part of being so hyper vigilant when i grew up was
i was so ashamed
of that world that i had to live in i
didn't want to bring anyone into it i
could not see myself that anybody would accept me
but the thing with that is that i had no definition of
what expectations should be so
they were not guided by the people around me
and so i would escape to define my expectations it's interesting but you didn't feel
um like your dad didn't put you in a prison of expectation
or
we because like that's if
you know a friend like
that so the flip side of that you don't have any other signals
it's
very easy to believe like when you're in a cult that
well
he you know
he was angry he
pushed me
he used me as a mechanism to alleviate his own frustration and
this may sound very crazy but he also believed in me
and so that's what created this weird duality where you were just i was always confused
that you
could be somebody great he
believed that you could be he did him
because i couldn't reconcile then the other half of the day you know those behaviors
but what it allowed me to do was i escaped
in my mind and i found these archetypes around me
that were saviors to me
so you know i grew up in ottawa ontario canada i
grew up right
at the point where the telecom boom was happening companies like nortel
and newbridge networks and mitel bell
northern research these
were all built in in the suburbs of ottawa
and so there were these larger than life figures entrepreneurs terry matthews michael copeland
and so i thought i'm going to be like them i
would read forbes magazine i would read fortune
magazine
i would look at the rich people
on
that list and say i would be like them
not knowing
that maybe that's not who you wanted it to be
but it was a lifeline and it kept my mind relatively whole
because i could direct my ambition in a direction
and so why that's so important just circling back to this is i
didn't have a group of friends who were like i'm going to go to community college
you
know i didn't have a group of friends that said well you
know the goal is just to go
to university get
a simple job and like you know join
the public service have
a good life
and so because i had no expectations
and i was so afraid to venture out of my own house i
never saw what middle class life was like and
so i never aspired
to it now if i was close to it i probably would have aspired
to it because i
my parents in their best year made 32 000 canadian together
and
if you're trying to raise a family of five people on thirty two thousand dollars it's
a complicated
job
and
most of the time they were probably making 20 something thousand
and i was working since i was 14.
so i
knew that our station in life was not the destination we
had to get out
um
but
because i didn't have an obvious place it's not like i had a best friend whose
house i was going to and
i
saw some normal functional
home
if i had had that in this weird way i would have aspired to that
what
was the worst job you had to do the
best job
but the worst job was
i worked at burger king when
i was 14 years old and i would do the closing shift and
that was from like 6 p.m till about two in the morning and
in ontario where i lived
ottawa borders quebec in ontario the drinking age is 19 you
can see where i'm going with this
the drinking age in quebec is 18 and
that year made all the difference to all these kids and
so they would go get completely drunk they would come back they
would come to the burger king you
know you
would
see
all
these
kids
you
went
to
high
school
with
can
you
imagine
how
mortifying
it is you know you're working there in this get up
and they would light that place on fire vomit everywhere puking pooing peeing
and
when the thing shuts down at one o'clock you know
you
got to clean that all up
all of it changing
the garbage taking it out it was
um a grind
and it really teaches you okay i do not want this job
i
don't want to but it's funny that that didn't push you towards the stability
and the security of the middle class
like
i
didn't have any good examples of that
i didn't have those around me i was so ashamed
i could have never built a relationship where i could have seen those interactions
to want that
and
so my desires
were framed
by these
two random
rich people that
lived in my town who i'd never met
and what i read in magazines about people like bill gates and warren buffett
you were an early senior executive at facebook
during a period of a lot of scaling
in the company history i
mean it's
actually a fascinating period of human history in terms of technology
well
in terms of human civilization honestly
what did you learn from that
time
about what it takes to build and scale a successful tech company a
company that
has
almost
immeasurable impact on the world
that was an incredible moment in time because everything was so new
to your point like even how the standards of web 2.0 at that time were
being defined we were defining them you know i
mean i think if you if you look in sort
of the if
you search in the patents
um
patent
library there's a bunch of these patents that like me and zuck have for like random
things like cookies you
know or like cross-site javascript like all these crazy things that are just like these duh
kind of ideas in 2023
we
had to invent our way around how
do websites communicate with each other you
know how
do we build in the cloud versus in a data center how do we actually have
high performance
systems
you
mentioned data science the
term and yeah we
invented this i invented
this thing called data
scientist because we had a phd from google that refused to join unless
because
he got a job offer that says data analyst yeah
um and so we said column
of scientist
because he was a phd
in particle
physics
so he
really
you
know he
was a scientist
and i said great you're a
scientist
here
and
that
launched
a discipline
that
launched it just made a term you
know what's
a
rose by any other name but yeah like you
know sometimes
words
like this can launch entire
fields
and
it did in that case and you didn't i
mean i guess at that time you didn't anticipate
the
impact of machine learning on the entirety
of this whole process because you need machine learning to
have both ads and recommender
systems
to have the feed for the social network exactly
right the first real scaled version of machine learning not ai but machine learning was
this thing that facebook introduced called pymk
which is people you may know and
the simple idea was that can we initiate a viral mechanic inside the application
where you log in we grab your credentials we go to your email inbox
we harvest your address book
we do a compare we
make some guesses
and
we start to present other people that you may actually know
that may not be in your address book really
simple you know a couple joins of some tables whatever
and
it started to just go crazy and the number of people that
you
were you were creating this density
and entropy
inside this social graph with what was some really simple basic math
and that was eye-opening for us and
what it what it led us down this path of is really understanding
the power of like all this machine learning and
so that infused itself into news feed you
know and how the
content that you saw could be tailored
to who you were and the type of person that you were so
there was a moment in time that
all of this stuff was so new
um how did you translate the app to multiple
languages how do you launch the company in all of these countries
how much of it is
just kind of stumbling into things using your best like first principles gut thinking
and how much is it like 5 10 15 20 year vision like
how much was thinking about the future
of the internet and
the metaverse and
the humanity and all that kind of stuff like because the news feed sounds
trivial i'll say something but that's like changes everything well
you have to remember like you know news feed
was named and we had this thing where we would just name things what they were
and at the time all
of these other companies
and if you go back into the wayback machine you can see this people
would vent would invent you know an
i you know an mp3 player and they would come up with some crazy name or
they would invent a software product and come up with a crazy name right
and it sounded like the pharma industry you
know
blockazimab
you
know tag your best friends yeah
and you think what is this this makes no sense and
you know this was zuck's
thing he was like well
this is a feat of news so we're going to call it news feed
this is where you tag your photos so we're going to call that photo tagging
i
mean literally you know pretty obvious stuff
um so
the thing the way that those things came about though was very experimentally
and this is where i think it's really important for people
to understand i think bezos explains this the best
there is a tendency after things work
to create a narrative fallacy because it feeds your ego and
you want to have been the person that saw it coming
and i think it's much more honest to say we were very good probabilistic thinkers
that
tried to learn as quickly as possible meaning to make as many mistakes as possible you
know i mean if you look at this very famous placard
that facebook had from back in the day what did it say it said move
fast and break things
in
societal language that's
saying make mistakes as quickly as you can
because
the minute you break something that's
you don't do that by design it's
not a feature theoretically
it's a bug
but he understood that and we embraced that idea
um i used to run this meeting once
a week where the whole goal
was i want to see that there was a thousand experiments
that were run and
show me them all from the dumbest to the most impactful
and
we would go through that loop
and what did it train people not
that you got celebrated
for
the right answer
but you got celebrated for trying
i ran 12 experiments
12 failed and we'd be like you're the best
can
i just take a small tangent on that is to move fast and break things
has
become as like a catchphrase
of the thing that embodies the toxic culture of silicon valley in today's
discourse which
confuses me of
course words and phrases get sort
of captured
and so on becomes
very reductive
you know that's a very loaded
set of words that together can be
many
years later people can view very reductive can you still man each side of that so
yeah
pro
move fast and break things yeah and against yeah
um so i think the pro have moved fast and break things is saying the following
there's a space of things we know and a massive space of things we don't know
and there's a rate of growth of the things we know
but
the rate of growth
of the things we don't know is actually we
have to assume
growing
faster
so the most important
thing is
to move into the space of the things we don't know as
quickly as possible
and so in order to acquire knowledge we're going to assume
that the failure mode is the nominal state
and
so we just need to move as quickly as we can break
as many things as possible which means like things are breaking in code
do
the you know root cause analysis
figure out how to make things better and then rapidly move into the space and
he or she who moves fastest into that space will win it
doesn't imply carelessness
right it doesn't imply
moving fast without also
aggressively
picking up the lessons from the mistakes you make well again let's
let's steel
manning the pro which is it's a thoughtful
um movement around velocity and acquisition of knowledge now let's deal man the con case
when these systems become big enough
there is no more room
to experiment in an open-ended way because
the implications have broad societal impacts that
are not clear up front
so let's take a different less controversial example if we said you know lipitor
um worked well for all people except south asians
and there's a specific immuno response that we can iterate to
and if we move quickly enough we can run 10
000 experiments
and we think the answer is in that space
well the problem is that those 10 000 experiments may kill 10 million people
so you have to move methodically when that drug was experimental
and it wasn't being given to 500 million people in the world
moving
fast made sense because you could have a pig model a mouse model a
monkey model you
could figure out toxicity
but we picked all that low hanging fruit
and so now these small iterations
have huge impacts that need to be measured and implemented
different example is like you know if you work at boeing
and you have an implementation that gives you a two percent efficiency by
reshaping the wing or adding winglets
there needs to be a methodical move slow be right process
because mistakes when they compound when it's already implemented and at scale have huge externalities that
are impossible to measure until after the fact and you see this in the 737 max
so that's how one would steel man the
the con case which is that when an industry becomes critical you
got to slow down
this makes me sad because
some industries like twitter and facebook are a good example
they achieve scale very quickly before really exploring the big area
of
things to learn so you basically pick
one low-hanging fruit and
that became your huge success and now you're sitting there with that stupid fruit well
so you're you're i think so as an example like you know if you had to
you know if if i was running facebook for a day
you know the big opportunity in my opinion was really not the metaverse
but it was actually getting the closest that anybody could get to agi
and
if i had to steal man that product case here's
what how i would have pitched it to the board into zuck
i would have said listen there
are three and a half billion
people monthly using
this thing if
we think about human intelligence very reductively
we would say that there's a large portion of it which is cognitive
and then there's a large portion of it which is emotional
we have the best ability to build a multimodal model
that basically takes all of these massive inputs together to
try to intuit how a system would react to all kinds of stimuli
that
to me would have been a profound leap
forward for humanity can you dig into that a little bit more so in
terms of
now this is a board meeting how would that make facebook money
i think that you have all of these
systems over time that
that we don't know could benefit from
um some layer of reasoning to make it better
um what does spotify look like when
instead of just a very simple recommendation
engine it
actually understands sort of your emotional context and your mood and
can move you to a body of music that you would like what
does it look like if you know your television instead
of having to go and channel surf you know 50
000 shows on a horrible ui you know instead
just has a sense of what you're into and shows it to you
um what does it mean when you get in your car and
it
actually drives
you to a place because you should actually eat there even though you don't know it
these are all random things that make no sense a priority
but it starts to make the person or the provider of that service
the critical reasoning layer for
all these everyday products that today would look very flat without that reasoning
and
i think you license
that
and you make a lot of money so in many ways
instead
of becoming
more
of the pixels that you see you've
become more of the bare metal that
actually creates that experience and if you and if you look at the companies
that are multi-decade legacy kinds of businesses
the thing that they have done is quietly and surreptitiously
move down the stack you
never move up the stack to survive you
need to move down the stack so if you take that osi reference stack right these
layers of how you build an app from the physical layer
to the transport layer all the way up to the app layer
you can map from
the 1980s all the big companies that have been created right
all the way from fairchild semiconductor and nat semi to intel to cisco to three com
you know oracle
netscape
at one point all the way up to the googles and facebooks of the world
but if you look at where all the locking happened
it's
by companies like apple who
used to make software saying
i'm
going to get one close i'm going to make the bare metal and
i'm going to become the platform or
google same
thing i'm going to create this dominant platform and i'm going to create a substrate
that organizes
all this information that's
just omnipresent
and everywhere
so the key is if you are lucky enough to be one of these apps
that are in front of people
you better start digging quickly and
moving your way down and get out of the way and disappear but
by disappearing you will become much much bigger
and it's impossible to usurp you yeah i 100 agree with you
um that's why you're so smart this is the depersonalization and
the algorithms that enable deep personalization almost like a operating system layer
so pushing away from the interface and the actual system that does the personalization i
think the challenge is there there's obviously technical challenges
but there's also societal challenges that
it's
like in a relationship if
you have an intimate algorithmic connection with individual humans you
can do both good and bad and so there's risks that you're taking you can so
if you're making a lot of money now is twitter and facebook with
ads surface layer ads
what is the incentive to take the risk
of guiding people more
because you can hurt people you can piss off people you can
um i mean there's a cost to forming a more intimate relationship with the users
in the short term i think you said a really really key thing which is
um which was a really great
emotional
instinctive
reaction which is when
i said the agi
thing you said well how would you ever make money from that
that
is the key the
presumption
is that this thing would not be an important thing at the beginning and
i think what that allows you to do if you were twitter
or google or apple or facebook anybody
microsoft
embarking
on building something like this is that you can actually have it off the critical path
and you can experiment with this for years if that's what it takes to
find a version one that is special enough where it's worth showcasing
and
so in many ways you get the free option you're
going to be spending
any of these companies
will
be spending tens of billions of dollars in opex
and capex
every year and all kinds of stuff
it is not a thing that money
um actually makes more likely to succeed in fact
you actually don't need to give these kinds of things a
lot of money at all because
starting
in 2023 or right now
you know you have the two most important tectonic
shifts that have ever happened in our lifetime in technology they're
not talked about but these things allow agi
i think to emerge
over the next 10 or 15 years where it wasn't possible
for the
first thing is that the marginal cost of energy is zero
not gonna pay for anything anymore
right
and we can double click into
why
that why
that
is and the second is
the marginal
cost of
compute
to zero
and so when you when you take the
multiplication
or you know if you want to get really fancy mathematically
the convolution of these two things together it's
going to change everything
so
think about
what a billion dollars gets today when we can use open ai as an example
a billion dollars gets open ai a handful of functional models and
a pretty fast iterative loop
right
but imagine what
um openai had to overcome
that to overcome a compute challenge they
had to strip together a whole bunch of gpus that
to build all kinds of scaffolding
software they
had to find data center support that
consumes
all kinds of money so that billion
dollars didn't go that far so
it's a testament to how clever
that openai team is
but in four years from now when energy costs zero and basically gpus
like you know they're falling off a truck and
and you can use them for effectively for free
now all of a sudden a billion dollars gives you some amount of teraflops
of compute that is probably
the total number of teraflops available today in the world like that's how gargantuan
this
move is when you take these two variables to zero there's
like a million things to ask i almost don't want to get distracted by the
marginal
cost of energy going
to zero because i
have
no idea what you're talking about that is fascinating
can i give you the 30 seconds sure okay yes okay
so
if you look inside of the two most progressive
states the
three most progressive
states new
york california
and massachusetts a
lot of left-leaning folks a lot of people who believe in climate science and climate change
the
energy costs in those three states are the worst they are in the entire country and
energy is compounding at
three to four percent per annum so every decade to 15 years energy
costs in these states double in
some cases and in some months our energy costs are increasing by 11 a month
but the
ability to actually generate
energy is
now effectively zero the
cost per kilowatt
hour to
put a solar
panel on your roof and a battery wall inside your garage it's
the cheapest it's ever been these
things are the most efficient they they've ever been and
so to acquire energy from the sun and
store it for your use later on literally
is a zero cost proposition
so what's how do you explain the gap between the cost going great question
so
this is the other side of regulatory
capture right you know we all fight to build monopolies
while there are monopolies hiding in plain sight the
utilities are a perfect example there
are a hundred million homes in america there
are about 1700
utilities in america so they have captive markets
but in return for that captive market the law says need
to invest a certain amount per year in
upgrading that power line in
changing out that turbine in making sure you transition from coal
to wind or whatever
just as an example
upgrading
power lines in the united states over the next decade is a two trillion dollar proposition
these 1700 organizations have to spend i
think it's a quarter of a trillion dollars a year
just to change the power lines that
is why even though it costs nothing to make energy you
are paying double every five every seven or eight years
it's capex and opex of a very brittle old infrastructure
it's like you
trying
to build an app and
being forced
to build your own data
center and you say but wait i just want to write to aws
i
just want to use gcp i just want to move on
all
that complexity solved for me and
some law says no you can't you got to use it so that's
what consumers
are dealing with but it's also what industrial
and manufacturing
organizations
it's
what we all deal with so how do we get rid ourselves off this old infrastructure
that we're paying so
the thing that's happening today which i think is
this is why i think it's the most important trend right now in the world is
that a hundred million homeowners
are each going to become their own little power plant and compete with these 1700 utilities
just
just deal with the united states for a second because i think it's easier
to see here
100 million homes solar
panel on the roof and by the way just
to make it clear the sun doesn't need to shine right these these
panels now work where you have these uv bands that can actually extrapolate
beyond the visible spectrum so they're usable in all weather conditions
and a simple system can support you
collecting enough power to not just run your functional day-to-day life
but then to contribute what's left over back into the grid
for google's data center or facebook's data center where you get a small check
the cost is going to zero how obvious is this to people you're making yourself okay
so
because this is a pretty profound prediction if the cost is indeed go to zero
that i mean the compute the cost of compute going to zero i can so
the cost to compute going to zero is can kind of understand but
the energy seems
like a radical prediction
of
yours well
it's just it's just naturally what's happening
right
now now let me let me give you a different
way of explaining
this
if you look at
any system there's a really important thing that happens it's what clay
christensen
calls
crossing the chasm if you explained
it numerically
here's how i would explain it to you lex if
you introduce a disruptive product typically
what happens is the first three to five percent of people are these zealous believers
and they ignore
all the logical reasons why this product doesn't make any sense
because they believe in the proposition of the future and they buy it
the problem is at five percent if you want a product to
get to mass market you
have one of two choices which is you either bring the cost down low enough or
the feature set becomes so compelling that even at a high price point an
example of the latter is the iphone
the
iphone today the 14 iphone cost
more than the original iphone it's probably doubled
in price over the last 14 or 15 years but
we view it as an essential element of what we need in our daily lives
it turns out that battery evs and solar panels are an example of the former
because people like president biden with all of these subsidies
have now introduced so much money for people to
just do this where it is a money making proposition for a hundred million homes
and what you're seeing as a result are all of these companies
who want to get in front of that trend why
because they want to own the relationship with 100 million
homeowners
they want to manage the power infrastructure
amazon home
depot lowe's
you
know you just name the company
so if you do that and you control that relationship
they're
going to show you they're going you know for example amazon will
probably say if
you're a member of prime
we'll stick the panels on your house for free
we'll do all the work for you for free
and it's just a feature of being a member of prime and
we'll manage all that energy for you it makes so much sense and it is mathematically
accretive
for amazon to do that it's not a creative
for the existing energy industry because they get blown up
it's extremely accretive for peace and prosperity
if you think the number of wars we fight over natural resources
take them all off the table if we don't need energy from abroad
there's no reason to fight you know this you'd have to find a reason to fight
um meaning sorry there'd be a moral reason to fight but
the last number of wars that we fought
were not as much rooted in morality as they were rooted in yeah
it feels like they're very much rooted in
conflicts
over
resources
energy specifically
and then sorry just the last thing i want to say i keep interviewing apologies
but the
chips
all
what what people want
to say is that you know now that we're at two and three nanometer
scale for
typical kind of like transistor fab
we're done and
you know forget about transistor
density forget about moore's lots over and i would just say no look
at teraflops
and really teraflops
is the
combination of cpus but
much much less important and
really is the combination of asics so application
specific ics
and
gpus
and so you put the two together i
mean if i gave you a billion dollars five years from now
the amount of damage you could do damaged in good way in
terms of you know building racks and racks of gpus the
kind of models that you could build the training
sets and the data that you could consume
to solve a problem
it's
it's enough to to do something really powerful whereas today it's not yet quite enough
so there's this really interesting idea that you talk about in terms
of facebook and twitter that's
connected to this that if you were running sort of twitter
or facebook that you would move them all to like aws
so you would
have somebody else to come the compute the infrastructure it
probably if you could explain that reasoning
means
that
you believe in this idea of energy going to zero compute going to zero so let
people that are optimizing
that
do the best job and
i think that's a you know the
initially in the early 2000s and the beginning of the 2010s
if you were a big enough scale
oh sorry everybody was building their own stuff then between 2010 through 2020
really the idea was everybody should be on aws except the biggest of the biggest folks
i think in the 2020s
and 30s i think the answer is actually everybody should be in these public clouds and
the reason is the engineering velocity of the guts
so
you know take a simple example
which is you know we have not seen a massive iteration in database design until
snowflake
right i think maybe postgres was like the last big turn of the dial
why is that i don't exactly know except
that everybody that's on aws and everybody that's on gcp in azure gets
to now benefit from
a hundred plus billion dollars of aggregate market cap rapidly iterating
making mistakes
fixing solving learning and that is a best-in-class industry now right
then
there's going to be all these ai layers around analytics so
that app companies can make better decisions
all of these things will allow you to build more nimble organizations because
you'll have this federated model of development
i'll take these things off the shelf maybe i'll roll my own stitching over here
because the thing that where you make money is
still for most people and how the apps provision and experience to
a user and
everybody else can make a lot of money just servicing that so
they work in a really
um they play well together in the sandbox so in the future everybody
just should be there it doesn't make sense for anybody i don't think because you
know if
you were to rule
your own data
centers
you
know for example
like google
for
a long time had
these massive leaps where they had gfs
and bigtable
those are really good in the 2000s and 2010s
and this is not just throw shade at google it's
very hard for whatever exists
that is a that
is the progeny
of gfs and bigtable
to be anywhere near as good as a hundred billion dollar industries
attempt
to build that stack
and you're putting your organization under enormous pressure to be that good
i guess the implied risk taken there is that you could become the next aws
like
um tesla doing some of the compute in-house
i guess the bet there is that you can become the next the
next aws for the
new wave of computation if that level if
that kind of computation is different so if it's machine learning
i don't know if anyone's won that battle yet which is machine learning centric well software
has a very powerful property in
that there's a lot of things that can happen asynchronous asynchronously
so that real-time inference can be actually really lightweight code deployment and
that's why i think you can have a very federated ecosystem inside
of inside of all of these places tesla
is very different because in
order to build the best car it's
kind of like trying to build the best iphone which
is that you need to control it
all the way down to the bare
metal in
order to do it well
and
that's just not possible if
you're trying to be a systems integrator which is what everybody other
than this modern generation of car companies
have been and they've done a very good job of that
but
it won't be the experience that allows you to win in in the next 20 years
so let's linger on the social media thing so
if you you said if you ran facebook for a day let's let's let's extend
that if
you were to build a new social network today
how would you fix
twitter how would you fix social media
if you want to answer a different question is if you were elon
musk
somebody
you know and you were taking over twitter what
would you fix i
thought about this a little bit
um
first
of all let me give you a backdrop
i wouldn't actually build a social media
company at
all
and the answer is the reasoning
is the following
um i
really tend to believe as you've probably gotten a sense of sort of patterns and probabilities
and if you said to meth
probabilistically
answer where where are we going in
apps and social experiences what i would say is lex
we spent the first decade building platforms and getting them to scale
and if you want to think about it again back to sort of this poker analogy
others mistakes minus your mistakes is the value
well the value that was captured was trillions of dollars essentially to apple and to google
and they did that by basically
um attracting billions of monthly active users to their platform
then this next way were the apps
facebook qq10 tick tock twitter snapchat that whole panoply of apps
and interestingly they were in many ways an atomized version of the platforms
right they sat on top of them they were an ecosystem participant
but the value they created was the same trillions of dollars of enterprise value
billions of monthly active users
well there's an interesting phenomenon that's kind of hiding in plain sight
which is that the
next most obvious atomic unit
are content creators now let me give you two examples lex friedman this random crazy guy
mr beast you know jimmy donaldson just the two of you alone added
add it up okay and
you guys are going to approach in the next five years a
billion people the
only thing that you guys haven't figured
out yet is how to capture trillions
of dollars of value now
maybe you don't want to and
maybe that's
not your state admission
right
right but
let's just look at mr beast alone because he is trying to do exactly
that probably yeah
and i think jimmy is going to build an
enormous business but
if you take jimmy and all of the other content creators right
you guys are atomizing
what the apps have done
you're providing your own curated news feeds you're providing your own curated communities you're
allowed
you let people move
in and out of these things in a very lightweight
way and
value is accruing to you so the
honest answer to your question is i would focus on the content creator
side of things because i believe that's where the puck is going that's
a much more important
shift
in how we all consume information content
and are entertained
it's
through brands like you individual
people that we can humanize and understand are
the filter
but
aren't you just arguing
against the point you made earlier
which
is what you would recommend
is the invest in the agi
the
the depersonalization
because because they they could
still be a participant in that in that end state if that happens you
have the option value of being an enabler of that
right you
can help improve what they do again you can be this bare metal service provider
where you can be a tax
yeah right you can participate in every thing
that you do every question that's asked every comment that's curated if
you could have more intelligence
as you provide a service to your fans in your audience you
would probably pay a small percentage of that revenue i
suspect all content creators would and so it's that stack of services that
is like a smart human being it's like you know how do you help produce
this information you
would pay a producer for that i mean maybe you would but so
back to your question so what would i do
i think that you have to move into that world
pretty aggressively
um i think that right now you first have to solve what
is broken inside of these social networks
and i don't think it's a technical problem
so just to put it out there i don't think it's a
you know it's one where there are these nefarious organizations that happens brigading xyz that happens
but the real problem is a psychological one that we're dealing with which is people
through a whole set of situations
have lost belief in themselves
and i think that that
comes
up as this very virulent
form of rejection that they tried to put into these social networks
so if you look inside of comments on
anything like
you could have a con like
you could have a person that says on twitter
i saved this dog from a fiery building
and there would be negative commenters
and you're like well again
put yourself in their shoes what
do you how do i steal man their case i do this all the time you
know i get people
throw shade at me i'm like okay let me steal man their point of view
and
the best that i can come up with is you know i'm
working really
hard over here i'm
trying i
played by all the rules that were told to me
i've played well i played fairly and
i am not being rewarded in a system of value that you recognize
and that is making me mad and
now i need to cope and i need to vent
so
back in the day my dad used to drink he
would make me go get things to hit me with
today
you
go to twitter you
spot off you try to deal with
the
latent anger that you feel so
a social network has to be designed in my opinion
to solve that psychological corner case because it is what makes a network unusable
to get real density you
have to find a way of
moving away from that toxicity because it ruins a product experience
you could have the best pixels in the world but if people are virulently spitting
into their keyboards
other
people are just going to say you know what i'm done with this it
doesn't make me feel good
so
the
social network has to have a social cost you
can do it in a couple ways one
is where you have real world identity so then there's a cost to being virulent
and there's a cost to being caustic
a second way is to actually just overlay an economic framework
so that there's a more pertinent economic value that you assign to
basically spouting off
and the more you want to spend the more you can say
and
i think both have
a
lot of value i don't know what the right answer
is i tend to like the
latter
i think real world identity shuts
down a lot of debate because
there's still too much
um you know there's a sensation that there that there'll be some retribution
um so i think there's more free speech over here but it cannot be costless
because in that there's a level of toxicity that just makes these products unusable
what
about a third option and
by the way all of these can work together
if
we look at this what you call the corner case was just hilarious
what i would call the human condition
which is you know that anger is rooted with the challenges of life and
what about having a
um an algorithm that shows you what you see
that's personalized to you and helps you maximize your personal growth in the long term such
that you're
challenging
yourself you're improving you're learning there's just enough of criticism
to
keep you on your toes but
just enough of like the dopamine rush to keep you entertained
and finding that balance for each individual person you
just described an agi of a very empathetic
well-rounded friend yes
exactly and
and then you can throw that person even anonymous into a pool of discord and
they would be better i think you're absolutely right that's
a very very very elegant
way of stating it you're absolutely but like you said the agi
might
be a few years away so
that's a huge investment like my concern my
gut feeling is this age thing we're calling agi
is actually not that difficult to build technically but
it requires a certain culture and it requires a certain certain
risks to be taken i think you could reductively boil down the human intellect
into
cognition and emotion
and you know depending
on who you are and depending on the moment they're weighted very differently obviously
um cognition is so easily done by computers
that we should assume that that's a solved problem
so our differentiation
is the reasoning part it's the emotional
overlay
it's that it's the empathy it's the ability to steal man the opposite person's
case and and
feel why that person
you know you can forgive them without excusing what they did as an example
um that is a very difficult thing i think to capture in software but
i think it's a matter of when not if
if done crudely it
takes a form of censorship just
banning
people off the platform let
me ask you some tricky questions
do you think trump should have been removed from twitter no what's the what's
the pro case can you i'm having fun here you still man each side yeah
um let's deal man to get him off the platform here we have a guy who
um is virulent in all ways he promotes confrontation
he lacks decorum he
incites the fervent believers of his cause
to act up and push the boundaries bordering on and potentially even including breaking the law
he
does not observe
the social norms of
a society that keep us while functioning including
an orderly transition of power
if he is left in a moment where he feels trapped and cornered
he could behave in ways that
will confuse the people that believe in him
to act in ways that they so regret that
um it could bring our democracy to an end or
create so much damage or create a wound that's so deep it
will take years of conflict and years of confrontation
to heal it
we need to remove him and
we need to do it now it's
been too long we've
let it go on too long
the other side of the argument would be he was a duly elected person whose
views have been run over for
way too long
and he uses the ability to say extreme things in order to showcase
how corrupt these systems have become
and how insular these organizations are in protecting their own class
and so if you really want to prevent class warfare
and if you really want to keep the american dream alive for everybody we
need to show that the first amendment the constitution the second amendment all
of this infrastructure is
actually bigger than any partisan view no matter how bad it is and that people
will make their own decisions
and there are a lot of people that can see past the words he uses
and focus on the substance of what he's trying to get across and
more generally agree than disagree and so when you silence that voice
what you're effectively saying is this is a rigged game and
all of those things that we've told we were told were not true are actually true
if you were to look at the crude algorithms of twitter of
course i don't have any insider knowledge but
i could imagine that they saw
the
let's
say there's a metric that measures how
negative the experience is of the platform and they probably saw
in several
ways you could look at this but
the presence of donald trump on the platform was
consistently increasing how shitty people are feeling
short-term and long term because they're probably yelling at each other having
worse
and worse and worse experience if you even do a survey of how
do you feel about using this platform over
the last week they
would say horrible
relative to maybe a year ago when
donald trump was not actively
tweeting or so on so
here you're sitting at twitter and
saying
okay i
i and i know everyone's talking about speech
and all that kind of stuff but i kind of want to build a platform
where the users
are happy
and they're becoming more and more unhappy how do i solve this happiness problem well
let's
ban
let's let's
yeah let's ban the sources of the unhappiness now we can't just say you're
a source of unhappiness so we'll ban you let's wait until that source says something that
we can claim
breaks our rules like insights violence or so on that would work if you could measure
your
construct of happiness properly the problem is i think what twitter looked at were active commenters
and got it confused for overall system happiness
because
for every piece of content that's created on the internet of
the hundred people that consume it maybe one or two people comment on it and
so by over amplifying
that signal and
assuming that it was the plurality of people that's
where they actually made a huge blunder because
there was no scientific method i think to get to the answer of de-platforming
him and
it did expose
this idea that it's a bit of a rigged game and
that there are these deep biases
that
some of these organizations have to
opinions that are counter to theirs and to their orthodox view of the world
so in general you lean towards keeping
um first of all presidents on the platform but also
controversial
voices all
the time i
think it's really important to keep them there let
me ask you a trick tricky
one in the recent news that's
become especially
relevant
for me what
do you think about if you've been paying attention to yay kanye west
a recent controversial outburst on social media
about
and jews
black people
racism in general
slavery holocaust all these topics that
he touched on in different ways on different platforms but including
twitter what
do you do with that and
like what do you do what do you do with that from a platform perspective what
do you do from a humanity
perspective
of
how to add love to the world
let's
um should we take both sides of them sure option one is he is
completely out of line and option two is he's not just the same sure right so
the
path one
is
he is an incredibly
important taste maker in the world that defines the belief system for a lot of people
and there just is no room
for
any form of racism
or bias or anti-semitism in
today's day and age particularly by people
whose
words and comments will be amplified around the world
we've already paid a large price for that and then the expectation
of success is some amount of societal decorum that keeps moving the ball forward
the other side would say
life i think goes from harmony to disharmony to repair
and anybody who has gone through a very complicated divorce
will tell you that in that moment your life is extremely disharmonious
and you are struggling to cope and because he is famous
we are seeing
a person really struggling in a moment
that may need help
and we owe it to him not for what he said because that stuff isn't excusable
but we owe it to him to help him in a way and particularly his friends
and if he has real friends
hopefully what they see is that what i see on the outside looking in
is a person that is clearly struggling
can i ask you like a human question and i know it's outside looking in but
there's several questions i want to ask
so
one is about the pain of going through a
divorce and having kids and all that kind of stuff and
two when you're rich and powerful and
famous i don't know maybe you can enlighten me into which is the most corruptive
um but how do you know who are the friends to trust
so
a lot of the world is calling kanye insane
and if orlick has mental illness all that kind of stuff and
so how do you have friends close to you let's
say
let's say something like that message but from a place of
love and
where they actually care for you as opposed to trying to get you to shut up
the reason i ask all those questions i think
if you care about the guy how do you help him right
i've been through a divorce it's gut wrenching
the most horrible part is having to tell your kids
i can't even describe it to you
um how proud i am and how resilient these three beautiful little creatures were when my
ex-wife and i had to sit them down and talk through it
um and for that thing i'll be just so protective of them and so proud
of them and
um it's hard now i don't know that that's what he went through
um but it doesn't matter in
that moment there's no fame there's no money there's nothing there's just the raw intimacy
of a nuclear
family
breaking up in that there is a death and it's the death of that idea
and that is extremely extremely
profound in its impact especially in your children
um it is really hard really
hard could you have seen yourself in the way you see the world being
clouded during
especially
at first to where you would make poor decisions outside
of your outside of that nuclear family so like business poor business decisions poor
tweeting
decisions poor
i think that writing decision if i had to boil down
a lot of those what
i would say is that there
are moments in my life flex where i have felt
meaningfully
less than
and in those moments
the
loop that i would fall into is
i would look to cope and be seen by other people so
i would throw away
all of the work i was doing around my own internal validation
and
i
would try to say something or do something that would get the attention of others and
oftentimes you know when that loop was
um was unproductive it's because those things had really crappy
consequences so
you know that was that was yeah so yeah i i went through that as
well so i had to go through you
know this disharmonious
phase in my life and then to repair it you know i had the benefit of
meeting someone and
building a relationship
um block by block where there is just enormous accountability
where my partner not had has just incredible empathy
um but accountability
and so she can put herself in my shoes sometimes
when i'm a really tough person to be around
but then she doesn't let me off the hook she
can forgive me but
it doesn't make you know what i may have said or whatever you
know excusable
and that's been really healthy for me and it's helped me repair my relationships
be
a better parent you
know be a better friend
to my ex-wife who's a beautiful woman who
you know i love deeply and will always love her and
it took me a few years to see that that
it was just a chapter that had come to an end but she's
an incredible mother and an incredible businesswoman
and i'm so thankful that i've had two incredible women in my life
that's like a blessing but
it's hard so
with that it's hard to find a person that
has that i
mean a lot of stuff you said is pretty profound but
having that person who has empathy
and accountability
so basically that's ultimately what great friendship
is
which
is people that love you have empathy
for you but can also call you out on your bullshit she's a lebron james-like
figure and the reason i say that is
i've seen and met so many people i've seen the distribution on
the scale of friendship and empathy
she's the
lebron
james of friendship she's a goat well
what's so funny is like you know we
have a dinner around poker
and it's taken on a life of its own mostly
because of her because these guys look to her and i'm like whoa whoa [laughter]
her registers are already full she's thinking of all kinds of crap with me
um but
um
but it's a it's a it's a very innate skill and
it's paired with you know it's but it's not just an emotional thing meaning
she's the person that i make all my decisions with
these decisions we're making together as a team i've
never understood that you know there's that african pop proverb like go
fast go alone go far go together
and
lex since since i was born i was by myself
i had to cope and
i didn't have a good tool kit to
use into the world
and
in these last five or six years she's
helped me and at first my toolkit was literally like
sticks you know and
then i found a way to you
know she helped me sharpen
a little rock and that became a little knife but even that was crap and
then she showed me fire and then i forged a knife and that and
that's what it feels like where now this toolkit is like most average people
and i feel humble to be average because i was here down here on the ground
so it's made all these things more reasonable so i see
what comes from having deep profound friendships and love to
help you through these critical moments i have another friend who
um who i would say just completely unabashedly loves me this guy rob goldberg he
doesn't
hold me accountable
that much which i love like i could say i killed a homeless person he's
like ah they probably deserved
it you
know whereas that would be like that was not good what you just did so
but i have both
i
mean i have nat
every day you know rob i don't talk to that often but to
have two people
i had zero i think most people unfortunately have zero
um so i think like what what he needs is somebody to just listen
you don't have to put a label on these things
and
you just have to try to guide in these very unique
moments
where you can just like
de-escalate
what
is going on in your mind and
i suspect
what's
going on in his mind again to play armstrong quarterback i don't know
is that he is in a moment where he just feels lower than low
and
we all do it we've all had these moments where we don't know how
to get attention
and if you didn't grow up in a healthy environment you
may go through a negative way to get attention
and it's not to excuse it but it's to understand it
that's so profound the feeling less than and at those low points
going externally to find it and maybe creating conflict
and scandal to get that attention the way that my doctor explained it to me is
um
you have to think about yourself worth like
a knot it's inside of
a very complicated
set of knots so
it's like a some
people don't have these knots it's
just presented
to you on a platter
but for some of us because of the way we grow up it's
covered in all these knots so
the whole goal
is to loosen those knots
and it happens slowly it happens unpredictably and it takes a long time
and
so while you're doing that you are going to have moments
where when you feel less than you're not prepared
to
look inside and say actually here's
how i feel about myself it's pretty cool i'm happy with how where i'm at
i have to ask on
the topic of friendship you
do an amazing podcast called all in podcast people
should stop listening to this and go listen to that you
just did your 100th episode i
mean it's one of my favorite podcasts it's incredible for
the
the the technical and the human psychological wisdom that you guys
constantly give and in the way you analyze the world but also just the chemistry
between the between you you're clearly there's there's a tension and
there's a camaraderie that's all all laid out on on the table so
i don't know the two davids that well but i have met jason what
do you love about him i mean i'll give you a little psychological
breakdown of all three of these guys sure
um just my opinion yeah and i love you guys
um would
they agree with your psychological
breakdown i
don't know you know i
i think that what i would say about
jay cal is
he is unbelievably
loyal
um to no end and you know he's like any of those movies
where
which are about like the the
mafia
or whatever where like you know something
bad's
going wrong and you need somebody to show up
that's jcal so if you killed the said proverbial
homeless
person he would be right there to
help you the body yeah
but
he's the one that he'll defend
you in
every way shape or form even if it's not doesn't
make sense in that moment he
doesn't see
that
as an action of whether it'll solve the problem he
sees that as an act of devotion
to you your friend and
that's an incredible gift that he gives us
the other side of it is that you know j cal
needs
to learn
how to trust that other people love him back as much as he loves us foreign
because
he assumes that he's not as lovable as the rest of us
but he's infinitely more lovable than he understands he's i
mean you have to see lex like he is
unbelievably
funny i mean i
cannot tell you how funny this guy is
um next level funny yeah his timing timing everything charm the care he takes
so he is as lovable but he doesn't believe himself to be and
that manifests itself in areas that drive us all crazy from time to time which
makes it for a very pleasant listening experience okay so what about the the two
david's
deus
ex and david friedberg
david
sacks
is the one that i would say i
have the most emotional
connection with
um he and i can go a year without talking and
then we'll talk for four hours straight and
then we know where
we are and
we have this ability to pick up and have a level of intimacy
with each other and
i think that's just because i've known david for so long now
um that i find really comforting
and then freeburg is this person who i think similar to me had
a very turbulent upbringing has fought through it to build an incredible life for himself and
i have this enormous
respect for his journey i
don't particularly care about his outcomes to be honest but i just have i
look at that guy and i think
and he did it and so if i didn't do it
um i would be glad that he did it if it makes any sense
um and you can see that he
um feels like his entire responsibility is really around his kids
and just kind of like give a better counterfactual
and
you know sometimes i think he gets that right and wrong but
he's a very special human being that way on that show the
two of you have a very kind of
like from a geopolitics perspective i don't know there's just a very
effective
way to think deeply about the world the big
picture of the world he's a very systems level thinker yeah
very very absolutely
fairy systems levels very
rooted in you know a broad body of knowledge which
i have a tremendous respect for he brings all these things in
sax is
incredible because he has this unbelievable
understanding
of things but it has a core nucleus
so
free bird can just basically abstract
a whole bunch of systems and talk about it i
tend to be more like that where i try to kind
of i
find it to be more of a puzzle
socks
is more like anchored in you know a philosophical and historical context as the answer
and he starts there but he gets to these profound understandings
of systems as well on
the podcast in
life you guys hold to your opinion pretty strong
what's
what's the secret to being able to argue passionately with friends so
hold your position but
also not murder each other which
you guys seem to come close to i
think it's like strong
opinions weekly held
yeah
like you know like look today you
and i yeah what
have we we steel man like the two sides of three different things yeah
um now you could be confused and think i believe in those things i
believe that it's important to be able to intellectually traverse
there whether i believe in it or not and like steel man not superman like that's
a really but we introde
those things by saying let us steal men in this position sometimes
you guys skip the
we
skip you're right we we edit
those things out and sometimes
we'll sit on either sides
and we'll just kind of bat
things back and forth just to see what
the other person thinks so
that's how like
as fans we should listen to that sometimes like so sometimes
because you hold the strong opinion sometimes
like for example the cost of energy going to zero
is that like what's the degree of certainty on that is is this
kind of like you really
taking a prediction of how the world will unroll and if it does this will benefit
a huge amount of companies
and people that will believe
that idea so you really you
you like
you spend a few days a few weeks with that idea i've
been spending
two
years with that idea and
that idea has manifested into
um many pages and pages of more and more branches of a tree
but
it started with that idea so if you think about this tree this
logical tree that i built i would consider it more of a mosaic
and
at the at the base or root however you want to talk about it is
this idea the
incremental
cost of energy goes to zero how does it manifest and
so i talked about one traversal which is the competition of households versus utilities
but if even some of that comes to pass
we're going to see a bunch of other implications from a regulatory and technology perspective if
some of those come to pass so
i've tried to think think
sort of this you know six seven eight hops forward
and i have some like
to use the chest analogy
i have a bunch of short lines which i think can work
um and i've started to test those by making investments
tens of millions over here to 100 millions over there
but it's a distribution based on how probabilistic i think this these outcomes are
and how downside
protected
i can be and how much i will learn how
many mistakes i can make you know etc
and then very quickly over the next two years some
of those things will happen or not happen and i will rapidly re-underwrite
and i'll rewrite that tree
and then i'll get some more data i'll make some more investments
and i'll rapidly re-underwrite so
you know in order for
me to get to this tree maybe you can ask how did i get there it
was complete
accident
the
way that it happened was
i
have a friend of mine who
works
at a great organization
called fortress
his
name is drew
mcknight
and
he called me one
day and he said hey i'm doing a
deal will
you anchor
it we're going public
and it's a rare earth mining company and i said drew like if
i'm going to get tart and feathered in silicon valley for backing a mining company and
he said just talk to the guy and learn
and the guy jim lotinski blew me away he's
like
here's
what it means for energy
and
here's
what it means
for the supply chain
here's
what it means for the united states versus china
but lax i did that deal and then i did seven others
and that deal made money let's have another
but i learned i
made enough mistakes
where the net of it was
i got to a thesis that i believed in i could see it
and i was like okay
i paid
the price i
acquired the learning
i made my mistakes i know where i am at and
this is step one
and
then i learned a little bit more i made some more investments
and that's how i that's
how i do the job that's the
minute that you try
to wait for perfection in order to make a bet either on yourself or
a company
a girlfriend whatever it's too late so if we just linger on that tree
it seems like a lot of geopolitics
a lot of international military even conflict is
around energy so
how does
your thinking about energy connect
to what you see happening in the next 10 20 years maybe
you can look at the war in ukraine
or
relationship with china and other places through the lens of energy what
what's the hopeful what's the cynical trajectory
that the world might take through with this
drive towards zero energy zero
cost energy so
the united states was in a period of energy surplus
um until the last few years some
number of years in trump and i think some number of now the current administration
with president biden
um but we know what it means
um to basically have more than enough energy to fund our own domestic
manufacturing and living standards
foreign
and
i think that by being able to generate this energy from the sun that
is very capex efficient that
is very climate efficient
gives us a huge tailwind
the second thing is that we are now in a world in a regime for
many years to come of non-zero interest rates
and it may interest you to know that the really the last time
that you know we had long-dated
wars supported you
know at
low interest rates
was world war ii where i think the average interest rates
was like 1.07
in the tenure
and every other war tends to have these very quick open and closes because
these long protracted fights
get very difficult to finance when rates are non-zero
so just as an example even starting in 2023
so the practical example today in the united states is president biden's
budget is
about 1.5 trillion
and
for next year that's
not including the entitlement spending okay meaning medicare
social security right so the stuff that he wants to spend that he has discretion
over is about
1.582
trillion is the exact number
next year our interest payments are going to be 455
billion dollars that's 29 of every budget dollar is going to pay interest
so you have these two worlds coming together right lex if you have us
you know hurtling forward
to being able to generate our own energy and
the economic peril that comes with trying to underwrite several
trillion dollars for war which
we can't afford to pay when rates are at five percent means
that despite all the bluster the
probabilistic distribution of us engaging in war with russia and ukraine seems relatively low
the the override would obviously be a moral
reason to do it that
may or may not come if there's some nuclear proliferation
but now you have to steal man the
other side of the equation which is well what were to happen if
you were sitting there and you were putin
let's deal man setting
off a tactical nuke
someplace
okay i'm
getting calls every other day from my two largest energy buyers india and china telling
me slow my roll
i have the entire world looking
to find the final excuse to
turn me off and unplug me from the entire world economy
the
only morally reprehensible
thing that's left in my arsenal that
could do all of these things together would be to set off attack nuke
i would be the only person since world war ii to have done that
you know it's it seems like it's a really really really
big
step to take
and so i think that
x of the clamoring for war that the military-industrial complex wants us to buy into
the financial reasons to do it and the natural reason resources
needs to do it are making it very unlikely
that is not just true for us
i think it's also true for europe i
think the european
economy
is going to roll over
i think it's going i see a very hard landing for them which
means that if the economy slows down there's going to be less need for energy
and
so it
starts to become a thing where a negotiated settlement
is actually the win-win for everybody
but none of this would be possible without
zero interest rates in
a world of zero interest rates we would be in war
so you believe in the financial
forces and pressures overpowering i believe in the human lives
i really do believe in these even in in international war more
so there i think the invisible hand and
by the invisible hand for the audience i think really what it means is you
know the the financial complex
and really the central bank complex and the interplay between fiscal and monetary policy
um is a very convoluted and complicated set of things
but if we had zero interest rates
we would be probably in the middle of it now
see there's a complexity to this game at the international
level where the nation some nations are authoritarian and are there's significant corruption
and so that adds
from a game theoretic optimal perspective
you know the invisible hand has is operating in the mud preventing war
the
person the
person that
is the most important figure in the world right now is jerome
powell
he is probably doing more to prevent more than anybody else
he keeps ratcheting rates it's just impossible it's a mathematical impossibility for the united states unless
there is such a cataclysmic
moral transgression by russia so there is tail risk that it is possible
where we say forget it all bets are off we're going back to zero rates issue
a hundred year bond we're going to finance a war machine
there is a small risk of that but
i think the propensity of the majority of outcomes is more of a negotiated settlement so
what about i mean if you what's
the motivation of putin to invade ukraine in the first place if
financial
forces are the most
um the most powerful forces
why did it happen because it seems like there's other forces at play of
maintaining superpower status on the world stage yeah it seems like geopolitics doesn't happen just
with the invisible hand in
consideration i agree with that i can't beg to know to be honest i don't know
um but he did it
and i think it's easier for me
to guess the outcome from here it
would have been impossible for me to really understand it is
what got him to this place
but it seems like there's an end game here and there's
um there's not much playability
yeah i feel like i'm on a sturdy ground because there's been so many experts at
every stage of this that have been wrong well there are no experts well on this
there are no experts lex i
understand this well okay let's
dig into that because there's some because we just said phil helmuth is the
um is the greatest poker player of all time he has an opinion yeah
he doesn't he's so he would be mistaken hey
poker
phil
has an opinion ivy
has an opinion as well on how to play all these games
meaning an opinion means here's the lines i take here are the decisions i make
i live and die by those and if i'm right i win if i'm wrong i
lose i've
made more mistakes than my opponent
i thought you said there's an optimal
so aren't there people that have a deeper understand
a higher likelihood of being able to describe
and know the optimal the optimal set of actions here at
every layer well
they're they're they're being
theoretically set of optimal decisions but you can't play your life
um
against a computer like meaning the minute that you face an opponent and
that person takes you off that optimal path you have to adjust yeah
like what happens if a tactical nuke it would be really bad
um
i
think the world is resilient enough i
think the ukrainians are resilient enough to overcome it it
would be really bad it's just an it's an incredibly sad moment in human history but
do you wonder what u.s does
is there any understanding do you think people inside the united states
understand not not the regular citizens but people in the military do
you think joe biden understands do you think i think joe biden does understand i
think that i think they have a clear plan i think that there are
few
reasons to let the gerontocracy
rule but this is one of the reasons where i think they are better adept
than other people
um you know folks that were around during the bay of pigs folks
that hopefully have studied that and
studied you know nuclear de-escalation
we'll have a better playbook than i do my suspicion
is that
there is a you know in an emergency break glass plan and
i think before military intervention or anything else
i think that there are an enormous number of financial
sanctions that you can do to just completely cripple russia that they haven't undertaken yet
um and
if you couple that with an economic
system in europe that is less and less in need of energy
because it is going into a recession it
makes it easier for them to be able to walk away while
the u.s ships a bunch of you know lng over there so
i
i don't know the game theory on all of this but does it make you nervous
that
or we're just being temperamental does
it feels like the world hangs in a balance like
it feels like
at least for my naive perspective
i
thought we
were getting to a place where surely human civilization can't destroy itself and
here's a presentation of what looks like a hot war or
multiple parties involved in escalating escalation
towards a world war is not entirely out of the realm of possibility it's not i
would really really hope that
he is spending time with his two young twins
well this is part
of
what i really i really hope he's spending time with his kids
agreed but not kids not just kids but friends and the the he
may not have friends but
it's very hard for anybody to look at their kids and not think about protecting
the future
well there's
um partially
because of the pandemic but partially because of the nature of power it
feels like you're surrounded by people you can't trust more and more i
do think the pandemic had a effect on that too the isolating effect a
lot of people were not their best selves during the pandemic
from a super heavy topic let me go back to
the space where you're one of the most successful people in the world
how to build companies how to find good companies what it takes
to
find good companies
what it takes to build good companies
what advice
do you have for someone who wants to build the next
super successful startup in the tech space and
you know have a chance to be impactful like facebook apple
that's i think that's the key word if your
precondition is to start something successful you've already failed because
you're now you're playing somebody else's game what success means is not clear you're
walking into the woods
it's murky it's dark it's wet it's raining there's all these animals about
um there's no comfort there so you better really like hiking
and
there's no short way to shortcut that so
isn't it obvious what successes like success scale
so it's not what are the no
i think that there's a very brittle basic definition of success that's outside in
um but it's not that's not what it is
um you know i know people that are much much richer than i am
you know and they are just so completely broken
and i think to myself the
only difference between you and me
is outsider's perception of your wealth versus mine
but the
the happiness and the joy that i have in the simple basic routines of my life
give me enormous joy
and so
i feel successful no matter what anybody says about my success or lack of success
um there are people
that live normal lives that have good jobs that have good families you
know i've this like idyllic sense like
i see it on tick tock all the time so i know it exists these
neighborhoods where there's like a cul-de-sac and these beautiful homes and these kids are biking around
and every time i see that lex i immediately flash back to
what i didn't have
and i think that's success look
at how happy those kids are
so no you there is no one definition and
so if people are starting out to try to make a
million dollars 100 million dollars a billion dollars you're gonna fail
there's a definition of personal success but is there's also some level of
um that's different from person to person but there's also some level of
the
responsibility
you have if there's a mission to have a positive impact on the world so
i'm not sure that elon is happy no
in
fact i think if you focus
on trying
to have an impact
on
the world i
think you're going to end up deeply
unhappy
but does that matter
like what may happen what happens it may happen as a byproduct
but i think that you should strive to find your own personal happiness and then measure
how that manifests as it relates to society and to other people but
if the answer to those questions is zero that
doesn't make you less of a person no
100 but then the other way is
there are times when you need to sacrifice your own personal happiness
force
for
a bigger thing for that you've created yeah if you're if you're in a position to
do it i
think some folks are tested elon is probably the best example and
it must be really really hard to be him
um really hard i have
enormous
levels of empathy
and care for
him i really love him as a person because
i just see that it's not like it's not that fun
and and he has these ways of
being human that
in his position i just think are so dear
that if he never i
just hope he never loses them just a simple example like two
days ago
i don't know why but i
went on twitter and i saw the perfume
thing yeah so i'm like ah
fuck it i'm just gonna go buy some perfume so
i bought his perfume the burnt hair thing yeah
and i said and
i emailed him the receipt and i'm like all right you got me for a bottle
um and he
responded
in like eight seconds and it was just a smiley face or whatever yeah just
deeply normal things that you do amongst people that are just so nobody sees that
you know what i mean but it would be
he
deserves
for that stuff to be seen because the
rest of his life is so brutally hard yeah
um he's just a normal guy that is just caught in this ultra mega vortex
why do you think there's so few elons
it's an extremely lonely set of trade-offs
because to your point if you get tested
so if you think about it again probabilistically
there's eight billion people in the world maybe
50 of them get put in a position where they are building something of such colossal
importance that
they even have this choice
and then of that 50 maybe
10 of them are put in a moment where they actually have to make a trade-off
you
know you're
not going to be able to see your fam i'm
making this up you're
not going to be able to see your family
you're
not you
know you're going to have to basically
move
into your
factory you're
gonna have to sleep on
the floor but
here's the outcome energy independence
and you know resource abundance and peace
you know a massive peace dividend
and
then he says to himself i
don't know that he did because i've never had this combo
yeah
you know what that's worth it
and like and then you look at your kids and you're like
i'm making this decision i don't know how to explain that to you
yeah
you want to be in that position there's
no there's no amount of money where i would want to be in that position so
that
takes an enormous fortitude and a moral compass
that he has and that's what i think people need to need
to appreciate about that guy it's
also on the first number he said it's confusing that there's 50 people or
10 people
like that are put in the position to have that level of impact it's unclear
that that has to be that way it seems like there
could be much more
there should be there's definitely people with the potential
um but you know think about think about his journey you know his
mom had to leave a very complicated environment moved
to canada moved
to toronto you
know a small apartment
just north of bain bloor you know if you've ever been to toronto
um i remember talking
to her about this apartment is
so crazy because i used to live like around the corner from that place and
raise these three kids and just have to so
how many people are going to start with those boundary conditions
you know and really grind it out it's just very few people in the end that
um will have the resiliency to stick it through where
you don't give in to the self-doubt
and
so it you know it's a really it's
just a really hard set of boundary conditions
where you can have 50
or 100 of these people that's why they needed to be really they
need to be really appreciated
yeah well that's true for all humans that
follow
the the threat of their passion
and do something beautiful
in this world that could be in a small scale or a big scale
appreciation
is a
that's
a gift you give to the other person but also a gift to yourself that's
somehow it becomes
like this
contagious
thing i went to this
you
are so right you just like it my my brain just lit up because yesterday
i went to an investor day of my friend of mine
um describe
brad gerstner and
you know on the one very reductive world brad
and i are theoretically competitors but
we're not he
makes his own set of decisions i make my own set of decisions we're
both trying to do our own view of what is good work in the world
but he's been profoundly successful
and
it
was really the first moment of my
adult life where i could sit in a moment like that
and really be appreciative of his success and not feel less then
and so you know little selfishly for me but mostly for him as well
i was so proud to be in the room that's
my friend that
guy plays poker with me every thursday he
is crushing it it's awesome you
know and that's the it's a it's a really amazing feeling
i mean to to linger on the the trade-offs the complicated trade-offs with all this
what's your take on work-life balance in in a in a company that's trying to do
big things
i think that you have to have some very very strict boundaries
but otherwise i think balance is kind of dumb
it will make you limited
i think you need to immerse yourself in the problem
but you need to define that immersion with boundaries
so
if you you know if you ask me like you know what does like my process
look
like
it's monotonous and regimented but it's all the time except
when it's not and that's also monotonous
and regimented
um and i think that makes me very good at my craft
because it gives me what i need
to stay connected to the problem without feeling resentful about the problem which
part the monotonous all in nature of it or
the the when you say hard boundaries essentially
go
all out until you stop and
you don't stop often i'm in a little bit of a quandary right now
because i'm trying to redefine my goals
and you're catching me in a moment where
i have even in these last few years of evolution i
think i've made some good progress
but in one very specific way i'm still very reptilian
and i'm trying to let go which was that exactly if
you can you know in my business it
really gets reduced
to what is your annual rate of compounding
that's my demarcation
you know
steph curry and lebron james michael jordan it's how many points did you average not
just in a season
but over your career
you know and in their case to really be the greatest of all time
its points rebounds assists steals there's all kinds of measures
to be you know in that pantheon of being really really good at your craft
um and in my business it's very reductive it's how well have you compounded
and if you look at all the heroes that
i have put on a pedestal in my mind
um they've compounded you know at above 30 percent for a very long time
as have i
but
now i feel like i really need to let go because i
think i know how to do the basics of my job
and
if i had to summarize like an investing challenge or investing
i think really it's you know when you first start out investing
you're
a momentum person you saw it in gamestop just a bunch of people aping each other
and then it goes from momentum
to
you
start to think about cash flows
you know how much profit is this person going to make whatever so
that's like the evolution
you know this is the this is the basic thing
to this is a reasonably sophisticated way then
a much smaller group of people think about it in terms of macro geopolitics
but then a very finite few cracked
this special code which is there's a philosophy and
it's the philosophy that creates the system
and i'm scratching
at that furiously
but i cannot
break through
and
i
haven't broken
through
and
i know that
in order to break through i
gotta let go
so this is the journey that i'm in as in my in my professional life
so it is an all-consuming thing but
i'm always home for dinner
you know we have very prescribed moments where we take vacation the
weekends
you
know like if i i
can tell you about my
week if
you're curious
but it's like i would love i
would love to know your week it's since it's regimented
and
monotonous i woke up i wake up at 6 45.
um
get the kids go downstairs we
all have some form of you
know not super healthy breakfast i make a latte i've become in and and the
latte is like i have a machine i
measure the beans you
know i
make sure that
the timer is
such where
i have to pull it for a certain specific
ratio
you
know just so you know 20 grams
i gotta pull 30 grams
with the water and i got you know i got to do it
seconds
etc so your
coffee snob it helps me stay in rhythm sure
um before i used to have another machine i just pushed a button yeah
but then i would push the button religiously
in the exact same way you
know what i mean because
actually
on that topic
you know the morning with kids can be pretty stressful thing
are
you able to find sort of happiness
is that also that morning is a source of happiness it's great my
kids are lovely their
maniacs
um
i just see
you know and maybe i
don't i've never asked friedberg this but i'll just put
my words i
see all of the things in moments
where
there was no compassion given to me and
so i just give him a ton of love
and compassion i have an infinite patience for my children not for other kids yes
of course but for a lot of kids so anyway so we have a breakfast thing
um and then i go upstairs
um and i go i change and i and i work out from eight to nine
and that's like the first 15 minutes i
walk up on a steep incline you know
12 to 14 you know three and a half to four miles per hour walk
and then you know monday's a push day tuesdays
front of the legs wednesdays pull thursdays back of the legs
um eight
to nine
monday
i
always start
talk to my therapist
from nine to ten
so
as soon as i finish working
out
i
get on the phone and
i talk to him
and
it helps me lock in for the for the
for the week
and i and i and i'm just talking about the past
um and it's just helping me the recent past usually
sometimes
the recent past but usually it's about the past past
something that i remember when i was a kid
because that's the work about just loosening those knots you
know so i put in that hour of work
um respect that hour
but then i'm in the office and then it's like you know i go until
12 15 12 30.
go home
have lunch
like
a proper like go home sit down have lunch with nat talk she
leaves her work
can we talk how are we doing you know just check in our
youngest daughter will be there because she's one
and she's making a mess
and then i i'll have another coffee
that's it my limit for the day oh no more caffeine that's it and then
i go back to the office and i'll be there until six seven sometimes
and i do that monday tuesday wednesday thursday monday
tuesday thursday friday i'm allowed to have meetings wednesday
nothing it's all reading must
be unless it's a complete emergency it has to be
kind of a full reading and reading is a bunch of blogs
youtube videos so i'm not trying not to do any talking no
talking it's like being in silence being present thinking
about things by
the way how do you take notes give
us a
sketch i have a pad and i write stuff down sometimes
i go to my phone i'm a little all over the place sometimes
i do google docs i
don't have this is one thing i need to get better at actually
but typically what happens is i
actually do a lot of thinking in my mind and
i'm sort of filing a lot of stuff away and
then it all spills out and then i have to write
and then that gives me a body of work that i can evaluate
and think about and then i usually put it away
um and a lot of the time it goes nowhere but
every now and then i come back to it and it just unlocks
two or three things and i have a sense of how
else i'm thinking about things
um and then friday at the end of the day
nat and i talk to a couple's therapists
um and that's about checking out properly
so it's like okay now it's like focusing the weekend is family
being present being aware you know and
if there's email obviously if i have to do meetings from time to time no problem
um but there's boundaries checking out properly
um oh man that is so powerful just like yeah officially transitioning yeah
so these are these are really important
boundaries
so
that i can be immersed and
what that means is like look on a saturday afternoon you
know on a random day she'll
be like where's your mouth and i'll be up in my room and
i've found a podcast talking
about like
um
decis which is like ductal cancer in situ because i've been fascinated about breast cancer surgeries
for a while and
learning about that and
she's like what are you doing i'm like i'm listening to podcasts about decis and
she's like what's that like you know ductal cancer in c2
she's like okay
and so you know i so i have time to continue to just constantly learning
learning putting stuff in my memory banks to
organize into something and that's like a that's a week
but then in these fixed moments of time
phone down everything down we go on vacation you know
we go on a boat we go to whatever where it's just us and the kids
is there a structure when you're at work is
there instructed to your day in terms of meetings in terms of south side of wednesday
you
know because you're having to keep meetings to less than 30 minutes
have to
and
you know oftentimes
meetings
can be as short as like 10 or 15 minutes because then i'm just like okay
because i'm trying to reinforce
that
it's very rare that we all have something really important to say
and so the ritual that is becomes really valuable to get scale
is not the ritual of meetings but the ritual of respecting
the collective time of the unit
and
so it's like you know what folks
i'm going to assume
that you guys are also tackling
really important
projects
you
also want to have good boundaries
in this immersion go back to your kids and have dinner with them every night it's
not just for me it's for you so how about this why
don't you go and do your work this
painting didn't need to be 30 minutes it could be five and
the rest of the time is yours and and
it's
weird because when people join
that system at social capital they just
it's
like face time and it's like let me make sure and
let me talk a lot so
i can't say anything i
respect
the person that
says
nothing for
two years and
the first thing that they say is not obvious
that
person is immensely more valuable than the person that tries to talk all the time
what
have you learned from your
um so after facebook you
started social capital or what what is
now called social capital what
have you learned from all
the successful investing you've done there
about investing or about life yeah or about running a team if
i'm very loath to give advice because i think it so
much of it is situational but
my observation is that starting a business is really hard any kind of business
and most people don't know what they're doing
and as a result we make enormous
mistakes
but i would summarize this and this may be a little heterodoxical
i think there are only three kinds of mistakes because
if we go back to what we said before in the business
it's just learning
you're exploring the dark space to get to the answer faster than other people
and those the mistakes that you make are three
or the three kinds of decisions let's say you'll hire somebody and
they're really really really average but they're a really good person oh yeah you'll hire somebody
and they really weren't candid with who they are and
their real personality and their morality and their ethics only expose them
over a long period of time
and then you hire somebody and
they're not that good
morally but they're highly performant
what do you do with those three things
and i think successful companies
have figured out how to answer those three things because those are the things
that in my opinion determine
success and failure so it's basically hiring and you just identified
three
failure cases for hiring but very different failure
cases and very complicated ones right like the highly performant person who's
not that great as
a human being do
you keep them around well
a lot of people would air towards keeping that person around what
is the right answer i don't know it's the context of the situation
um and the second one is also very tricky
what
about if they really turned out that they were just not candid
with
who
they
are
and
it
took
you
a
long
time
to
figure
out
who
you
were
these
are all mistakes of the senior person that's running this organization
i think if you can learn to manage those situations well
those
are the real edge cases where you can make mistakes that are fatal to a company
yeah that's what i've learned over 11 and a half years honestly
otherwise the business of investing
i feel that it's like a it's a secret
and if you are willing to just keep chipping away
you'll peel back enough of these you know
layers
will come off and you'll see if the scales will come off and you'll eventually
see it i
really struggle with maybe you can be my therapist for a little bit well
that first case which you originally mentioned because
i love people i see the good in people i
really struggle with just a mediocre performing
person who's who's a good human being
that's a tough one
i'll let you off the hook yeah i think those are incredibly important and useful people
i think that if a company is like a body they
are like cartilage can you replace cartilage
yeah
but would you if he didn't have to no
okay can i can i play devil's advocate yeah so those folks
because of their goodness make it okay to be mediocre
they they create a culture where well we what's important in life which
is something i agree in my personal life is
to be good to each other to be friendly to be good
vibes all that kind of stuff you
know when i was at
google just like the good atmosphere everyone's playing and just it's fun fun right
um but to me
like
when i when i put on my hat of like having a mission and a goal
what
i
love to see is the superstars
that shine for some in some way like do something incredible
and i want everyone
to
also
admire
that those superstars and perhaps not just for the productivity's
sake or performing
or successful company's sake but because that too is
an incredible thing that humans are able to accomplish which
is shine i hear you but that's not a decision you make meaning you
get lucky when you have those people in your company
that's
not the hard part for you the
hard part is figuring out what to do with one two and three yeah keep
demote
promote fire what do you do
and
this is why it's all about those three buckets i
personally believe that folks in that bucket one
as long as those folks aren't more than 50 to 60 percent of a company are
good
and they can be managed as
long as they
are one
to two degrees away
from
one of those people that you just mentioned yeah
yeah
because it's easy then to drag the entire company down if
they're too far away from
the lebron james because
you don't know what lebron
james looks
and feels and smells and you
know so
you need that tactile sense of what excellence looks like in front of you
a
great example
is if you like if you just go on youtube and
you search these
clips of how
kobe
bryant's teammates described
not
kobe
but how their own behavior
not performance
because
there's a bunch of average people that kobe played with this whole career but
their behavior changed
by being somewhat
closer to him and i think that's an important psychological
thing to note for how you can do reasonably good team construction if
you're lucky enough to find those generational talents
you have to find a composition of a team that keeps them roughly close
to enough of the org that way that
group of people
can continue to add value and then you'll have courage to
fire these
next two groups of people and
i think the answer is to fire those two groups of people because
no matter how good you are that stuff just injects
poison into a into
a living organism
and that living organism will die when exposed to poison
so
would you invest in a lot of companies you've looked at a lot of companies what
do you think makes for a good leader so
we talked about building a team but
a good leader for a company what are the qualities
you know i
um when i first meet people
um i never asked to see a resume
um
and when i'm meeting a company ceo
for the first time i couldn't care less about the business in
fact
um and i try to take the time
to let them reveal themselves now
in this environment you know i'm doing most of the talking but
if this were the other way around and you were ever raising
capital and usage math i'd be interested in you looking at this business
i'd probably say eight to ten words
for hours and just listen prod you
know i throw things out prod and let you meander and
in you meandering i'm trying to build a sense of who this person is once
i have a rough sense of that which
is not necessarily right but it's a starting point
then i can go and understand why
this
idea makes sense in this moment and
what i'm really trying to do is just kind of like unpack
where are the biases that
may make you you know fail
and then we go back to you
the thing that silicon
valley has
the benefit of though is that they don't have to do any of this stuff
if there's momentum because then the
rule book goes out the window and people clamor to invest so
one of the things that i do
and this is again back to this pugilism that i inflict on myself
is i have these two things that i look at thing
number one is
i have a table that
says
how much did we make from all of our best investments
how
much did we lose from all of our worst investments what
is the ratio of winners to losers over 11 years
and
in our case it's 23 to 1.
on you know billions of dollars so you can you can kind of like you
can see a lot of signal
but what that allows me to do is really like say wait a minute like
we
cannot violate these
rules around how
much money we're willing to commit in an errant personality you
know the
second is i ask myself of
all the other top vcs in silicon valley name them all you know
um what's our correlation meaning
when i do a deal how
often does anybody from sequoia excel benchmark kleiner who you name it
do it at the same time or after
and vice versa
and
then then
i look at the data to see how much they do it amongst themselves
what's a good sign i'm at zero as
virtually close to zero as possible that's a good thing well
it's not a good thing when the markets are way way up because it creates
an
enormous amount of momentum so i have to make money the hard way
i
have to you know because i'm trafficking and things that are highly uncorrelated
to the the gestalt of silicon valley which can be a lonely business
but it's really valuable in moments where markets get crushed because correlation
is the first thing that causes massive destruction of of capital massive
because one person all of a sudden with one blow up in one company boom
the contagion hits everybody except
the person that was you know not and so now
those are like more sophisticated elements of risk management which is again this pugilism
that i inflict on my nobody asks
me to do that nobody
actually at
some level when the markets are up really care that
when markets are sideways or when markets are down i think that
that allows me to feel proud of our process
you know but that requires you to think a
lot a lot outside the box it's lonely because you're taking risks also your
public personality so you say stuff that
if it's wrong you get yelled at for constantly for
for being i mean your mistakes aren't private no and that's something that
um has been a really really healthy
moment of growth
it's like an athlete you know
if you really want to be a winner you got to hit the shot
in front of the fans
and if you miss it you
have to be willing to take the responsibility
of the fact that you bricked it
and
over time hopefully
there's a body of work that
says you've
generally hit more than you've missed
but if you look at even the best shooters what are they 52 percent
so these are razor thin margins at the end of the day which
is really so then what can you control
i can't control the defense i can't control what they throw up me i
can just control my preparation
and whether i'm in the best position to
launch a reasonable shot
you said that the world's first trillionaire would be somebody in climate change in the past
um let's update that what's
today as we stand here today what sector will the world's first trillionaire
come from yeah i think it's energy transition so
energy so the things we've been talking about yeah really
so isn't it okay well i think i think the way that i think about so
this is a single division it's hard to interrupt you see their
ability to actually build a company that makes huge
amount of money as
opposed to this distributed
idea that you've been talking about yeah i'll give you my philosophy
on wealth
um most of it is not you
um an enormous amount of it is
the genetic distribution of being born in the right place and blah blah irrespective
of the boundary conditions of how you were born or
where you were raised right so you
know at the end of the day you and i ended
up in the united states
it's
a huge benefit to us
second is the benefit of our age
it's much better and
much more likely to be successful as a 46 year old in 2023 than
a 26 year old in 2023
because
in my case i have demographics
working for me
with a 26 year old he
or she has demographics
working slightly against them can you explain that a little bit what
are the demographics here
in the case of me
the
distribution of population in america looks like a pyramid
and in that pyramid
i'm swedged in between these two massive population cohorts
the boomers and then these you know gen z and millennials
um and that's a very advantageous
position it's not dissimilar to the position that buffett was where he was you
know packaged
in between boomers beneath him and the silent generation above him and
being in between two massive population cohorts
turns out to be extremely advantageous because when
the cohort above you transitions power and capital and all of this stuff you're
the next person that likely gets handed it so we have a disproportionate
likelihood to be you know we are lucky to be older than younger
um so that's that's an advantage
and then the other advantage
that has nothing to do with me
is that i stumbled into technology
i got a degree in electrical
engineering and i ended up coming to silicon valley
and
it turned out that in that moment it was such a transformational wind of change that
was at my back right so
the wealth that one creates is
a huge part of those variables and then the last variable is your direct contributions
in that moment and the reason why
that can create extreme wealth is because when those things come together at the right moment
it's like a chemical reaction i mean it's just crazy so
that was sort of part number one of what i wanted to say the
second thing is when you look then inside
of these systems where you have all these tailwinds
right so in tech i think i benefit from these three big tail ones
if
you build the company or are part of a company or a part of a movement
your economic participation
tends to be a direct byproduct
of the actual value that that thing creates in the world
and that the thing that that creates in the world will be bigger
if it is not just an economic system but it's like a philosophical system
it changes the way the governance happens it changes the way that people think
about all kinds of other things about their lives
so there's a reason
i think why database companies are worth acts social companies are worth why but
the military industrial complex is worth you know as much
and i think there's a reason why that
if you for example were to go off and build some
newfangled
source of energy that's clean and hyper abundant
and safe
that what you're really going to displace
or reshape is trillions
and trillions of dollars of worldwide gdp so the global gdp is
i call it 85 trillion right it's going at two to three percent a year
so in the next 10 years we'll be dealing with a hundred trillion dollars of gdp
right somebody who develops clean energy in 2035
will probably shift 10 of that around 10 trillion dollars
a company can easily capture thirty percent of a market three trillion dollars
a human being can typically own a third of one of these companies one trillion dollars
so
you can kind of get to this answer where
it's like it's
going to happen in our lifetime
but you have to i think find these systems that are so gargantuan
and they exist today
it's more bounded because price discovery takes longer and
an existing thing it's more unbounded
because you know what it is you know the tentacles
that energy reaches
right of that 80 trillion dollars of worldwide gdp i
bet you if you added up all the energy companies
but
then you added up all of manufacturing
you know if you added up all of transport you'd
probably get to like 60 of the 80.
do you have an idea of which energy
which alternate energy sustainable energy is the most promising well i think that we
have to do a better job of exploring
what i call the suburbs of the periodic table
so
you know we're really good in seattle you know the upper northwest yes
you know we're kind of good in portland
but we're not existent in san diego and we have zero plan for
north carolina through florida
yeah and so is
that a fancy way of saying nuclear is should be part of the discussion
i think nuclear i think room temperature semiconductors
i'm
i'm not convinced right now that the existing set of nuclear solutions will
do a good job of scaling beyond bench scale i
think there is a lot of complicated technical
problems
that make
it work at a bench scale level even partially but the energy equation
is going to be very difficult to overcome in the absence
of some leaps
in material science
have
you seen any leaps
is there promising
stuff like you're
you're seeing the cutting edge from a company perspective
yeah i
would say not yet i
do but the precursor
yes i
have been spending a
fair amount of time so talking about like a new framework that's in my mind is
around these room temp superconductors
um and so i've been kind of bumbling around in that forest
for about a year
i
haven't really put together any
meaningful perspectives but again talking about like trafficking
in in companies and investments that are very lonely but they allow me to generate returns
that are relatively unique and independent
that's
an area where i don't see anybody else when i'm there i'll
give you another area
you know we
um i think are about to unleash in a world of zero energy and and
zero compute costs
computational biology will replace white chemistry
and when you do that you will be able to iterate on tools
that will be able to solve a lot of human disease
i think like if you look at the head
of like the top 400 most recurring rare diseases
i think like half the number 200
is
a specific point mutation as
just the mismethylation between c and t
i mean that's like whoa wait you're telling me in billions
of lines of code i
forgot you know semicolon
right there that's
causing
this the whole thing to miscompile
so i just got to go in there and boom and it's all done that's
a crazy idea that was a c plus plus c
c throwback for people that don't know there's two people who are two people there everybody
it's perfect sense um but but
um so
that couldn't that be a truly a source of the competition
biology unlocks
i mean obviously medicine is
begging
for the
thing with energy
though
is that the groundwork
is well laid
um and talking about sort of like the upper bound is well defined
the upper bound in medicine is not well defined because it is not
the
sum total of the market cap of the pharma industries it
is actually the sum total of the value of human life
and that's an extremely ethical and moral question isn't there special
interests that are resisting
moving
making progress on the energy side so like
governments
and
how do you break through that i mean you have to acknowledge
the reality
of that i think it's less governments
in fact like i said i think president biden
has done a
really incredible job while chuck schumer really is done a really incredible job because
so just to give you the math on this right like back to this so
three percent of everything is of a market or zealots
but when you get past five percent things
tend to just go nuclear
to 50 60 percent
the way that they wrote this last bill
the
cost
i'll just use cars as an example the cost of an average car is
22 and a half thousand the
cost of the cheapest battery car is thirty thousand and
lo and behold there's a seventy five hundred dollar credit and it's like to
think the invisible hand didn't
know that that math was
right i
think is kind of a little bit malarkey
and
so the
battery ev
car
is going to be the same price
as
the
thing and
it's going to go to 40
percent
um so we're already at this tipping point so we're kind of ready to go
um
in these other markets it's a little bit more complicated because there's a lot of infrastructure
that needs to get built so you
know the the gene editing thing as an example you
know we have to build a tool chain
that looks more like
um code that you can write to facebook is written in i think php originally
hbo which
is i'm
still a big fan of sometimes
you have to use the ugly solution and
make it look good versus trying
to come up with a good solution
um which will be too late let
me ask you you consider a run for governor of california then decided against it what
went into each of these decisions and
broadly i should have maybe a selfish question about silicon
valley
is it over as a world leader for new tech companies
as a this beacon of promise of
young minds stepping in and creating something that changes the world
i don't know if those two questions are connected so
it's not it's not over but
i think it's definitely
we're in a challenging moment
because
so back to that analogy of the demographics if
you think about the like if you bucketed forget like our
relative successes
but there's a bunch of us in this
mid 50s to mid 30s cohort of people that
have now been around you
know for 20 years 15 years to 25 years that have done stuff right
from andreessen to zoc to jack dorsey
etc elon you know whatever maybe you throw me in the mix david sacks whatever okay
none of us have done a really good job of becoming a statesman
um or a states woman you know
um and really showing a broad empathy and awareness for the broader systems
so silicon valley is to survive as a system
we need to know that we've transitioned from move fast and break things to
get
to the right answer and take your time if that's what it means
and so we have to be a participant of the system
and i believe that and i think that it's important to
not be a dilettante and not be thumbing your face to washington
or
not push the boundaries and say you know we'll deal with it after the fact but
to work with folks that are trying to do the best again
steel man their point of view
you know work with them potentially
run for office so
potentially like be you know understand
the system it makes me
sad that there's no
tech
people or not many tech people in congress and certainly not in the presidential level not
many governors or senators well
i think that we also have roughly
you know our rules will
never allow
some of the best and brightest folks to run for president because
of just the rules
against it but you know if
if oh you mean yeah yeah i mean like more than this i think david sacks
would be an incredible presidential
candidate now i
also think he'd be a great governor no he was born in south africa
you know i think he'd be a great governor i think he'd be a great
um secretary of state i mean he'd be great at whatever he wanted to do
um you know friedberg you know wasn't born here
um so there's there's a lot of people that could contribute at
different levels and i hope that
by the way the other thing i like about the pod is like i
also think it helps normalize
tech a little bit because
you just see like normal people dealing
with normal situations
um and
i think that that's good you
know it is a really normative place it's not the caricature
that it's made out to be but there
is a small virul and strain of people that make it caricature-like
with this in one direction what do you think about the whole
culture of
um i don't know if better turns but woke activism so sort of activism
which
in some contexts is a powerful and important thing but infiltrating
companies
i'll
answer this in the context of renee
gerard so like he
says that people tend to copy
each other
and
then when
they're copying
each other they're
really what they're fighting what they're doing is they're fighting over some
scarce
resource
and then you find a way to organize against you know the group of you
against
a
person or
a thing that you think is the
actual
cause
of all of this conflict
and you try to expel
them
the thing that wokeism doesn't understand
is that unless that person is truly to blame the cycle just continues
and
you know that was a that
was a framework
that he developed that you know he's really conclusively
proven to be true and it's observable in humanity in life
so these movements i think the extreme left and the extreme right
are trying to interpret away to allow people to compete for some scarce resource
but
i also think that in all of that what they don't realize
is that they can scapegoat
whoever they want but
it's not going to work because the
the bull work of people in the middle realize
that it's just not true
yeah they realize
but they're still because in leadership positions
there's still momentum
and they still scapegoat
and they continue
and it seems to hurt the actual ability is more successful in
fairness though if you had to graph the effectiveness of that function it's
decaying rapidly it's
the least effective it's ever been you're
absolutely right being canceled five years ago was a huge deal
today i think it was jordan peterson on your podcast he
said i've been canceled and it was amazing he said 38
times or 40 he said some number which was a ginormous number a
that he kept account of it and b was able to classify
it yeah i'm like what classifier
is going on in his mind where
he's like ah
that's an attempt to cancel me but this one is not but my point is
was clearly not working
and
so the guy
is still there and the guy is you know putting his view out into the world
um and
so it's not what
not to judge whether what
he says is right or wrong
it's just to observe that this mechanism mechanism of action is now weakened but
it's weakened because it's not the thing that people think is really to blame yeah
you've
been canceled on
a small scale a few times so let's not i'm
sure it didn't feel small actually
it wasn't small i'm trying to minimize
did that did that psychologically hurt you yeah
it was tough i mean in the moment you don't know what's going on but
i would like to thank a certain ceo of
a certain well-known company
and he sent me
basically like a step-by-step
manual
and does it involve mushrooms no no and
and he was right
you know the
storm passed and life went on is
it
i don't know if you can share the the list
of steps but is the fundamental core idea
is that just
life
goes on
the
the core fundamental idea is like you need to be willing
and able to apologize
for what is in your control but not for other people's mistakes
your mistakes yes and if you feel like there's something then
you should take accountability
of that
but to apologize for somebody else for
something that they want to hear
isn't
going to solve anything
yeah there's something about apologies
if you do them they should be authentic
to what you actually want to say versus
what somebody else needs to wants to hear
otherwise
it doesn't ring true yeah
and people can see through that and people can see through it and also what
people see through is not just the fact that you
know your
apology was somewhat hollow
but
also that this entire majority of people now walked away the mob was like okay thanks
yeah and then people are like also you didn't care at all this is like
and so then it reflects more broadly on them yeah
i
know you said you don't like to give advice but
what advice would you give to a young person
you've
lived an incredible life from very humble beginnings difficult childhood and
you're one of the most successful people in the world so what advice i
mean a lot of people look to you for inspiration
kids in high school or early college they're not doing good or
um are trying to figure out basically
what to do when they have complete doubt in themselves what advice would you give them
it is really important that if somebody
that
you respect and i'm gonna just
for the purpose of this put myself in that bucket and if you're listening to this
um i wish somebody had told this to me
um we are all equal
and you
will fight this demon inside you that says you are less than a
lot of other people
for reasons that will be hard to see until you're much much older
and so you have to find
either a set of people far far away like what i did
or one or two people really really close to you or maybe it's both
that will remind you in key moments of your life that that is true otherwise
you will give in to that beast
and
it's
not the end of the world and
you'll recover from it i've made a lot of mistakes
but it requires a lot of energy
and sometimes it's just easier to just stop and give up
so
i think that if you're starting out in the world if
you've been lucky to have a wonderful life and you had wonderful parents
man
you
should go and give them a huge hug because
they
did use
such
a service
that
most folks don't do to most kids unfortunately
and it's not the fault of these parents
but it's just tough life is tough
so give him a kiss
and then figure out a way where you can just do work that validates
you and where you feel like you're developing some kind of mastery
who
cares what anybody else thinks about it
just
do it because it feels good do it because you like to get good at something
but if you're not one of those lucky people
um you can believe in your friends or you can just believe in me
i'm telling you preserve optionality
how you do that is by regulating
um your reactions to things
and
your reactions
are going to be largely guided
in moments where you think that you are not the same as everybody else and
specifically that you are less than those people and you're not
so just save
this part of this podcast and just play it on a loop if you need to
um but that is my biggest learning is i am equal
i'm the same as all these other people and
you can imagine what
that means to me to go out in the world to see people and think okay
i'm the same as this person i'm i'm as
good as them
and you could imagine what you're probably thinking of what i'm thinking is not that thing
right you're probably thinking man this guy yeah this guy i'm so much better no
i am fighting this thing
all the time
well i've also met a bunch of folks who
i think is a counter reaction to that once they become successful they
start developing a philosophy then they are better or even some people are better than others
i understand you
know there's lebron james versus other people and so on but
i always really resisted that thought
because i feel like it's a slightly better
they have mastery in a thing that they fall in love with yeah
i'm trying to develop mastery in a thing that i love
you know i love the art i love investing it's like solving puzzles
and i love that i love trying to develop mastery and poker i really love that
um i'm
learning
how to be a parent to a teenager
because i have finally have one
it's all new stuff to me and i'm learning
um
that's what it's all about
yeah so you don't want to think you're lesser than and
you don't want to think you're better than because those both
lead you astray i've never thought i was better than i
manifested better than
because i was trying to compensate for feeling less then
my
goal is just to feel like everybody else feels
on the presumption
that everybody had
like a normal life
given
your nickname is the dictator do you trust yourself with power like
if i if
the world gave you absolute power for a month
no
because i think that you know i'm still riddled with bias i
i don't i don't deserve that position i don't and
i would not want that weight on my shoulders
i had a i had a spot naturally where it was a very
important and big poker game
and it was a spot where i was in the pot and
it was a really large pot it was like a million dollar pot
and
i had to make a ruling and the ruling was in in my favor and okay
i was just beside myself
because
i don't
play i play for the challenge i like to get pushed
to the limit of my capabilities
i
want to see
can i think
at the same level of these folks you
know because these guys are all experts they're all pros
and i get enormous joy from that challenge
and i like to win but i like to win just a small amount
you know what i mean and then i never wanted to win in that way
but because it was you know my game i had to make this call
on a million dollar pot and i wanted to just
shoot myself i
just was like this is gross and disgusting and and he was a complete gentleman
which made it even worse
so
i do not want absolute
power well those are the people you do want to have power is
the ones that don't want it which
is a a weird system to have because
then you in that kind of system don't get the leaders
that
you should have because
the ones that one power aren't the ones that should have power it's
a weird weird system
what
do you think let
me sneak
this question in there what
do you think is the meaning of life
i don't well why are we here
look up at the stars and think about like the big
why question
i think that it's a chance to just enjoy the ride
i don't think it really like
i don't believe in this idea of legacy that much i think it's a real trap
so do you think you'll be forgotten by history i hope so i
really really hope so because
if you think about it there are two or three people that are remembered
for positive things and
everybody else it's all negative things and
the the likelihood that you'll be remembered for a positive thing is
harder and harder and harder and so the surface area of being remembered
is
negative and
then the second what
will it matter i'll be gone
i really just want to like have fun do my thing learn
get better
but i want i want to reward myself
by feeling like
oh that was awesome like i've told this story many times and i
have put again my
own narrative fallacy on top of this but
you know steve jobs's
sister wrote this you know obit in the new york times when he died and
she ends it by saying his last words were oh wow oh wow oh wow
that seems like an awesome way to die
you're surrounded by your friends and family not
the fact that he died obviously but
in a moment where what i read into it was your family was there
maybe you thought about all the cool shit that you were able to do
and then you know you just started the simulation all over again and
so yeah just
on the off chance that that's true i don't want to take this thing too seriously
you know what i mean just enjoy it so you're not afraid of it the end
good in tomorrow get in right now
so
every day you can go and you're happy you're happy with the things you've done yeah
you know there there are obviously things i want to do that i haven't done
um but there are no gaping things i've really really been in love
total gift there have been moments where i've really really felt like everybody else
there have been moments where i have deep deep deep joy
and connection with my children
there are moments where i've had incredible
giggling fun with my friends
there's moments where i've been able to enjoy really incredible experiences wine food all that stuff
great i mean what more do you want like i i could keep asking for more
i would just be a really crappy human being at some point
you know what i mean it's enough yeah
yeah it's enough it's
enough this
life this life is pretty beautiful if
you allow yourself to see it yeah it's
really great and it's better than it's ever been
um for
most of us actually yeah
it's pretty nice you know and all of the like you know millennials
and gen z's
you're about to get a boatload of money from your parents
and you better figure out
how to be happy before you get that money yeah because otherwise you will be miserable
get a lot of dairy queen
no
that would that only worked the first time it
worked two times in grade five and grade six my god that next year flex
i worked my ass off i'm like but
i could never bring myself to ask her yeah
and then she did it and i was like man she's
this woman's miss bruni
the
room is a gem yeah
but the third time it faded
isn't that the sad thing in my life you
know the finiteness of it the scarcity of it
without that we perhaps wouldn't ice cream wouldn't be so damn delicious you're an incredible human
um i definitely recommend that people listen to on all all
platforms
just we're very lucky to be able to get your wisdom i enjoy i agree with
um i've
talked a lot about you with the audrey capothy who's somebody i really respect and
he just loves
the shit out of you you know in in how much you
how deeply you understand the world it's
a huge honor he's an incredible human being so that's on a different yeah
speaking
of semicolons
there's some human beings that understand everything at
the very low level and at the very high level and those people are also
um very
rare so it's
it's a huge honor and also a huge honor that you
would be so kind to me just
like in subtle ways offline
that you would make me feel like i'm
worthwhile
well can i just say something as just a layman listener
um what you do just so i could give you my version
is that you take things
and people so ideas and people
that are mostly behind a rope
and you demystify it
and what that does for all of us is it makes me feel
like
i can be a part of that
and
that's a really inspiring
thing because you're
not giving advice you're not telling us how to solve the problem
but you're allowing it to be understood in
a way that's really
accessible
and
then you're intellectually curious in ways that you
know some of us would never expect
that we were and then you kind of end up in this rabbit hole
um and then you have the courage
to go and talk to people that are really all over the map
um like for example like i when i saw your
jordan peterson example like you
went there like you talked about nazism
and i was just like man this is a complicated argument
these guys are going to tackle and it's
just it's really
um really
impressive
so i have an enormous amount of respect for what you do i think it's very
hard
to do what you do so consistently
um and so i i look at you as somebody i i respect because it's
um it just shows like somebody who's immersed in something and who's
very
special so thank you for including
me in this i'm
going to play that clip to myself privately
over and over just when i feel
low
and self-critical about myself thank you so much brother thank you incredible thanks man
thank you for listening to this conversation with your mouth
to
support this podcast please check out our sponsors in the description and
now let me leave you with some words from jonathan swift
a wise person should have money in their head but not in their heart
thank you for listening and hope to see you next time