- A crazy thing in the kidnap business.
We used to get asked by FBI leadership,
"When is this gonna be over?"
And the answer would be,
"When the bad guys feel
like they've gotten everything they can."
Now dissecting that statement,
you're talking about when they feel
like they got everything they can.
So the key to kidnapping negotiations are the feelings.
They're the bad guys.
We're talking about feelings, kidnapper's feelings,
which drives everything.
Doesn't matter what human endeavor it is.
- The following is a conversation with Chris Voss,
former FBI hostage and crisis negotiator
and author of, "Never Split the Difference:
Negotiating As If Your Life Depended On It."
This is a Lex Fridman podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors
in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Chris Voss.
What is it like negotiating for a hostage with a kidnapper?
What is the toughest part of that process?
- The toughest part is, if it looks bad
from the beginning,
and you gotta engage in the process anyway.
- What are the factors that make it bad?
That makes you nervous?
That, if you were to observe a situation
where there's general negotiation,
or it's a hostage negotiation,
what makes you think that this is going to be difficult?
- If they wanna make it look like they're negotiating,
but they're not.
Like in the 2004 timeframe,
Al-Qaeda in Iraq was executing people on camera
for the publicity,
and they wanted to make it look like they were negotiating.
So they'd come on and they say,
"If you don't get all the women out of,
Iraqi women out of the jails in Iraq in 72 hours,
we're gonna kill a hostage."
That was one of the demands
in one of the cases in that timeframe.
Now, first of all, even if we'd have been willing,
the US government, the coalition,
would've been willing to do that,
it wouldn't have been able to happen in 72 hours.
So it was an impossible ask from the beginning.
And so then that looks really bad.
Like they're trying to make it,
they're trying to make it look
like they're talking reasonably, but they're not.
So your hostage is in bad shape there.
They've made a demand that you just,
even if you wanted to do, you couldn't do.
So then what makes that very difficult is,
in kidnappings especially,
you're working with family members,
you're coaching people,
bad guys are in touch with family members,
or if they're not directly in touch with family members,
the other thing that Al-Qaeda was doing
at that time was they didn't give us a way to talk to 'em.
They're making statements in the media,
but then not leaving their phone number, if you will.
So that's one more thing.
Like they're intentionally blocking you.
They're asking you to do something you can't do.
They're not giving you a way to talk to 'em.
So you gotta get with the family
and discuss with the family
how you're gonna approach things.
Now the family definitely wants to know,
"Is this gonna help?"
There was a bunch of cases like that in that timeframe.
And you gotta be honest with 'em,
"It's a long shot.
Our chances here are slim and none."
And when it's slim and none, I'll take slim,
but it's still very, very slim.
And there were a number of people that were killed
in that timeframe before the tide finally got turned.
And it was,
it was hard dealing with families at the time.
- Can you negotiate in public
versus like a direct channel in private?
- Oh yeah. Bad guys picked the media.
They're making statements in the media.
So, and that's a big clue.
Their channel of choice tells you an awful lot.
And if they're choosing the media,
then that means there's people they're trying to appeal to.
That means, in their view,
there's such a thing as good media.
So if there's good media, there's bad media.
How do you make it bad?
And we made it bad for 'em.
It just, unfortunately it had to go through a number
of iterations before they got the message and quit.
- In that negotiation,
do you think about the value of human life?
Is there a dollar figure?
Is there, how do you enumerate, not enumerate,
quantify the value of human life?
- Yeah, that's, it's like beauty.
It's in the eye of the beholder.
So that was the first lesson on any hostage negotiation.
Really any negotiation.
Like it doesn't matter what it is to you,
matters what it is to the other side.
One of the things, especially in your conversation
I listened to with Andrew.
By the way, you guys,
another thing I really liked about that conversation,
first of all, I think the world of him.
- [Lex] Andrew Huberman.
- Yeah, Andrew Huberman.
And you released it on my birthday,
I appreciate that. (Lex chuckles)
It was a nice birthday present-
- [Lex] I tried to time it perfectly just for you.
- Yeah, nice job. Thank you.
But empathy is in the eye of the beholder
in every negotiation.
Whether it's over a car, a house,
collaboration in your company, with the bad guys.
How does the other side see it?
Now the nice thing about kidnapping for ransom,
if there's an actual ransom demand
that's an actual demand,
is it's a mercenaries business.
They're gonna take what they could get.
And they tend to be really good
at figuring out how much money somebody has.
So, and again, I'll keep drawing business analogies.
You're looking for a job with an employer.
There's a market price of the job,
and then there's what the employer can pay you.
Now, maybe the market price of the job,
market's 150 grand, employer can pay 120.
But it's a great job.
You know, we were talking about Elon a minute ago.
Like, I'd work minimum wage to follow him around.
You know, that would be worth it.
More the value other than the dollars.
And how hard is it to get the dollars?
And how quickly can you get to them?
These are all things that the bad guys are good,
in kidnapping, are good at figuring out.
So the value of human life to them
is gonna be what can they get?
A crazy thing in the kidnap business.
We used to get asked by FBI leadership,
"When is this gonna be over?"
And the answer would be,
"When the bad guys feel
like they've gotten everything they can."
Now dissecting that statement,
you're talking about when they feel
like they got everything they can.
So the key to kidnapping negotiations are the feelings.
They're the bad guys.
We're talking about feelings, kidnapper's feelings,
which drives everything.
Doesn't matter what human endeavor it is.
- So it's not reason, it's emotion.
- There's no such thing as reason. (chuckles)
- (laughs) I should say for a little bit of context,
I just talked yesterday
with a guy named Sam Harris.
I don't know if you know Sam,
but Sam, and because I was preparing
for a conversation with you,
I talked to him about empathy versus reason
and he lands heavily on reason.
Empathy is somewhere between useless
and erroneous and leads you astray
and is not effective.
That reason is the only way forward.
- Well, let's draw some fine lines there.
And the two fine lines I would draw is,
first, what is your definition of empathy?
And then secondly,
how do people actually make up their minds?
And I'm gonna flip it.
I'm gonna go with how people make up their minds.
You make up your mind based on what you care about.
Period.
That makes reason emotion based.
What do you care about?
You start with what you care about.
You see some guy swimming out in off the coast of the ocean
and you see a shark coming up behind him.
Who are you cheering for?
If it's Adolf Hitler out there,
you're cheering for the shark.
You might actually feel bad for the shark,
'cause it's gonna taste bad.
Who do you care about?
- You mean the human will taste bad? (laughs)
- Yeah, you know, if he eats Adolf Hitler,
you know, it's gonna leave a bad taste in your mouth,
even if you're a shark.
So you're making up your mind on every circumstances
based on what you care about.
So then what does that do to reason?
Your reason is based on
what you care about from the beginning.
Now then empathy.
If you define it as sympathy,
which it was never meant to be sympathy, ever.
You know,
etymology, I think is the word.
I keep getting etymology and entomology mixed up.
Etymology being right, you know,
where words came from, the origin.
Entomology being bugs.
- [Lex] (laughs) Got it.
- Right? So I like etymology.
Where did something come from?
I also like entomology.
Anyway, etymology.
My understanding from my research,
the original definition of empathy
was an interpretation of a German word,
where people were trying to figure out
what the artist was trying to convey.
It was about assessing art.
And so it was always about understanding
where somebody was coming from,
but not sharing necessarily that same thing.
So then when I was with the FBI
and I first started collaborating with Harvard,
Bob Mnookin wrote a book "Beyond Winning,"
second chapter is,
"The Tension Between Empathy and Assertiveness."
Still the best chapter on empathy I've ever read anywhere.
And Bob writes in his book.
Bob was the head of the program on negotiation.
He's also agreed to be interviewed for a documentary
about me and my company that hasn't been released yet,
but it should be released sometime this year.
- [Lex] What's the name of the documentary?
- "Tactical Empathy."
- [Lex] Good name.
- So Bob's definition of empathy, he said,
"Not agreeing or even liking the other side."
Don't even gotta like 'em,
don't gotta agree with 'em.
Just straight understanding where they're coming from
and articulating it,
which requires no agreement whatsoever.
That becomes a very powerful tool,
like ridiculously powerful.
And if it, if sympathy or compassion
or agreement are not included,
you can be empathic with anybody.
I was thinking about this
when I was getting ready to sit down and talk to you,
'cause you use the word empathy a lot.
Putin.
I can be empathic with Putin easy. It's easy.
I don't agree with where he is coming from.
I don't agree with his methodology.
Early on, Ukraine/Russian war,
I saw an article that was very dismissive of Russia.
That said, "Russia's basically Europe's gas station."
And I thought, "All right."
So if you are in charge
and the way you feed your people
is via an industry
that the entire world is trying to quit.
The whole world is trying to get out of fossil fuels.
If that's how you feed your people,
if you don't come up with an answer to that,
the people that you've taken a responsibility for
are gonna die alone in the cold, in the dark.
They're gonna freeze and they're gonna die.
Right, so that doesn't mean that I agree
with where he is coming from or any of his means,
but where is, how does this guy see things
in his distorted war?
You're never gonna get through to somebody like that
in a conversation unless you can demonstrate to them
you understand where they're coming from.
Whether or not you agree.
Early '90s, last century.
I'm a last century guy, I'm an old dude,
refer to myself as a last century guy.
Also a deeply flawed human.
So terrorist case, New York City,
civilian court.
Terrorism does not have to be tried in military tribunals.
That's a very bad idea. It was always bad.
The FBI was always against it.
I'm getting ready.
We have Muslims testifying in open court
against a legitimate Muslim cleric.
The guy that was on trial had the credentials
as a legitimate Muslim cleric.
The people that were testifying against him
didn't think he should be advocating murder
of innocent people.
We'd sit down with them, Arab Muslims, Egyptians mostly.
And I would say to them,
"You believe that there's been a succession
of American governments for the last 200 years
that are anti-Islamic?"
And they shake their head and go, "Yeah."
And that'd be the start of the conversation.
That's empathy.
You believe this to be the case.
I never said I agreed.
I never said I disagreed,
but I showed 'em that I wasn't afraid of their beliefs.
I was so unafraid of 'em that I was willing
to just state 'em and not disagree or contradict.
'Cause I would say that
and then I'd shut up and let 'em react.
And I never had to say, "Here's why you're wrong."
I never gave my point of view.
Every single one of 'em that testified. That's empathy.
Not agreeing with where the other side is coming from.
I'm not sure how Sam would de define it,
but common vernacular is its sympathy and its compassion.
And that's when it becomes useless.
- And there is a gray area, maybe you can comment on it,
is sometimes a drop of compassion
helps make that empathy more effective in the conversation.
So you're just saying you believe X,
doesn't quite form a strong of a bond with the other person.
- You are imagining it doesn't.
- Maybe you're right, yes,
I'm imagining it doesn't.
I'm imagining you need to show
that you're on the same side.
That you need to signal a little bit
about your actual beliefs,
at least in that moment.
Even if those, that signaling is a,
is not as deep as it sounds,
but at first, you know,
basically patting the person on the back and saying,
"We're on the same side, brother."
- You know, that's what most people,
when they're really learning the concept,
that's the basic human reaction.
And in application,
especially in highly adversarial situations,
like, I need a regular guy,
Muslim, but how's that guy gonna say
"Buy it, if I like, you know,
dude, I'm on your side.
I've been there, I feel you."
No, no, no, no, no, no.
People get conned by that so much.
Like, if we're on opposite sides of the table
and I try to act like I'm not on the opposite side
of the table, that makes me disingenuous.
So I would rather be honest.
You know, my currency is integrity.
And at some point in time, if you go like,
"You know where I'm coming from?"
My answer's gonna be like,
look, I can agree on maybe where we're going,
but if we're talking about, you know,
am I on your side now?
As a human being, I wanna see you survive and thrive.
Not at my expense.
I think the world is full of opportunity.
I'm optimistic.
I got more than enough reason for saying that.
There's enough here for both of us.
So I got no problem with you getting yours.
You know, just don't take it outta my hide
and I'm gonna be honest about it.
About both of those things,
I'm not interested in you taking it outta my hide.
I think there's plenty here for both of us.
Now, I don't need to be on your side
except in a human sense.
But I don't,
do I have to side with you over the war?
No. Or how we're distributing the stock?
Or how much you get paid,
or how much you make off this car.
I think people,
my experience as a layman
is that empathy's not got a downside.
That you don't need me to act
like I'm on your side for us to make a great deal.
- Great deal. Well, we'll talk about two things.
A great deal and a great conversation.
They're often going to be the same thing,
but at times they're going to be different.
And that's a, you mentioned Vladimir Putin.
There is some zoom level at which you do wanna say,
"We're on the same side."
You said the human level.
It's possible to say,
kind of zoom out and say that we're all in this together.
Not we Slavic people, we Europeans,
but we human beings.
- We're on the same planet. - Same planet, right.
- Several years ago,
and his name is evidently been mud now,
but he was very nice to me,
a lawyer here in town named Tom Girardi.
And no shortage of bad reporting on him now,
I have absolutely no idea if any of it's true.
I do know that in my interaction with him,
he was always a gentleman to me and was very generous.
When he'd get into conversations with people,
he'd always say like, you know,
"Let's look at 10 years from now,
where we could both be in a phenomenal place together.
Now let's work our way back from there."
- (laughs) That's a good line.
- Yeah, and then, you know,
I saw him do it in simulations.
I was teaching a USC, we were at a function together,
and a gentleman at the time told me who he was,
and that he was really influential.
So I walked up to the guy cold and I said,
"Hey, you know, how about coming
to talk in my class at USC?"
He didn't know me other than the fact
that we had a mutual acquaintance,
and he graciously consented to come in.
And he said, "What do you want me to talk about?"
I said, "Look, dude, just from your success here,
it doesn't matter what you talk about.
You know, either I'm gonna agree
or I'm gonna disagree or I'm gonna learn from it.
My students are gonna learn from it."
So students wanna role play with 'em, you know,
they dispute, you know, "Let's do a negotiation."
Every single time he'd go to "Pick a point in the future
where we're both happy.
10 years, 20 years from now, and let's work our way back."
Now, hostage negotiator, same thing.
I call into a bank, bad guy picks up on the,
picks up on the phone,
and I'm gonna say, "I want you to live."
You know, "I wanna see you survive this, you know,
whatever else goes with that.
Let's pick a point in the future
that we're both good with.
And then we work our way back."
And people make also,
we were talking before about emotion
and what you care about.
People make their decisions
based on their vision of the future.
Like without question.
I think there's a Hindu temple in the United States,
being, has been, or being assembled,
same way that the Hindu temples were in India
a thousand years ago by hand.
Volunteers, by hand.
These people are knocking themselves out
for a place in paradise, a vision of the future.
What you will go through today
if the future portends what you want,
you'll go through incredible things today.
So it's a vision of the future.
- So you have to try to paint a vision of the future
that the person you're negotiating with will like.
Which is tough to do.
- It's find out what their vision of the future is
and then remove yourself as a threat.
You know, if we can collaborate together at all.
If you think that I could do anything at all
to help you to that point and, you know,
integrity's my currency,
I'm not gonna lie to you.
Which gets back before,
did I lie to you about whether or not I'm on your side?
You know, right now, at the moment
we're on opposite sides of the fence.
That's not gonna stop us from being together in the future.
Inside you're gonna say,
"Wow, well, you didn't lie to me about today.
Maybe you won't lie to me about tomorrow."
- So going back to world leaders, for example,
whether it's Volodymyr Zelenskyy or Vladimir Putin,
you don't think it closes off their mind
to show that you have a different opinion.
- Depending upon when you showed it.
Are you arguing from the beginning
or are you displaying understanding from the beginning?
I don't think it stops you from being adversarial.
That was the thing about Mnookin's,
the chapter in his book,
"The Tension Between Empathy and Assertiveness."
I remember reading that,
reading that name of the chapter, thinking like,
"Eh, you know, in my business there is no tension."
And then I got into it and I read, I thought,
"This is a red herring."
He's drawing people in
because his entire chapter is
that empathy puts you in a position to assert
and that there is no tension.
It's a sequencing issue.
And that's why, again, I think it's,
it was written for lawyers.
- Yeah, sequencing issue.
The timing is everything.
So you emphasize the importance of,
in terms of sequencing and priority of listening,
of truly listening to the other person.
- I'm sorry, what'd you say?
That was a bad joke, sorry. - I forgot.
Your timing is just perfect.
How do you listen?
How do you truly listen to another human being?
How do you notice them?
How do you really hear them?
- I always hated the term active listening.
If anything, it's proactive.
And as soon as you start to try and anticipate
where somebody's going, you're dialed in more.
Because along the way,
either you're congratulating yourself for being right,
or, when suddenly they say something that surprises you,
you really notice it.
Like, "That's not what I expected."
You're dialed in, you're listening.
So it's proactive.
And then one of the reasons, you know,
we named the book "Tactical Empathy."
Named the book "Never Split the Difference,"
but we're talking about tactical empathy.
Calibrated emotional intelligence.
What's it calibrated by?
First it was experience as host negotiators,
but then we'd come to find out
that our experience as host negotiators
is backed up by neuroscience.
Another reason why I listen
to Andrew Huberman's podcasts all the time.
Heavy, heavy, heavy, heavy on the neuroscience.
And so then emotional intelligence calibrated
by what we know about neuroscience.
What do we know about neuroscience?
And I'll talk about it from a layman's perspective,
and to even say we is an arrogant thing,
you know, human beings.
I didn't do the research.
I'm scooping up as much of it as I can as a layman.
The brain's largely negative.
I think there's ample evidence.
People would argue with you as to what the wiring is
and what does what,
and the limbic system and all of that.
But the brain is basically 75% negative.
As is in a layman I make that contention.
Number one. Number two.
The best way to deactivate negativity
is by calling it out.
And I could say, "Look, I don't want you to be offended
by what I'm getting ready to say."
That's a denial.
Your guard is up, you're getting ready to get mad.
If I say, "What I'm getting ready to say
is probably gonna offend you."
Then you relax a little bit and you go,
"All right, what is it?"
And then I say it, whatever it is.
And you're gonna be like, "Oh, that wasn't that bad."
Because we knew from hostage negotiation
by calling out the negativity it deactivated it,
and then, a number of neuroscience experiments
have been done right and left,
by calling out negativity, deactivating the negativity.
- Calling out ahead of time.
So like acknowledging that this is,
that this is ahead of time, that this is going to hurt.
- The experiments that I've seen
have been when the negativity was inflicted
and then having a person that it was being inflicted upon
simply identify it.
- [Lex] Just identify?
- Yeah, what are you feeling?
I'm angry. And the anger goes away.
- It's tough because I've had a few,
and again, we're dancing between things,
but I've had a few conversations
where anger arose in the guests I spoke with.
And I'm not sure identifying it,
that's like leaning into it and going into the depths,
'cause that's going into the depths of some emotional,
psychological thing they're going through
that I'm not sure I wanna explore
that iceberg with the little ship we got.
You have to decide,
do you want to avoid it
or do you wanna lean into it?
It's a tough choice.
- It's the elephant in the room.
- It is an elephant in the room.
It is an elephant.
Especially when, I think that's the big difference
between conversations and negotiations.
Negotiation ultimately is looking for closure
and resolution.
I think general conversations like this is more exploring.
There's not necessarily a goal.
Like if you were to put,
like, if I had to put a goal for this conversation,
there's no real goal.
It's curiously exploring ideas.
So that'll, gives you freedom to not call out the elephant.
(chuckles) For a time you can be like,
"All right, let's go to the next room,
get a snack and come back to the elephant.
- Right. All right.
So I'd make a tiny adjustment on the negotiation definition.
'Cause you said, I think, "Seeking closure."
You used two words, and closure was one of them.
- Goal was maybe another.
Well, yeah, what is negotiation?
- Well, I would say seeking collaboration.
And, 'cause closure kind of puts
a little bit of a finality to it, and the real problem
in any negotiation's always implementation.
That's why we say, "Yes is,"
I say, "Yes is nothing without how."
And yes at it's very best is only a temporary aspiration.
It's aspirational.
It's usually counterfeit.
So if you're looking for-
(Lex laughs) Huh?
- That's a good line.
Yes is usually counterfeit.
It's aspirational without the how.
It's just a good line, yeah. (laughs)
- Thank you. I've been working on it.
I was practicing in front of the mirror
before coming in today. - You're pretty good.
(both laughing)
You got a bright future ahead of you.
You should write a book or something.
(Lex laughing)
Your book is excellent, by the way.
- Thanks. Appreciate that.
What am I doing here anyway?
- This? On earth?
In general? - With you?
- I don't know.
(Chris laughing) We're collaborating.
- Why me though?
Why'd you wanna talk to me?
- I've heard you speak in a few places.
I was like, "This is a fascinating human."
I think on Clubhouse and different places,
and I listened to some YouTube stuff.
And this is just,
you meet people that are interesting.
That's what I love doing with this podcast,
is just exploring the mind of an interesting person.
You notice people- - Thanks.
- Sometimes there's like a homeless person,
that's outside of 7-Eleven, I notice,
who are you?
- [Chris] Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's fascinating.
It doesn't, like, I don't look at the resumes
and the credentials and stuff like that.
It's just being able to notice the person.
- As I've been leafing through
the different choices of the podcast,
the young lady that,
OnlyFans and the sex workers.
That's a fascinating human being.
- Yeah, it's fascinating. - Like I wanna know
what makes that person tick 1,000%.
- The fascinating thing about her
is her worldview is almost entirely different than mine.
And that's always interesting to talk to a person
who just is happy, flourishing,
but sees the world, and the set of values she has
is completely different,
and is also not argumentative,
is accepting of other worldviews.
It's beautiful to explore that.
- Yeah, no kidding, I would agree.
And then, yeah, thought provoking.
'Cause I consider myself,
the word I was looking for before is abundant.
I think it's an abundant world.
So I'm pretty optimistic.
I consider myself,
I don't know happy exactly describes it, but yeah,
you know I'm.
So then if I'm happy, optimistic, abundant,
I got a worldview and then you run into somebody
that has a vastly different worldview
and they're happy and they think it's abundant too.
And you're like, "What is going on in your head,
or mine, or what am I missing?"
Yes. That's fascinating.
- And the pie grows.
Which is useful for kinda negotiation
when you paint a picture of a future,
if you're optimistic about that future,
there's a kinda feeling, like we're both gonna win here.
- Exactly. - And that's easy.
We'll live in a world where both people can win.
- Yeah. And in point of fact, that's the case.
Although a lot of people want us to think otherwise.
Mostly because of the negativity
that I was talking about before.
- So the brain is generally cynical.
- Yeah, my description of it is,
the pessimistic caveman survived
and we're descendants of the pessimists.
The optimistic guy got eaten by a saber-toothed tiger.
- (chuckles) Yeah, but on the flip side,
the optimists seem to be the ones
that actually build stuff these days.
- There's a switch.
Like, so at what point in time do we catch on?
'Cause the difference between survival and success mindset.
The success mindset is highly optimistic.
So where do we switch or how do we stay switched
from survival to success?
That's the challenge.
- Yeah, somewhere we stopped being eaten
by saber-toothed tigers and started building bridges
and buildings, and computers and companies, and.
- We started to experience,
we got enough data back to collaborate,
and we stopped listening to our amygdala
and we started listening to our gut.
- Let me just to return briefly to terrorists.
What do you think about the policy
of not negotiating with terrorists?
- Well, that's not the policy, first of all.
Now, everybody thinks that's the policy.
It hasn't been the policy since 2002
when Bush 43 signed
a National Security Presidential Directive, NSPD.
At the time it was NSPD 12,
which basically said, "We won't make concessions.
That doesn't mean we won't talk."
So I'm in Columbia at the same time
and I have been intimately involved
with the signing of him signing that document.
I knew exactly what it said,
and he didn't inherit it from somebody else, he signed it.
And I'm in Columbia
and the number two in the embassy says,
"Last night on TV, the president of the United States
said we don't negotiate with terrorists.
Are you calling a president of the United States a liar?"
And I remember thinking like, "All right,
so he probably said that,
and that's not on the document that he signed."
So I said, "Look, you know,
I'm familiar with what he signed
and that's not what it says."
"Well, you know." And so the argument.
But that's always been the sound bite that everybody likes.
"We don't negotiate with terrorists."
Depends upon your definition of negotiation.
If it's just communication,
we negotiate with 'em all the time.
Number one. And number two.
Like every president has made some boneheaded deal
with the bad guys.
Like Obama released
five high-level Taliban leaders
from Guantanamo in exchange for an AWOL soldier
that we immediately threw in jail.
And I thought that was a horrible deal,
and that's putting terrorists back on a battlefield.
And then Trump turned around and topped it
by putting 5,000 terrorists back on the battlefield.
So we haven't had a president that has stuck to that
on either side of the aisle,
since people started throwing that out as a sound bite.
- What do you think of that negotiation?
Forget terrorists, but the global negotiation,
like with Vladimir Putin,
the recent negotiation over prisoners,
the exchange, the Brittney Griner.
Is there a way to do that negotiation successfully?
- First of all, I agree with the idea
that she was wrongfully detained
and she didn't deserve to be in jail.
And that US government,
there should be no second class citizens ever.
And whether you're an WNBA player
or you're just some bonehead
that walked into the wrong situation,
your government should not abandon you ever, ever.
Now what they do in the meantime,
there should have been a negotiation.
They were desperate to make a deal at a bad time.
They'd been offered far better deals
than prisoner swaps earlier and turned 'em down.
And then the heat gets turned up,
and thank God for Brittney Griner
that the public got enough attention.
They kept pressure on the administration,
they made a deal.
Now if governments wanna make those kind of deals,
that's fine, as long as it,
'cause that was basically a political negotiation.
You're putting 5,000 Taliban back on the battlefield,
that ain't negotiating with another government.
You're putting five of 'em back on the battlefield
that ain't negotiating with another government,
that's directly contradicting this thing that you claimed.
And those were all bad deals.
Now was the Brittney Griner thing a bad deal?
I think it was great for her.
If I was in the middle of it,
it would've been better and she still would've come home.
- Yeah, there's some technical aspects of that negotiation.
What do you think is the value, just to linger on it,
of meeting in-person for the negotiation?
- I think it's a great idea.
- Can I just follow that tangent along.
There's a war in Ukraine now.
It's been going on over a year.
It's, for me personally, given my life stories,
is a deeply personal one,
and I'm returning back to that area of the world,
I was there.
Volodymyr Zelenskyy said
he doesn't wanna talk to Vladimir Putin.
Do you think they could get in a room together?
And say you were there
in a room with Putin and Zelenskyy
and Biden is sitting in the back drinking a cocktail,
or maybe he is at the table participating.
Is it possible through negotiation,
through the art of conversation to find peace
in this very tense geopolitical conflict?
- I think it's eminently possible.
I think getting people together in-person
has always been a good idea.
Now how many,
who's getting 'em together under what circumstances
and how many times are you getting 'em together?
The documentary, "The Human Factor,"
about the Mid-East peace negotiations
mostly through the '90s,
mostly under the Clinton administration,
got kicked off under Bush 41.
And then the documentary continues through Trump,
but just touching basically on it.
But they're getting Arafat
and the different Israeli prime ministers
together in-person.
And these guys did not wanna talk to each other.
And depending upon the prime minister,
you know, the mere thought
of being on the same planet with Arafat was offensive.
And they started getting these guys together
in-person regularly and they started seeing each other
as human beings.
And they started realizing
that there was enough room on the planet for 'em
and that people dying was stupid.
And they would slowly work things out
by getting these guys together in-person.
So how long does it take?
Who's hosting it?
But it's a good idea.
- But the skill of achieving that thing
that you talk about a lot, which is empathy.
And I would say in that case, not just empathy,
but empathy plus a bit, you might disagree with this,
but a drop of compassion in there.
- I think compassion, compassion is helpful,
but it's not essential.
Like, if you just know where I'm coming from.
Like, the thought,
the feeling of being understood.
- Yeah, heard and understood. That's powerful.
- It is, yeah, and again,
I know I picked the vast majority of this up
on Andrew's podcast,
but I picked it up in other places.
'Cause early on,
when we were putting the book together,
Tahl Raz, the writer,
my son, uncredited co-author.
So the book's really a collaboration between me,
my son Brandon, and Tahl Raz.
And we're driving for that's rights.
You know, when somebody feels like what you've said
is completely their position, they say "That's right."
Not you're right, but that's right.
So Tahl says, "You know,
I think what's happening here
is you're triggering a subtle epiphany in somebody."
So I'm like, "All right, I'll buy that."
So I start looking up the neuroscience
of the feeling of epiphany,
getting a hit of oxytocin and serotonin.
Oxytocin is a bonding drug.
You bond to me, I don't bond to you.
When you feel completely understood by me,
you bond to me.
Then in one of the relationship podcasts
that I'm listening to on Andrew,
it says, "Oxytocin inclines people to tell the truth."
You're more honest.
All right, so you feel deeply understood by me,
you bond to me and you start getting more honest with me.
Serotonin, the neurochemical of satisfaction.
Epiphany, you feel oxytocin and serotonin.
Being understood.
All right, I got you bonding to me.
I got you being more honest with me
and I got you feeling more satisfied,
so you want less.
What more do you want out of a negotiation?
- Of course there's already,
with leaders and great negotiators,
there's walls built up,
defense mechanisms against that, right?
You're resisting,
you're resisting this basic chemistry.
But yes, you should have that.
You should work towards that kind of empathy.
And I personally believe,
I don't actually understand why,
but I've observed it time and time again,
but getting in a room together
and really talking, whether privately or publicly,
but really talking, and like this,
so I'll comment on this.
So right now this is being recorded
and a few folks will hear this,
but when you really do a good job
with this kind of conversation,
you forget there's cameras.
And that's much better
than there being even a third person in the room.
But often when world leaders meet there's like press
or there's others in the room.
Like, as you know, man-to-man or man-to-woman,
you have to like meet like in a saloon,
just the two of you and talk.
There's some intimacy and power to that
to achieve the,
if you're also willing to couple that with empathy,
to really hear the other person.
- [Chris] Yeah, yep, yeah.
- I don't know what that is.
That's like a deep, deep intimacy that happens.
- And I think there's actually,
'cause we get asked this
in The Black Swan Group all the time.
Like, "How do, you know, Zoom?
That's bad.
You know, 'cause you don't have
the same visual feedback on Zoom."
And that's not true.
Like you and I,
I see you from the waist up right now.
If we were on Zoom, I'd be looking at you from the waist up.
- I'm not wearing pants, yeah.
(Chris laughs)
For the internet.
I apologize for that.
(Chris laughs)
(chuckles) Sorry. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, you only see a small portion.
- Usually I, that's usually where I go.
But anyway.
- (laughs) I'm glad we both
have a ridiculous sense of humor, I appreciate it.
- But what makes this different in-person?
I actually think,
I think there's energy that we're unable,
we don't have the instrumentation to define yet.
And I think that there's a feel,
I think there's an actual energetic feel that changes.
And just 'cause we don't, again,
just 'cause we can't measure it,
doesn't mean it's not there.
- Yeah, I would love to figure out what that is.
Folks that are working on virtual reality
are trying to figure out what that is.
During the pandemic everybody was on Zoom.
Zoom and Microsoft,
everybody is trying to figure out how do we replicate that.
I'm trying to understand how to replicate that
because it sure is not fun to travel across the world
just to talk to Snowden or Putin or Zelenskyy.
I'd love to do it over Zoom, but it's not the same.
It's not the same. - No, it's not the same.
I'd go in a room with Putin.
- You would go in a room? - I would, yeah, 1,000%.
I'd get it that's right out of him.
- That's right.
Well, first you would give him a that's right probably.
- Ah, gettin' and givin'. You see.
And here's the issue that trips everybody up in negotiation.
The difference between hearing
and speaking the same words are vastly different.
And what I'm looking for
is the responses I'm getting outta you.
'Cause if you can't first, that's right especially,
like if you can't appreciate what that really means,
hearing it is unsatisfying.
- So those two words are really important to you.
You talk about this in your book.
What does that's right mean? Why is it important?
- Well, it means that what you just heard
you think is unequivocably the truth.
Like it's dead-on, it hit the target.
It's a bullseye.
And there's been a topic of discussion,
especially between my son and I,
a lot like what happens?
This oxytocin bonding moment.
And his contention has always been
like Donald Trump is the poster child of what it means.
Because Donald Trump's addressing an audience,
you know, he's in a debate with Hillary,
or he's giving a speech someplace,
and when the people that are devoted to him,
when they believe that what he's just said
is completely right, it's insightful.
They look at him or they look at the TV
and they go "That's right."
And it's what people say
when they're bought-in to what they just heard.
Now if you're not convinced of the way
that Donald Trump's followers are bonded to him,
and he also just like this, in my view,
destroys the idea of common ground.
Because when he first started to run for president,
the pundits all said, "Ah, he's a New Yorker.
Nobody in the Republican party's gonna like him.
It's middle America," you know, "it's blue collar,"
you know, "it's regular common folks, factory workers.
They're not gonna like Trump 'cause he's from New York.
And he went to Warden, he's an Ivy Leaguer,
and he's a son of a wealthy real estate mogul.
And he had a million dollars handed to him
when he got outta college.
He," you know, "he's born with a silver spoon in his mouth.
The Rankin-fire Republicans
are never gonna accept this guy."
Based on common ground.
Look how smart that was.
- Do you think he's a good negotiator?
Do you think Donald Trump was a good negotiator?
- No, I think he's a great marketer.
If you look at his negotiation track record.
All right, so I started following Donald Trump
in the '80s when I was in New York.
I'm a last century guy, he's a last century guy.
We've got mutual acquaintances.
The minister that married him to Marla Maples
was a friend of mine, a close friend of mine.
And in 1998 I threw a fundraiser in his apartment
at Trump Tower that he attended.
So no shortage of mutual friends.
We went to the same church.
Still have mutual acquaintances, friends.
And I've watched his track record negotiation history,
which is exactly his track record with North Korea.
Where are we with North Korea?
What was the deal that he made with North Korea?
See, your answer is the same as everybody else's.
Well, I remember it started out with a lot of fanfare.
But I don't know what happened,
'cause nothing ever happens.
- There's more public fanfare,
so marketing-minded presentation-
- Starts out with a bang.
If he doesn't cut the deal in a short period,
a really short period of time he moves on
and everybody wonders what had happened
because there was so much fanfare at the beginning.
Now at the beginning,
him even opening that dialogue with North Korea
was masterful.
Like, I was such a fan.
When you got a president of the United States
that is willing to sit down and talk with the leader
of another nation, when every other president,
all our advisors are saying,
"The leader of North Korea is beneath you.
You cannot dignify him by responding to him directly."
And consequently the Trump administration
inherits a can of worms
that has been simmering for 30 years.
He didn't get us into that.
And he opened up a dialogue
where nobody else was capable of opening a dialogue
and then it just went away.
Nobody knows what happened.
And there was no deal made.
Now great negotiators make deals.
- What do you think about these accusations
that he's a narcissist?
If you're a narcissist, does that help you or hurt you?
- Is there a more popular term these days than narcissist?
Like everybody's a narcissist.
- Everybody you don't like is a narcissist.
- Like the homeless guy down on the corner,
he's a narcissist, that's why he is there.
- Yeah, it's lost meaning for you a little bit?
- Yeah, and first of all,
most psychological terms,
as a hostage negotiator, and really
we were never into psychology
and we steered away from it,
'cause psychology at best is soft science.
If it's not informed these days,
if it's not informed by real studies
or neuroscience, the guys
that I'm impressed with these days,
are psychologist neuroscientists,
now I'm interested in that guy or gal.
But then a psychology convention,
do you get 'em all together and they all agree?
- No. - No.
- But also the interesting thing about psychology
is each individual person is way more complicated
than the category psychology tries to create.
And there's something about the human brain.
The moment you classify somebody as a narcissist,
or depressed or bipolar, or insane in any kind of way,
for some reason you don't,
you give yourself a convenient excuse
not to see them as a complicated human being
to empathize with 'em.
I had that when I was talking to,
I did an interview with Kanye West
and then there's a lot of popular opinions
about him being mentally unwell and so on,
and I felt that that kind of way of thinking
is a very convenient way of thinking
to ignore the fact that he's a human being
that, again, wants to be understood and heard.
And that's the only way you can have that conversation.
- Yeah, I agree completely.
That's right.
(Lex laughing)
I feel so close to you now.
(both laughing)
- It might 'cause I'm not wearing pants.
(Chris laughing)
All right, so, what were we-
- You're funnier than I am. That bothers me.
- All right. (laughing)
I'll say something stupid soon enough.
Don't worry about it.
But you said, we were talking about terrorists
and not negotiating with terrorists.
Is there something- - Nice job
going all the way back to where that rabbit hole started.
- Oh, sh, where's rabbit,
we're "Alice in Wonderland" right now.
Is there something about walking away?
Of not negotiating?
Is there power in that?
- All right, so it depends
upon whether or not you're doing it with integrity
or a tactic to start with.
And then also,
hostage negotiators are successful 93% of the time,
kind of across the board.
Which means that there's 7% of the time it's gonna go bad.
And that was my old boss, Gary Noesner,
I learned so much from Gary.
But a phrase that he used over and over and over again
until I finally worked a case that went bad,
was "This is gonna be the best chance of success."
Best chance of success.
And then something went bad, and I remember thinking,
like, "Well best chance of success
is no guarantee of success."
So your question is,
are there negotiations you should walk away from?
If you got no shot at success, then don't negotiate.
And you have to accept the fact
there's some deals you're never gonna make.
You know, we teach in my company,
it's not a sin to not get the deal.
It's a sin to take a long time to not get the deal.
And, you know, Gary, in his infinite wisdom, you know,
they realized that there was something
called suicide-by-cop,
and that it might have,
Gary was very much into clusters of behavior,
he kept us away from psychological terms
and there would be clusters of behavior
that would be high-risk indicators.
And he wrote a block of instruction
called high-risk indicators.
Which meant if you start seeing this stuff show up,
this thing's probably going bad.
And you're gonna need to,
you're gonna need to recognize that from the very beginning
and adjust accordingly.
And it's the same way in business and personal life.
I'm talking to a head of a marketing company
I had tremendous respect for,
I admire what this guy and his company does,
started from scratch.
He borrowed space in the back of a drugstore
to start his company.
And now it's hugely successful.
And he's laying out to me
that he finally had to confront a potential client
and walk away from him.
And he said, "How do you think I handled this?"
And my answer was, "1,000% correct.
And as a matter of fact,
the behavior that he indicated, he's a type,
and you should have walked away sooner than you did,
because this guy was playing it all the time."
Al-Qaeda, 2004, they're playing us.
They're not negotiating.
We called them out on it.
We don't think you're negotiating.
You wouldn't say it exactly like that,
but that was absolutely the approach, you know,
confront people on their behavior in a respectful way.
- And signal that you're willing to walk away.
- And mean it, 1,000%.
- And mean it. Isn't that terrifying?
I mean, it's scary,
'cause you don't want to really walk away,
or do you have to really want to walk away?
- Well, yeah, this core values your view of reality.
If it's an abundant world, it's not scary to walk away.
If it's a finite world with limited opportunities,
then it's horrifying.
- (sighs) But you have to use that worldview
to be willing to actually walk away.
- [Chris] Yeah.
- It could be walking away from a lot of money.
It could be walking away from something
that's gonna hurt people,
'cause if you lose a hostage.
- Yeah, well, but if they're not gonna let the hostage out?
Suicide-by-cop, they ain't letting him go.
- The 7%. How do most negotiations fail?
- The bad guys were never there
to make a deal in the first place.
If it was suicide-by-cop.
If they were there to, if they're on a killing journey,
it's an Israeli phrase.
If they're on a killing journey
and the actions that they're currently engaged in
are part of that killing journey.
- Killing journey.
Is there advice you can give about,
you mentioned Israel Palestine, the Middle East,
taking on a few conversations on that topic.
Is there hope for that part of the world?
And from that hope, is there some advice you could lend?
- Yeah, I think there's hope, there's.
Then I got friends on both sides,
and also, when I got my,
after I left the FBI,
most people listened to this,
but probably not gonna remember
who Rodney Dangerfield was.
- [Lex] Oh, come on.
- But he's a comedian.
- Still doesn't get any respect, yeah.
- [Chris] Yeah, yeah.
- New Yorker? Is he a New Yorker?
- I think he was a New York guy.
- [Lex] Or like Jersey, or something, yeah.
- Yeah, and he did a movie a long time ago,
called "Back to School."
He went back to school as an old guy, back to school.
So I went back to school after I left the FBI.
I did get a masters at Harvard Kennedy.
And that's where, you know,
I'm running across people on both sides of that.
And when they could talk, they said,
"Let's start from the premise that both sides
want a better life for our kids."
Which is this version that I was telling you earlier
from Tom Girardi, let's pick a point in the future
that we're all happy with.
And they found that they could talk, you know.
All right, so it might not be better for us.
How do we make it better for our kids?
And that's where the hope derives from.
Because I think both sides ultimately
want it to be better for their kids,
which is why they still engage in interactions,
and which is why I think the leadership,
regardless of how compromised they might be on either side,
there're few straight players in the game
in the Middle East, or anywhere for that matter,
but they want a better future for their kids.
You get people to agree
that you want a better future for your kids,
now you can start talking about,
"Well, how do we work our way back from that?"
And then, all right, so we got a mutual point in the future.
The Israeli Palestinian negotiations
are also for me interesting,
'cause you mentioned Clubhouse.
About almost two years ago now,
when Israel was shelling Gaza.
They hit the UPI office.
You know, they were hitting,
they got fed up with the rocket attacks from Hamas.
And of course Hamas is putting rockets in the UPI office
or the AP office, whichever press office it was there.
How's that office gonna be there otherwise?
Hamas is running the show.
You're not gonna run that office unless they let you,
unless you let them store weapons there.
That's just part of the game.
And are they gonna,
are they gonna store 'em
in specially designated ammunition dumps?
No, they're gonna put 'em in schools,
they're gonna put 'em in hospitals,
they're gonna put 'em in all places
that when Israel hits 'em, they're gonna look really bad.
So after a while,
Israel gets fed up, they start shelling Gaza
and they're hitting these places.
Friend of mine, Nicole Behnam,
is hosting rooms on Clubhouse and she says,
"You gotta come on. The vitriol is killing me.
These are all turning into screaming matches.
Nobody's talking to anybody."
I said, "All right, cool.
We'll go on, we'll do it,
and watch, we won't have a single argument.
And we'll invite people on from both sides."
There was one rule.
Before you started to describe
what you thought of the other side,
you had to say, "Before I disagree with you,
here's what I think your position is."
And you gotta continue to state the other side's position
until they agree that you it.
Now what happened?
No agreement and no arguments.
That was what we were really going for.
We wanted to show that people on both sides
in one of their emotional timeframes,
if your only requirement
was you had to state the other side's position first,
nobody got outta control.
- Did it work?
- That's exactly what happened.
We wanted to show people that you can have conversations
that do not devolve into screaming matches
with vitriol, talking about how you're dedicated
to the destruction of the other side.
Just first see if you can outline where they're coming from.
- That's really impressive because I've just,
having seen on Clubhouse,
people, which part of the reason I liked Clubhouse,
'cause you get to hear voices from all sides,
they were emotionally intense.
(laughs) It was, I mean, I was,
I'm sweating just in the buildup of your story here.
I thought it's gonna go to hell.
But you're saying it kind of worked.
- Not one person lost control.
Now of the two sides,
the people that were speaking
on behalf of the Israelis were a little better
at articulating supportive positions for the Palestinians.
Most of the people that wanna speak up
on behalf of the Palestinians, they just,
they'd wanna start in like, "You're doing this."
And I'd say, "No, no, no, no.
You can go there, just not yet.
Before you go there,
you can say that all you want.
you've gotta try to articulate to them
where they're coming from.
They gotta tell you you got it right."
And what would consistently happen
is there's a leveling out of a person
to try to see the other side's perspective
and articulate it.
It's enormously beneficial to the person
who's trying to do it.
Which was really the point that we were trying to make.
- It's a really interesting exercise.
I mean, that by way of advice.
So if it works at Clubhouse, for people who don't know,
that's a sort of like a voice app
where you can be anonymous.
So it's really regular people,
but regular people who can also be anonymous.
It's just, it could be chaos.
If it works there, that's really interesting
for when you sit down for a conversation
across the table from somebody.
Don't have them even steal me on the other side,
have them just state the other side.
Just explained your understanding of it.
That's it.
- And every now and then I would jump in,
like, you know, "And is somebody supporting Israel?"
You know, whoever the heck they were.
And they'd say a couple things.
And the Palestinian guy would be like, "Ah,"
or gal, or a supportive of them, would say, you know,
"You missed some stuff."
And I'd say, "Let me jump in.
First of all, I know what the Nakba is.
The Nakba is a catastrophe.
That's the day Israel was born.
You, you know, for the rest of the world
it's the birth of Israel, for you it's the Nakba."
I said, "You've got members of your family
that is still walking around carrying keys
to the front door of the house they abandoned."
And he'd be like, "Yeah."
And I'd say, "You feel bad that,
in point of fact,
that in World War II the world stood back
and watched while the Nazis
threw the Jews off a building.
The only problem was they landed on you."
And they'd be like,
"Yeah, that's where they're coming from."
So articulating, you know,
deeply what the other side feels
is transformative for both people involved in a process.
- What's the toughest negotiation you've ever been a part of
or maybe observed or heard of?
What's a difficult case
that just stands out to you?
Or maybe just one of many.
- Well, the stuff we went through
with Al-Qaeda in and around Iraq,
Iraq in Saudi, first one was in Saudi, 2004 timeframe.
The hardest part about that was working with family members
and not deceiving them about the possibility of the outcome.
- Yeah, how do you talk to family members?
Is that part of the negotiation?
- Yeah, empathy, learning empathy the hard way.
And then being able to take it up to higher levels.
'Cause at its base level,
a guy that we're working with now
that's coaching us in the US and is a business partner,
his name is Jonathan Smith,
he pointed out to us that there's kinda,
there's a Shu Ha Ri concept.
Are you familiar with Shu Ha Ri?
It's a martial arts concept.
And Shu is, do it exactly
as the master's telling you to do it.
Wax on, wax off, "Karate Kid" stuff.
Ha is, when you've done the repetitions enough times,
you're getting a feel for it,
and you begin to see the same lessons
coming from other masters.
You're seeing the same thing show up in other places.
And at the Ri level, you're still in the discipline,
but you're making up your own rules.
It's almost a flow state.
And you don't realize that you're making up your own rules.
And if somebody asks you, "Where'd you learn that?"
You probably say, "I," you know,
"my sensei taught it to me, my master taught it to me."
This will come back around the negotiating
with families pretty quick.
We did this once because, there's a bunch of people
that we coach, business people,
that are scared of the amount of money
that they're losing if we're not coaching 'em regularly.
One of these guys, Michael,
we're interviewing him for a social media posting
about two years ago and Michael says,
"Yeah, you know, you gotta gather data with your eyes."
And I remember, and I went, "Woo, I like that."
I said, "Where did you hear that before?"
And he goes, "I, you know, I don't know.
I heard it from you, I think."
And I'm like, "No, no, no, no.
(Lex laughing)
I'd have remembered saying that.
- Yeah.
- That's the first time I've heard that.
He's in Ri.
So what's this got to do with families?
Empathy, at its base level and the Shu level,
I learned it on the suicide hotline,
is saying like, "You sound angry."
I'm just calling out the elephant in the room.
Your emotions. What's driving you?
I'm throwing a label on your affect
and I'm saying, "You sound," or "It sounds like you are."
'Cause that's the basic "Karate Kid"
wax on, wax off approach.
Now there are a lot of hostage negotiators
that'll tell you empathy doesn't work at home.
Not true.
They've never gotten outta Shu.
You're getting ready to talk to your significant other
and you wanna go someplace that you know
is gonna make her angry.
You wanna go do something.
- Now that's real negotiation right there.
- You could say to her, "You sound angry."
In which case she's gonna blow up,
'cause her reaction is,
"You made me angry, bozo.
How can you act like you're an innocent third party?
Or that you were independent of how I feel bad."
And you learn a little bit more,
and you say, the high level is,
"This is probably gonna make you angry."
And then, what I did with families,
I knew how they felt before I walked in the door.
I knew that they were scared to death.
You find out that your husband, your father,
your brother has been grabbed by Al-Qaeda,
who are in the business of chopping people's heads off,
you're gonna be horrified.
I can't walk into them and go like, "You sound angry."
"Of course I'm angry, you idiot."
But knowing what they are,
I used to walk into family's houses and I'd say,
"I know you're angry."
Now what do the circumstances dictate
that they should also feel?
They're gonna feel abandoned by their government.
They're gonna feel totally alone.
They're gonna be scared and they're gonna be angry
because they feel the government abandoned them.
Now they're, in point of fact,
is this an accurate statement?
That their loved one voluntarily went into a war zone
and voluntarily went someplace
their government told them not to go.
Are the facts that the government abandoned them?
Absolutely not.
As a matter of fact, the government warned 'em,
tried to get 'em to not go and they went anyway.
But that doesn't change how they felt in a moment.
And I'd walk into a house and I'd go,
"I know you're angry.
I know you feel abandoned and alone
and I know you're horrified
and I know you feel the United States government
has abandoned you."
And they would look at me and go like, "Yeah.
What do we do now?"
Now we're ready to rock.
- Is there, with Al-Qaeda or in general,
is there a language barrier too?
It could be just barriers or different communication styles.
I mean, you got like a New Yorker way about it.
(Chris laughs)
That might make somebody from like, I don't know,
Laguna Beach uncomfortable.
(Chris laughs)
Do you feel that language barrier in communication?
Is that language and communication style in itself
creating a barrier?
- You got a barrier when you think that your way is the way.
- [Lex] Sure, that's the biggest barrier.
- Yeah, like, and that happens all the time.
When people talk about,
"What about cross-cultural negotiations?"
You know, "What hand do I gotta shake hands with,
so that I can get my way?"
Well, if you strip it all down,
we're all basically the same blank slate when we were born.
We got, everybody's got a limbic system.
Everybody's limbic system works pretty much the same way.
People are driven by the same sorts of decisions.
How's this affect my future?
What am I risk of losing?
How does this affect my identity?
You're a Al-Qaeda kidnapper,
you're a New York City businessman,
you're a tobacco farmer in the south,
all making those same decisions based on those same things.
So as soon as I start to navigate that
and I tailor my approach,
which is what empathy is,
to what you think and how you see things.
So I can be the biggest goofball ever
from, if you live in the south, yeah,
maybe I'm a New Yorker,
or I'm somebody from LA or somebody from Chicago,
but my geography is foreign to you,
but as soon as I start dialing in
on how you see things, suddenly you're listening.
- What about the three voices you talk about?
The different voices you can use in that communication?
- Right. The assertive's voice, direct and honest.
I'm a natural born assertive.
- Natural born. I thought we're all a blank slate.
If you're born- - Well, yeah.
That's it, stop catching me on what I said.
How dare you throw, accuse me of what I've said?
To quote Bono, "I stand accused of what I've said,
the things I've said."
- That's a good line.
(Chris laughs)
He's got a few good lines.
So assertive voice.
You're born that way.
Which one, what are the other ones?
- Analyst.
You're an analyst.
- And I could tell you're assertive.
(both laughing)
What's an analyst's voice?
- Well, an analyst is close- - Smarter.
(Chris laughs) More thoughtful. (laughs)
- No, as a matter of fact. (laughs)
Look, you ever do a decision tree?
- Yeah. - See,
you like it too, don't you?
- So a decision tree is, you know,
I'm a computer scientist, so the way I have,
I like mathematical, systematic ways of seeing the world.
- [Chris] (laughs) You're just an analyst.
- (laughs) Yeah.
- You think Donald Trump would ever say that?
Unlikely.
- (laughs) What, is he more the assertive kind?
- [Chris] He's a natural born assertive, yeah.
- Yeah. Are all New Yorkers like this?
Is this something in the water or?
- Nah, it's the craziest thing.
I mean, there's an affect that a city can have.
And, you know, New York's Northeast, not just New York,
but the Northeast is a little more the affect
of the area, of the culture of the area.
The individuals,
individuals still boil down into the three types,
across the board.
- [Lex] What's the third one?
- Accommodator. Smiling, optimistic, hopeful.
I'm 1,000% convinced that the phrase
hope is not a strategy
is designed at people's frustration
over a third of the population being accommodators
that are hope driven.
I hope this works out.
And they're very relationship, on the surface,
they're very relationship oriented.
They tend to appear to be very positive.
And they are, but it's really built around hope.
- And the idea is you can adopt these three voices when-
- You can, yeah, you can learn 'em.
They're all learnable.
Analysts are often mistaken for accommodators
because, as you said before, you know,
analysts are more introspective, more analytical.
They're looking at the systems at work.
And, if they like to learn,
they notice that accommodators make more deals
than they make.
They also notice that there's a higher failure rate
of the deals.
But since they notice stuff and they think about it,
they catch on faster than assertives do.
That the pleasant nature of an accommodator
contributes strongly to them making deals.
Like my daughter-in-law, is an analyst.
You know, another descriptor we have,
an analyst are assassins.
You know, an analyst will snip you
from a thousand yards out in the middle of the night
and you never know what hits you.
And they're really happy with that.
(Lex laughs)
- But how has assertiveness, the assertive voice
served you in negotiation?
- Poorly.
The assertive voice is almost always counterproductive.
It feels like getting hit in the face with a brick.
And that's almost always counterproductive.
So for me to be more effective, especially in a negotiation,
I'll need to slow down and smile.
- You know, I heard that Teddy Roosevelt
was a good negotiator and that he was extremely stubborn,
and perhaps the right term for that would be assertive,
but he picked his battles.
Is there some value
to holding strong through principles?
So, I don't even know if,
that's probably the opposite of empathy,
are there times when you can just stick,
be extremely stubborn to your principles to win-
- Oh, we do it all the time.
We just, you know, we're just nice about it.
- [Lex] Okay, it helps to be nice, you're saying?
- Well, yes, because I need you to hear me.
And the assertive tone of voice.
So when we do our training,
typically we do an exercise called 60 seconds or she dies.
And I play the bad guy bank robber.
And I ask you to be the hostage negotiator.
And your job is to, I'll give you
the four real-world constraints.
And then you gotta try and negotiate me out of the bank.
Now we're doing this.
Now the first voice that I always use in that exercise
is the assertive's voice, which is the commanding voice.
It's the voice that all police officers are taught
to use in the street.
Issue loud and clear commands.
You know, it doesn't, to me,
I don't feel like I'm attacking you.
I just feel like I'm being direct and honest and clear.
You, on the other hand, feel attacked.
Now we're doing this exercise in Austin couple of years ago.
The first participant has an Apple watch on.
He tells us afterwards
that sitting still, not even answering,
when he first gets hit in the face
with the assertive's voice, his heart rate jumped to 170,
which is a typical fight or flight reaction.
I come at you like I'm fighting you.
Your fight/flight mechanisms all kick into gear,
which clouds you're thinking.
You're automatically dumber in the moment.
So if I wanna make a great long term deal with you,
highly profitable, I'm agnostic to you being profitable.
Listen, you be profitable, well, that's fine.
I'm here to make money for me.
Me making you dumber will always hurt me.
Me making you feel attacked will always hurt me.
- So there's never a value in being,
in you making me afraid?
- There's never a long term value in it.
That's another thing that Tahl Raz,
when we were writing a book, braced me on,
'cause he said,
"There's scientific data out there
that's called strategic umbrage."
Well, there's data.
Well, whether or not it's scientific,
I would call that into question.
But he said there's studies out there
that show that strategic umbrage works.
And another thing that I also enjoy,
you probably get tired of me
saying wonderful things about Andrew.
He talked- - There's never,
there's never enough wonderful things to say
about the great Andrew Huberman,
the host of the Huberman Lab podcast
that everybody should subscribe to.
You should talk to Andrew.
- You're funnier than he is though.
I'll give you that.
- Hear that Andrew? - He's funny accidentally.
He makes me laugh all the time.
Not when he is trying to be funny. (laughs)
- Yeah, he's a really,
he's one of the people in this world that's truly legit.
He's a really strong scientist
and a really strong communicator
and a good human being.
Those together don't come often.
And it's nice to see.
- [Chris] Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, he's a treasure, a national treasure.
Anyway, you were saying.
- Well, he sort of taught me how to think about data
and studies and science,
and also from different books
that he's turned me onto,
he's really helped me think about this stuff.
So the studies about strategic umbrage were done,
the ones that I've seen, that show it's effective,
they were simulated negotiations with college students.
Now here's the problem with that.
A simulated negotiation with a college student.
College students are gonna sit down
as part of their assignment.
They're gonna sit down one time,
they're gonna sit down for 45 minutes,
and they're gonna think
that if they didn't come to a deal at all,
that they failed.
And there's no ongoing implementation,
there's just the deal,
and then they walk away from a pretend situation.
So they got no actual real skin in the game.
There's no deal on earth
do you sit down and come to an agreement in 45 minutes
and never see each other again,
'cause there's the implementation of the deal.
Even if it's only payment.
So the data is flawed based on the way it was collected.
It's a highly flawed study,
and all data is flawed as you know, as a scientist.
You just gotta be aware what the flaws are
and decide whether or not that destroys the study.
Or what do you think if you take a look at the data,
there's no such thing as perfect data.
Look at the data, see what you think of it.
The data that says that strategic umbrage works
is based on flawed circumstances.
- [Lex] Can you explain strategic umbrage?
- Getting mad, scaring the other side into a deal.
Getting mad and using anger strategically
to bully the other side into an agreement.
- That's nice to hear, in some sense.
It's nice to hear that empathy is the right way
in almost all situations.
It's nice. - Best chance of success.
Not that it works every time,
just it works more than anything else does.
- What is the technique of mirroring?
There's a lot of cool stuff in your book.
Let's just kind of jump around.
What's mirroring?
- Mirroring is like,
it's one of the most fun skills
because it's the simplest to execute.
You just repeat one to three-ish words
of what somebody said,
usually the last one to three words.
What I found about it
is the people that really like mirroring,
love it because it's so simple
and so effortless and invisible.
They typically, for lack of a better term,
tend to be both high IQ and high EQ.
Like, I'm not a high IQ guy.
I'm an average dude.
I like to think that I can learn.
In EQ, emotional intelligence is a skill you can build.
And I'm always working on building it.
But a lot of really regular average people
will be like, "Mirroring, that's stupid.
I'm not doing that."
And I don't know why they don't like it.
But when I find somebody that loves to mirror,
I'll always ask 'em, you know,
"How'd you score on IQ?"
And typically their IQ is pretty high.
Now I don't know why that combination attracts people
to mirroring, 'cause there's nine skills.
Eight from hostage negotiation,
and the ninth really was tone of voice
and we just defined that as a skill.
And each one is different and focuses
on different components of the conversation.
And a lot of people don't like to mirror.
They find it so awkward.
Like, I don't particularly,
I'm not particularly strong in mirroring,
I gotta do it intentionally.
I'm good at labeling.
- But does it almost always work?
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah. It feels maybe awkward, but there's,
it's true, there's gotta be ways to signal
that you're truly listening.
- [Chris] That's part of it.
- I think you can do body language, you can, yeah.
There's a lot of ways to signal that,
but mirroring is probably just this trivial little hack.
- It kinda is.
- You know what, there's a situation.
I had a conversation with Stephen Kotkin,
he's this historian
and he would say my name
a lot throughout the conversation.
He would be like, "Well, you have to understand Lex."
Is that?
And for some reason that was making me feel really good.
I was like, "He cares about me."
And I wonder if that key, if everyone has that key,
that could be a name.
Just using people's name could be powerful.
- Using the name is really context driven.
It can be extremely powerful
with someone who's genuine,
and it comes across in their demeanor,
and it's used in a way that you can tell
is meant to encourage you.
As opposed to exploit you.
And the people that are really into exploiting
will also use it to do the same thing.
- So you have to be,
(chuckles) you have to avoid using the things
that people that are exploiters manipulators use.
'Cause it might signal to others
that this person is trying to trick me.
- Gotta be very conscious of it, yeah.
- What's labeling, that you mentioned, the thing you like?
- Well, you know, I said earlier
that whole progression from you sound angry,
to this is probably gonna make you angry,
to I know you're angry.
Labeling is hanging a label on an emotion or an affect
and then just calling it out.
- Is that almost always good?
Could it be a source of frustration
when a person's being angry
and you kind of put a label on it,
call out the elephant. (sighs)
Is it possible that that will lead to escalation
of that feeling versus a resolution?
- Well, what would make it bad?
Like, if I'm pointing out like that blatantly obvious.
Like if I say, "Look, I need you to get up
and go down to the bank and make the deposit."
Let's say I'm talking to my,
somebody who works for my company.
"I need you to get on the phone with this person
and make the appointment."
And they go,
"Sounds like you want me to talk to this person."
Yes. (Lex laughs)
That would be annoying.
If it's just so absurdly obvious,
that there's no insight in your label at all.
And as soon as you're demonstrating an awareness
or a subtlety or an insight, either to you or to them,
now we're making progress.
So the only time a label
could ever potentially be counterproductive
is like if you weren't actually listening,
and the label is, indicates that you're not listening.
You know, I'm teaching at USC
and I'm teaching labels and, you know,
one of the kids in a class,
he just wants to take the skills
and make his deals and just hustle 'em,
and he's just looking for a hustle.
So he writes up a paper about, you know,
he goes, there's some malls,
I think over by Palm Springs or someplace,
some outlet malls, a lot of people go to buy suits.
So he goes in there and he immediately starts the bargaining
that my book teaches, with no empathy.
And he's like, throws a price to the guy
and the guy's like, "No."
And he throws another price to the guy and guy's like, "No!"
And then he says to the guy behind the counter,
"Sounds like we can make a deal."
Like no, it doesn't.
I just shot down everything that you just said.
If anything, it sounds like we're never gonna make a deal.
But he tried to use this label for manipulation.
Now the guy didn't get mad on the other side,
but it's like clearly this dude is not listening to me.
- And at the core of everything,
you have a bunch of like, you know,
almost like hacks, like techniques you can use.
But at the core of it is empathy.
At the- - Core of it is empathy.
Yeah. - That's the main thing.
You're gotta be able to just sit there and listen.
- And perceive.
Yeah, and look for insights.
- You know what, I like silence.
Or like you're both sitting there chilling with a drink,
looking up at the stars.
There's a moment the silence
makes you kind of zoom out
and realize you're in this together.
As opposed to playing a game,
or some kind of like chess game of a negotiation.
You're in it together. I don't know.
There's some intimacy to the silence.
And like, I'll ask a question,
and just let the other person sit there in silence
before they answer or vice versa.
They ask me a question,
I sit there in silence.
That's a big, feels like a big intimate thing.
- Yes.
And the other two types,
until they've experienced that, are afraid of it.
And what I'm actually gonna do is,
for whatever reason, I'm really comfortable with silence.
I think because I've experienced its effectiveness.
And also my son Brandon,
like he's the king of dynamic silence.
Like he coaches people.
He says "Go silent, count thousands to yourself.
Don't stop till you run out of numbers."
- (laughs) That's a good line.
He's also good, full of good lines.
- He is. That he is.
And so there's so much to it.
But the other two types are natural wiring against it,
until they've experienced it.
And you know, your gut instinct,
intuition's giving you data,
once you've experienced it.
But your amygdala is kicking into gear,
again, sorry, I realize it's more complicated than that,
until you've experienced it.
So accommodators, hope-based.
How do they signal fury?
The silent treatment.
So when you go silent,
they're scared to death you're furious.
'Cause that's how they indicate it.
The assertive thinks to use the analyst when silent,
'cause you want 'em to talk some more.
When a point of fact you're either,
you're thinking or,
and I love your description,
the feeling of intimacy in silence
and experiencing the moment,
'cause I'm actually gonna factor that into trying to get.
The accommodators love shared intimacy,
they would love to experience a moment.
And I can see that being very compelling,
than be willing to cross that chasm
and experience silence and see how it works for 'em.
- Yeah, it's nerve wracking.
Which is why it's intimate.
'Cause you start thinking,
"What's the other person thinking?
Are we actually gonna do this?
Are we gonna sit here for 10 seconds and count?
I mean, there's tricks to it, I guess,
like Brandon says, is to just count it out
and realize through data that there's intimacy to it.
I had a friend of mine,
he lost his voice 'cause singing.
So he couldn't, the doctor said he can't talk
for a week just to heal the voice.
The vocal chords.
But he hung out with other people,
with friends, and didn't talk to them.
He just hung out and he said it was really intimate.
They both didn't talk to each other.
They just sat there and enjoyed time together.
I don't know. It's a wake up call.
It's a thing to try maybe with people in your life,
just hang out and don't say anything.
Like as an experiment,
don't say anything the entire day, but spend.
- [Chris] Or try. Yeah, definitely.
- It's interesting.
I haven't tried it myself. (laughs)
It seems, it's kinda like a silent retreat,
but more active as part of like regular everyday life.
Anyway. (laughs)
Is there other interesting techniques
we can talk about here?
So for example,
creating the illusion of control.
- Yeah, that's principally, you know,
by asking what and how questions.
'Cause people love to tell others
what to do or how to do it.
It does a lot.
That was really the way, when the book was first written,
that we really thought about what and how questions,
is giving the other side the illusion of control.
And there's a lot more to it than that,
that we've discovered.
I mean it triggers deep thinking.
It wears people down.
Deep thinking can be exhausting.
- And you want, so what's the role
of exhaustion in negotiation?
Is that ultimately-
- You gotta be careful with that.
Some people exhaust intentionally.
One of my negotiation heroes,
a guy now who's unfortunately suffering
from dementia and Alzheimer's,
Giandomenico Picco is the UN hostage negotiator
that got all the western hostages out of Beirut in the '80s.
And he wrote a book called "Man Without a Gun."
And I'm acquainted with Gianni, at this point in time,
I don't think he has any memory of who I am at all.
But he writes in his book,
one of the great secrets of negotiation
is exhausting the other side.
Political negotiations, that could be Gianni,
was very deferential.
He was in the middle of,
in the '80s leading up to about 1986-ish,
every negotiation involving
waring parties in the Middle East that you can imagine.
He was in Cyprus.
He was in Afghanistan,
Iraq and Iran.
The Iranian government had tremendous trust in him
as a westerner, a representative of the UN.
Got all the westerners out of Beirut
and he was just ridiculously patient.
And then, which the other side found,
would often find exhausting.
- So exhaustion can't be a component
of finding resolution in a negotiation.
- If it tamps down the negative emotions,
often exhaustion will tamp down negative emotions.
And if it puts you,
and getting, the real trick
is really getting negative emotions out of the way.
'Cause you're dumber in a negative frame of mind.
- So the goal is always positive emotion as you talk about.
That's what you're always chasing together.
- [Chris] I think so. Yeah.
- And that's what the that's right is about.
- [Chris] Yes.
- Like whatever you're triggering,
whatever the chemistry you're triggering in your brain,
you're like, "Yeah, yeah, we're doing good here."
- Yeah, I think so, long term for long term success.
Absolutely.
- How's the word fair used and abused?
- [Chris] The F-bomb.
- The F bomb as you call it.
How is it used in abused in negotiation?
- It's usually used,
it's most frequently used as a weapon.
It's abused as a point of manipulation.
It's what people say when they feel backed into a corner
and they can't come up with any legitimate reason
as to why they're being backed into a corner.
Like nobody uses the word F, the F-bomb,
nobody uses the word fair
when they've got criteria to back 'em up.
So consequently, when somebody starts dropping it,
you gotta realize the other side's
got no legitimate outside criteria.
They're feeling very vulnerable.
They can't explain it, but they feel defensive.
And saying, "Hey look, I've just,
I've given you a fair offer,"
is a way for me to knock you off your game
if you're not not aware of it.
So a lot of cutthroat negotiations,
negotiators are gonna use it on you
to knock you off your game.
The NFL strike,
probably now, it's been a good 10 years ago,
and maybe even longer than that.
One of the sticking points was
the owners were not opening their books to the players.
Players wanted to see the numbers.
And in order to not open their books,
they just sent a rep to tell the press conference
saying, "We've given the players a fair offer."
Well, if it was fair, you'd open your books.
- (laughing) Yeah.
- If you gave 'em a fair offer and it was justified
by what was in your books,
you'd open 'em to prove your point.
So what ends up happening though, that, well,
the owners gave the players a fair offer
starts to get picked up in the media
and then it starts getting repeated.
And now the different people on a player's side
are going like,
"Yeah, maybe they have given us a fair offer."
It caused people to be insecure about their own positions.
It's an enormously powerful word
that can be used and abused.
And it almost always comes up in every negotiation.
It's shocking the number of times it comes up
with people who don't really understand
how or why it's coming up.
- So usually it's a signal
of not a good place in negotiations.
- Without question, I'm completely convinced
that if the person is using the word as a means
of getting what they want,
then either accidentally or on purpose,
either in their gut or they know
they got a bad a position,
or their gut is afraid that they are.
Do I use the word?
What I'll say is, "I want you to feel
like I've treated you fairly,
and if at any given point in time
you think I'm not treating you fairly,
I want you to stop me and we're gonna address it."
- Big ridiculous question.
But how do you close the deal?
How do you take the negotiation to its end?
Is implementation ultimately-
- You gotta pivot to agreed upon implementation,
to really move out on the negotiation.
And I may say, "How do you wanna proceed?"
And if you don't know, I might say,
"No one to question, is it a ridiculous idea
if I share with you some ideas of how to proceed?"
- And then you agree on the actual steps,
and that's the implementation,
it's not just a philosophical agreement,
it's actual steps.
- The big problem in all negotiations
is a lack of discussion of next steps.
- That is deep.
Who is the best negotiator you've ever met?
- Yeah, actually probably my son, Brandon.
- Yeah? - Yeah.
He's ridiculously talented.
I mean, he's ridiculously talented.
And he, yeah, he's, you know,
and what was it, Coyle's book,
"The Talent Code," says that, you know,
people just noticed it and started getting good at it.
There's no such thing as a child prodigy.
They just got interested when they were a kid.
I mean, Brandon started learning how to negotiate
when he was two years old,
and he's been in it and immersed in it, you know,
since he could make complete sentences.
Even before he could make complete sentences.
He's ridiculously talented.
- What's his future?
What's he want to do?
- He has been involved.
He run and built my company
and now he's gonna be an affiliated licensee,
run his own operation.
He's pretty much gonna end up doing very much.
It's gonna open his entrepreneurial opportunities
to do whatever he wants
and not have his dad say no. (laughs)
- [Lex] And do a better job than his dad.
- Most likely.
- Yeah. (laughs)
Okay.
Do you see some of the techniques
that you talk about as manipulative?
- Manipulation is whether or not
I'm trying to exploit you or hurt you.
Am I trying to manipulate a bank robber
into letting me save his life?
Yeah.
So manipulation is like,
what am I trying to do to you?
- But so you don't see the negative connotation?
If you're trying to bring a better future,
it's not manipulation?
- It's not if I'm trying to bring a better future,
if I'm being genuine and honest,
like I compliment you.
If my compliment is genuine, that's not manipulation.
Like, and, but, you know, if I think,
you know, you got a pair of shoes
that are the dumbest looking things I've ever seen,
and I go, "Wow, those are great shoes."
Now that's manipulation.
- So there's guys like Warren Buffett
who are big on integrity and honesty.
What's the role of lying effective?
- I think it's a bad idea.
Lying is just a bad idea for a variety of reasons.
First of all,
there's a really good chance the other side
is a better liar than you are.
They're gonna spot it right off the bat.
Secondly, they could be luring you into a trap
to see if you will lie.
Thirdly, the chances are they're gonna find out
that you lied to 'em eventually is really high.
And then the penalties and the taxes are gonna be way higher
than what you had in the first place.
- So long term, you wanna have a reputation of somebody
with integrity and the more you lie,
the harder it is to maintain that reputation.
- Yeah, exactly. And words' gonna get out.
- Yeah, so what's the,
if we can just return to that question.
What's the difference between a good conversation
and a good negotiation?
Can we, because I think just reading your work,
listening to you, there's a sense I have
that the thing we're doing now,
in this conversation on the podcast and so on,
is different than negotiation.
It feels like the purpose is different
and yet having some of the same awareness
of the value of empathy is extremely important.
But it feels like the goals are different. Or no?
- Really close, fine line.
I mean, I, you know, I rolled in here
not having any expectations,
not looking for anything other
than having an interesting conversation.
And to hear what was behind the questions
that you were asking me and what interests you.
And then also your description of silence
and the power of silence.
Something I'm gonna take away as a learning point
and help learn to teach others.
But I didn't come in here.
I suppose a negotiation is when we're both aware
of a problem we're trying to solve.
- Right, there's no problem in the room
for us to solve.
Except maybe like the human condition and. (chuckles)
- [Chris] Insight, you know. Wisdom.
- Insight. - Learn.
- How do you train to become better at negotiating?
In business, in life.
- Yeah, just small stakes practice for high stakes results.
I mean, decide what kinda negotiating resonates with you.
I mean- - What's that mean?
Small stakes practice for high stakes or small stakes?
So small, little incremental,
like picking up girls at a bar,
or what are we talking about?
- Well, it can be for some people
that's high stakes practice.
Well, you know, labeling mirrors,
what are the basic tools of great negotiation?
Labeling, mirror, and paraphrasing, summarizing.
So you start labeling and mirroring people
that you just having regular interactions with,
just to gain a feel for
whether or not you can read somebody's affect,
or how accurate your read is
to get better at it.
And so, you know,
label the Lyft driver,
or the grocery store clerk,
or person behind the airline counter at the airport.
- So putting a label on their affect.
- Or throwing something at 'em that,
'cause negotiation is a perishable skill.
Emotional intelligence is perishable.
So seeing if you can indicate
that you understand their label.
One of my favorite labels to throw out on somebody,
which, you know, maybe Ri level,
I might look at somebody who looks distressed
and I'll go, "Tough day?"
So several years ago,
I'm at the counter at LAX.
Well, I'm waiting in the line to get to the counter
and a lady behind the counter
is clearly making it a point
to not meet my eyes so that I don't approach.
And she looks, and so like you, you know,
you know when you're next in line
and they're making sure that you don't meet eyes.
And I'm thinking to myself, "All right,
so they're having a bad day."
So I walk up and as soon as I approach the counter,
I go, "Tough day?"
And she kinda snaps around
and she goes, "No, no, no. How can I help you?"
And goes out of her way to help me.
Now I'm practicing, but I also know I made her feel better.
It relieved some of the stress.
So now I'm going through TSA,
wanna look for people who are having a tough day.
- [Lex] (laughs) It's a good place to find them.
- It's a good place to find and practice.
And I'm rolling through the line
and I realize I haven't tossed a label out
on any one of these guys.
And there's this guy watching the bags
come out of the x-ray machine
and he's just kind of got an indifferent look on his face.
And I go, "Tough day?"
And he kind of goes,
I could see from his body language like, no.
And I go, "Just another day, huh?"
And he goes, "Yeah, just another day."
You know, he felt seen but I missed
and I'm practicing and I'm trying to stay sharp.
So these are. - Just a few words.
With just a few words,
you're trying to like quickly localize their affect.
- Nice. - And deliver on it.
- Very analytically said, thank you.
(both chuckling)
I'm not letting it go.
- I love it.
(both laughing)
Does the same apply to just conversation in general?
Just how to get better at conversation.
I think a lot of people struggle.
They have insecurities,
they have anxiety about conversation.
I, as funny as this is to say,
have a lot of anxiety about conversation.
Is that, basically do the same kind of practice?
Practice some of the techniques in your book?
- Yeah, genuinely, just trying to make sure
you heard somebody out.
- What's the best conversation you've ever been in?
Except this one, of course.
(Chris laughs)
- [Chris] Wow.
- What, I mean, not the best conversation,
but what stands out to you
as a conversation that changed you as a person, maybe?
- Well, there's probably been a lot of them along the way.
I mean, but one that I remember on a regular basis.
Actually, there's two.
But when I was in the bureau,
I'm at Quantico, I'm there for an end services,
another guy from New York, buddy of mine named Lionel.
And we're both trying to decide
whether or not we wanna be,
try to get into profiling or negotiation
'cause they're both about human dynamics
and both of us really like human dynamics.
And we're sitting around talking about it
and we're talking about several things.
And he labels me.
And I knew he didn't know what he was doing,
I think he was just,
he had picked it up,
and I'd been talking about my family, quite a few things.
And he said to me,
and I never said this directly that we were close,
but he said to me,
"It sounds like your family's really close."
And I can remember in the moment like this feeling,
just, like I felt great in the moment.
I mean, what he said just drew together everything
that I'd been saying and nailed the essence of it.
And I have a very clear recollection
of how good that felt in the moment.
So a couple years later, I'm on a suicide hotline.
Now, I got this line in the back of my head,
you know, line, technique, reaction,
read, whatever you wanna call it.
Guy calls in on the hotline
and I could tell the dude is rattled by his tone of voice.
I mean, just amped up.
And he goes, you know,
"I'm just trying to put a lid on the day,
I need your help putting a lid on the day.
I gotta put a lid on the day."
And I go, "You sound anxious."
And he goes, "Yeah."
And he came down a little bit
and he was a guy that was, he was telling me about,
he was battling a disease of paranoia
and he is gonna go on a car trip
with his family the next day.
And he knew that on the car trip he was gonna, you know,
twist himself into knots.
And so the night before,
he is twisting himself into knots.
And he's laying out everything
that he is done to try to beat paranoia
and how much his family's helping him.
And he's going on the car trip with the family
'cause they're gonna take him to see a doctor.
And so I hit him with the same thing
that my buddy Lionel said.
I said, "It sounds like your family's close."
And he goes, "Yeah, we are close."
And he leveled out a little bit more.
And then he started ticking off all the things
that he was doing to try to beat paranoia.
And he sounded determined.
And so I said, "You sound determined."
And he goes, "Yeah, I am determined
and I'll be fine tomorrow.
Thanks."
And that was all I said.
So those two conversations,
which are overlapping conversations,
those two things really stick out in my mind.
- Do those things,
like through all the different negotiations
and conversations you've had,
do they kinda echo throughout?
Like you basically,
because when you empathize with other human beings,
you start to realize we're all the same.
And so you can start to pick
little phrases here and there
that you've heard from others,
little experiences that we're all about,
like, we all want to be,
to be close with other human beings.
We all want love.
That we're all,
I think we're all deeply lonely inside (laughs)
looking for connection.
We're just, if we're honest about it.
And so all humans have that same,
all the same different components
of what makes them tick.
So you kind of see yourself basically
just saying the same things
to connect with another human being?
- Yeah, there aren't that many different things
that we're looking for, or understanding on,
or connection on or satisfaction of.
There just aren't that many of them, regardless.
And so yeah, you're looking for,
to manifest itself in some form or another
and you're willing to take a guess
on whether or not that's what you're seeing or hearing.
- What advice would you give to me
to be better at these conversations?
To me and to other people
that do kinda interviews and podcasts and so on.
- [Chris] Wow.
- 'Cause I really care about empathy as well.
Is there a kind of,
there's a lifelong journey in this process?
- Yeah, well, I think,
I would advise you to take that approach,
which is the approach that you're taking.
You care about it, you're very curious about it.
You see it as a lifelong journey.
You're fascinated by it.
You enjoy learning about it.
And you definitely do see it as a lifelong journey
as opposed to this is what I can,
if I can acquire this, then I can manipulate people.
- No, I mean, I fall in love with people I talk to.
There's a kinda deep connection and it lingers with you,
especially when I'm preparing.
The more material there's on a person,
the more you get to fall in love with 'em ahead of time
that you get to really understand, not understand,
but what I mean by fall in love is.
- [Chris] Well, appreciate, huh?
- Appreciate but also become deeply curious.
That's what I mean by fall in love.
Like, you appreciate the things you know,
but you start to see, like "Alice in Wonderland,"
you start to see that there's all this cool stuff
you can learn if you keep interacting with them.
And then when you show up and you actually meet,
you realize it's like more and more and more and more.
It's like in physics, the more you learn,
the more you realize you don't know.
And it's like, it's really exciting.
And then it could also be heartbreaking,
'cause you have to say goodbye.
The goodbye, I hate goodbyes.
I hate goodbyes.
- Seems total, right?
- Yeah. It reminds me that I'm gonna die one day.
(laughs) Like things end,
good things end, it sucks.
But then it makes the moment more delicious, you know,
that you do get to spend together.
(laughs) Okay.
I just wanna, I completely forgot
I want to ask you about this.
The 7, 38, 55% rule.
(Chris laughs)
This is really interesting.
Does this,
is there at all truth to it,
that 7% of a message is conveyed from the words used,
38% from the tone of voice,
and 55% from body language?
Is there really truth to that?
- All right, so Albert Mehrabian,
I think is the name of the UCLA professor
that originally proposed
the 7, 38, 55 ratio and discussed it
in terms of that it wasn't the message,
but how much the, he called it liking,
like are you, not that you're,
the meaning is coming across,
but your liking of the message.
And so it's been extrapolated heavily
by people like me
to this meaning of the meaning,
in 7, 38, 55, from liking to the meaning.
What I've seen regularly
is people that communicate verbally,
if they're speakers, Tony Robbins,
7, 38, 55 guy,
he throws the ratio out there.
Go, "That's it exactly.
That's exactly how the message comes across.
This is how we gotta balance it,
this is how we gotta do it."
Those that communicate principally in writing,
the meaning of the words are much more important to them,
so they're deeply uncomfortable
with 7 being the words,
'cause the content, the words,
the meaning of the words when you're writing,
it's so important that you hate to poo poo it that way.
So I, first of all,
I 1,000% believe it's an accurate ratio,
but the real critical issue
is not what the ratio of those three things are,
it's what's the message when they're outta line?
Like, what's the message
when the tone of voice is outta line with the words?
Like, it don't matter what your ratio is,
you got a problem if their tone
does not match their words.
- And that's hard to really put a measure on exactly.
Even in writing there's a tone.
I mean, it's not just, even in writing,
it's not just the words, there's the words,
but there's like a style underneath the whole thing.
And there's something like body language,
the presentation of the whole thing.
I mean, they're, yeah, I'm a big fan
of constraint mediums of communication,
which writing is, or voice, like Clubhouse.
There's a personality to a human being
when you just hear their voice.
That there's, it's not just, it's, you could say,
it's the tone of voice, but there's like,
you can, like, what is it?
The imagination fills in the rest.
Like when I'm listening to somebody,
I'm like, I'm imagining some amorphous being
like doing things, when they get angry,
I'm imagining anger.
I don't know what exactly I'm visualizing.
- If you, well, and so you may think of a funny story
'cause we were talking about your buddy Elon before.
And I told you, you know, about, you know,
that I'd interacted with some of the senior executives.
So I know that they love working with him.
And they think he's an interesting guy
and they realized that he could be funny,
you know, he jokes around.
So they're telling me,
they're on this conference call, just words.
And a guy on the other end of the line says something,
you know, that wasn't, was wrong but wasn't bad.
And so they said they're on a phone
and Elon goes, "You're fired!"
And then everybody in the room with him
can see that he's joking.
But the person on the other side can't,
and they're all going, "Wait, wait, wait, wait,
they can't see your look on your face right now.
You gotta stop, you gotta stop,
'cause the guy on the other side is dying right now.
He doesn't realize you're joking."
So there was, you know,
there were the words and the tone of voice,
but it lacked the visual to go with it.
- (laughs) Nevertheless it was probably funny.
- I'm sure it was very funny at the time.
- Maybe not to him.
Just as a interesting to ask,
I don't know if you're following along
the developments of large language models,
there's been something called ChatGPT.
There's just more and more sophisticated
and effective and impressive chatbots essentially,
they can talk, and they're becoming
more and more human-like.
Do you think it's possible in the future
that AI will be able to be better negotiators
than humans?
Do you think about that kind of stuff?
- Well, so definition of better versus less flawed.
Like, there, you know, chatbots
have been out there for a long time
and probably about five years ago now,
a company approached us
'cause they were doing a negotiation chatbot.
And they said two things.
First of all, I said,
you know, "Why are you talking to us?"
Said, "Well, on point of fact,
we already spoke to the people
that are teaching quote 'The Harvard methodology.'
And you know, the rational approach
to negotiation just doesn't work.
The rational approach just does not work.
Our chatbots are not getting anywhere.
But we're showing in around
about 80% of the interactions
a higher success outcome with these chatbots."
And they showed me what they were doing
and it was still a lot deeply flawed
emotional intelligence wise.
But the reason why that they were having
a higher success rates is the chatbots
were never in a bad mood.
And you could reach out for chatbot
in the middle of the night.
So if you were talking to somebody that was never upset
and was always available,
then you're gonna have a higher success rate.
Negotiations go bad when people are
in a negative frame of mind.
- So the natural ability
of a chatbot to be positive
is just going to give you a higher success rate.
- Yeah, and they're not gonna get mad
and argue with you.
You know, you say to a chatbot, you know,
"Your price is too high."
Chatbot is designed to come back with a smiley face.
You say to a person, "Your price is too high."
They go, "How dare you, I'm trying to make a living."
You know? They're gonna go off the deep end.
- Unfortunately, or fortunately,
I think the way chatbots are going now,
they will come back negative,
because they're becoming more human,
more and more human-like, that's the whole point.
To be able to pass the Turing Test,
you have to be negative, you have to be an asshole,
you have to have boundaries, you have to be insecure,
you have to have some uncertainty.
- Well, there's a difference between having boundaries
and being negative.
Like, I can, like you throw a proposal to me,
you know, before I say no, I'm gonna say,
"Look, I'm sorry, that just doesn't work for me."
I'm gonna set up a real clear boundary
without being negative.
And a lot of people really struggle with setting boundaries
without being negative, without name calling,
without indignation, without getting upset.
- But see there's a, when you are,
when you show that you're not getting upset,
I'm not just seeing that,
I'm seeing a flawed human
that has underneath it a temper,
underneath it the ability to get upset,
but chooses not to get upset.
And a chatbot has to demonstrate that.
So it's not just going to be cold,
and, you know, be this kind of corporate
blank empty
sort of like vapid creature that just says,
"Oh, thank you, thank you for saying that."
No, it's basically you have to,
the chatbot has to be able to be mean
and choose not to be.
- Interesting. I don't know.
I'd be willing to see that play out
and see how it plays out.
- But I guess what I'm saying is to be a good negotiator,
you have to be, have the capacity
to be a bad person and choose not to.
- Really? - I think so.
- See, I think you just gotta have the capacity
to set a boundary and stick to it.
- Interesting.
'Cause I think, it's hard for me to trust a person
who's not aware of their own demons.
'Cause if you say you don't have any demons,
if you don't have any flaws, I can't trust you.
- Yeah, well, first of all, it's a lie, right?
So somebody's lying.
It goes back to lying.
- Yes, so you have to have a self-awareness about that,
but you'd be able to control it
and demonstrate that you're able to control it.
I mean, this is humans.
I just think humans,
intelligent, effective humans are able to do this well
and chatbots are not yet,
and they're moving in that direction.
So it makes me think about what is actually required
for effective negotiation.
That's what AI systems do,
is they make you ask yourself,
what is it that makes humans special at any discipline?
What is it that makes humans special at chess and Go games,
which AI systems are able to beat humans at now.
What is it that makes them effective at negotiation?
What does it make them effective at,
something that's extremely difficult,
which is navigating physical spaces.
So doing things that we take for granted,
like making yourself a cup of coffee
is a exceptionally difficult problem for robots.
Because of all the complexities involved
in navigating physical reality.
We have so much common sense reasoning built in,
just about how gravity works,
about how objects move,
what kind of objects there are in the world.
It's really difficult to describe
because it all seems so damn trivial,
but it's not trivial.
Because a lot of that we just learn as babies,
we keep running into things
and we'll learn about that.
And so AI systems help us understand
what is it that makes humans really,
what is the wisdom we have in our heads?
And negotiation to me is super interesting.
'Cause negotiation is not, it's about business,
it's about geopolitics,
it's about running government.
It's basically negotiating how do we,
the different policies, different bills
and programs and so on.
How do we allocate money?
How do we reallocate resources?
All that kind of stuff.
That seems like AI in the future
could be better at that, but maybe not.
Maybe you have to be a messy, weird, insecure,
uncertain human and debate each other
and yell at each other on Twitter.
Maybe you have to have the red and the blue teams
that yell at each other in the process
of figuring out what is true.
Maybe AI systems will not be able to do that,
you know, figure out the full mess of human civilization.
- Yeah, interesting.
Well, I mean the two thoughts
that I had along the way was, I mean,
anytime you're talking about systems or scaling,
you know, you're talking,
my belief is chatbots systems,
things that don't require decision making,
just following instructions,
at least 80% of what's going on.
Now, the remaining percentage, whatever it is,
does it require the human interaction and what's required?
Like I'm not like, I am not pro conflict.
And I also know that there's a case to be made
in the creative world that some of the best thinking
came outta conflict.
Reading interviews of Bono and U2.
You know, their admiration
for some of the Beatles best music
came when they were fighting with each other.
And the song "One,"
which is I believe from the album "Achtung Baby."
Those guys were fighting.
I mean, they were on the verge of breaking up,
and their appreciation that conflict
could create something beautiful.
And then when I was in the crisis negotiation unit,
you know, my last seven years in the FBI,
there was a guy named Vince, brilliant dude, brilliant,
brilliant negotiator.
And he and I used to argue all the time.
And then when we had a change
in the guy who was in charge,
the guy who was in charge took me off to the side
and he is like, you know, "I can't take you
and Vince fighting all the time."
And I said, "Well, I got news for you.
I think we come up with much better stuff
as a result of our battles."
And he said, "You know,
Vince said the same thing to me."
And I'm like, "So, well,
if we don't have a problem fighting,
why do you have a problem with it?"
But you know, there is something there
that sometimes the most difficult insights,
you rack your brains as to why someone
is so dug in on something
that so many of you think is so wrong.
Yeah, maybe there's something to it.
I think there's something to it.
- There's something about conflict,
even drama that might be a feature,
not a bug of our society.
- [Chris] Interesting.
- Do you think there'll always be war in the world?
- Yeah.
(Lex laughs)
- So there'll always be a need for negotiators
and negotiating.
- Well, as it turns out.
- Why do you think there'll always be war?
What's your intuition about human nature there?
- Yeah, just because we're basically 75% negative
and then, for lack of a better term,
I call it two lines of code.
Like somewhere when you, everybody, when we were little,
somebody planted in two lines into our head.
We don't know when it got in there.
But somebody said something to us that stuck.
And there are a lot of people
that had some really negative garbage dumped in their brain
when they were little.
And just based on the numbers.
What kind of opportunity they were given afterwards.
Did they ever have an epiphany moment
when they genuinely believe
they can get themselves out of it?
Like what is it, one of Joe Dispenza's book
is "Breaking the Habit of Being Yourself."
You know, like how do you get at that two lines of code
that either mean or well-intentioned,
but stupidly speaking adult said to you
at the wrong moment and planted in your brain?
Like, the chances of everybody on Earth
getting that out.
Even the majority of people on Earth,
getting that out of their heads is really small.
- What advice would you give to a young person today
about how to have a career they could be proud of
or a life, maybe somebody in high school,
college, trying to figure out their way in this world?
- Yeah, it's probably a take on a cliche
of do what you love.
But if you figure out your ideals
and pursue your ideals
and stick to 'em when it costs you.
Like a guy I admire very much,
Michael Mogill runs this operation,
Crisp Video at Atlanta.
In one of his talks, he would say,
"Core values are what you stick to that cost you money.
It's not a value that really matters to you
unless it's costing you and stick to your values."
Now, when I was in the FBI, I worked really hard at,
you know, the number one core mission of the FBI
is protect and defend the American people.
So I could pursue that value at all times, which I did,
or I could follow the rules.
You don't have time to do both.
- (laughs) When did you know you found what you love?
Like, when did you fall in love
with whatever this process is that is negotiating?
- I think it was in a conversation
on the suicide hotline that I was telling you about earlier
with the guy who was paranoid.
When I thought, I can have that significant of an impact
on another human being in this short of a period of time,
that's really cool.
- How hard is it to talk somebody off the ledge?
So this question, is a big question.
Why the hell live at all?
How do you have that kind of deeply philosophical,
deeply psychological and also practical conversation
with somebody and convince them
they should stick around?
- Well, it's more clearing the clutter in their head.
And let 'em make up their own mind.
That was what volunteering on the suicide hotline
was really about.
Just let me help, let me see
how quickly I can clear out the clutter in your head
if you're willing to have it cleared out.
Like, did you call here
'cause you are actually looking for help?
Or did you call here to fulfill some other agenda?
So are, you know, are you willing to have,
are you willing to clear the clutter in your head?
Not everybody is.
- So once you clear out the clutter
is there at least somewhat hopeful chance
that you'll continue for another day.
- Yeah.
And like, if you step back,
like very few people that commit suicide
physically are up against it that hard.
Like most of them by and large
are pretty intact physically human beings,
they're struggling with emotional stuff.
But it's an emotional issue.
It's not a physical issue.
So if you were to be a complete mercenary,
like a guy I'm a very big fan of,
a guy named Mark Pollock, born a great athlete,
lost his eyesight and then became paralyzed.
Like, he's an emotional leader.
He's about helping people thrive and live great lives.
Like Mark was born, he was a spectacular athlete
and first he lost his sight in one eye,
then he lost his sight in the other eye,
and then he fell out a window in a tragic experience.
Like, if there was ever a dude
that was saying like, "Living sucks."
You know, "And if there's any doubt in my mind,
something worse happens to me every few years."
But Mark's about being alive and inspiring other people.
So the hard part with navigating with somebody
who's tossing it in because there's a chemical imbalance,
or they're, it's the way they're interpreting the world.
There's clutter in their head.
Like, how can you help clear that clutter in their head?
- And help 'em by themselves,
inspire them to reinterpret that world,
as one worth living in.
What do you think is the meaning of life?
Chris Voss, why live? (laughs)
What's a good reason?
- Well, I have very strong religious beliefs.
Spiritual, you know, I don't 1,000%,
if you were to try to confine me in a box,
I'd be a Christian.
And I have tremendous respect for the Jewish.
I don't think any religion's got it nailed exactly.
I'm, again, you know, I keep mentioning him,
I'm kind of a Bono Christian.
I think Bono's, he's like, what?
And I'm gonna butcher it.
But, you know, "My belief in Jesus
is what I've got after Christianity leaves a room."
You know, the Dogma,
man's application of spiritual beliefs.
So, but that being said,
I truly believe that my life was a gift
and there's a purpose here and, you know,
my creator decided that I woke up in the morning
'cause he still had some cool, interesting things
for me to do.
- And you have gratitude for having the opportunity
to live that day. - Yeah.
- Well, you do one heck of a good job at living those days.
I really appreciate your work.
I appreciate the person you are.
Thank you for just everything you've done today,
for just being empathic.
Honestly, you're a great listener,
you're a great conversationalist.
It's such an honor to meet you and to talk to you.
This was really awesome, Chris.
- Been my pleasure.
- Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Chris Voss.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you with some words
from John F. Kennedy.
"Let us never negotiate out of fear,
but let us never fear to negotiate."
Thank you for listening
and hope to see you next time.