I don't think I've ever had a Guinness.
Unlike Scott Wu,
I've had many, many, many beers, perhaps thousands,
but I'm not sure I've ever had a Guinness.
Without an alarm clock, I will wake up
almost exactly
between 2:55 and 3 a.m. almost every day.
Wow. So you wake up ahead of earnings.
No, no. Forget earnings.
Every day.
You just want to see what happens at the open.
No, I don't want to wake up.
I actually don't want to wake up.
I mean, if I ran a private company like Stripe,
I wouldn't go public.
I think the public markets—
It's ironic because you're a public markets investor.
Yeah.
I think the public markets
are kind of problematic at this point.
Should we try to split the G?
Oh my God. No.
We cover this in an episode with an actual Irishman.
It's a completely—it's an invasive species.
It's a made up TikTok thing.
Yeah, but how did that start?
But you can.
You're a crass American so you can,
and maybe we should get it on camera,
and that would be funny.
We really trying to do this? Split the G?
Only Mike is.
Only Mike is, unless you...
Not close.
Oh!
That's not bad. That's not bad.
Can we zoom in here, please?
Camera roll three.
Dan Sundheim is one of the world's
top hedge fund managers.
He runs D1 Capital, which invests in public
and private companies across a bunch
of totally different industries.
Dan's one of the smartest investors I know.
So Daniel Gross and I try to get into his head
and figure out how he analyzes companies.
Cheers! Cheers.
Okay, Dan and I were wondering,
what trading app do you actually use?
Like, if you are trading underneath the table
during the interview, like, are you in Interactive Brokers?
Are you WhatsApping someone who executes this?
I'm just emailing. Okay.
I'm emailing the trader with that, yeah.
I mean, I'm checking Bloomberg all day long.
Yeah. Yeah. That's the app on my phone.
Yes. But I'm just emailing,
texting my traders.
And if the trader's like sleeping or something,
is there an app that you use?
Or is— If he's sleeping
during the day...
We haven't encountered that problem.
That'd be a different problem,
but if he's sleeping at night,
we actually have overnight traders in Asia.
So, once you told me sometimes when you struggle
to sleep at night, there's nothing better to do
than wake up and start trading Asia.
So, is that your East Coast trader
or do you have another person?
Yeah, we have another person that we outsource.
I see, yeah. I see.
And then how, what fraction of AUM
is just Dan Sundheim trades?
Or Dan Sundheim decisions?
95% plus.
Oh, so all of it?
Yeah. Okay.
I mean, people have trading authority,
but most of the trades, I put in myself.
Okay, so memos come up to you
and then you ultimately size them
and decide whether to do them or not or something like that?
Yeah, I mean, you know,
the process starts way before the memo.
I'm in dialogue with the team about the idea,
why they like it.
You know, we're having conversations
way before it gets to the memo stage.
But then we get to the memo stage,
and usually we start buying it before,
because in the public markets, you know,
if you have a good idea,
you could take a month and a half to like write a memo,
but by that time, the price may have moved.
So usually we start buying it before the memo's done,
and then the memo is kind of the final, you know,
compilation of the due diligence.
And that's when the best thing that could happen
is we're buying it and then the stock keeps going down.
So by the time you have the memo
and have even the most conviction, you can buy more.
A lot of times it's going the wrong way.
But what fraction of the time, like,
do you finish writing the memo and you're like,
"Oh no, this is a terrible company.
This is not good."
Yeah, yeah. No, like, that doesn't happen
because usually they'll start writing the memo
and then they'll come to me and be like,
"I think I made a mistake," and we'll sell it.
Like rarely have I—I don't think I've ever
owned a position because we had discussed it,
then read the memo and been like,
"Oh my God, what are we doing here?"
That'd be a bad sign for the analysts.
We jumped right off the deep end.
Describe what D1 does. AUM, strategy, for the uninitiated.
Yeah. So we invest in public and private companies.
We do fundamental analysis.
And so, deep research, trying to understand business models,
trying to understand company prospects,
choosing the right management team,
and whether it's public or private,
we're investing with the horizon of three to five years.
And we apply the same due diligence process
to both public and private.
Obviously private is a one-way door
and public is a two-way door.
So, you know, that's different.
Is private actually a one-way door,
even as just the private markets have matured
and there's so much more secondary activity
and things like that?
Like, do you still have to treat it as a one-way door?
Definitely.
I mean, you can sell like,
the best companies you can sell easily.
But those aren't the companies you want to sell.
So, you know, we rarely transact in the secondary market
because we don't want to sell the best companies.
And it's hard, like, people think you can just transact
in the secondary market but if you want to sell $50 million,
$100 million, people have to get information rights
from the company and then it's like...
And it's viewed as a signal if you're like large—
Exactly, they go to the management team and say,
"I want to sell," and the person doesn't follow through.
It's not great.
So, the AUM is about $25 billion, about two-thirds private,
$10 million public.
Public is long-short, you know, all bottom up.
No, you know, no quant.
Really kind of the same thing people were doing
in terms of stock picking 30 years ago.
And when you say no quant, that is, you're contrasting
to some of the more short-term technical firms
that are just trading based on what'll happen the next day,
the next week, the next month?
Exactly.
We're not using any computer programs to guide our trading.
You know, we are not trading based on quarters.
You could be doing my job
the same way 20 years ago.
You wouldn't have exactly the same tools,
but it's just, you know.
Do you think of any of those signals
that people talk about when you think of when
to enter or exit a trade?
Like, the stock would be oversold or overbought?
No. Okay.
What I find interesting about you guys
is you're long term in that you're not,
like you were saying, some of the quant guys
who are just trying to predict what happens
in the next, you know, what's the next buyer doing
or the high frequency guys or something like that.
You're instead just thinking, like,
is this company selling good product?
Will their sales exceed, you know, what people expect,
and will that add up to a good business?
And so, the work is evaluating future earnings
of the company, but there are some people
who are really buy and hold.
Like Costco seems to attract a lot of shareholders
who think there is no price
that is too expensive for Costco,
and there's kind of a huge loyalty there.
Whereas, you can have a price on both ends where,
at this price, I am an enthusiastic buyer
and at this price, you know, God bless 'em.
I'm selling the entire position.
And you kind of have that price boundary at both ends.
Yeah, practically we may say,
"We think that in three years this company
is going to be worth double."
Right? So kind of roughly 20-something percent IRR.
But if we're right about the company,
usually it doesn't go 24%, 24%, 24%.
People will pull forward the IRR.
The stock may go up 50% in the first year
if things go well, then the forward IRR
all the sudden looks a lot, you know, worse
and you're moving capital to the next opportunity.
I think the biggest mistakes, if we would look back,
I mean, it's easy to think about the mistakes
where you lost money, and you think about those a lot,
but the biggest mistakes are selling the Costcos too early.
Because, you know, the IRR is totally dependent upon
what you assume the exit multiple is.
And that is difficult to be precise about,
what the right exit multiple is for a business.
So let's talk about painful mistakes.
Like, can we talk about Netflix or something like that?
Yeah, so Netflix, when we started the firm,
almost every LP I met with,
they always want to hear a stock pitch.
So I pitched them Netflix,
and actually when we were interviewing candidates,
what we did was we gave every single interviewee
the same case study.
We said—this is in 2018.
So we said, "Look at Netflix, look at Spotify.
If you had to buy one of these businesses
and hold them for five years,
which one would it be and why?"
So, it was like Netflix all the time
because I was talking about Netflix with LPs,
I was talking about it with interview candidates,
and ultimately the thesis was correct
and I didn't hold it long enough.
And so, in 2018, the reason Netflix was contrarian
was it was obviously a great product that people loved,
but they were burning a lot of money.
And so it was just not clear
was this like a classic tech company,
where, would they ever make money?
Like, that's why it might've been contrarian with LPs.
Yeah, I think the issue is
there's very few tech companies
that are massively capital-intensive, right?
Almost every tech company loses money for a period of time.
But the typical software company, you're looking at, like,
there's operating losses, you leverage it,
and then people are very used to that business model.
Up into the LLMs, there are very few tech companies
where it's like a huge fixed investment,
and then the incremental margins on the sales
are extremely high.
And so, what that meant was that Netflix
was investing heavily in content, which is a fixed cost,
and then they were selling that to consumers.
The next year, they were investing more in content
and selling it to more consumers.
But you're constantly investing more and more in content.
And the skeptics thought this would have
to keep going up forever and they'd never make money.
Yeah, because cash flow just looks worse and worse
every year because you're investing more and more.
But ultimately, that created a moat that was
I think the defining aspect of the business model
that made Netflix what it is today,
meaning that it's like a flywheel.
You invest a ton before anyone else.
Actually what happened here is the media companies
enabled Netflix by selling them content
and then Netflix invested a ton, sold to people globally,
took that money, invested more in content,
actually borrowed in the high yield market,
invested more in content, sold it to more people,
and then the flywheel then, you know,
within five years they're investing way more
in content than anyone else.
They're selling it to way more consumers.
The incremental cost of selling that content
is very, very low.
And so you have this fixed asset
that you've built up that...
And what ultimately caused you to sell it?
We had transitions on our team.
And, look, we cover every sector, right?
So, there's like,
we're covering at any given time 300 stocks,
and we had transitions on our team
and our media analyst left and
I was focused on other things.
It was not excusable, because if I look back,
we get plenty of things wrong. But Netflix,
we got exactly right. Yeah, how do you think
about, there's like a sense of, do you ever have this issue
where like people want to pitch new things
because they're like new and exciting,
and, I guess, the good old Occam's razor idea—
just hold what you have.
Do you ever have to push back against that?
Yeah, I probably should push back more.
I mean, you know, I think it's like a human tendency,
like, "Oh, this is a new company.
I love investing.
Let's learn about this new company.
And this sounds super exciting."
But at the end of the day,
there's like only so many amazing companies,
and trying to
sell them and move into something else
is almost always a bad decision.
That's the nice thing about the private markets
is that, once you invest, you can't sell.
And usually for the best companies,
that's a huge benefit, ultimately.
Yeah. I just want to go back to starting D1 for a second.
So the lore is that prior to D1,
you were at a firm called Viking.
Is that right? Yep.
And the lore is that almost all of Viking returns
increasingly came from Dan Sundheim offhandedly
making a comment to someone at the
water cooler that, "Oh, that could be a good stock,"
or "Definitely don't invest in that,"
and people would be like taking those trades
as their own for the most part.
Those are your words, not mine.
That's the lore.
I never said that.
And I guess my question is, when someone comes up to you,
an analyst on your team today, and says,
"Oh hey, what do you think of X, Y, Z?"
And you do that sort of Dan Sundheim 30-second,
10-second take. What is going through your head exactly
that gives you just this binary sense of
looks good, not good?
Well, I mean, every situation's different.
I think the biggest risk is sometimes people will come to me
with an idea, and like,
and they pitch it for a little bit,
and I think about it, and I give them an answer,
and I don't have enough information
to give them a really solid answer,
but whatever I say they think is like,
"Okay, well if he said that's not good,
then I'm just going to forget about it."
And that's actually not, you know, that's not constructive.
Like, I am wrong all the time.
Even when I've done a ton of work.
And if it's just like a 30-second pitch at the water cooler,
I can say like, "That sounds interesting,"
or I could say, "That doesn't sound interesting,"
but I'd say my hit rate there is dramatically lower
than once we've done all the work.
And there is a risk, like, analysts are like,
they try to take my temperature and if I'm going to be,
if it's going to be something that interests me
and if it's not going to interest me,
don't waste time on it.
That's actually not great.
But I think what Daniel is getting at is,
you seem to have an intuitive sense for companies
and in this underwriting.
Like, it's not just all about does the model
spit out a 19% or a 21% IRR. What is that,
that the Spidey sense is picking up on?
I mean, I think it's like anything else in life.
It's pattern recognition, right?
Part of it is just understanding business models,
understanding what kind of valuations
companies should be trading at.
Part of it is just having invested in this capacity
for 20-something years,
you get a sense. Like, if somebody comes to you
and pitches an idea to allocate a ton of R&D resources
to some engineering project,
you probably have a pretty good sense upfront,
whether or not like they should go write a big memo
proposing that or not.
When you interview young, younger—
It's an art, not a science.
Right, so when you interview younger,
say, portfolio managers, or when you meet—
do you have a sense, fairly quickly,
if they have whatever this is?
Like, do you think this is a thing
just people have or they don't?
I think the answer is yes.
So, a couple things.
One, we don't hire portfolio managers.
I pretty much only hire people
who've never done public equity before,
which has pros and cons. So what have they
done before?
Piano teacher.
Hey, glad we're pouring Guinness.
Let's split the G.
We typically hire from private equity
because then they have the analytical skills,
they understand accounting,
they understand financial modeling,
and then we can teach them the stock picking.
And if I hire somebody laterally
who's a portfolio manager at another fund,
that's rarely been successful.
Almost never.
There's some negative transfer?
Like, they have expectations that are wrong?
Everybody has a different,
like, every firm has a different approach to investing
and getting people to change their habits
to align more with how we invest is incredibly difficult.
Now, if I hire somebody from private equity,
it takes about three years for them
to really be like contributing to D1.
So, obviously it would be much faster
for me to just hire an external
and there's funds— And what is that?
So like they come in, you say it takes three years.
What's happening?
You know, say they're three months in
and they're trying to speak up in a meeting,
and you must be thinking to yourself,
"This isn't really the D1 way."
What is that exactly that changes in them
over the course of the three years?
Yeah, I mean look, I would tell you that I wish that—
it is incredibly difficult to figure out
who is going to be great.
And even after three years,
I'd say our hit rate still is not as high
as you would expect.
I imagine if you hire an engineer, after three years,
you probably have a pretty good sense
if that guy's a good engineer, or girl's a good engineer.
I think that I have a pretty good sense,
but it takes even five years to really get a sense
because some people start out
where they're analytically really solid
and they work incredibly hard,
but the actual intuition of stock picking
hasn't come to them yet.
Is it because you're saying like the job
is so pattern recognition-oriented
that you just need some time
to build up the pattern recognition?
Is that what they're learning?
Once in a while, people come in and,
you know, right out of thee the gate you're like,
"Wow, this person, like, sees it.
They see the ball really clearly."
But that is a very small fraction of the time.
Most people get great over time
and they have to learn an industry.
So when they come in, we will say,
"You're going to cover fintech,"
and it just takes them a year just
to understand fintech, right?
Then they have to see, you know, well why is X, Y, Z stock
trading at this multiple?
Why is this stock trading at this multiple?
What's the market saying?
And yeah, I think it's like the market
is constantly giving you data points.
Some of them are, you know, false signals
and some of them are good signals,
and over the long term, they're all good signals.
And the people who do great at this job,
you have to have some commercial sense,
which I think is like probably just,
you're either born with it or not.
Charlie Munger's money-making gene.
Yeah, I wish I could like test for that.
It's impossible.
But you also have to love the job.
Like, you have to wake up in the morning in the shower,
you're thinking about, like, your stocks.
This isn't the kind of job where
you close your laptop, you go home,
and you forget about it.
It's, kind of, you have to always be on
and there's people who love it,
and if you love it and you have that commercial instinct,
that's, you know.
And you have to be analytically sharp.
Do you have a leaderboard of individual people's
portfolios and how they're doing compared to each other?
Yes.
Everyone has what we call a mock portfolio.
So, every week they have to take the positions they cover
and they have to say, "If I was managing capital,
here's how I would allocate capital
among the names I..." Wow.
And then what happens at the end of the year
is that sometimes it's like I own these five stocks,
my mock portfolio was up, and we take it very seriously.
Like, you know, the mock portfolio
actually goes into people's comp.
Sometimes it's like
that person did phenomenally well in their ideas
and I didn't monetize them.
And then sometimes it's the opposite.
But like, it takes care of a lot of the typical
hedge fund thing of, you know,
at the end of the year, like, oh, everyone like remembers
the things that they wanted to do that worked out,
and forgets the—you know. Ah.
But people have to pre-register
what they're going to come to you at the end of the year
and say, "See I was right."
Yeah, exactly.
So, I know, did I—
Do you ever have a situation with the mock portfolio
where someone goes short something you're long
or vice versa?
That hasn't happened yet?
No, that hasn't hasn't happened yet.
But there are big discrepancies because
sometimes analysts will be like,
"I think this is a 5% position,"
and I'll be like, "I think you're crazy.
I think this should be double that."
Do you have a mock portfolio yourself
or is D1 your mock portfolio?
That wouldn't be very useful.
D1 is my mock portfolio.
Yes, and then, you talked about sizing positions.
Everyone's coming to you with all these good ideas,
because, presumably, they're not bringing you
their bad ideas, and they're like totally idiosyncratic.
Like, some are super safe bets,
some are kind of flyers,
some are industrials and tech and banks and everything.
How do you size positions
and how do you just assemble that into a sensible portfolio?
Yeah, that is really difficult to answer
because it is, you know, it is entirely an art
that we're always trying to get better at,
and we look at tons of data just to
see what we could do better.
But it is really just to feel like, look,
for every stock there is a target price
but then there's also what kind of risk?
There's a risk-reward calculation.
Like, okay, maybe you could make 50%
but you also could lose 50% if you're wrong.
Sometimes you can make 25%
but the risk of losing money is quite low over time.
And it's a matter of like,
you have to compare those two ideas which are
inherently very, very different
and construct a portfolio which has—
you don't want all names where you could make
a hundred percent but lose 40,
but you probably don't want to have a portfolio
full of names where you're only
going to make 20% and lose three.
So, it's a lot of things that go into it.
There's the risk-reward,
there's the ultimate upside.
There's a sense of
what's currently happening in the business.
Like, if a business we think
currently has a lot of momentum,
I'm not predicting quarters.
But if the business currently has a lot of momentum,
the chance of you losing money in the short term,
assuming it's at a reasonable valuation, is much lower
than if a business—we're often buying businesses
when they're going through really tough periods, right?
You have to be very careful because
often that's the best buying opportunity
but that's the riskiest time too,
because sometimes it's hard to call the bottom.
When you say you have to be really careful,
isn't there a principle agent issue here
where when you analyze a company, you try to see,
you try to predict what its earnings will be
three years hence, and be more right than everyone else's.
Maybe there are too pessimistic on the company
and you think it'll actually really over-earn
compared to people's expectations.
But, you're actually really sensitive to what people think
in the short term because your LPs are grading you
on the performance in the year
and the performance in the quarter.
Correct. And you're judging
this poor analyst and their job
on the mock portfolio, which you're saying
is like updated weekly.
And so, aren't you not actually looking at companies
on a three-year time horizon because they have to
perfectly perform at every step along the way
and they can't be misunderstood for any short period?
Yeah, the way I think about it is,
any given time we are planting seeds
and then we're harvesting.
Like, there's some companies that we invested in a year ago
and our thesis is starting to play out
and you're making money, hopefully, on that idea,
and maybe you're selling that idea at that point,
and then you're putting in new ideas in the portfolio
that might take another year to play out.
And so, it's not like if we started out
with a bunch of ideas that all had three-year targets
all at once, like, yes.
But like, the portfolio's a living thing where
you have a range of positions.
Some you've had for a year or two and you think the
business is going to turn the stocks into work,
and then there's other companies
that you're buying now because they're really depressed
and really out of favor and
you know they're not going to go up,
you don't think they're going to go up
in the next three or six months,
but over any medium term timeframe they will.
So, it's like always—
So you've limited capacity in your portfolio
for the out-of-favor stuff where,
ultimately, you're smoothing this for LPs
where you always need some companies
that are performing and are popular.
No, because like,
I may have bought a company a year ago
that was out of favor, and maybe it's still out of favor,
but eventually, the way economic cycles
or industry cycles work, the company I bought a year ago,
maybe I didn't make money on it for the first nine months
and now it's starting to inflect.
And I'm putting a new company in the portfolio,
which is out of favor, and that will start to work,
it's impossible to predict, that'll start to work
6, 12, 18 months in the future.
But if you have a portfolio of things
that you've built over time,
our monthly returns and quarterly returns
are purely an output.
Like, it is arbitrary in some respects.
I think Jeff Bezos once said,
when people congratulate him on the quarter, he said like,
"Yeah, but that quarter was cemented like three years ago
when I made this decision to do X, Y, Z."
It's kind of the same thing with us.
When the stock's working, we probably were investing
in that stock a year, 18 months ago.
And then, you know, now we're investing in a new stock
which hopefully will pay off in 18 months.
So one thing you're kind of famous for is pain tolerance.
You know, you go through phases of euphoria in markets.
You go through phases of pain in markets.
And I was just wondering if you'd like walk us through,
maybe across D1's history, the most painful phase
and just how you, yeah.
How was that for you?
That's a very oblique way of asking about GameStop.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I do have a high pain tolerance.
So, the first three years of our fund,
our fund did phenomenally well.
Way better than I would've expected.
There's always some mean reversion. You expect,
okay, the next 12 months are going to be harder
because you've just made so much money.
As we were entering 2021, we had an amazing run.
Everybody in our firm was elated.
Everyone had done well,
they were part of a winning team.
And, for me, I'm always a little nervous
in the back of my head when things are going too well.
What I didn't expect was that the mean reversion
would happen within three weeks and would, you know,
be so dramatic that, like, it...
We never came close to going out of business,
never had margin calls.
But it was an absolutely insane,
harrowing experience. So what happened?
What three weeks was that?
Okay, so, 2020 ends, everything's great.
We're up by, I don't even remember how much we were up,
but very, very high. A lot.
And back then,
we are fairly aggressive short sellers.
I like shorting stocks.
It's masochistic, but I love doing it
and I've always liked shorting stocks.
This is at a time when,
we go back to like 2021, think in your head,
the government was mailing everybody checks,
everybody was sitting at home,
they weren't going to the office.
Reddit was starting to become a big thing.
And all those things came together to create
a massive short squeeze on the order
that I've never seen before.
The way I've always thought about stocks is
let's say I short a stock. I think it's going to earn X.
I know that if I'm wrong, it's going to go up this much
and probably goes up more than it should fundamentally
because people are short and they're going to have to cover.
That's my whole career.
I've never had, in my risk-reward framework,
nothing happens fundamentally
and a stock goes up 400% in two weeks.
That's what happened.
And if you think about what shorting is,
shorting is leverage, right?
It's just borrowing shares that you have to pay back.
Imagine borrowing a lot of money
and the amount that you have to pay back goes up
by a hundred percent every week.
That's very stressful.
It's a development market deathtrap kind of.
That was quite stressful.
And then imagine that also at the same time,
the American populace is basically all coming together
to think that like, these are the people you should attack,
these short sellers.
And so, it was like CNBC was like—
it felt like everybody was behind this massive short squeeze
and felt like it was a great thing
because these hedge fund managers were paying
for what—
That was the surprising thing, right?
Because it's the age-old "in a crisis,
all the correlations go to one,"
and things that are supposedly in your model uncorrelated
actually turn out not to be.
This is the long-term capital management issue.
It's like, oh crap, everything's correlated.
And similarly here, wasn't it that like any one stock
spiking 400% would've been fine
but it was the fact that this new retail phenomenon
of all of the highly-shorted stocks by hedge funds
melting up together was maybe the thing that
you couldn't have predicted. Exactly.
People say GameStop, but GameStop is just like,
that's a name that people use
because it was the most prominent name.
But like, what was the experience like?
So it's week one, it's up a hundred percent.
The week was like, the experience was,
I was almost like in shock.
We were losing an amount of money that was almost hard
to even fathom that you could lose that much money
in a short period of time.
And imagine, like, we were going from being
on top of the world, to within three weeks we were like,
people were saying like,
"Oh, these funds are going to go out of business."
And I am generally pretty even-keeled
when it comes to markets.
I've been doing this a long time.
I've seen a lot of things.
That was the toughest period I've ever had.
And it was really stressful to the point of like,
I felt like I was in emotional shock.
Now, I was still laser-focused
and I knew I'm on top of it,
you know, I'm acting completely rationally.
But it was very, very, very hard.
And I had friends who were getting bailed out by other funds
and you felt like the whole world was against you
because you know, there's all these people—
It kind of was.
Yeah, it kind of was.
It's like, it was really hard.
What I'd say about this job is that,
there's like an asymmetry of emotion, right?
When you're making a lot of money,
it's not like I'm like,
tap dancing around my house, like euphoric.
My lifestyle doesn't change.
I feel like, yes, I'm happy that we're succeeding,
but, you know, I'm happy but I'm not euphoric.
When you go through something like that,
it is like— Yeah, it's not 1 over x.
So painful and stressful
and it's not because I'm losing my own money.
It's more about losing other people's money.
You know, it's more about
you know that what's happening
is completely economically irrational
and how long can you actually stick with it?
Yeah, is that the painful thing,
that if you're covering the short,
you know that you're covering it at a bad time
because this is not a long-term sustainable price level?
Yeah, so we covered everything at the worst time
and I knew it was the worst time,
but if it kept going on for two weeks,
all of a sudden there's a real problem.
And I wasn't going to put the firm at risk.
And I told my investors, I said, "This is the worst time."
Now, if I had held that short portfolio,
forget like from the top.
If I had just held from the end of 2020,
I mean, they underperformed massively.
Like, it would've been like—
You were right on the shorts.
I was right on the shorts
but I was wrong on their risk management.
So again, there's this new phenomenon
of retail melt-ups in stocks, and in particular,
certain stocks seem to attract the retail crowd
and the price movement of the company stock
just seems to, like, I was just looking now,
there's a lot of retail interest in Opendoor.
And so the price movement just kind of takes off
and starts doing its own thing
that's kind of different to what's been happening,
how it's been valued previously.
How does this new retail phenomenon
change the short-selling game for you?
I would say that the opportunity for short selling
is better than it's ever been in my career.
However...
Oh, damn it.
Like, however. There's a "however."
However, you cannot capitalize on that opportunity.
Like, if we went back to 2019
and the same thing was happening,
I would be massively short these companies.
But after going through GameStop,
there's a ton of opportunity
but you have to be much smaller in each individual name
so that you don't subject yourself to
what happened in January of 2021.
But is this a new kind of science
just like understanding what the crowd is going to do?
Or is that just like, it's too random.
There's no science behind that. It's like—
But you could have the Reddit analytics
and following the tweets and—
Yeah, you could follow
Reddit tweets all day long,
but like, what does that tell me?
Like, okay, the stock went up a hundred percent.
There's a bunch of people who like the stock.
Obviously, if I read the Reddit,
duh, they like the stock.
It went up a hundred percent.
There's no information signal there.
I know that people are buying the stock,
I know that they're buying the stock for a reason
that I think is kind of silly.
The most important thing to me
is that we just have to be able to ride it out.
So, whatever happens,
a risk management cannot happen after the fact.
Like, anything you do after the fact is not risk management.
It's actually just destroying capital.
Risk management has to happen before the fact,
meaning you size these positions
so that when it goes up, you don't have to cover.
Anyone who says,
"Oh, I like risk-managed the portfolio
because things were going against me."
If you're a bad stock picker, sure.
Yeah, it's like I cut my losses.
If you're any good at stock picking,
risk management after the fact is a bad idea.
So we now size things.
So I said, look, I'm not trying to figure out
what's happening on Reddit or this or that.
It's like people get excited about,
one stock is in fashion one day,
then the next week they move on to another one.
I can't predict that.
All I can do is size a position such that
if they get excited and the stock goes crazy,
we don't have to cover.
We just kind of let it go and ride it through.
So is it something like previously you could have had
a more concentrated short portfolio where you could have had
a few shorts that you really like,
and you would have said, "Oh, it can go crazy
and it can 2x if it wants, and I'm still fine."
Whereas now you need to have many more
individual short positions where any of them can 10x or 20x
and you're still able to ride it out.
Correct. 10x or 20x is a little extreme.
We don't have that very often.
But this kind of stuff happens!
It does happen.
Yeah, we don't trade like $1 stocks.
But yes, that's exactly right.
After GameStop, we took about a year off of short selling,
and then I reengaged in short selling.
It's like someone going through a tough breakup
and saying, "I'm not dating right now."
Yeah, it was like, okay, we're going to step back.
I didn't know a 500 mile per hour hurricane existed.
I didn't know that could happen. It happened.
Okay, so now we have to figure out
what kind of windows we're going to put in our house, right?
So, we took about a year off from shorting,
which hurt us a lot in 2022.
When we got back into it, I said,
"Look, we're going to have to be more diverse.
We're going to have to be less aggressive."
And my view going in is like,
logically you should expect that your returns will be worse.
And then the question is like, okay, so shorting
is a really hard thing to do.
So, at some point it's like, okay,
if you're going to diversify so much
and your returns are going to go down,
like is it even worth it?
And if you asked me at that time, my LPs asked me,
I'd say like, "I don't know.
I like shorting stocks, I think we can do it,
but this new strategy, not quite sure
if the juice is worth the squeeze."
As it turns out, if you look at our short alpha
since that time and since we implemented
the more diverse portfolio you referenced,
our short alpha has been as good or better.
And I think the reason is because—
As your long alpha or as the prior short alpha?
No, as the prior short alpha
when we were more concentrated.
I think the reason is is that you can't be as big,
but there's so many more mispriced stocks
that you can have 40 of them
instead of having 8 of them.
What makes a good short?
Good question.
Yeah, like, I mean there's a lot
of different kinds of shorts.
So, the ones we've been talking about are like stocks
where usually what gets the retail crowd excited
on social media. Usually it's stocks that have some story
which is novel and exciting.
Maybe it's new technology, the revenue growth is really good
and you're kind of analyzing the business model
and saying this technology just doesn't work,
or this company's actually,
you know, the founder's horrible.
That's its own thing.
And then you have shorts where,
shorts that we think have like real terminal value risk,
where we look at the company and say,
"I actually don't think
this company will be around in 15 years."
And that's usually because something secular
is happening in the economy.
But does Kodak type stuff,
where like the business will go away,
as opposed to Theranos type stuff,
usually where it's like pure fraud.
Exactly.
Theranos would be like it's own thing.
So there's frauds,
which I used to do a lot more when I was younger.
It's hard to find frauds at $10 billion companies.
It happens, but we're not—
US capital markets are pretty good
for eliminating frauds from the...
Yeah, you'll find them
but they're usually in companies
like that are $1 billion market caps,
or $2 billion market caps,
which is kind of below the threshold where we play.
Because you can't get enough exposure.
Yeah, I mean a fraud rarely gets
to be, like, Enron size.
So you have the retail stocks,
which are just like story stocks that have, you know,
there's really no real substance to the company.
Then you have terminal value stocks,
like Kodak would be good example,
where you just look and say, like,
here is where I see the economy going
because of some secular trend or
some technological innovation,
and this company's business model
is going to be severely compromised over the next decade.
Then you have stocks where you just think
that the business from a competitive standpoint
is just really disadvantaged
and it's going to cede market share
for a very long period of time.
And then I'd say the last and least attractive shorts
are the ones where it's like, cyclically,
they're just over-earning a lot
and you believe that the real earnings,
if you were to look through a cycle,
are much lower than people think.
And how do you think about, so there's a company,
maybe they're in a bad place in the economy,
it just doesn't seem like it'll work out,
but there's always this fear
that they get bought out,
or that there's a sudden management change,
and do you just size your books
such that that's okay for you?
Or do you use options?
Take over.
I find that, generally, companies
that have secular risks almost never get bought.
Rarely do I ever see a CEO say,
"I want to go buy something that grows slower than I do."
Right? That just doesn't happen, right?
Nobody wants to take the time
to do an acquisition that's going to
invite a bunch of secular risk into their business.
Maybe Ron Perelman did that back in the day
but that doesn't happen.
What can happen is if you have a company,
like the example I gave where there's a company
in the industry that you just believe
is going to cede market share for a long period of time
because of their positioning or management or strategy.
And then what can happen is an activist comes in,
takes a big stake in the company, and says,
"We're going to replace the management team
and once we do that,
the new management team will pursue a different strategy
and they will no longer lose market share."
That is a big risk in that category, right?
That's kind of the only category where like—
And to manage that risk,
you just managed your book.
Do you use derivatives at all?
I really don't use derivatives at all.
The problem with derivatives is, look,
at the end of the day when you break down
what is a derivative?
It's just leverage and implied volatility.
If I want leverage, I can go
get leverage from a prime broker.
I don't have any view on implied volatility.
And the problem with derivatives
is there's typically a timeframe
and I'm not good at timeframes.
I don't know when a stock is going to work.
That's very difficult.
So, I don't like having something that,
making a bet that something's going to happen
in a certain period of time.
We keep it pretty simple
and just trade underlying stocks.
So, I think that like nobody buys businesses
that grow slower than them, or rarely.
People usually don't buy companies
that are market share donors.
With CEOs, I really want to like buy this.
It's like, that's a headache, right?
So there's a stage of the life cycle
where companies kind of become unacquirable, kind of?
Those companies, like,
I don't worry about them being acquired.
What you worry about, as I said, activist comes in,
replaces management.
Usually the new management team can't fix it,
but sometimes they can and that's a risk.
In terms of the companies
where I said they have no terminal value,
the risk is just that they usually trade
at low multiples, right?
And so, you're basically just DCF-ing the cash flows,
and if the cash flows, if something happens
and people perceive the cash flow is going to
last a little bit longer,
because the starting valuation's low, they can go up.
Cyclical shorts are just entirely different.
The risk is just that you're early
or you're just wrong about the cycle.
Like, there's something about the cycle
which is different this time.
But those are kind of the main categories of shorts.
Speaking of cyclicals, why has Rolls done so well?
Like, they're up 5x, 10x over the last few years?
This is Rolls-Royce, the jet engine
and turbine manufacturer.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Main business is aircraft engines for wide-body jets.
They're not big in AI, IGTs?
Not as far as I know.
It is like a little bit.
It's only a matter of time. They have an SMR business.
Okay.
So, that could eventually help.
Rolls is not very cyclical.
The reason why— Aren't engine makers
historically cyclical?
Not as much as you would think
because most of the business is,
I sell you an engine,
I sell you an engine for not much money,
but I make a lot of money in aftermarket,
which is much more predictable.
So the air framers are cyclical,
but the engine makers aren't?
Air framers are cyclical, but pretty good secular growth,
and it's a duopoly.
Rolls-Royce was just horribly managed for a long time.
Making jet engines is incredibly difficult.
It sounds hard.
A new jet engine. It looks hard.
You're like, wow.
A kind of idea you think might be hard.
It probably takes 5 to 10 years to do the R&D
to develop a new jet engine.
So, Rolls-Royce actually had good technology.
It was just very, very poorly managed.
And they signed a bunch of contracts with airlines
that were very unfavorable.
And they had a new CEO come in,
and he operationally turned the business around
in a pretty fantastic way.
You guys were long Rolls-Royce?
Right? Yes.
So, that's a good example of like, how do you,
because every management team says—
Yeah, how'd you figure that out?
Yeah, every management team says,
"We're going to turn this thing around,
and every management team has a projection
that looks good.
And so, how did you determine that now finally
they were going to turn it around?
Okay, so let me start by saying
the US and Europe are very different in this respect.
I find that if we—let's take a US company
that had a turnaround, an industrial company like 3M.
3M had been a horrible stock for a very long time.
Wasn't well managed.
New CEO comes in, puts up one or two good quarters,
and we owned it. Everybody basically understands
what's happening and the stock goes to fair value,
with the assumption that the margins
are going to go to where they should go.
The US is pretty quick at seeing change happening
and then pricing in that change.
In Europe, I find once a company,
like a company like Rolls had underperformed for so long.
I guess that European mutual funds,
they just kind of got in their head
that like Rolls is something we just don't want to touch.
So the voting machine is laggier in Europe?
Laggier.
Why is the information connectivity higher in the US?
Like, what's going on?
I think it's hard for me to explain
but I've seen it over and over again in Europe.
It's almost like when Rolls was being turned around,
it was pretty clear after the first year
that what he was doing was going to work.
And it wasn't really that difficult to—
Based on earnings, based on deliveries,
based on talk to customers?
Based on... You meet with the management team,
they say, "Here's our plan,
here's what we're going to do."
You see things playing out,
you see the income saving progressing
as the person said, you get a sense
for like Tufan, name of the CEO.
You get a sense for, okay, is this person good?
The same way you would assess—
Yeah, yeah.
Is the right framework that it's US and rest of world?
Or is Europe kind of uniquely bad at this
compared to Latin America, compared to Asia?
I don't do enough in Latin America to have a strong view.
But like a Japanese turnaround, would that—
I think Japanese turnaround would be closer
to Europe than the US
but I've done a lot more turnarounds in Europe.
If Rolls-Royce was traded in the US,
I'm fairly confident that after the first few quarters
and people meeting the CEO, it was very clear to me
that the CEO was excellent.
And why is that, functionally?
Like, do hedge fund managers,
or most of them presumably are in the US
and they mostly like to buy American stocks, or?
I think the American markets are just much more efficient.
There's just a lot more capital, and...
But there are no hedge funds that have,
very few hedge funds presumably only invest in the US.
You'd be surprised.
I think you'd be surprised.
I think Europe is generally viewed,
appropriately so, as a extremely low-GDP,
unexciting place Wow.
to deploy capital. For peak growth.
There's an issue where like presenting that to your LPs
is kind of embarrassing.
Is that part of the problem?
Like, oh, we took— Present what?
Oh, "We took a position in a European company.
I'm not sure we would want to do that."
No, no, no.
Obviously you don't, but I'm just trying to understand
why the average hedge fund manager
doesn't just back up into Rolls.
But isn't it just a home country bias?
Like, people invest in what they know?
Yeah, I mean I think it's, let's see.
I think it's much easier
from the US to invest in US companies.
You understand the accounting,
it's US GAAP.
You don't have to stay up all night,
in the middle of the night, to follow the stocks
when they report earnings.
Do you do that?
You're assuming like hedge funds—
If you have a big position in another time zone,
do you stay up to watch earnings?
Or do you wake up to watch earnings?
I actually, like, without an alarm clock,
I will wake up almost exactly
between 2:55 and 3 a.m. almost every day.
Wow. That's amazing.
Wait, let's dig in.
Yeah, there's so much to unpack there.
So you wake up ahead of earnings.
No, no. Forget earnings.
Like, every day. Oh. Oh, okay.
Like, every day.
Just because I've been doing it for,
who knows, 20 years?
Like, the European market opens—
depending on Daylight Savings Time—opens at 3 a.m.
You just want to see what happens at the open.
No, I don't want to wake up.
I actually don't want to wake up.
Yeah, but you're there.
But it's just like old habits die hard.
So you wake up, check Yahoo! Finance, and go back to sleep?
Yeah, sometimes I'll send out
a bunch of texts to— Thoughts.
Thoughts for the team.
People who have no interest in getting a text at 3 a.m.,
and you know, I like, think of things and then, you know.
Does your team have like a special setting
on their iPhones where it doesn't just like
chirp at exactly— Boss calling.
Yeah, like it just tracks an alarm.
I've never actually asked them.
I don't expect—if the company reports earnings,
I expect the analyst to be awake.
Wow. And I'm awake, too.
You can't... That would be like—
Wow. That's happened.
Like, one time I heard—
Do you go back to sleep then?
I try to, but like— But don't.
I try to but, look, it's like—
I just want to have a split screen.
So, you are in Miami, you're up.
The analyst is in a one-bedroom in New York City,
laptop in the bed, on the phone with you,
it's three o'clock in the morning.
Company's about to report earnings.
His girlfriend doesn't understand why.
She's already at the couch in the other room.
And then it gaps down, it's gapping down, it's red.
We could see the red reflected on the analyst's face.
This would make a great movie.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
And then what are you telling them to do right now?
Are you just saying, "Why is it red?
It should be green."
Well, usually it's red for the right reason,
and then it's just a matter of understanding,
okay well, is the stock overreacting?
Or, what actually happened?
Does this actually change our view
of the intrinsic value of the company or not?
And that's a matter of,
you know, the analyst is in real-time,
we're discussing what happened,
and sometimes we're buying,
rarely we're selling, but sometimes
there's a quarter where it's like
your whole thesis is just wrong.
Usually, it's like your thesis isn't totally broken.
Maybe the stock is down 5, 10%,
and you kind of say like, "I understand why,
but it doesn't really change my long term."
So it's been 30 minutes now, you did your stuff.
Now it's four o'clock in the morning.
Do you go back to sleep?
Yeah, it depends. Because the analyst
is not going back to sleep, I'm telling you that.
Yeah, it depends.
Ideally I go back to sleep.
It depends how red it is.
If it's really red, then it's hard.
Just push through.
Then there's more... We have to like,
if it's down 20%, it's not like,
"Oh, that's interesting, the stock's down 20%."
What's for breakfast?
Yeah, I'm going to go back to bed.
Catch you in the morning.
Then we're like, game on.
Then it might as well
be three in the afternoon because we're
deeply trying to understand
where we were wrong or if we were wrong, or—
You might be right at that moment
and it's time to buy maybe?
Yeah, sometimes.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay, let's talk about, so you wake up.
So now it's—
You went back to bed
because it was up 2% or something.
You go back to bed. Now it's what, 7 a.m., 6 a.m.?
You wake up again. And then you reach for your phone,
and what's in your inbox?
What are you reading?
Because you said you're not CNBC.
At that point, like the analyst...
Usually when the earnings report comes out,
it's stressful for the analyst
because the company reports.
You're being judged
on your position. The company reports,
and I'm on the phone with them,
and I'm like— Think!
"What's happening?"
And they're like, Do the math!
"Give me a second.
Let me digest the information."
I'm like, "Think faster."
I'm kidding.
But not really. But in real time,
but not really.
In real time, the analyst is like looking at it
and telling me
his perception of what's happening.
And then by the time I wake up in the morning,
there's usually a thoughtful earnings review
which goes through, in detail, what happened.
And I only go back to bed if
there's nothing that has to happen that's like...
If we're not going to have to make dramatic changes
one way or another to the position, I'll go back to bed.
And in the morning, I'll read
what is like the analyst has time to step back,
think about it, write things up,
and then we, by that time,
we have a few more hours of trading in Europe.
We may do something, we may not.
Let's talk about the, across all markets,
there is this after hours thing,
and you would know better than me
but I feel like it's gotten even crazier in recent years
where it reports, the stock can occasionally
act extremely erratically in both directions.
I think after APP reported earnings last quarter,
it was down 13% and then it opened the next day up 13%.
Yeah.
What's going on there?
And you'd think it's thin enough.
At some point, someone should come in and make markets.
Well, look, for sure this is not what we do
but there are bonds that,
as soon as the earnings report goes out,
they are effectively having AI
read the earnings report and interpret,
and then it's just like, it's just trading.
When you're staring at that,
I presume you sometimes will wait
because you kind of anticipate this thing
to flop around for a while?
I mean, we transact in the aftermarket but it depends.
Like, if NVIDIA reports,
the aftermarket liquidity is going to be huge.
If a company that's $10 million reports,
it's a waste of time.
If you try to buy the stock,
you're just going to send it up too much.
It's better to wait.
Dan's in the business of money management,
efficiently allocating capital
to companies around the world.
That's the job he signed up for
and seems to be going pretty well for him so far.
But what we see at Stripe is that as companies scale,
every founder, every CFO, every finance team,
they are becoming money managers, too.
And not in the way that they want or that Dan does.
Managing a fleet of international bank accounts,
dealing with trapped liquidity, paying global teams,
it's the kind of complexity
that creeps up on fast-growing businesses.
At Stripe, we believe that treasury management
should be fast, globally native, and programmable.
And that's why we're building a new financial home
for your business right inside your Stripe dashboard.
You can now do things like hold balances
in pounds and euros and dollars
and convert between them instantly 24/7 and at low cost.
If you need to pay a partner,
you can send money to over 150 countries
with just an email address.
Explore Stripe's new money management capabilities
at stripe.com/treasury.
Another thing funds will often do is,
as they get big, they'll expand
to other kinds of products. Macro.
Is that ever something you think about?
Definitely not macro.
First of all, it's tempting to think
that because you're good at one thing,
you're going to be good at all these different things.
And I think that, in and of itself, is a mistake.
But the thing about my business that I like
is that if you buy a great company,
you might be wrong for a little bit
but time is your friend.
Like you own it, maybe it has a couple bad quarters,
doesn't go up, blah, blah, blah.
But as time goes on, the company compounds value,
you know, it grows.
If I'm going to short US government bonds,
I might never be right.
It's not like, oh, over time it has to go back to 5%.
You're just basically making a bet,
where like in my job, I like the fact that
if you buy bad businesses you don't have that.
But if you buy great businesses,
you overpay for them a little bit.
You get the earnings wrong a little bit in the short term.
Over time, value compounds
and time is your friend.
Macro, that's not the case.
It's more of a binary bet.
So you have this story of like,
it basically takes time and then the market catches up.
Do you have like any particular stocks
that you can share where the markets didn't get it
for a very long time and it actually took quite some time
for it to catch up?
Yeah, I mean sometimes it takes the markets
like years to really get it.
What's an example?
I mean, Netflix is an example.
If you really like—
And is the "get it" moment the multiple expansion moment?
Yes. Okay.
So that's really
the thing, right? Yeah.
The interesting thing about
when people don't get it.
So, if I told you what's logical, okay?
Let's say you have a company, here's a good example.
Booking.com, which was called Priceline
back when I owned it.
It was growing 40% a year
and it traded at nine times earnings.
Why did it trade at nine times earnings?
It traded nine times when it was growing 40% a year?
Correct.
That's not meant to be an occupied corner of the—
Yes, it didn't make a lot of sense.
But like the narrative back then was like, okay,
they're just like arbing Google
and this is like a flimsy business model, whatever.
Now, you know, years go by.
I don't know how fast Booking is growing
right off the top of my head
but I imagine it's single digits.
High teens, I think.
Is it that fast? Okay.
I'd be surprised if it's still growing high teens,
but it's a lot slower than it used to be
and it trades at like 3x the multiple, right?
So like, the multiple should be correlated with growth rate,
but sometimes the market is just so skeptical
about the business model that even as the business slows,
the multiple goes up.
So would it be fair to say that D1 makes-
I think Meta is trading at a higher multiple
than it did for the last 10 years.
And we'd have to look, like don't take that as fact
but I would say Meta's multiple has expanded over time,
even though, just with the law of large numbers,
it's still growing incredibly fast for its size,
but it's growing slower than it was 10 years ago.
But now, I think for Meta's whole life
there was a lot of question about the moat
and TikTok and this and that,
and now it's growing slower,
but it has a much higher multiple.
But would it be fair to say that D1 makes
most of its money on this concept of multiple expansion?
Like, is that the actual trade?
Yeah, so that's what I wanted to ask about,
because Ben Graham talks about the voting machine
versus the weighing machine, and if I read a D1 memo,
it'll all talk about company fundamentals
voting machine stuff where
Siemens Energy is a great business
and like there's going to be so many turbine orders
because of AI and the wind thing is complex
but it's actually grand, and whatever.
But over a one-year period, the largest part of stock moves,
as Daniel is saying, will be multiple expansion,
which is basically sentiment.
And so, aren't you actually in the sentiment—
Is it vibes? Are you kind of vibe trading?
Yeah, I mean I like to think of myself
as being a little more academic than vibe trading.
But, look, I think that you're always going to
make the most money from multiple expansion.
Just like it's hard to have that differentiated a view
on a company's growth rate.
You can have differentiated view on the longevity
of the growth rate or the ultimate margin profile
of the company based upon some work you've done.
But the multiple over the long term
is a function of the perception of the stability
of the cash flows over the long term.
And sometimes people are skeptical of a business model,
and then over time it gets proven out
that the business model doesn't deserve
to have that skepticism, and then the multiple expands.
You do make most of your money on multiple expansion.
And that's why I said at the beginning,
we talked about
like actually gauging what is the right multiple
for a business is quite hard.
And when I sell companies too early,
it's almost always because we use too low
of a multiple at exit.
If I'm a non-profit that you want to help out
and I say we need to put all our money into a single stock
for the next, and we're not going to touch it,
we're actually going to lock it up contractually
for the next 10 years. What would you recommend?
I think if we start like narrowing it down,
there's very few tech companies I would say
I feel comfortable saying
because I just think tech just changes too quickly.
So, it wouldn't be a tech company.
It would have to be a company with like a moat
that I just felt like would be incredibly difficult
to penetrate with a growth rate that was probably
not like super high but well above GDP
for a long period of time.
And you're including valuation in this equation?
Yeah, we're just going to buy a stock
for our non-profit endowment now,
and then in 10 years time we're going to sell it.
It's an odd trading strategy
but we're in the non-profit business,
not the investment business.
I like Siemens Energy quite a bit.
I think that you may get a lot of the multiple expansion
in the next two years, and then the next eight years
might be less exciting, but—
We're not even going to look at it over the 10-year period.
There's a company called Clean Harbors
which I like a lot, which is they do hazardous waste
and they own the majority of the incinerators
in the United States.
You can't really build more incinerators because of NIMBY.
And as you have more onshoring,
there's going to be more hazardous waste,
and they have both the incinerators
and they have the network to go collect.
And so it's just a very, very good business.
And the starting multiple is pretty reasonable.
And I think I can grow earnings
well into the teens for 10 years.
I would tell you like I think that predicting things
beyond three years is incredibly difficult.
I've seen more instances in my career
where things change in a way you just couldn't expect.
And that happens all the time.
So, 10 years is hard.
Why do you like Siemens Energy so much?
I think that over the next 5 to 10 years,
first we started with
training these AI models, and I think we're still
in the early stages of that, it's early innings.
At some point, the scaling laws
will asymptote out but I think we still have years
of high energy uses to train models,
and then there's going to a really long tail of inference.
And so I think that,
and interestingly the gas turbine companies,
being Siemens Energy, GE Vernova, Mitsubishi,
they're not AI native, right?
So when they look at this, they say like,
"Hmm, this is like every other cycle we've seen.
This is, you know, we're not going to do it again.
We're not going to build capacity,
and then all these crazy people
who are building these data centers
all of a sudden realize it was a bad investment
and we're stuck with the capacity."
So, I think that there's a disconnect
between what people in Silicon Valley
think is going to happen in the next 10 years
and what gas turbine manufacturers think is going to happen.
I think that gas turbines are going to be in shortage
for a very long time.
Because all of the producers are conservative by nature.
Conservative, yeah, their conservative nature.
Siemens are literally German, you know.
And by the way, it's not crazy.
You look at it, you're sitting there in Germany,
you're like, okay, Masa's putting in
tens of billions of dollars.
Every day there's an announcement
of a hundred million dollars.
This sounds insane. I am not getting on board with this.
I tend to think that the turbine manufacturers
are more wrong than...
Look, I think that the electrical grid,
in the United States and globally,
people have not invested in the electrical grid at all
because electricity demand in the United States
grew at 0% for the last 20 years.
And so, if you think about the next 20 years,
I think electricity demand will grow at 4%.
It doesn't sound like a lot,
but if you compound 4% over 20 years,
and you haven't invested for 20 years before that,
it's very material.
The second thing with, they have a few businesses,
but the main ones that are important are gas turbines
and then products that upgrade electrical grids.
The other thing about electrical grids is not only
have they not been invested in,
as you start to introduce solar farms and wind farms,
and people having solar on house,
all of a sudden you need to have a much more dynamic—
it used to be you have a power plant,
that power plant sends power out through power lines,
to houses or businesses, and that's it.
Now all of a sudden you have solar, wind-producing power
in far away places that then have to connect to the grid.
Now the grid is handling
both consumers actually consuming energy,
and actually sending energy into the grid.
So, the grid just wasn't set up to one,
handle the amount of energy that's going to be consumed
in the United States and globally,
and two, it wasn't set up for all these renewables
which are going to fragment the electrical production,
in all kinds of different places,
and require that it's not just like one power plant
sending it this way.
It's going to be like a pretty dynamic
distribution of electricity.
How should we be thinking of,
so if we take Siemens as an example,
so they make the turbines...
Siemens Energy.
The turbines are in short supply, so the price goes up.
The commodity producer, in this case Siemens,
does not want to produce more of the commodity
because of their fear of cycles.
And, so in theory, the amount they can charge should go up,
the shortage goes up.
But then I would assume if they don't produce more
and demand continues to go up,
the year at which you would get your turbine
should also elongate.
So it goes from '27 to '28 to '29,
and then you start to ask the question,
are there other sources of energy we should be using?
And then, you get into the whole battery thing
and the whatever.
The solution to long lead times is long lead times.
Yeah.
My question is, as you think about
what the right price for the stock is,
is there a point at which like the lead time
becomes so extreme that...
Because at the end of the day,
people don't want the turbines, they want the energy,
that like other forms of energy
become more exciting somehow?
Yeah, I think it's two things.
I think one, eventually,
let's assume that Silicon Valley is correct
and that all this investment is going to be high ROI,
and therefore they're going to keep doing it.
Eventually, I think Siemens and Mitsubishi and GE will say,
"You know what, we have to build some more capacity."
That will happen. I see.
I think over a very long period of time,
nuclear will be probably a more viable option for energy.
That's probably the best
in terms of taking everything into account,
like steadiness of like the electricity,
environmental factors, nuclear is much better than gas.
But nuclear plants take a really long time to bring on
and have all kinds of other complexities.
So, I think that two things will happen.
I think over the very long term there will be more nuclear
but I think that like people miss that,
like the United States has been pretty early
in building out these huge clusters.
Most countries in the world that have developed economies
are going to need to build out.
Maybe they don't need to have like the same kind of clusters
that OpenAI is building in Abilene,
but they're going to need to have, probably
for national security reasons,
their own training clusters, and at a minimum,
they're going to have their own inference clusters.
So, I think that everyone's focused on the US,
and the US is important,
but this is going to happen everywhere.
AI is not contained to the US.
It's going to happen in Japan,
it's going to happen in Korea.
So, I think that the tail on this,
it may be like any kind of, like the internet,
it may, there may be—
Ebb and flow. Overbuild and then they...
But if you look over 20 years,
I just think that electricity is basically intelligence
and intelligence is what everyone's investing in,
and ultimately the bottleneck is going to be electricity.
So companies that enable electricity production,
assuming they have some moats,
are going to be good investments.
And I would tell you, interestingly,
going back to the Europe comment,
Siemens Energy and GE Vernova
are basically the same company.
There's no two companies I've ever looked at
that are more similar.
They have almost the same revenue, dollar revenue,
I think it's like 45-something.
The products they sell are pretty equivalent.
Like, nobody would say like this one's dramatically...
They're in the same business as turbines, electrical grid,
and then wind energy.
GE Vernova trades at 2x the enterprise value
of Siemens Energy.
Just to give you a sense of like,
and ultimately there's no reason why the margin
should be higher at GE Vernova.
The revenue base is the same.
So, I think the Europeans are implicitly
just a lot more skeptical of the sustainability
and longevity of this AI cycle.
And that has to narrow one way or another.
I don't think you can have two companies
and one trade at half the price of the other one,
and there's nothing about it that's actually worse.
There's also the other open mystery,
which is I believe the onshore TSMC trades
at a 20% discount to the US ADR.
What's going on there?
How is that possible?
That is also extreme,
and it just shows you
the US equity markets either have more liquidity
or just a different perception
of the risk inherent in buying TSMC.
And 20% is quite meaningful for the same company.
But Siemens energy is 50% discount.
Now, I understand TSMC is the same company, literally.
Yeah.
But like these are pretty close.
Well, okay, you raised different regions
trading at different multiples, and you raised Asia
which is a great segue.
Asian multiples.
Yeah, everything in China is really cheap right now.
You know, ByteDance trades at a really low multiple,
Alibaba trades at a really low multiple.
Do you guys do much in China?
Yeah, what's going on there?
Is that just a value trap? What's going on there?
Yeah, we stopped investing in China about three years ago.
So, look, everything has a price, right?
I think that the reason we stopped investing there
is, fundamentally, I have an issue
with the way their economy works.
I think the government has way too much influence
on how resources are allocated and—
Sorry, you have an issue as a moral matter
or you just have an issue as a practical, capitalistic...
Practical, capitalistic.
They can, you know.
I'm not making moral judgements on China.
I personally don't think it's the best.
You're just saying you don't know how to predict
how the market will perform.
Look, I think that what markets don't like is uncertainty,
and the problem with China is twofold.
One is that the government has way too much influence
on how resources are allocated.
I don't think they're particularly good
at making those decisions as you saw during COVID
when they shut everything down for no reason for, you know.
And they will arbitrarily decide
which industries are important
and which ones are not important.
And if you make too much money, that's bad.
And so all of those factors, you know,
for a while we were seeing Chinese internet companies,
they didn't want to beat earnings
because if you beat earnings, your stock goes up too much.
You might be flagging that, like,
you're over earning and you know...
Things have a target.
If you look at a company.
If you know they're not going to beat earnings,
what are you left with?
You're left with a distribution
which is not particularly attractive.
And so I think that the economy there is,
it's just very, very difficult.
That being said, I think the valuations are extremely cheap,
and I think the Chinese people
are probably the most commercial, hardworking, smart.
If you look all over Southeast Asia,
you know the best companies are usually run by Chinese.
Chinese people are incredibly industrious,
incredibly smart, incredibly commercial.
So, I find it kind of sad that
what's happening in China is stifling innovation
that probably would be better than...
Before this all happened, if we went back 10 years ago,
I think we would probably all sit here and say,
these Chinese internet companies are actually
probably technologically ahead of where we are.
Like, TikTok was... obviously came out of China.
Like, WeChat was like really probably
the most advanced form of social media globally.
But, you know, the way governments behave
is incredibly impactful to companies.
So you think the tech is very cool, but just fundamentally
being an equity holder there is hard?
The tech is very cool.
I just don't think it's progressing
at the same rate it used to
because a lot of the great entrepreneurs have left
because they felt like the environment
for starting companies, for
driving new innovation that
was going to make a lot of money,
like that wasn't something that was
looked favorably upon by the government.
So, the best people left.
A lot of them went to Singapore.
And that to me, I think that's a shame
because with the right government
and with the right economic system,
China should be
the most important economy in the world,
and it should be a technological leader,
and I think the geopolitical tensions
would be entirely different,
and I have a ton of respect for
what China did from 1970s to 2020.
I think it's pretty much an economic miracle.
But what we've seen the last five years is,
governments matter and
it matters what your political system is,
and it matters how the government intervenes,
and due process matters.
There's the famous case where many
of the digital education apps were banned overnight.
Did that really update your view of China?
Yeah, that like, investors hate uncertainty.
And you want to, okay, like in the US,
can something bad happen to social media companies?
They get called in front of Congress,
but there's due process, right?
Like, you know that like there is a system
that you can't have,
Donald Trump can't just wave his hand and get rid of Meta
because he doesn't like the fact that
they're allowing people
to say bad things about him.
And so, when you have a government
that can act capriciously,
that has a humongous gravitational pull on valuations.
Some big picture questions related to China.
So, there's all these charts one could look at
of the concentration of Mag 7 into the S&P 500,
and you could look at the 1970s equivalent
of the Nifty Fifty.
There's the inflation, which seems to be tracking
the double hump story.
First of all, do you
care at all about these analogies?
Like, do these analogies mean anything to you?
These charts with all the JPEG artifacts on them.
They're always very convincing.
I think there's, like, look.
History rhymes, right?
And the same thing in the market,
so there is like, it's interesting to look
at what's happened historically to these companies.
It's dangerous to say, like,
look at it and just extrapolate to the point
where you say— So you can overcorrect
on the chart.
But then my question would be,
what would be the sign for you actually
that the bubble is close to peaking?
Is there something, an anecdote
or an actual piece of evidence you'd look at,
you'd say like, "Okay, maybe we all believe in AI, but we—"
So you're saying AI is a bubble?
No, I'm saying I believe in cyclicality.
Like, the internet worked but it was also a bubble.
It was also a bubble, yeah.
Derek Thompson said this recently in a way that I liked
which is people associate using an AI,
that AI may, currently be or in future be a bubble
as like some kind of negative statement.
But because every major tech change—
the canals, the railroads, the internet, whatever—
has been accompanied by a huge speculative bubble.
Because it has to
when you think about it. It has to.
Yeah.
Because Americans are optimistic.
Right, but it's an AI-optimistic statement to make.
Yes, that's right.
That there will be a bubble.
We are actually celebrating how important it is.
So Daniel's saying he's an AGI believer,
and AI's clearly going to be a big thing.
Therefore, is it this year, is it next year?
Like, when's the bubble?
If you look at like the checklist of things,
you want to like look at for like what's going to be closer
to the end of the bubble.
If you went back like a year ago, you'd be like, okay,
yes there's a lot of money being spent,
but these companies have massive amounts of cash flow.
Microsoft kicks off a ton of cash flow.
Once you start having debt-fueled investment,
that's usually a bad leading indicator.
Because, obviously, when you have a lot of debt,
there's not much room to make mistakes.
And you are seeing, like, some of these latest projects
are debt finance.
I think that nobody knows, like, I think even if you spoke
to... I know when Dario was sitting here,
it's like they keep investing in training,
and maybe it's pre-training, it's post-training,
but at some point the returns on that training
are going to be disappointing.
And then it's that people will be freaked out a little bit,
but usually then the next time it's like back to, okay,
the next model's good.
At some point people are going to say like,
"Well, we're asymptoting out.
The returns on this new investment
are actually not working."
That's when I think you'll see a pretty big correction.
Okay, so there's the theory that there's a correction
because the returns to pre-training start asymptoting,
and then there's a theory of bubbles.
If you look at the 1970s, and to some extent dot com,
which I think was really hampered
by the fact that the Fed raised rates into '99 and 2000.
There's another view of bubbles which is,
there's an awesome thing happening,
everyone gets overexcited,
but then some random thing hits the bubble,
and because things have run up so much,
everyone starts panic selling all the way down
because there's all the people that bought in,
their cost bases of, you know, NVIDIA
not to pick on anyone, is like 4 trillion.
And so my question is, do you think we're in that mode,
and is this a productive line?
Like, at D1, do you guys ever think,
oh, what could be that thing,
and how do we prepare for that thing?
Or do you sort of think like—
I think to our detriment.
We should have owned more AI stocks.
There are definitely things,
you go down the list of what constitutes a bubble,
and you can check some things like
massive debt-fueled investment,
just like people were building—
What else is on that checklist?
Valuations,
and bad companies trading crazy valuations.
Circular financing.
I would tell you like NVIDIA is,
we can have a debate about what the earnings
are going to be in a few years, but it's not expensive.
Like, NVIDIA trades at 20-something times multiple.
That's, I think, within reason
and I don't think there's anything I see
in the public markets which is bubble-like
from a valuation standpoint.
I think if you look back in history,
70% of the time you have this
major breakthrough technology,
there is a stock market bubble.
And maybe what you're seeing right now
in some of these retail stocks, like where
Opendoor goes from 1 to 10.
Maybe that is like things are starting to,
you know, bubble.
But we haven't seen like large cap...
I don't think the large cap AI stocks
are trading at crazy valuations at all.
We're not seeing that yet,
so maybe it's 1997, 1996 and by the time that
we're in the equivalent of 1999, NVIDIA
will be three times higher, and it's possible.
Someone said to me recently as well that
for a proper kind of crisis you also need things
that people thought were safe to not turn out to be safe.
Like in 2000 when the NASDAQ went down 85%,
it's like well that's a real bummer,
but we did know that we were buying these
highly-gassed tech stocks.
Whereas, when the debt actually turns out to not be safe...
The debt turns out to be equity.
Exactly. Yeah.
That's when you get real issues.
It was very different in 1999, though.
Like, there were horrible companies
which had no real economic prospects
trading crazy valuations.
I'm just not seeing that in the public markets now.
I am, just not in AI.
You're a huge fan of SpaceX and a big holder.
What are you so excited about?
What's going on there?
Everyone understands Elon is, you know,
an amazing inventor, an amazing entrepreneur.
I think people underestimate
how good of a business person he is in that like—
Been my theory, yeah.
It's like okay, yes, does he invent great things?
He does, but he is ruthless about bringing down costs
to a point where his business becomes
a natural monopoly
because it is the low-cost provider.
With SpaceX, the whole problem
with space in general, doing anything in space historically
was that it was very expensive
to launch anything into space because, one,
the rocket blew up and, therefore,
it better be really high value
if you're going to send it up there,
because if you're going to take a plane
from New York to LA and every time you do it,
the 747 blows up, the plane tickets
will be really expensive.
You better really want to go up to LA, right?
I think, so the first thing is
the idea of bringing down the cost dramatically
by making things reusable.
Now I think like he was like 5 to 10 years
ahead of everybody else.
Now, obviously, it's more reusable
and the scale of the rockets is getting so big,
and each rocket will be able
to be flown more than a hundred times.
And so, the cost per ton of launching things into space
is going to go down by relative to
five years ago, it's going to go down like 99.9%.
It's dramatic, the cost.
Once you bring down the costs that way.
Obviously, the first order effect
is like you launch a bunch of LEO satellites,
which gave us this great Starlink.
And I think that will continue in a way
that probably surprises people
in that I think SpaceX will probably capture
more of the global telecommunications market
than people expect.
You saw them buying Spectrum from EchoStar,
but then it's like, okay, so if you really step back
and say like, "Well what else should we be doing in space
if the cost per ton is like dramatically lower?"
I value the company based on the launch business,
which is a near monopoly and a fantastic business,
and then our expectation, like what happens with Starlink,
which is just a matter of like P times Q subs.
But when you bring the cost per ton down so dramatically,
you open up markets— There's option value.
They would say, yeah, you fly from LA to Sydney
in 30 minutes, or we start having solar panels
in space that are, you know,
people say data centers in space.
I don't know what it's going to be.
Certainly there will be US defense deployments
in space, right?
For sure.
And then I think there's a lot of option value.
I look at it and say like,
I think the business can triple without having
to make any big bets about people traveling
30 minutes across the world or
data centers in space.
But there are legitimate, like a lot of medication
is better manufactured in space than it is on Earth.
There will be plenty of allocation over long term,
and that's why I think like it's the equivalent
of Tesla's Robotaxi.
There is this option value out there that,
no, Tesla's not an EV company.
It is going to own global transportation
because it's a low-cost provider and it's, you know,
and so I think you have that with SpaceX.
I like it because you have the downside of the cash flows
from Starlink and the launch business,
but you still have the option value
of all the things we could dream about,
which are impossible to quantify.
I totally agree on the underappreciated aspect of Elon
being the business savvy where,
let's not forget Tesla invented a new mode
of selling cars direct to consumer.
They had to get the laws changed in certain states
because the current dealership system was enshrined,
similarly with SpaceX.
For what they do,
it's actually a very capital-efficient business
and they've run it in a, you know,
they've built it with profits
rather than venture funding,
or they've built it with revenues,
customer revenues rather than venture funding.
And so, I think that's really underappreciated.
I think he's a better business person than he is inventor.
He's amazing at both,
but like people don't understand,
like he just naturally understands,
just get the cost down, get the cost down,
get the cost down.
And that's very hard to compete against.
Do you want another?
Sure, I'll have another. Sure. Great.
You keep going there.
You know, they say Stripe is actually controlled
by an Irish mafia behind the scenes.
Did you actually, I mean, it's quite interesting,
I didn't realize until you said it
that D1 is mostly privates now, by size.
Yes, by size.
Did you expect that to happen? When you started?
No, I did not. I did not expect that to happen.
It's actually just more a function
of how things played out than a deliberate strategy
for us to grow the private business
at the expense of the public business.
Our public business went through some big ups
and some big downs.
I think our public business... We are,
and look, there is a limit to how much we can manage
on the public side.
We announced a few weeks ago that at the end of this year
we're going to be closing the hedge fund.
We may replace redemptions,
but the most important thing is in our business,
returns are negatively correlated with size.
Especially on the short side.
Because you just own too much of a company to, like,
you move the stock when you try to trade it and stuff?
It's not so much on the long side, it's on the short side.
As you turn things over.
And it's like, if I'm $30 billion,
you can't really short $5 billion companies, and most—
Could you not grow AUM and be more long exposure?
Probably what you'd want to do is,
and what we may do in the future is,
and what other funds have done,
is you have your hedge fund, which does long, short,
and then you have a separate fund
which is like just long only,
and that can scale quite a lot.
because we tend to hold them longer
and you can buy very large cap companies.
So, privates.
So what was your first private position for D1?
That's a good question.
We launched, I think our first private position
at launch was I rolled a stake.
I had taken a stake starting in like 2010
in a company called Lineage,
which is a cold storage warehouse company
that I rolled off of my personal balance sheet
into the fund, and then we made subsequent investments.
And then in the first couple years,
we did a variety of different things.
Like, some I think worked out not as well.
JUUL was like a, I'm not quite sure if that was,
it was good and bad at times.
I think it's going to be good now.
And then, we did Ramp really early.
That was good.
John was nice enough to allow us to invest
in Stripe in 2019. Yeah, how did you
underwrite Stripe?
Because again, we weren't profitable at the time,
and I don't know, yeah, what does the process look like
for something like that?
I actually started out my career
as a financial service analyst.
So, I had looked at all the card networks,
all the processors.
It was pretty clear to me that the competitive set
in merchant processing was very mediocre at best,
and that their technology was not conducive
to most internet companies.
Nor did they have the tech stack that would allow them
to adjust to what was happening
in terms of e-commerce.
And, look, at the end of the day
it was like, I think that there's going to be one,
maybe two companies that actually can provide the technology
for companies to enable e-commerce
or any online transactions,
and you guys seem pretty smart.
We do a lot of work on management teams
and, you know, huge market, great management team,
weak competitive set, is like,
perfect recipe for making a lot of money.
So you've got Ramp, Stripe, SpaceX,
and maybe one day of course
all these companies go public,
but it would seem as if there's like a lot
of later-stage private companies now.
Why do you think that's happening,
and where do you think that's going
to go in a couple of years?
Are public markets just going to be the laggards
and all the new hot stuff will be private?
Or will it rebalance one day?
I mean, if I ran a private company like Stripe,
I wouldn't go public.
I think the public markets—
Which is kind of ironic
because you're a public markets investor.
Yeah, I think the public markets
are kind of problematic at this point.
Let's just take Stripe for example,
and I won't speak for John. But basically,
Stripe grows earnings, cash flow at some amount.
Value compounds, and they do tender offers,
and the tender offers are relatively in line
with the value creation,
and therefore the people who are working at the company
and are creating that value, get paid for that value
because the stock price goes up in line with value creation.
Now what we see in public markets
is you take your company public and,
depending on what the retail crowd is doing that day,
the stock may trade at some insane value, right?
And most people are high-fiving.
"This is amazing.
Our stock is like trading 2x where it should be.
This is great. We're all rich."
The problem with that is that—
Cuts both ways.
You've now pulled forward a ton of value.
And so all the people working at the company now
are being overpaid because
they didn't actually create this value,
that's not...
and then the people who you're hiring,
those people are probably more likely to just cash out
because they've just made too much money.
You're robbing future employees to pay current employees.
Exactly.
And then your future employees,
now you have to give them stock options
or RSUs at a stock price you don't really believe in.
And so, the stock is so volatile that
you're actually not being paid
as an employee based on value creation.
You're being paid arbitrarily based upon multiples
which have nothing to do with the true intrinsic value
of the company.
So, obviously it's bad
to be undervalued as a company,
because then you're issuing stock to employees
at too low of a value,
and then they don't appreciate it usually.
But it's pretty bad to be overvalued, too.
Because like, employees,
if a stock doesn't go up,
they will definitely come back to you
and ask for more options.
If the stock goes up way more than it should,
they're not going to come back to you and be like,
"Oh, you know what?
Hey, I made too much money."
And so you end up having this asymmetric...
I think it's really not a healthy dynamic
to be a public company.
Is there anything that should be changed
about the public markets to make it better?
So, for example,
Robinhood got rid of commissions.
Is zero the correct amount of friction
for entering and exiting trades?
This is hard.
I had breakfast with Vlad this morning
and I really like Vlad.
I think that it's a moment in time.
My view is that over the long term,
stocks will go to intrinsic value.
It's taken longer than I've expected
for some of these things.
Some of the shorts you were—
I still believe it. I believe it.
I can't tell you I have a lot evidence that's the case,
but that will happen.
That doesn't necessarily help a company like Stripe
if they go public and if eventually in five years
it's in fair value, but in the meantime
they're just kind of like...
Whips up and down.
Yeah, whips up and down. That's bad.
I'm not sure you can do anything to change markets.
Markets are inherently volatile.
It just so happens that at this moment they are more,
like, you would think that in the current world
if I told you that like we just have perfect information,
everybody has all the information,
it's at your fingertips.
Everything should be more efficient.
Yeah, yeah. Wow, stocks are going to be so correctly priced.
It should be correctly priced
because everyone has access to the same information.
It's actually gotten less efficient over time, for sure.
And I don't know.
I don't think you can just necessarily fix that.
You mentioned starting your career as a banking analyst.
How has the banking industry changed?
Most of the banks
tend to be very dominant in one geography.
They're not like tech companies like Google or Meta
where they're just dominant.
Like, JP Morgan is dominant in the US,
but like Europe doesn't matter.
Same thing with the European banks.
Up until now, I think the legacy banks have more or less
in most geographies been able to keep their market share.
However, you increasingly are seeing banks
like Nubank or Revolut that don't have the tech debt
of like mainframes and old code.
And just offer better customer experiences.
Don't have branches.
Iterate on product faster, have better engineers.
And I think that those banks are going
to increasingly take market share.
Neobanks have happened in Brazil with Nubank,
have happened in Europe with Revolut and Monzo
and people like that.
Haven't happened in the US, really,
and there's probably other geos where they have and haven't.
Do you have a view on will it happen in all markets?
Are certain markets more impervious than others?
I think that it depends how good
the incumbent bank is.
Like, I think JP Morgan is a very well-run bank
and the big banks are well-run,
but do I think that they are vulnerable to disruption?
Definitely.
But you still buy bank stock,
so how do you get comfortable?
Then there's like a more theoretical question of,
okay, well if all these AI agents,
if before Revolut and Nubank just hired the best engineers,
and so they were just naturally going to beat JP Morgan.
But if like AI agents make, you know,
now everybody has the best engineers
because best engineers are actually not people,
they're just agents. Maybe JP Morgan can be as good
as some other companies.
That's theoretical. It's probably not correct.
In the US I haven't seen someone come in
and be that disruptive.
But is that because of market structure reasons,
or just we haven't seen the great founder yet?
It's a good question.
I mean, banking is not, it's not like,
you have both sides.
Like you need deposits, you need to provide credit, right?
And you need a lot of scale.
And a market like the US is much more difficult
to penetrate because it's so big
and the competitors have so much capital to invest.
Whereas smaller countries,
like Revolut has low single-digit
market share in every country.
I think that'll keep growing,
but they don't actually provide credit.
So, I think we're in the early days of disruption.
I think you roll forward like 20 years,
there's going to be some companies
that didn't exist 10 years ago
but are going to become enormously large banks.
But I also think the incumbent banks
are probably going to innovate enough
that they're not going to
go the way of like JCPenney.
Last question.
If you're a youngster interested in investing,
you have views on companies but you don't feel confident yet
in how to underwrite and construct a model
and things like that, what advice would you give them?
Someone who's interested in this stuff
but still getting their feet wet?
I think that pretty much with
anything you want to do in life,
I just believe that reading, just incessantly
is the way to get ahead.
And investing's so different.
It's just like, read stock pitches,
over and over and over again,
and then watch those stocks, see how things play out.
The market will be your mentor.
But I think you need to just like, really, like...
I learned by, there's a website called Value Investors Club,
and like, I just read everything that people pitched.
You want to have some framework.
I liked reading Buffett's books because,
he has some faults obviously,
but he just he has a way of like distilling down
the complicated into very simple ideas.
And so I would read a lot of Buffett books,
I'd read a lot of stock pitches.
Anything I could get my hands on with regard
to like what's happening in technology,
what's happening in the economy.
And to me it's just like, the more you read,
the better you are.
Obviously, the Buffett stuff is very worth reading,
and there's the Cunningham book
that takes all the letters
and smushes them together because there's
a lot of repetition. That's my favorite book.
Exactly. Yeah, yeah.
So that is a classic and a lot of people listening
have probably read it.
So, all the Berkshire letters.
What I actually only read recently for the first time
is if you go back and read the Buffett partnership letters,
so this was, the partnership he had
with which he bought Berkshire Hathaway
and turns into, but this was like a fund,
more of a hedge fund than
the C corp that is Berkshire.
What's interesting is I find it
stylistically very different.
This is the late '50s, early '60s
and it's before he got so polished.
You know, it's before he got so folksy and approachable
and careful in what he said,
and a little more of the raw ambition is on display
before he sanded that off.
And it's, I don't know if you've gone back and read them.
I haven't read them.
Oh, it's awesome. I'll send it to you.
It's really good reading.
But the original Buffett partnership letters are,
I mean obviously it's Buffett so it's similar in a way
to the Berkshire letters,
but I actually think they're better in certain ways.
Yeah, he is a brilliant guy, but he actually does like
to portray himself in a certain light.
The Buffett partnership letters felt more authentically
Buffett to me. Yeah, they shine a light
on like who he truly is, but it's been good for his business
to portray himself in that light.
It makes sense.
You can't argue with the results. Yeah.
All right, Dan, Daniel, thank you, guys.
All right. Thank you.