- T. rex is definitely weird, even compared to all the other
giant tyrannosaurs that are very closely related to it,
because it is by far, ludicrously by far, the largest carnivore in its ecosystem.
- So it doesn't really have competition, actually.
- I mean, this is a Velociraptor skull. There are some carnivores
that are a bit bigger than this, but not enormously
so which were knocking around as T. rex. The skull's the same type.
...toothed crap. But, like, you think about that.
And that's like going to Africa and
going, "Okay, there are lions. What's the next biggest
predator? And it's like, well, there's a weasel about this big.
Like, it's that kind of size difference and
you don't get that normally in ecosystems.
- It would eat those, the juvenile of the herbivores, but not...
- Oh yeah, it's gonna be eating Triceratops and Edmontosaurus and Parasaurolophus.
There's even a couple of giant sauropods knocking around.
- Got it.
- In some places it's gonna be hoovering them up, but like,
how often is it gonna eat... Again, Velociraptor isn't there, but how often
is it gonna eat something the size of an adult Velociraptor?
I mean, they're a fraction of our size and we're probably too small.
This is like lions hunting mice. Like, you're just not gonna bother,
unless one, like, virtually runs into your mouth, you're not gonna try and eat it.
- The following is a conversation with Dave Hone, a
paleontologist, expert on dinosaurs, co- host of
the Terrible Lizards podcast, and author of many scientific
papers and books on the behavior and ecology of dinosaurs. This was truly a fun
and fascinating conversation. This is the Lex Fridman Podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description and consider
subscribing to this channel. And now, dear friends,
here's Dave Hone. Let's start with the T.
rex dinosaur, possibly the most iconic predator in the history of
Earth. You have deeply studied and written about their evolution, biology,
ecology, and behavior, so let's first maybe put
ourselves in the time of the dinosaurs and imagine we're standing in front of a T.
rex. What does it look like? What are the key features of
the dinosaur in front of us?
- It's gigantic. It's almost trite now
because everyone knows T. rex is massive. But yes, if you actually
stand in front of one, you would be seriously impressed just how
absolutely vast they are. So I've got a copy of a T. rex
skull in my downstairs from my office and yeah, I could fit comfortably through its mouth.
So it would be just about capable of swallowing me whole, and I'm a pretty big guy.
- Your body, you could fit- ... in it's, its mouth?
- I can fit through, I can fit through it.
- Wow.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. And it's not even a particularly big one. It's a copy of the one that's
in the Smithsonian, and they get bigger than that.
- You have a to-scale copy.
- Yeah, it's a cast, so it's just a giant mold made and then-
- Nice.
- ...pulled out like the dentist do your teeth, but very, very big. So yeah,
they are 12-ish meters long, so what's that? 14 yards. Four and a half, maybe five
to the top of the head, standing up. So another six yards high.
And then seven-ish metric tons. What's that?
About eight and a half short tons. So a colleague of mine, Tom Holtz,
described them as an orca on land, but that's it. It is a
killer whale-sized animal but on legs, on
land. And those are massive predators. So you're
looking at something absolutely colossal, and I think that is what will
stun you. I think people don't realize how big a lot of
animals are, which sounds weird, but I used
to work in a few zoos, and something I think you notice is when you go and see things like
elephants or giraffes or rhinos, everything's built to the scale of
the animal. The elephant house is huge. The doors are huge. The
bars are huge. The food is huge. And so you don't
see them in the context of something that you have a good
frame of reference for. And I learned this, yeah, when I was at London
Zoo and was going into the basement of the
old elephant and rhino pavilion, and a rhino stuck its head out from like this gap in
the wall, and the head was twice the size I thought it was
once you stood next to it. And the same with an elephant. I once stood next to an
elephant closer than you are to me now, and you go, "Oh, they
are so much bigger than I thought." And I think it's similar in
museums. Like even when you get up relatively close to a T. rex
skeleton, there's a bit of space between you and it, and then some
bars. And then it's usually raised up a little bit on a mount, on a little mount
to hold the platform. And then you stand back from that, and you don't
actually get to stand like under them. And when you do
that, you realize that, yeah, the foot finishes at my knee.
- So is a T. rex bigger than an elephant? That'd be fair to say?
- Yeah, I mean, a very large savanna African
elephant is five to six tons, and we're looking at seven plus.
And a biped and a carnivore. So
yeah, you know, a big lion. A big lion is 200 kilos. So 430 pounds. Yeah.
- Well, that's what, that's why I mean, it's why they consider it to be probably the
most epic predator in the history of Earth.
- Yeah, I mean, and I think more than that, it's I think it's one of the most iconic animals
period. I mean if you, if you're listing things that the average person has
heard of: lion, elephant, giraffe, tiger, hippo,
rhino. There's a few more, but T. rex is coming somewhere up in that
list. That, that's how prominent it is as an animal.
So yeah, it's, it, it's almost inescapable as a
paleontologist. And then doubly so for me, who works on dinosaurs, and doubly so again,
'cause I do work on tyrannosaurs. But yeah, it just dominates conversations.
- Well, some of the other features, maybe we can go through.
- Yeah, sure.
- So big skull, big head, small hands.
- Massive head. Very kind of boxy. It's very robust. Big forward-facing
eyes. Massive eyes. Massive. I mean, tennis
ball-sized eyes. These things had amazing eyesight.
Yeah. Giant teeth. There's a cast of a-
- What?
- ...Tyrannosaurus rex tooth.
- Yeah, I know. So-
- How...
- It, it looks a bit bigger than it is. So this is all root, so this would be stuck in the jaw. This would be supporting it.
- Right. But that tip part is-
- But that-
- ...that's the tooth?
- The tip, as you call it.
And, yeah, you know, so that would comfortably go through pretty much any part.
- Wow.
- And then you realize just how thick it is. So this is a cast of a
thing called Carcharodontosaurus from Africa. You get it down in
Niger and a few other places like that.
And they're very, very big. Not as big as T. rex, but not a
million miles away. And then if you look at the teeth in profile, they're a
surprisingly similar shape and not far off in size as
well. And then you look at them that way on, and you realize it's
a third of the width. So this isn't just massive,
it's thick. And of course, being thick, it makes it strong. And with
that giant head, with all that extra bone and then all the extra musculature
attached to that giant head, they've got this uber-powerful
bite and the ability to just chomp through basically anything it wants to.
So yeah, they are truly unusual in that regard, even actually compared to a lot of the
other very big tyrannosaurs, they're often a kind of step above
in their proportions.
- So, incredible crushing power in the jaw?
- Yeah. And then, as you say, like this really short, bull neck, 'cause you've got this
massive weight of this head up front that you need to hold it up and not tip
forwards. Really quite a massive body. Again,
there's two or three other big carnivorous dinosaurs which
people argue, oh, maybe they're a little bigger than T. rex, maybe they're a little smaller, but it's
always in terms of length, which is one way of looking at things. You know,
pythons are very long but
they're nothing like as massive as, yeah, a lion or a tiger. Same
thing. T. rex is massive. It is built. So really
big kind of barrel-shaped chest, making the body very, very big
as well. And so that's why, yeah, there's things like Giganotosaurus and
Mapusaurus from South America. Maybe they get a bit longer, another
meter or so in length. But in mass, we're talking about maybe
only two-thirds, three-quarters. So T. rex is just massively bigger
than basically any other big carnivore we know of.
And then, yeah, little arms, as you say. So this is a, not great, but
it's a cast of a T. rex arm. It's not the biggest animal.
They do get a bit bigger than this. But as I love showing, it's not a
million miles off the size of my own. And
I could do with a diet, but I don't weigh seven tons. So
yeah, it really is really pretty small.
- Two claws, two fingers.
- Yeah, so two fingers. You will see sometimes that they say there's a third.
This is a slight misnomer. So you do see this extra little bone here?
This doesn't turn up in all of them, and it's an extra hand bone.
So it's these, the metacarpals. But it's not supporting an extra digit.
- So mostly functionality-wise, it wasn't very functional.
- They're not doing very much at all. This is what's called the
deltopectoral crest. It's really important for big
arm movements because it's deltoids and pectorals. The radius and
ulna are really quite thin, thinner than ours. The fingers are pretty stocky.
The claws look big and curved, and they are, but
other tyrannosaurs, and indeed other carnivores generally,
have much more curved claws. And then they have these
little things, oh, where can I say it? There, there you can see there's a little mark.
That's a ligamentous pit. And so what you can imagine is,
if you're trying to hold onto something and something's wriggling, you want grip.
And there's a risk that you'll just dislocate your fingers. So we have
ligaments that hold bone to bone. And if you just put it
flat to flat surface area, there's only so much you can attach. Whereas if you turn
that into a little hemispherical dip, you get a lot more surface area for your area.
If that makes sense.
- Yeah.
- So if you have a really big ligamentous pit, it means there's a really big ligament,
which means your fingers are really strong and they're really resistant to being
wiggled around and pulled, as if you've grabbed something that doesn't want you to kill
it. Well, T. rex has probably the smallest ligamentous pits of any
tyrannosaur. So that kind of suggests it's not doing very
much. And again, when you look at the claws, proportionally, they're not that big and
they're not that curved. So even though it looks like quite a wicked
thing to us, remember, put this on a seven-ton animal
whose individual teeth are the size of entire fingers.
Suddenly that arm doesn't look like it's doing very much.
- What about the feet?
- So massive. Again, not surprisingly, you're supporting a
colossal amount of weight. But they have this beautiful
adaptation in the foot. So the equivalent bones in the foot, the
metatarsals, for us make up the flat of the feet. But these animals walk
like birds. They got three toes on the ground and then the metatarsals stick nearly
vertically. That overall extends the length of the leg, so you can walk a
little bit faster. You get a slightly bigger stride length. Don't worry,
I've got the right bone here.
- Nice.
- But they also have... Yeah, there's a good one. That one's a great one. But
they also have this really neat adaptation in the middle bone. So you
can see it on this one quite well, and that this is actually not a
tyrannosaur, this is an ornithomimosaur. So one of the really
ostrich-like ones, Gallimimus from the first Jurassic Park. It has the
same thing. You can see the normal bones would be really quite long and
square and then flat at the top. And instead, this thing shrinks in the
middle and turns into this kind of flattened diamond shape. And what that means
is... the bones either side kind of lock it. In
fact, at the top end, it actually tends to wiggle a bit. So it actually goes left and
then right. And of course, what that really does is then help these things
lock together. And so this is an adaptation to basically lock the
foot and make it stable, and we see it in a whole bunch of things,
independently evolved. Early tyrannosaurs don't have this. Early ornithomimosaurs don't have
this. The oviraptodiraurs, the early ones don't have this, and the later ones
acquire it, and a couple of other groups as well. And it's about making the foot
stable. And what that really does is make the foot energy
efficient. So you can imagine, as an animal, you know,
we have some cartilage and we've got some ligaments and tendons joining all the bones
together and holding joints stable. When you push down,
that's going to compress them to a little degree, and when you lift that weight off, they're
actually going to spring back. You're going to get a tiny little energy return. It's the
idea of those air soles they put in all the trainers and
stuff in the 90s. It's that same principle.
And you will. You'll get a little bit of energy return, but of course, big
force, particularly for a big, heavy animal, it's going to take the path of least
resistance. And so if your bones are all kind of loose in the
foot, what they're going to do is they're going to tend to splay out, and you're actually going to lose
that energy. But if you lock the feet together, the bones can't
move and instead, that's going to further compress those
soft tissue bits and give you a bit more spring.
- And this is all about... I mean, this is about the mobility, about the dynamics of the
movement.
- It makes you more efficient. It means you're putting less energy in to
walk, because you're just getting a little bit of spring of every single step.
- I should say that I deeply admire people like Russ Tedrake, like the Boston
Dynamics teams, like the Tesla Optimus robot teams
that look at bipedal and quadruped robot movement.
And they try to make human-like movement to, you know, basically
efficient movement. And so the question here is, how the hell is a
T-Rex its size, bipedal, able to move as a predator? It's a weird body shape,
is it not?
- I mean, the big head makes it look more odd, but you
look at dinosaurs as a whole, and over a third, probably 40, 45% is the group called
theropods, which were all bipeds, so T-Rex, Allosaurus, Velociraptor,
Spinosaurus, many, many others that people may have heard of, they're all bipeds
built in this way. There's a whole bunch of ancestral groups which were doing something very
similar, including various crocodiles or relatives of crocodiles,
and then the birds are bipeds. Birds are actually doing it in a much
weirder way than theropods are. Theropods are basically a lizard on its back legs.
I'm oversimplifying a lot. I can hear paleontologists screaming, as I've just said,
"It's a lizard standing up." It's not a lizard standing up, but they're doing a lot of the same
stuff in the same way, and that is really functionally about where
you put muscles, because what you really want to do to walk
forwards is you want to basically pull the leg back
so that you're pushing the body off.
And the way they do that is the musculature on the tail. We don't have a
tail, and indeed, mammals that even do have a, you know, elephants and even
lions, it's a piddly little thing. There's not a lot of muscle there.
But if you look at a lizard, particularly if you look at something like a crocodile, you see this
massive, massive block of muscle sitting on the first
third to half of the tail. And that's what dinosaurs
are doing. It's the same thing as lizards and crocs. They have this giant set of muscles on
the first half of the tail that's anchoring on the femur, so the thigh bone, on the
back of that, and muscles contract. That's the one thing they
do. But now you've got a giant muscle. And T-Rex, this muscle is
like two and a half, three meters long.
It's going to be like this wide in the middle. So when that contracts,
the leg goes back, the foot's stationary on the ground, so the animal goes
forwards.
- So the tail is...
- integral to movement.
- ...so it's a huge part of the biomechanics of the movement.
- Yeah, we do it with the butt. So we're kind of weirdly how
we organize our muscles. But this is
generally probably a better way of doing it, because you can get a really long
muscle. And of course, the longer the muscle, the more contraction you can have.
The hyper version of this is kangaroos. So kangaroos supposedly get more
efficient the faster they move. They get so much energy return
that when they're moving faster, they get more compression from the
landing, meaning they get more spring.
- So we should be imagining this gigantic thick tail, big body,
- Oh, yeah.
- ...big head.
- Yep.
- ...and biped. And how fast does it move?
- So this is one of those things that's gone backwards and forwards and backwards and forwards.
There was a paper arguing that we'd probably been overestimating various
speeds, primarily based on footprints. There's been I don't
know how many papers trying to do T-Rex speed. The most
recent one that was pretty detailed I think had it clocked
at... So I think it was 25 miles an hour, so 40 kph was the very
upper end of the estimate. So probably a bit less than that.
- Well, that means it can move.
- Yeah, so that's the thing.
Big things move quick. I've seen rhino and hippo going at
full tilt, and yeah, they're a lot quicker than you'd
think. And at least part of it is simply stride length. When
your legs are three-ish meters long, it's hard
not to cover a lot of ground with a single
step. And yeah, big theropods, T-rex is going to
be a power walker. It's not going to run in the conventional
biomechanical sense, where both feet are off the ground at once.
- So it's not running. It's power walking.
- Yeah. But when you've got a four or five meter long stride,
it doesn't really matter whether you're airborne or not.
- Power walking, so you're never... So, or running,
there are moments in time when both feet are off the ground, and you're
saying likely here one foot is always on the ground.
- Yeah, pretty much has to be for loading.
- Oh, just because of the mass of the thing? Okay. All right.
- You know, that's the origin of cinema?
- What's that?
- It's where... This is Eadweard Muybridge. So the
origin of cinema was a bet as to whether or not,
while running, a horse had all four feet off the ground.
And no one really knew this for sure. And a guy called Eadweard Muybridge,
he was British, but he was living in the States. He was a keen
photographer, and he basically did what people have
seen the Wachowskis do for The Matrix. He set up a whole row of
cameras and set up a whole bunch of triggers and had a horse run through
them, so it took loads of photos. And lo and behold, in one of them, the
feet were off the ground. The guy won his bet. But he also realized that we already had things
like zoopraxiscopes, you know, the little thing you spin with a slit?
So you see the... Right. So he did that with horses. And now you have
a moving photograph. And that's pretty much the origin of cinema, was...
a bet about biomechanics.
- Yeah, it's always a good question and a bet, and there you go.
You're off to the races.
All right, all right, so we're standing in front of this thing.
- Yes.
- How screwed are we, you and I? We're back in the time of the
dinosaurs. What's the probability of our survival?
- There's two big things to weigh up, which are going to be interesting, which is,
would they even consider us a potential meal?
Because we know that animals have never encountered things. Animals have to
learn stuff. And so animals that have never encountered things before are often...
They don't have a response because they don't know what their response should be.
- We should say during that time, there was not something that looked like primates.
- No. Absolutely nothing. We, we-
- So we would look very weird, right?
- We would look weird, yeah. So, you know, there's lots of really cool records of,
particularly you've got down in Indonesia and stuff,
where you've got these insane volcanic spires, and it leads to these tiny little
valleys. And people go in there, and they go, "Yeah, the animals walk up to us."
They've never seen a human. They don't know what it is.
So it might look at us, and... Animals are fundamentally
cautious. It doesn't know if we're a threat.
So maybe it might just find us weird or in some way,
shape or form off-putting, and so we may not even
be considered on the menu. The other thing
is we might be too small. My suspicion is we're not.
So animals, carnivores typically take stuff that is much, much smaller than them,
despite basically every dinosaur documentary movie
ever shows T-rex hunting an adult Triceratops, which is, like, the same size as
it. And every documentary, you gotta have lions taking down a wildebeest or even a
buffalo. Like, these are weird and rare outcomes. These
don't usually happen. The vast majority of active predation
is on stuff much, much, much smaller than you. I totted some of this up
for a paper I did on Microraptor, this really small gliding dinosaur from
China, where we actually have a bunch of specimens with various stomach contents in them.
And we were coming up with numbers of about, like, 5 to 20% of the mass being
typical, so prey versus predator. And that's
actually very similar to what we see with modern carnivores, and it's not
far off what we've seen even with things like tyrannosaurs, where you occasionally
find consumed bones from prey. So,
if we put the lower end of that as 5% of the mass of a T-rex, we might actually
be okay. If it doesn't consider us worth the hassle, then
assuming you're encountering a big adult and not a half-size one
that maybe only weighs a ton, then we might be all right.
- What would be the survival strategy? So there's a thing that you criticized
as not being true that I, I guess in Jurassic Park, not moving.
- Yeah, it's nonsense. They can see really well. Like I said, like,
T-rex has giant eyeballs. People don't realize
that 'cause, like whales and like elephants, it looks small compared to
the size of the animal, but what you're saying. And really important for vision is
absolute size, not proportional size. And absolutely, their eyes are gigantic.
- Probably the biggest on Earth at that time.
- Yeah. A guy called Kent Stevens did a paper, and he's got a really nice
graphic of it. If you just put Stevens T-Rex,
there, it's the one with the... There we go.
It's the one with the googly eyes. That's a baseball or a tennis
ball-sized eyeball. And when you think about the
incredible visual acuity of something like an eagle, which has eyes
not much bigger than ours, think about what that's going to
do. And we absolutely know, there's been loads of studies on this
in mammals and birds and other things as well.
that basically eyeball size correlates with visual
acuity. And that can fold in two different ways. It can be like general
sharpness. Like, how well can you see a long way away?
So eagles and vultures, it's really important. Or it can be good in low light.
- And I now discover that there's a Nature Was Metal- ...subreddit-
- On Reddit, yeah, for-
- ...which is looking at-
- ...gnarly, gnarly paleo things. Yeah, I come across it occasionally.
- For dinosaurs, let's see what's the top post of all time.
- Oh, that's a glyptodontid.
- An Argentinian farmer recently found a 20,000-year-old fossilized glyptodont.
- So these are giant armadillo-like animals with club tails.
- Interesting. Wow.
- Oh, that's Black Beauty, and that's at the Royal Tyrrell Museum. So giant
eyeballs, they can either see very well, they can see a very long way in daylight, or they
can see very well at night. And my suspicion is it's the latter. I think they're
probably primarily nocturnal, when they get that size.
- Well, not moving might be a good strategy because it's cautious because it doesn't understand
what these- ...primates are.
- Yeah. But I think if it starts coming towards you,
...if you're truly in the open, then you're in real trouble
and I'm not sure what you do.
I mean, the one thing, the one advantage humans have over almost
anything else on Earth, there's a handful of exceptions, is we have
range. I can pick up a rock and hurl it with reasonable
accuracy. Most things can't do that, and
animals probably don't like being hit in the face or hit in the eyes with a rock
at a range because, again, they're not going to know how it's happened or how to
respond to this. All they know is they're taking damage-
...and that's bad. And that might genuinely be enough to do it. I
wouldn't want to try, but again, if I was
dumped on a plain or a prairie with nothing else but a T-rex that was interested in
me, it's worth a shot. If you're in the
forest, I would try and get behind a tree. They're quite good at
turning. There's been a couple of nice papers looking at the mechanics of the foot
and the ankle and how quickly they could pivot.
But we're much better because we're just so much smaller. So it
would be very kind of Looney Tunes, but I think you could go round and round a big
tree- ...yeah, but much faster than it could. And so,
...it's going to get bored or lack interest sooner or later.
- So let's zoom out. What did it eat?
- I mean, you could go for the classic joke of whatever it wanted, but the
reality is the relatively big herbivores that are around at the time,
it's probably largely leaving them alone because, again,
just the classic dynamics of
predators even like, quote, super predators, like Tyrannosaurus, they're still
real animals. If you get injured and you can't hunt,
that's probably the end of you. So you don't want to
tackle an adult Triceratops that weighs the same as you and has
meter, a meter and a half long horns on its head and
it's potentially pretty aggressive, and then even the
big, so the Hadrosaurs, the kind of classic duck-billed dinosaurs, they're
not, they're not present with any like obvious defensives. They don't have armor.
They don't have horns or spikes or anything like this, but they're simply massive.
Again, you know, yes, T-rex has got the teeth and the bite and
even if they're a bit rubbish with the claws on the hands, but like just grappling another
animal which is the same size as it, there's a risk you're going to get a foot trodden
on, that it's going to get off some kind of body slam or whatever. And then even if you
do bring it down, you're never going to eat it. Like if you,
you bring down an animal that weighs five tons, it's nearly your own
mass. You're not going to eat it before it goes rotten. That's a huge amount of kind
of, not like wasted energy, but you've probably put a lot of effort into this and
you're not getting that much reward out. And again, there are,
again, there are exceptions. You've got things like lynx are the classic one. Lynx are not
very big cats and yet they'll hunt adult deer
way bigger than them. Lions hunt things like
buffalo, but they're operating in a group, so it's a bit of a cheat. So
there are some things that do this, but fundamentally, the vast majority of carnivores
tackle stuff that's way, way smaller than them, and that's what we see.
Every record we have of basically any large carnivorous
dinosaur where you have stomach contents, whether it's like
consumed something or healed bite marks, we get quite a, we get a
quite a few. There's a handful of them where there's an obvious damage to a
bone, in more than a couple of cases with a tooth broken off in the
bone, and then the bone has healed over it, so you know, it
got away. They're, they're juveniles. They're relatively young animals.
And that's what they're targeting. It makes
ecological sense. It's what modern animals do for very good reason.
Juveniles are relatively small and weak. They don't have the horns or
frills or armor or shields and other stuff. They're naive. They
don't, they have, you often have to learn what predators are or you have to
learn how to avoid them or to check the wind
or even physically see them before you know, see them kill
something else before you know that they're a threat. And juveniles forage
badly. They're relatively inefficient, so actually they need to eat
more for their size than an adult does. And on
top of that, they're not very experienced at foraging in the right areas. And even if they can
find a good patch, the adults will often beat them up and chase them off.
- You're talking about juveniles across various species?
- Everything. This is just a universal pattern of being a smaller animal versus a
larger, or a younger animal versus a larger animal.
- So, so hunting young, uh-
- Young things.
- ... young things is easier.
- Yeah because-
- Because they're dumb.
- Right. They're dumb, but they're inexperienced.
- Inexperienced.
- But they're often feeding in suboptimal areas. So this
is the place with all the best food. The adults will kick you off, so now you have to feed somewhere
else. Maybe the food isn't as good, in which case you need to eat more of it, so it takes
longer, or maybe it's the one next to the edge of the forest where the
T-rexes hide. But either way, you're stuck there and then you
don't really know what you're looking for and you haven't got the armor, so guess
who's getting eaten? Like this is,
again, there's lots of exceptions. You can't have nature without things like that.
But this is the absolute rule of thumb for how foraging and
growth and predation operate across everything from
fish to starfish, fish as predators, starfish, praying
mantis, all the way up to things like big cats via stuff like crocodiles.
It's how it works, so it'd be very weird if it didn't also
operate for dinosaurs. And as I say, we've actually got the direct evidence for this
from bite marks and stomach contents. They're taking small stuff.
- Bite marks give a lot of information. That's a powerful signal in paleontology.
- Yeah, absolutely. I've done really quite a lot of work on it and they can
tell you an awful lot if you've got the right understanding of the burial conditions,
because you, weird thing that I think a lot of people don't appreciate is
you basically can't take fossils at face value, particularly when you're trying to
get into stuff like behavior and ecology. So between the animal
dying and the paleontologist digging it up, potentially
quite a lot has happened, and that's where it's really
easy to start misinterpreting things because if you just go...
I had one like this not too long ago where I was an editor on a paper, and the authors had
done a pretty good job, to be fair, but it was this discussion of
whether or not several animals were together at the time of their death.
So multiple theropods together in this
quarry, and it's like, right, but there was loads of debris, and you had loads of
things like fish scales and other small bones, and it's like, okay,
but this looks like these animals potentially died somewhere
else, and then a flood or a river washed them into
this bay or a channel or the water level dropped and they ended up
together, but that doesn't necessarily mean they were together when they
died. And so just 'cause you've got three animals together,
what is potentially the story of how they got there?
- So you have to consider multiple explanations and then try to figure out what is the most
likely.
- Yeah, or what can you test with various bits of evidence? So there were
some tyrannosaur-inflicted bite marks on a duckbill
from Mongolia that I worked on years ago.
The specimen was from Mongolia, but it was held in Japan in a Japanese museum.
I was working with the Japanese on it.
I'm not a taphonomist or the study of decay and the history of specimens.
I am in no way, shape, or form a geologist. I did zoology for my degree,
but the guys I was working with, they were really hot on
erosion and damage, and they were looking at some of the
way the bones had been damaged, and they're like, "Okay, we're pretty confident that
the bite marks are sitting on top of erosion."
- What does that mean?
- So it means that the animal had died, and it was found in a it was
found in sand-covered, but in what would have been a river channel.
So this animal has died, washed downstream, ended up on a
sandbank. The sand is whipping past 'cause I've been in a sandstorm in-
in China. It is not fun, and that's starting to etch some of the
bones and damage them.
- And after that, there's a bite mark?
- After that, you're getting bite marks coming in. So that
- Oh, man.
- can only be scavenging. That thing has been dead and sitting out for
days, possibly weeks, before something came along and chewed on it.
- Wow.
- It pretty much can't have happened any other way.
- And you have to take these really subtle signals to-
- Yeah.
- to reconstruct the story.
- But then you can start piecing some other stuff together. So in this
case, the skeleton is pristine. It's one of the best hadrosaur
skeletons out there. It's certainly the best from Mongolia I've ever seen.
And all the bite marks are on one bone, the humerus, the upper arm bone.
Every mark- we went over the rest of the skeleton, nothing. And then the humerus is
chewed to bits. There's bites all over it, but when you look,
there are two really distinctive patterns. There are deep
circular punctures. Remember what the shape of this thing looks like, at the ends.
And then along the deltopectoral crest, okay, it's much, much bigger in a hadrosaur,
but this bit, remember, that's where all the big muscles attach. There are all of these
types of- this is from a different bone, but a different animal, but all these types of close
parallel scratches. And so that looks like selective feeding because it's using its
giant crunchy teeth at the ends to get the bone
off, and this is off a buried skeleton.
then it's got these- actually, T. rex has really small teeth at the front of
its mouth, right in the front where our incisors are. They're called
incisiform teeth. They look like incisors. They're a fraction of the
size of the big ones, and they've got a really weird flat back.
And that's what these are. It's hidden this with the front of the mouth and pulling.
- And that's mostly for eating?
- Yeah, and that's why it's just on the deltopectoral crest, 'cause that's where all the muscles are.
So I always liken it to getting something like an Oreo, and you take the
top off and then you scrape the cream out with your teeth.
I think most people have done that.
Right, but that's what it's doing. So it's got this little row of teeth-
...and everywhere you get lots of muscle, you get little rows of
teeth together, pulling.
- So there's different bite marks for sorting, fighting, killing, and
then there's different bite marks for eating.
- Yeah, so it kills and dismembers with the big teeth up the side-
...and then it feeds with the little front teeth.
- And all of that has evidence? In the bones?
What hunting strategy does it use? Can we figure that out?
- So that comes down to that foot stuff. Um,
they're relatively efficient compared to a lot of other things.
And particularly compared to the herbivores, so that means they're probably looking at long
distance rather than speed, and that makes sense 'cause even though the kind of stuff
we're talking about, like I said, maybe they get into 20, 25 miles an hour. That's
pretty quick, but some of the smaller stuff is going to be a lot faster than
that. And remember, that's a real upper estimate. They're- they're probably not that
quick, but yeah, almost-
- They're just jogging after you.
- Right, but they've got the distance, so yeah, so it's much more, uh-
...hyena or wolf-like strategy than like a
cheetah going for hyperspeed or a lion going for a relatively quick
burst, and it either gets you or it doesn't. And then people
kind of then just go, "Well, like, but that's ridiculous. Like, they're not even that quick," and it's like, yeah,
but if you're hunting something big that's not that
quick either, and so that's a misconception. Like when I'm talking about juvenile
dinosaurs, I don't mean just out of the egg and weigh a
kilo. Like a juvenile Triceratops can still weigh a ton-
...and be the size of a rhino. They're not that fast, and
again, if you get a head start on them because, as I said, I suspect they're
nocturnal. That's the other thing, it's really hard to hide a T. rex, even
lions and tigers struggle to kind of hide in long
grass. When you're three and a half, four meters tall, you can't
hide. Maybe in a forest, but even then, you're probably going to stick
out, and it's going to be hard to maneuver between the trees. We've got big tyrannosaurs
living in what we know to have been relatively open environments. Maybe there's some
stands of trees, but it's not a woodland or a forest or anything
like that. So they're living in the open and surviving in the open, so they've got to have a
way of doing this. I think it's either some combination of being nocturnal, so it's
relatively easy to... "sneak" isn't quite the wrong word, but
approach things to cut the distance down for your initial
strike and then just running them down. Because, yeah,
maybe a one-ton Triceratops or one-ton Hadrosaur is rather
faster than you, but if you've covered the first couple of
hundred meters to get up to your top speed before they start
running, then you're probably much closer to
them. Then will they exhaust faster than you'll keep
going? Probably not 100% of the time. No predator's that
effective. But I suspect that's what they're doing, and it fits with what we know of
their size, their vision. They have a very good sense of smell. Again, that
makes sense at night. It makes less sense if you're diurnal and operating primarily
in the day. You've got to hide this thing, and then we know they're
pretty efficient versus relatively fast but not that efficient prey.
- Well, there's a bit of a debate of scavenger versus hunter.
- They're obviously both. A, because we've got things like the bite marks I just
described, which is pretty much definitive scavenging. Then we've got
the healed bite marks with T-rex teeth buried in bones, which is pretty much
definitive active predation. So we've got evidence of it doing both.
- But can we possibly figure out what was the primary strategy?
- That gets much harder. My guess is they're probably still
primarily actively carnivorous. Because if you look at
stuff that's reliant on being a
scavenger, I mean, the true scavengers, like the vultures and
condors and stuff like this, you have to be ultra-long
distance, very energy-efficient travelers. They're
soaring in thermals. They're barely using any energy to
fly. It's really hard to get very far.
- How far were they spread? Where did they live?
- So the ones we've found, you've got them from Alberta
down to probably New Mexico. There's
some... I want to say there's some tyrannosaurine, so
very close to T-rex, teeth that may or may not be T-rex in New
Mexico. There are similar teeth in Mexico proper, down in
Coahuila, so about halfway down Mexico.
- Mongolia also, or no?
- So Mongolia, you have a thing called Tarbosaurus, which is a very, very close relative of T-rex.
It's the nearest species, or nearest genus, that we have.
genus, that we have. But T-rex is probably
occupying almost all of western North America.
So at times, the east was kind of split off and separate.
- But the entire surface of Earth had dinosaurs on it. Well, most of it.
- Yeah, we've got them in Antarctica. We've got them in Antarctica even close to the mass extinction event.
the mass extinction event.
- Just an insane number of dinosaur species all over the Earth,
just the same kind of variety we have in the animal kingdom today, you just have
in the dinosaur.
- I mean, this is, like, how many dinosaur species were there? I- I mean,
I basically wrote an entire book chapter about this
because there's so many. But this would make the number high, but this would make the number lower,
this would make the number high, but this would make the number
lower, counter versus counterarguments,
that you can guesstimate almost any number and probably be very accurate or very far out.
very accurate or very far out.
- Yeah, but we should say that a large number of dinosaur species are constantly being
discovered.
- Yeah, so we've named, give or take, in the realm of
1,500, 1,600 valid species. Though that is, not everyone agrees on every species,
not everyone agrees on every species, but most people would be satisfied with that number.
number.
But we also name in the realm of 40 to 50 a year, and we've been doing that for at least
the last 10, 12 years. That number is rocketing
up. Shows no signs of slowing down. There's loads of are-
Like, we still never really explored India very much. We're starting to find entirely new beds in places
new beds in places like Ecuador. Argentina we know has a ton of stuff, but we've never
we know has a ton of stuff, but we've never excavated there very much. Australia,
we know there's a ton of stuff and we haven't excavated there very much. So there's
lots of places, even now, to still go through.
- This is a good moment to take a brief tangent and look at paleontology. So how do we,
how do we find these fossils? What's the magic? What's the science? The art?
the science? The art?
- The same way, more or less, that people did in the
1750s or whenever you first start getting them. There's...
There's... For dinosaurs in particular, but this is true of the vast majority of stuff,
there's essentially two ways of doing it. The simple one is where you have
The simple one is where you have
quarries of particularly things like lithographic limestone, so the printing limestones,
the printing limestones, or stuff that's very similar to
that sometimes it's often volcanic you get
these super, super, super fine layers of sedimentation. And that's where you get these places of exceptional
get these places of exceptional preservation. Whenever you see, like, the feathers, or almost
feathers, or almost always, whenever you see feathered dinosaurs, it's like, "Oh, we
got the skin, we got the claws," and the whole skeleton's laid out. So
Archaeopteryx being the first bird is an absolute classic example.
it's from these beds. And there you find them by basically splitting limestone. We don't
splitting limestone. We don't usually dig for them. It's because there are
quarry workers and people who are already doing this because the
stone is useful, because there might be one decent
fossil for every, you know, few hundred tons of rock you shift. In which
case, you could get every paleontologist in the world there for a couple of
years and you wouldn't find very much. You rely on the fact that hundreds of guys are doing this
constantly. And then sooner or later, they'll find something, and then you've got
it. That's the super easy way. The only slightly more complicated way is you go to
somewhere where geologically we know it's the right age and it's the right
kind of rock and ideally fossils have been reported from there
before. And again, you know, geologists mapped all the world's
geology years ago in quite a lot of detail. There are gaps, there are
places where we don't have the details, but in general we know. And then you
go there and then you walk around and you look. And that's basically it.
- And you're looking for something that's sticking out of the rock.
- Yeah. So you always get the... So there's
this constant, and I think, you know, borderline
myth of the idea that dinosaurs and mammoths and lots of
other fossil things, like, entered lots of indigenous cultures
because it's impossible that the guys were wandering around,
say, Dakota, and the Native Americans didn't come across
some dinosaur fossils. That I'd agree with. It's pretty much impossible they
didn't come across some dinosaur fossils. Did they come across a whole
skeleton laid out on the ground? No, because those don't usually exist
because even if they're tougher, or it doesn't matter if they're tougher or weaker
than the surrounding rock, dinosaur bones
are, you know, in some way, shape, or form, they're lithified. They turn to
rock and they will absorb some of the minerals from
whatever they've been buried in. And so even in places like
Mongolia and Northern China where I've been to, where actually the
fossil bone is quite a lot tougher than the sandstone that it's embedded in.
You can find a bit of bone and pull it out, almost like rub it with your hands and the
sand comes off and there's your bone. They will decay pretty quickly. You know,
sandstorms, you know, sand just etches stuff. The
tiniest bit of moisture, particularly in winter, gets into the cracks. Bones are incredibly
porous. That freezes, that expands, that cracks, bones just
shatter. And yeah, you find shattered bone on the
surface everywhere. What you rarely find is a
decent bone on the surface, let alone a skeleton.
- So there has to be something that's sticking out just a tiny bit-
- so that you can see it, but it's still buried. Right. And it happens. The
greatest one that I saw, or that I didn't see, it happened
with a friend of mine when we were in Northern China
and he went, "Yeah, I can see a bit of a claw sticking out of a hill." And it was
like this much. You could see
you know, less than a centimeter coming out of a hillside. And
it's like, so you know,
- That's the dream, right?
- Dig a little bit, and there's a little bit more. Dig a little bit, there's a little bit more. Okay.
And then the system we were running there is some guys were searchers and some
guys were diggers. So he and I were searchers. We're told, "Okay, you guys have..."
He found it. "You found something, go and look for something else. We'll dig it out."
And so we come back a couple of days later and check in on the digging team.
"So what is it then?" "Oh, it's a complete skeleton." And it was a thing,
a very, very close relative of Velociraptor. Ended up
naming it Linheraptor, so the raptor from Linher, which was the nearest
town. And it was, yeah, the legs were a little messed up
because water had got to them and the end of the tail was missing and that was about
it. So like 90-plus percent complete skeleton, and it had been found
with, you know, five mil, a couple of sixteenths of an
inch of bone sticking out of a hill. And that's what you want, because every
so often behind that is a whole skeleton. If you're looking for skeletons
on the surface, they're going to be gone before you get to them.
- And when it's a near-complete skeleton, you, you did a show of,
Terrible lizards on Stan.
- Oh, yeah.
- the T-Rex fossil that sold for $31.8 million.
- Sight and some of them.
- So that, that's a nice sort of big adult T-Rex. So looking at a fossil like this...
...so for $31.8 million, what's the excavation process
for when you have a claw sticking out, like you were mentioning, and getting that
whole thing out without damaging the bones? What can you say about that process?
- So it depends where you are. It depends how many people you've got.
It depends on your budget and it really depends on the rock.
So again, like going into China or Mongolia, where this little guy's
from, the bone tends to be relatively strong
compared to the sandstone that it's in. That
also, that means that, A, it's fairly tough and resistant,
but it also means that it's really easy to
dig. Like again, I've dug stuff by almost like pulling it with my hands or
like getting my fingers in. Getting something like a chisel or a
hammer, you can just cruise through this rock.
- But like, you have to be really careful not to touch the bone, I guess?
- So it depends how strong it is. So again, some bone
is incredibly strong, some isn't because they've all fossilized
differently. What we're usually doing is applying glue to it though.
There's this wonderful stuff called Paraloid, and it's a special glue
for fossils. And I said bone's super porous, so
it's really good at sucking up liquids.
- Oh, so you're basically filling it with glue so it like makes it stronger.
- Yeah, and Paraloid's really great because you can dissolve it with acetone,
and it basically doesn't react with anything. So you can fill your fossil with
glue, but then if you want to take all that glue out, you can pretty much just
dissolve the glue back out again.
- Very cool.
- So, yeah, what you would normally do is for something, say in China,
where the rock is relatively soft and the bone's relatively
tough, and where we don't have any, like,
manpower and shipping problems, which is a real issue in other
places, you basically map out where you think the skeleton's
going. So in the same way that you were doing it, like, you know, if you can imagine
like a cake or something and someone said, "Oh, put a toy dinosaur in there."
And you've got to find it without damaging it. Sort of like, well, you'd stick your finger in the
cake and just kind of dig until you hit the edge of it and then you go in somewhere else and go in.
And that's what we're doing. We're just going in from kind of all sides. And once you've
hit three or four bones, you kind of know which way it's going into the
hillside, usually. Sometimes they're very weird and mixed up.
And then you can just almost trace the outline of it. And
then you'll just dig all the way around that, which might involve
taking the top off a mountain, depending on where you are.
In the desert, it tends to be a bit easier. But yeah, we've had stuff where,
like the first three days is just ten people with pickaxes just
digging a hole to get down to the right level.
- But sometimes the excavation requires like large equipment, right?
- Yeah, we've used jackhammers and stuff. We've used a backhoe and we've just
literally driven it into the desert and just dug a big hole next to the
fossil. And then the classic thing of covering it in
a plaster of Paris jacket. Strips of burlap sacking,
plaster of Paris and some water, wooden beams if you want to
make something really big and really solid, and just
basically wrap it all up and then take it out.
And that's, again, that's what they were doing 150, 200 years
ago, that hasn't changed. Where it gets more
complicated is if you've got really hard rock that's very hard
to get through, particularly if the bone is fragile. Then it becomes difficult
because if you want to get a jackhammer in, the vibrations mean you're
going to shatter your bones before you've even
cut through the rock. So then you might be down to doing it manually.
- And manual is like-
- Yep, hand-chipping it out. Yeah, the other way you end up with that is
like the classic Jurassic Park thing, like, was it the
second scene where they're digging in the desert and there's the whole skeleton
laid out and five or six guys all digging around it and exposing
it. And that's actually quite common in the States. And the
reason is huge amounts of those excavations are being done
on government land, their national parks or whatever, or protected land.
And very often the rules are, you're not allowed wheeled vehicles,
full stop, at all, to protect the environment. You can walk in and walk out, but you
can't drive.
And it's like, well, when we're in the desert in Mongolia or in China or
Mongolia, and we're allowed to do this, literally, yeah, my boss drove into
town, hired a guy with a JCB. He drove
out, picked it up with a bucket and drove it back into town and put it on the back of
a flatbed and we drove it to Beijing. If you're out in a
protected area and you can't, you've got two choices. You
can take it out by hand, but that means it's got to be light enough.
that half a dozen people can lift it.
Which if it's a block of stone the size of this desk, you know, a couple of meters by a couple of
meters by a meter high, is basically impossible. So that means
you've either gotta carve chunks off, so take the head off, take the
arm off and whatever, and you can get it out that way, but it's not
ideal. There's always the risk of breaking, you're losing some information,
and if you wanna make a really spectacular display, you don't wanna join
through every big bit of bone. You want to show the public one piece.
So the alternative is to get rid of every bit of rock you
possibly can to make it light enough to helicopter it out.
- Wow.
- And so normally... So in China, if we hit that bit of bone
going in, we're just like going in round the sides until we've hit
Take the top off, take the bottom off, and just take it so the
skeleton is completely encased in rock and it's as safe and secure as it can
be. And then we'll do the preparation work back at the lab.
- That's heavy though.
- But-
- That's real heavy.
- If you're going to have to lift it with a helicopter and they've got a weight limit of only a
couple of tons or if it's not, then you need to pay twice as
much more expensive helicopter, then you take off every gram of
rock that you think you can-
... to get the weight down so you can ship it. So it, so it varies
massively. Yeah. Something the size of Stan, that's, that's months of work.
You're, you're probably doing that across three or four years with a team of half a dozen
people.
- So can we just talk through? Because just using Stan as a case study,
Stan was first discovered in the spring of 1987 by amateur paleontologist, Stan-
Skekanson in Hell Creek Formation near Buffalo, South Dakota.
- Yeah. But it was the Larson brothers from the Black Hills Institute who dug it up.
And so they're, they're a commercial outfit, so they dig stuff up
to sell it. But they also make casts and sell them.
This, oh, I brought my other... I do have a cast, a cast of one of Stan's teeth.
- Oh.
- So like you can buy casts of Stan's teeth. You could buy casts of the head.
you could buy the whole skeleton.
- So it's a famous skeleton.
- You see Stan in a whole bunch of different places. There's a Stan just up the
road from here at Oxford. Oxford's got a cast of Stan.
- Oh.
- I was just at Lyme Regis the famous fossil locality in the south of the
UK a couple weeks ago. One of the fossil stores has a skull of Stan in the window.
Stan turns up again and again and again.
- So the process as written here involved removing the overlying rock.
...using heavy equipment like a Bobcat.
- Yeah, so we call that the overburden, the extra stuff that's all
the rock that's sitting above the layer with our fossil in.
And when you're lucky, that's a foot of sandstone, and you shovel it out in an hour.
And I've seen guys in South America. There was a team in
Argentina, I think it was my old boss, Ollie Rowhurst, showed me this.
And they took like 20, 30 feet off the top of a hill to get down to this
fossil, you know. Something, you know, it was
probably half an acre in size, 20, 30 feet of rock.
- This is incredible.
I wonder if you could speak to some of these other components: Carefully extracting each fossil bone by
hand with picks and brushes, plotting and diagramming the bones...
...using a grid system at the dig site, wrapping the bones in burlap and
plaster for safe transport to the BHI lab. Some of this stuff you've
spoken to. What's with the diagramming? What's with the plotting and the diagramming?
- So yeah, you may well have seen something like this for
archeology shows or something like that. Nowadays, again,
tech's getting better; people are using drones and stuff for this,
or taking hundreds of photos and then building photogrammetry models.
You just get a 3D model in the computer.
- Or just kind of modeling what we're looking at here.
- Yeah, but where you found everything. So it goes back to that stuff we were saying
about the process of fossilization or the process of what's happened to that
animal from death to discovery. A classic thing is bones being in a line.
So you can imagine if, you know, bones are lots of weird shapes,
but mostly, or at least certainly lots of bones, ribs, arms, and
legs, things like this, they're quite long bones.
So if they're in a current, they will tend to spin in the axis so that they
are facing the current. So if you're finding all the bones are in a
line, that probably tells you that this thing has had quite a lot of
water washing over it.
- Mm-hmm. Got it.
- You're then probably going to be missing most of the small bones because the big heavy bones won't
be shifted by that current, but maybe the small ones will.
- Oh, so you actually model where the bones, where you're likely to find the bones,
the big bones, the small bones...
- So it might tell you where to go and dig further down the hill, quite
literally, but it can also just tell you, "Okay, this thing, there's
no way this thing died here. It absolutely got moved,
so we need to factor that in when we're trying to interpret it."
- Okay.
- Or we've got this one weird bone and we can't work out what on earth it
is. Well, maybe it's from something else because if we know a whole bunch of stuff washed
together, maybe that's a random bone from a different animal.
- Yeah. Maybe that was eaten or there might be a different story if it was washed
like you were describing.
- Any of that kind of thing. So that's where you want to have as much
information as possible.
- It says here, "Once at the lab, the bones underwent more than 30,000 hours of
cleaning, preservation, restoration, and documentation." And,
Stan's skeleton is notable for its high degree of completeness,
about 70% by bulk, 63% by bone count, and the
exceptional preservation of its skull, which has become a scientific standard for the
species.
- Yeah. So there's this unbelievably beautiful skeleton,
Borealopelta. This is a helicopter lift. Absolutely.
- It's awesome.
- Phenomenal preservation from
- What?
- Northern Alberta.
- What is this thing?
- Its full name is Borealopelta markmitchelli, and it's called
markmitchelli, named after Mark Mitchell, the preparator, who
basically spent, I think Mark spent the thick end of two years on
this. This was his job. And he did other stuff as well. He's doing some
other prep, he's doing some fieldwork. But Mark basically went in
every day, nine to five, cleaning the rock because the rock was
hard and the bone was soft, and it's extraordinarily well-preserved.
- Borealopelta is a genus of plant-eating armored
dinosaur. Sure as hell looks armored. This is an incredibly preserved specimen.
- Yeah.
- from the early Cretaceous period, about 112
million years ago, found in what is now Alberta, Canada. Amazing.
- Yeah.
- Look at this thing.
- So Borealopelta is one of the ones where we've even got some of the evidence
of patterning, and it suggests that it's darker on top and lighter underneath. So this
illustration, I think that's, yeah, that's Julius Chattoni did that. He's a Canadian
paleo artist, and so that color pattern is roughly accurate.
- Oh, wow. So this is true to color.
- Yeah.
- And so we can figure out the colors that
- Well, give or take some very large uncertainties
- Look at this thing.
- it's going to be something like this.
- That's so awesome.
- Yeah. So these guys are
- That's hard to eat, that thing.
- nearly armored pine cones. Yeah. Though it's very much the
adult condition. The juveniles seem to be far less, if not unarmored.
- We're back to the juveniles thing.
- Right. So, right, so
So, but that's why we... That armor is absolutely going to be effective
as anti-predator, but it's probably evolved primarily for
combat and display between members of the species because otherwise if
they stopped you being eaten, the babies would have it.
- This fossil is considered one of the best- preserved dinosaur specimens ever
found, with armor, skin, keratin sheaths, and
even stomach contents all intact. Incredible.
And so for that, he really did the work.
- And also found miles and miles and miles out to sea, or
the, the paleo sea. So this is from a site which normally gives us big marine
reptiles. So predatory plesiosaurs and ichthyosaurs and
and then mosasaurs and stuff like that.
And then it turned up an Ankylosaur. Well, Nodosaur in this case.
- Yeah. Wow. This is incredible.
So, okay. Let's complete the journey of Stan to the museum
to, like, you get, you get to the process of cleaning everything, stitching it all together.
- Yeah. Like Mark suggested, you know, this can be
even with an animal that size. Borealopelta is, you know, four or five meters long.
We've only gotten the front two-thirds of it. Yeah. This can be, like,
needle-level stuff.
- That's how you get to the 30,000 hours.
- Yeah. Exactly that, if it's that quality and you want to get everything
open. And then something like Stan, actually really complicated
skull. The skull's full of lots of little bones. The bones are really
fragile. So that just adds to the time. I mean, at least with the Ankylosaurids,
the skull is just this giant solid block of bone, which makes life a little bit
easier. So yeah, they're going to put those hours in, and that's really going to help them
sell the animal, which is ultimately what happened. I mean, Stan sat in the Black Hills
Institute for decades. I mean, '87, and they sold it in like
2020, so they had it for 30
years sitting in their kind of little museum. And then my
understanding was basically the brothers broke the company up and that's why
they sold it.
- Yeah. But it was still incredibly surprising that it was sold for 31 million.
- Yeah. I mean, far more than I think anyone thought it was going to. I mean,
I, I liken... Well, you know, if you're not buying, like, teeth or an ammonite in
some small fossil shop, you know, when you're talking about things like whole dinosaurs and whole
tyrannosaurs, I think it's a bit like the art market in it's worth
what people will pay for it. And so, you know-
... plenty of T-rexes had sold for a few million dollars and therefore everyone thought it
would, might be five. You know, ten would be an absurd
sum of money. And then yeah, it, it went for
30 and it's like, "Okay, well... Two." I was going to say, someone
wanted it that bad, but clearly not two people wanted it that bad, because if only one guy is
prepared to bid 30, then it goes for, you know, a million more than the
next highest bidder. But presumably, two people, if not three, bid
it to get that high.
- Yeah, it was anonymous at the time, but now it's Abu Dhabi's Department of
Culture and Tourism came out that they were the ones.
- I know they've got it.
- And that record has since been beaten, apparently, by, uh...
- by Apex, the Stegosaurus, which I still haven't
seen, though a friend of mine has sent me some photos of this thing.
- Is it impressive to you, this thing?
- No, not especially. That's why I can't imagine that it sold for that much. It's a
really nice Stegosaurus. It's a pretty big Stegosaurus.
- Well preserved.
- I've seen other very good Stegosaurus, and I don't understand why that's worth
that much more than something like Stan. But it shows you the
market. So, we're here in London. There's a Stegosaurus called Sophie in the
Natural History Museum in London. Sophie is a young
animal, so she's not very big. I mean, it's a sizable specimen. I'd
say five-ish, six meters, off the top of my head, total length.
But Sophie's truly exceptional. There's a couple of
plates missing, a handful of ribs, a couple of bones in the tail. I
think a couple of toe bones. This is, by far, the most complete
stegosaurus out there.
- Wow.
- That sold for, I think, 250,000 pounds, so maybe
$400,000, about a decade ago. So this has now gone up, like, 100-fold
for an animal which is quite a bit bigger but is way less complete.
So, for me, those two things kind of balance out
because size is always impressive, and that's what the public likes, but also a complete
one is better than a half a one or two-thirds of one. So yeah. So how has
the price gone up 100 times, or from 400,000 to 40,000,000 in 10 years
for roughly the same thing?
- A T-rex is a little bit more epic than
- Well, that's the thing.
- a Stegosaurus.
- T-rex has a massive premium on it,
because it's, yeah, a Stegosaurus is one of those
top-tier, you know, it's... You can virtually do the list.
You know, T-rex, Triceratops, Diplodocus, Brontosaurus, Stegosaurus. It's
in that first six or seven. Okay, these days, Velociraptor, thanks to
Jurassic Park. But it's... Right, there's the list of seven
or eight things that any random human
who doesn't care about dinosaurs and doesn't know anything about dinosaurs, but they've probably heard of them.
You know, Stegosaurus is in that list and would have an idea of what it looked like.
Oh yeah, it's got like the big stuff stuck along the back. You'd get that answer
from almost any, you know, 99% of people on the
street. But yeah, it's not a T-rex. So how it's worth, yeah, 50% more
So how is it worth 50% more, and it's not even a particularly complete skeleton, to my
understanding? I don't get it.
- Actually, since we're on the topic of money, if I gave you, let's
say, $10 billion, how would you spend it? I'd force you to spend it
on dinosaur-related things. How would you spend it?
- I mean, I'd probably drop half a billion or so on the best museum you'd ever seen.
- So, put together a museum. You're like one of the great communicators.
One of the great scientists, and so you would want to push forward the whole field.
- Yeah.
- And one of the ways to do that is a great museum, actually.
- Yeah, but you want to... So it's twofold because,
yeah, there's the communication and the education part of it, which is something I'm massive on,
and I think research is pointless if you don't communicate it at some
level. I'm not saying everyone needs to communicate everything. If you're working on the
nuances of a calculation of the volume of a black hole or something,
yeah, it probably doesn't need a press release or a new museum exhibition. But
fundamentally, we should be talking about our work. But also, you've got to
store this stuff. Many fossils are fragile. They need to be kept
not necessarily in climate control, but at least you want a basement
that is much more even than, you know,
just sticking it in a box in a warehouse somewhere. So you've got to be able to
store this stuff to be able to study it, or it's kind of pointless.
But with the rest of that money, I'd buy a ton of land, like the
quarries that gave us Archaeopteryx in Bavaria and have given us a ton of
other stuff. I've worked on a load of pterosaurs, the flying reptiles from there.
These stuff are mostly
commercially run or just straight-up privately owned and not being
commercially run. Someone's just inherited it, and is just sitting on this stuff.
- So if somebody's building stuff on land, does that threaten the possibility
of discovering something on it?
- It's more that they're not necessarily exploiting it with fossils in mind.
- Presume you have to balance the search efforts and then the land by-
- Yeah, but you know, one billion on its own would go a
very, very long way, almost infinitely, if you're just creaming off the
interest and then funding excavations and supporting scientists
who are already embedded in other museums or other universities or other
research institutes.
- So the rest is for buying up land so that those people can do their work.
- Yeah, you look at somewhere like, you know, Brazil, and there's... I can never remember the name
of it, but there's, again, one of these zones of exceptional preservation where
superlative pterosaurs, fish... We've had a handful
of dinosaurs and a whole bunch of other stuff has come out, and it's just a giant
commercial mining operation. And yeah, when they hit a fossil when
they think they're close to it, yeah, they stop and pull it out and they'll send it to
a museum, and more often they'll sell it to a museum, and museums only have so much
money. Whereas what if I owned that quarry
and then I made sure everyone who worked there was trained and got a bonus every
time they found anything and then I just handed everything they dug
up straight into a museum?
- So there would be some element of a crowdsourced paleontology or...
- Yeah, but it's more that like no researcher ever needs to...
spend money to access that. No museum needs to go and find a new
donor to give them half a million to go and buy this
one specimen, knowing that it might still go, yeah, to some Silicon Valley
billionaire's foyer or whatever. It's like, "Well I own the land,
so it's mine, so problem solved." Like, that's what's in my head.
- It just would be wonderful to scale up the effort to where we can map
out the whole, sort of, story of this time, because it's such a fascinating
time in the history of Earth.
- I've jokingly written a couple of times about
how all science funding in the world should go to paleontology.
And the idea being that, like, if you want to investigate black
holes or neutrinos or chemical crystallography or
panda genetics or whatever it is, you can do that
any time you want. That's not gonna
change a million years from now as it will from tomorrow.
But fossils are in places that erode, and if we don't dig them up,
they're gone. So we should dig all the
fossils up now and then we've got forever to study them.
But if we don't dig them up now, who knows, maybe there's something twice the
size of T-Rex and it sat on a hillside for six months and then the wind
got to it and it's gone and that was the only one that ever preserved. Well,
we'll never know now. To be clear, this is a joke.
I'm not suggesting we should stop doing cancer research and physics and other
things, but it is, we're in a fundamentally different field
where our science is literally disappearing.
- Yeah. I mean, I know it's a joke, but there's some truth to it. And,
on the flip side, one of the things, one of
the hopes is that technology will somehow ease the search and discovery
process, but as you said, so far most of it...
- It hasn't. Yeah, I mean...
- So far.
- Yeah. You know, Jurassic Park '93, you've got that little scene where they've
got the, like, thumper or something they call it, and it hits the ground and seismic,
and then they go, "Look, look! Here's the whole
skeleton." They tried it. It doesn't really
work. We've tried looking for stuff with
drones. That helps you getting into some inaccessible
areas, but until the resolution is probably better,
you've still got that problem of, like, looking, you know, with human
eyes which are binocular, and being able to, you know, just tilt
your head completely changes how you see something in a way that flying
over just won't. I know they've
tried looking... So because the bones are porous, they tend to suck things
up, so actually dinosaur bones can be really radioactive if they're in areas
where there are
things like uranium. So yeah, there are drawers which have lead boxes
around them and stuff like this for dinosaur bones, or just signs saying, "Do not
handle." They're very low-level radioactive.
Like, you'd have to stick it in your pocket for six months to run any real risk.
But they're radioactive, much more so than the background. So can we do
that? Hmm, turns out, not really. So again, maybe tech will advance.
- But for now-
- Right, and-
- ... humans are quite incredible.
- Yeah, we are. But also, paleo's kind of at the bottom of the
pile, you know. There's not many of us. We don't have a lot of funding.
It takes real money to adapt stuff. So, you know, like, we're scanning stuff
with MRIs and things like that in hospitals, but it mostly doesn't
work very well because the problem you've got is, like I said, the bones
take on some of the properties of
the minerals in which they're embedded, which means their
density is really similar, and things like MRIs or
seismic activity is basically looking for differences in density. What if it's the
same density as the- you know, it's like I put some green plasticine in some
blue plasticine, there's gonna be a bit of a join and they're gonna be very, very
slightly different. But ultimately, you're not gonna be able to detect
that through most means if you're looking for density or mass or anything like that.
- Well, I personally think that there's few things as important to
understand as the history of life on Earth.
There's like books, right? There's like a-
or maybe you could think of it as chapters, and then one of the chapters is the time of the
dinosaurs- and then there's a great extinction, so it just goes up and up.
- I mean, that's not a million miles off. I think Darwin had an analogy like
that of we've got a few words on a few pages
spread out, but between them you get an idea of what the
story is and where it's going.
- I think what humans don't quite realize is we may end up
being just a chapter in a book. It might be our
extinction event, self-created, perhaps a nuclear war,
perhaps robots take over, perhaps we don't know.
- Well, or dumb luck. I mean, the dinosaurs were doing absolutely fine until
a dirty great rock hit them and you
can't, you know, Ben Affleck and Bruce Willis movies aside, there's
only so much you can do about that.
- Hey, you take that back.
There's nothing they can do wrong. All right. Quick pause. Bathroom break?
We've taken a few tangents, but let's continue on the thread of T-Rex.
Go to the skull. So the skull of T-Rex is iconic. You describe it as
being incredibly robust and overbuilt.
- Yeah. There's a lot of bone on there. So we mentioned a couple of other
things, like Giganotosaurus, is this, you know, giant carnivore. If you put
Giganotosaurus T-Rex in- That's the one. So that's, yeah, that's from my old blog.
It's not my image. Um...
- What are we looking at, on the left and the right?
- So you've got T-Rex on the left, in orange, and Giganotosaurus on the right, in red.
As I said, they're pretty similarly sized, but just look at the
robusticity. Like, the front of the snout of T-Rex is all
bone. And yet, the major openings, there's a thing called the antorbital fenestra,
the opening in front of the orbit, is absolutely massive in Giganotosaurus. It's like
half the skull. The opening at the back of the skull is much
bigger. The opening in the lower jaw is much bigger. And actually, the
jaw, what you can't see, side to side, is much thinner. So
their heads are the same size, and as animals, they are about the
same linear dimensions. But you can just see, there's just way
more bone in the T-Rex.
- It's incredible.
- So it's not overbuilt; it's obviously evolved that this is the
right amount of bone for the stresses and strains, for what it's doing and how it's acting.
But you compare it to anything that's not a very large
tyrannosaur, and suddenly you see just how much bone
has gone into it. It is a very large... It's an absolutely
large head, but it's a very heavy head with a lot of bone. And a lot of that bone
is there to resist all the forces of all the muscles, because it has this giant,
super-powerful bite. Which again, you can see in the teeth.
- So the bone and the muscles kind of evolve together...
- Yeah, yeah.
- ...to get bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger. So you need this kind of structure for the power that,
...the crush has.
- So one of the big things tyrannosaurs have... And this goes all the way
down to the earliest tyrannosaurs were like our size. Like little diddy
things, like two, three meters long, be a meter and a half tall.
But they have fused nasals. So the pair of bones that,
in us there's not a lot there, but obviously in something like a dog or something like a baboon with a long
nose, it's like the whole top of the snout. And there's two, one each side.
In tyrannosaurs, they fuse together, so it forms a solid bit of
bone. So the whole top of the nose is solid. And then that makes the
skull just fundamentally more rigid and able to take
more power through it. The very early ones weren't super biters, I suspect,
but they do also have the little flattened teeth at the front, so
I strongly suspect the fused nasals, at least originally, is
for resisting that. If you've got a long nose and you're pulling with quite a lot of
force at the very tip, that's going to bend your snout. So, strengthen that.
- Can you speak to the evolution from the smaller to the bigger of the
T-Rex? What were some of the evolutionary pressures? What's the
story of the evolution?
- So tyrannosaurs go back to the Middle Jurassic. Tyrannosaurs were around
for a hundred million years, so from about 160-ish,
165-ish million years till the extinction, 66.5 I
think is the current dating on that. So yeah, you've got a hundred million years of
them. And the Middle Jurassic, annoyingly, is probably the bit of the
Mesozoic, so the whole dinosaur period, that we know the least of.
Just by chance, we just don't have many rocks exposed of the right age that
are fossil-bearing. But we've got two or three tyrannosaurs from
that time. And yeah, they're really quite diddy. They'd
be chest-high to us, two or three meters long, including the tail.
Probably more like three, a lot of them. Little
heads, long arms. They look every other
carnivore going. There's not a lot special to them,
at this point. They've only just separated from their
nearest groups, which is actually something like the ancestors of Giganotosaurus,
actually. They do have the fused nasals early on. They do
have these special little teeth at the front of the jaw very early on. They're
feathered early on, definitively. We have
skeletons with feathers on them that are early tyrannosaurs,
at least until the Early Cretaceous.
But yeah, they're knocking around as relatively small animals in Europe and Asia.
We have a couple from the UK. We have a whole bunch from China. There's stuff from
like Kyrgyzstan and places like this. I think there's one, a relatively early one from
Russia. And then when they get into the
Early Cretaceous, they start getting quite a bit bigger. So someone like
Yutyrannus, if you want to... There you go. So Yutyrannus is
fuzzy. We have three specimens definitively feathered. It gets
to six, seven meters long.
- There's something funny-looking about the sexy, smaller, earlier version of the
T-Rex.
- But again, this is seven, eight meters, maybe weighs half a ton or a
ton. Like, we are very much on the menu for an animal that size.
And it's massive and dangerous. Quite what triggered
them... There are general patterns in evolution of size change, and one famous one
called Cope's Rule, I've worked on a fair bit, which is the idea that over time, things tend to
get bigger, and they do for various different reasons, one
of which is just pure, almost, like, diffusion. If you start small and you
evolve, well, you can't get much smaller, but you can always get
bigger. So you'll naturally kind of diffuse away. Whereas if you're a
blue whale, you probably can't get much bigger, and its descendants will probably end up
being smaller. But there are reasons that bigger things do better. You
can hunt more stuff. You are more energy-efficient. You can move more
efficiently. You're dominant in contests,
particularly with conspecifics. If you're trying to win a territory or win mating
rights, bigger things usually beat up smaller things. So there's going to be
selection favoring them. But then big things don't usually do well in
extinction events, so that tends to reset the clock by killing off the big stuff, and
then smaller stuff does better again.
- So mostly, there's evolutionary advantages, but-
- But a fairly big one. So yeah, it's the classic thing of there's a
day-to-day advantage of being bigger, and that might last for a few million
years, right up to the point that suddenly there's the biggest drought the Earth has encountered
in five million years, and then all the big stuff just gets nailed.
- Oh, so we should probably say, is this accurate to say that the bigger you get, the fewer of
you there are?
- There are, yeah. There's just less fundamental space, you know? There's
more mice than there are elephants. There are more elephants than there are
whales. Like, there is only so much biomass that an ecosystem can support.
- And bigger things are just worse at repopulating in extinction events-
- Right, so they're less likely to survive because they need more fuel. You
know, what would feed a mouse for a year won't feed an elephant for a week. So
if... And, of course, the mice are going to have an easier time finding a few
little seeds than an elephant's going to find tons of food, and then they've got less
genetic diversity. There might be 5,000 mice, there might be 200
elephants, so who's likely to have more genes or who's likely
to have selection acting on those genes to produce a
survivor? Well, the one with five or ten or a thousand times the
population. And then, on top of that, you've then got the very slow
reproductive cycle which then, again, gives evolution not a
lot to work with if, as an elephant, you're breeding once every five
years, and as a mouse you're doing it once every eight weeks.
- What can we say about the evolution of just the massive bone-crushing power of-
- So that starts kicking in seriously, kind of Eotyrannosaurus up. So
that's when you start getting not just bigger animals that are getting to a
comparable size to the other big dinosaur carnivores of the time, you start
getting those bigger heads. But even then,
relatively late in tyrannosaur evolution, so getting into the middle part of
the Late Cretaceous, you see a split and we have a group called the
Alioraminous which have really, really long, thin
skulls and they look much more like a kind of, here's a Velociraptor,
they look much more like a giant Velociraptor-ish than a
tyrannosaur. Still relatively small arms but
it's a very long snout. And so this is a fast-biting animal with a
relatively light bite, so it's probably taking really quite small stuff
proportionally. And then the other side you've got the
tyrannosaurines which are the really big-headed
ones. And so that is few ancestral things like Albertosaurus and
Gorgosaurus, both from Alberta, but then
Daspletosaurus, a thing I named called Jiuchengtyrannos in China, and
then Tarbosaurus and Tyrannosaurus. And you've really only got three or four
of these ultra-giants, which are all kind of 10 meters
plus in size and then have the really broad skull with a real kind of excessive bite
force. But even things like Albertosaurus, which
is, I mean, a big animal, seven, eight meters, yeah, a ton or
so. They're not quite T-rex but they're definitely more robust
than the other contemporaneous carnivores. So
there is this progression of getting bigger, getting a bigger
head, the teeth get bigger but there's fewer of them,
building up the bone biting and the power. But
with some interesting evolutionary offshoots, in the way that, yeah, cats
are largely much of a muchness but then you get things like, well, like bobcats and
lynx which are actually
quite bulky, stocky little cats that don't have the long tail and are doing something
quite different.
- Can you just speak almost more generally? Because T-rex is
sort of one of the great apex predators of history on
Earth. How does an apex predator evolve? Why did T-rex
win? Why isn't everybody, why isn't there, like, a vicious race to the top
and everyone's-
- I have a problem with the term apex predator because
ecologically, apex predators are generally defined as things that eat other
predators. So a great white shark is because it's
eating stuff like tuna and sea lions which are themselves
predators, so it's a predator of predators. Whereas
people love saying lions are apex predators and they love saying T-rex is an apex
predator. They're eating herbivores. This is not some weird and unusual thing.
They're the largest predator in their
ecosystem and they are a giant one. My friend, Darren Naish, has
moved to using the word arch predator, so it's like some kind of
massive thing but avoiding the term apex because I think that
leads into a... It's a subtle terminology thing, but like-
- An important one. I just learned something new today. I didn't understand, I thought I
was using the word apex predator as meant that, but that's what
- But that's because everyone keeps using it when I don't think they should.
- All right.
- And now you're getting into linguistics and it's like, well, if everyone uses it to mean that,
does it now mean that rather than what it should mean? And then I'm probably losing that argument
because actually you'll probably find way more stuff calling it an apex predator than you will
an arch predator, but here we are.
- Arch predator, beautiful. I learned something today.
- It's-
- But that you're saying T-rex didn't eat other predators?
- Well, it's probably not going to. So we can get
into, though I'd prefer not to 'cause it's tedious, the argument of whether or not there's
these small things which some people have said is a different group called Nanotyrannus, or a
different species called Nanotyrannus. But fundamentally,
T-rex is definitely weird, even compared to all the other
giant tyrannosaurs that are very closely related to it,
because it is by far, ludicrously by far, the largest carnivore in its ecosystem.
So-
- So it doesn't really have competition actually?
- I mean, so this is a Velociraptor skull.
There are some carnivores that are a bit bigger than this,
but not enormously so, which we're knocking
around as T-rex. The skull's the same type-
tooth. Right, but, like, you think about that.
And that's like going, that's like going to Africa and
going, "Okay, there are lions. What's the next biggest
predator?" And it's like, well, there's a weasel about this big.
Like, it's that kind of size difference and
you don't get that normally in ecosystems.
- So it didn't have some of the other big dinosaurs around it?
- Not carnivores. There's huge herbivores.
- Oh, there-
- But there's no huge carnivores around.
- Oh, I see. It would eat those juvenile herbivores, but not-
- Oh, yeah. It's gonna be eating Triceratops and Edmontosaurus and Parasaurolophus.
There's even a couple of giant sauropods knocking around in some places.
- Got it.
- It's gonna be hoovering them up, but, like, how often is it gonna
eat... Again, Velociraptor isn't there, but how often is it gonna eat something the size of an adult
Velociraptor?
I mean, they're a fraction of our size and we're probably too small. That, that,
this is like lions hunting mice. Like, you're just not gonna unless
one virtually runs into your mouth, you're not gonna go and try and eat it.
- So the question still stands about arch predators then, like how
does it, how do you win in evolution?
- Yeah. Well, I mean, so I mean, there's no real
winners, there's just, you know, turnover because ultimately the birds, you know, it,
it's still lost out when things went wrong. And as we were just talking about, you
know, things do tend to lose out when they're big. They're just so much more
vulnerable to extinction. But clearly, dinosaurian ecosystems
had much bigger herbivores, and therefore by extent, much
bigger carnivores than any system we've seen
before or after. Even in relatively sparse
ones like bits of the late Triassic, so when the dinosaurs were really just
getting going, or the very early Jurassic, but you've still got
some like multi-ton herbivores and then you've got
some multiple 100-kilo predators, so about as
big as elephants and lions get today. And then
once you're in the Jurassic and Cretaceous, it is entirely normal to have
multiple species that are 10, 20, 30 tons plus as
herbivores and anything up to five tons as a carnivore. I
mean, T-Rex is probably the biggest of them, but carnivores that exceed terrestrial-
fully terrestrial carnivores that exceed a ton, there's
dozens of species of dinosaurs.
- Is it interesting to you that no other carnivore
predator was able to develop in that environment over millions of years?
- I mean, they're probably just ecologically dominant in the way that mammals are
now, you know. Crocs get bigger than lions and tigers,
but they're fundamentally tied to the water. But you don't see crocs roaming
the Serengeti or anything like that. But
yeah, big, I mean the really big crocs even now get to over a
ton, so those are very serious animals. And I think big polar bears
are in the, like, 500 kilo range, though again, they hunt a lot of stuff in water.
And then things like grizzlies are at least partially herbivorous or omnivorous.
- Well, so there was a very large marine reptile,
Mosasaurus. Did T-Rex ever come across that?
- In theory, at least, the really giant Mosasaurs
are much bigger, in the same way that unsurprisingly whales are much bigger than
terrestrial carnivores now. Um, Jurassic Park
unsurprisingly has rather exaggerated it so the one from I think Jurassic World
is like twice the size it should be. But some of these things were still,
like, you know, 15, 20 meters. But yeah, some of them are absolutely
giant. We, we had one dug up in the UK just a couple of years ago and I got to
see the skull of it, or a cast of the skull, and yeah, it's about
the same size as a T-Rex skull.
- If we take a ridiculous detour before we get back to
science, what creature in the history of Earth would
challenge a T-Rex in a fight, would you say? What-
- On, on land?
- On land.
- I mean, nothing reasonable. The really big ones are gonna be...
The only other thing you can really add is, so, this might be a very
British adage of it's not the size of the dog in the fight, it's the size of the
fight in the dog. So yeah, maybe there's something a bit smaller
which is just hyper-aggressive and that would be enough to win. Like, the classic
honey badgers chasing off lions. It's not that a honey badger would win in a fight,
but if the honey badger is prepared to put up that much of a fight and the lion really doesn't want to get
hurt, then, then he kind of technically wins.
- You can't imagine, like, any of the cats? Like, tigers, none of them...
can do, I mean, the size difference, the power of the jaw, all of that kind of stuff.
- Yeah, but going to T-Rex, like, what could reasonably challenge it?
There's a couple of other giant tyrannosaurs, there's a couple of giant Carcharodontosaurs from
South America that I would say are comparable in linear
measurements, but are probably rather smaller and rather
lighter. In which case, your money is gonna be on the bigger guy with the bigger
bite. And that simply is T-Rex.
- And the bite is important.
- Yeah, I think it is, because, yeah, these guys,
the Carcharodontosaurs, they're much more cutting.
And they're really killing stuff probably by
grappling with the arms, because they do have big, muscular arms with big claws.
And then slashing away at stuff. So I think they're probably
doing something more like almost like wolves or hyenas or a hunting...
dog, where they're harrying stuff and slashing at
it and you're basically bleeding them out. ...And wearing them down.
- So what about that strategy? So maybe you could speak to biting
strategy. So a T-Rex
is a, I guess, a relatively slow bite but extremely powerful. What about
animals that have very fast bites?
- So it's very simple mechanics, you know. If you have a very long
jaw, you're going to close faster but with less power at the tip than if you
have a really short one that's deep. And so that really
is it. But yeah, let's say there are things like the Aramins and then there are
things like, you know, Velociraptor and a lot of its relatives, really very
small but, you know, narrow. It is narrow-snouted. There's not going to be a lot of
fundamental strength here. The teeth, very numerous, very
small so they're much more about grabbing
something tiny, you know. Velociraptors eating rat-sized
stuff, that's going to be probably its primary diet or-
- So I wonder if there's a bunch-
- ...kind of diet.
- ...of smaller, fast-biting things that could just bleed a T-Rex to death.
- They're going to struggle though. I remember doing some work for
one documentary and they literally wanted Velociraptor fighting a T-Rex
and I was sort of like, "You do know this is, like-"
"...we're going to shoot some meerkats killing a lion." And it's like, well, you can film it
but no one would believe it because, you know, these
ankle-high things trying to, like, savage a
shin bone are, yeah, I'm sure they'll make some holes and it'll lose some
blood and it may not be very happy but I don't think they're going to win.
- The size of a Velociraptor was exaggerated by Jurassic Park.
- Oh, enormously. I mean, they get a bit bigger than this.
...in terms of the skull. But yeah, they're kind of thigh-high,
to me, like a meter or so to the top of the head, two
meters long, whereas in the movies, they're, like, standing
taller than guys who are six feet. So it's just
massively, massively scaled up, and then these kind of big, domey heads, and
they're not the really long, narrow snout.
- Maybe we could take that, change it. What does Jurassic Park and Jurassic World
franchise get right and wrong?
- I mean, they get wrong a hell of a lot.
- What are some of the really definitive things to you that are interesting that it
gets wrong, and also what are the things it gets pretty close to right?
- I mean, I just want to preface my answer 'cause I always get asked
about this, understandably. It's like, I get that it's a
movie. But if someone's going to ask me, "What does it get wrong?"
I'm going to give them an answer. But I do get people going, "Ah, you're just nitpicking."
"Ah, you know it's fiction. Ah, you know it's made up." Yeah, I do know.
But someone asked the question, so here's the answer.
- I should say that some of the things that I've heard you
describe, I feel like it's the responsibility of those folks to get it
right. I think there's something I really
deeply admire. There's a show called Chernobyl.
It's like they don't need to be that accurate,
but they really... the detail of the kitchenware-
in a room, just to get the tiniest detail right. Who's
that for? I don't know who that's for, but that's for great art.
That's for the spirit of the thing. And if you
focus on getting those tiny details right, some magical thing
happens about the bigger story. If you don't care about the details, it...
the story gets corrupted. So I just wanted to say that some of the things you describe,
like how many fingers-
it's important to get that right 'cause if you do, some magical stuff can really emerge.
And it could become a legendary film as opposed to just a-
- Yeah, I mean, that-
- a summer hit.
- that's my take. Again, I've worked on documentaries where they're
claiming that accuracy is absolutely critical and 100% important,
and they won't put anything on screen that I haven't told them to, and-
then many of those things turn out not to be quite as true as advertised,
once you get around to it. So I'm aware that
even documentaries will take massive liberties,
you can't be too harsh on what is popular fiction. On the other hand,
I am also aware that it is by far, by a ludicrous degree, the most popular
bit of any kind of media that includes my work,
as it were, or something that I'm actively engaged in and know about,
and so whether or not it should have that influence or the filmmakers should have
responsibility, it does. It does have that knock-on.
So I mean, it's simple as stuff as a T-rex can't see if you can't move. Yeah, it
could. I don't know where that came from. As far as I can tell, Crichton just dreamed it
up. In The Lost World, his sequel book, he
hints that there's a research paper that says it, and that's where he got it
from. There's a second paleontologist character
who's advising Dodgson, the evil InGen guy, and he
says, "Oh, no, well that's from such-and-such's research." And I tried looking it up.
As far as I can tell, it doesn't exist and never did. So I think it's just straight
fiction. And it's like, it works for the book and it works for the movie, but
as far as I can tell, it's straight fiction and Crichton just made it up.
If it's buried in some bit of literature, he's done better finding it than I have,
and I've had a really good look and I know how to look. And I've never come across anyone
who's found it either. But it just warps the
perception, you know. Velociraptor, cheetah speed, pack hunters,
super intelligent, giant-sized animals and... okay, 1993, it's a bit more forgivable,
but even then, we were pretty confident they had feathers.
confident they had feathers.
- Is any of that true? Wait, so...
- Probably not.
- The pack hunter aspect of it?
- So that's something I've written quite a lot about. The evidence for pack hunting in any dinosaur at all
is almost nonexistent. It basically doesn't exist. And that's going exactly back to, again,
basically doesn't exist. And that's going exactly back to, again, that
that stuff we were talking about, bite marks and taphonomy and, like, the history of specimens and how you interpret stuff.
history of specimens and h- and how you interpret stuff.
- So, so what kind of evidence would show, like, maybe bite marks from multiple sources?
- So it's really, really tough. So the main one which was put forward is... there's this famous
forward is... there's this famous association
association in Montana of Deinonychus, which is often confused with Velociraptor, including in the books
and movie. Basically a bigger version of this that's rather older, from the early Cretaceous,
version of this that's rather older, from the early
and a thing called Tenontosaurus, which is kind of iguanodontian. So an iguanodon with spiky thumbs.
Basically, otherwise, a fairly run-of-the-mill herbivore. And there are two sites, I believe, for this,
fairly run-of-the-mill herbivore. And there are two
but there's one that's much more important, where you have a Tenontosaurus carcass with Deinonychus carcasses.
a Tenontosaurus carcass
with Deinonychus carcasses. And so the interpretation of this
And so the interpretation of this is, well, this is a group that brought down the herbivore.
And of course, the immediate kind of counterargument to that is, "Well, why did they all die there?"
all die there?"
Like, when, you know, when lions kill a wildebeest, they eat it. They don't all just die next to it.
it. They don't all just die next to it.
Or even if they did kill it and start eating it, and then, like, if they got into a fight and killed
each other, well, lions as a species are not gonna hang around for very long if every time they kill
something they get into a mortal fight and kill half their pride. There's nothing obvious that killed them,
half their pride. Um, there's nothing obvious that killed them but it's at
but it's at least possible that this was something like a predator trap. So predator traps are really neat.
So La Brea Tar Pits is a classic example. The idea is a herbivore stumbles into something
example. The idea is a herbivore stumbles into something like
like tar. You've got your deer or wildebeest or mammoth or whatever it is, waist deep in tar and going,
"I'm dying, I'm dying," and making horrible noises, and, you know, Smilodon walks over and goes, "Great,"
horrible noises, and, you know, Smilodon walks over and goes,
and wades out after it, and he's now stuck. And then the next one, and then the next one,
and the next one, and the next one. And then, lo and behold, you now have something like La Brea where they've got,
And then lo and behold, you now have something like La Brea where they've got,
like, the numbers are something absurd. Like I think they've got, like, three mammoths and one ground sloth,
and then it's like a hundred dire wolves and 40 Smilodon because it's just sucking the carnivores in.
and 40 Smilodon because it's just sucking the carnivores in.
- Wow.
- And you get these really distorted ratios. I don't think that's the case with the
Deinonychus-Tenontosaurus stuff because there's ways that you can probably...
because there's ways that you can probably rule that out. But there are probably
places like this where it's happened. Again, the other one is the toxin one,
whose name Yeah, Cleveland-Lloyd, so it's just coming up on your screen.
That's another one with loads of dinosaurs. There's Allosaurus.
But we've definitely seen it with... I think this has come up with something
like lions or wolves. Like, they found loads of them dead by a
lake and it turned out... or this pond. And this pond had got some really sort of
nasty algal bloom toxin in it, and the interpretation was the
same kind of thing, is that, like, a couple of deer were
drinking. This stuff's toxic and kills you within minutes. Keels
over, dies. A wolf smells dead meat, comes over,
starts eating it, has a drink, keels over and dies. So it's not
getting you're just dying from the toxicity rather than being, like,
physically sucked in and trapped. But the same effect can happen, and so you just end up
with a pile of dead bodies.
- So I'm pulling up some stuff here. First of all, shout out to Perplexity.
Super awesome. It'd be great if you fact-check some of this
stuff. So, fossil discoveries, including parallel trackways and bone
beds containing multiple tyrannosaurs suggests these large predators
sometimes moved and possibly hunted in groups. You as a person who wrote
a book about the behavior of dinosaurs.
- Yep. Let me deconstruct that almost instantly.
So it's... because it's really easy, cause this is... My book on dinosaur
behavior, this is just the kind of thing I'm talking about.
So the tyrannosaur trackways of a group of tyrannosaurs is, I think,
four or five tracks total. So it's, like, two from one
animal, two from a second animal, and one from a third animal. That's not the end of the world.
That's somehow how trackways form. Like, you know, the rock's
broken up. They stood on mud, and then they didn't, whatever.
- Just to clarify, trackways means footprints of multiple, maybe, steps?
- Yeah. One of them has got a left and right, and the other two don't. It's very
fragmentary, but I have no... That's not a problem with the interpretation.
The problem is this is interpreted as a group of them moving
together. Well, why? Because
they're going in roughly the same direction. Okay. And they're roughly equal
sizes. Okay. But, like, I've seen solitary animals moving in
groups. A guy I know quite well in South Africa...
I go to South Africa regularly for my teaching, actually, and he's one of
the big guys at South Africa National Parks, and he gives me the skinny on all kinds
of weird stuff. And he was telling me a few years ago that one of his park
rangers had observed leopards hunting together in a group. Now, leopards are
basically not just solitary, they're like antisocial. Like, they beat the hell
out of each other if they come near each other. But I've also seen...
you know, you get... Game trails are a thing, paths that single
animals take. If a female is in heat, like, males will track her down and follow her.
So you'll get one set of footprints, and then a couple of hours later a male will come
past, and a couple of hours later another male will come past. And now you've got three sets of
footprints all traveling in the same direction on the same bit of path, but they live
on their own. Let alone hunting together, which is a massive step above this.
And then the one I've talked about quite a bit in my book is spotted hyena, Crocuta
crocuta, which is the one... There's a whole bunch of hyenas, but this is the one everyone knows.
They're the big laughing hyena. And you can see plenty of
Attenborough-type documentaries of them, seven or eight of them, or even
10 or 12 of them going into a herd and ripping apart wildebeest or zebra or whatever it
is. But actually, if you read the scientific literature, this is really rare. They
mostly hunt on their own. Now they do live in these social
clans with hierarchies and complex social interactions. They
are very social animals. But they mostly hunt on their own. So
even if you find loads of trackways of them moving together or as ...
Again, there's one, if not two, for tyrannosaurs, where we've got multiple tyrannosaurs
together, and that's been argued for pack hunting. At best, that argues
they might have lived together, but it doesn't tell you whether or
not they hunted together.
- So, how can we make a decision on one way or the other?
- So, I mean, I tend to be ultra
conservative in this context, and I think we should probably avoid
saying things that we're not quite confident about. I don't want to
ever go down the, "We must have really definitive, 100% convincing evidence," because this is
paleo and we don't have that kind of data.
But just as I talked about with things like the predator prey
size ratio stuff, there is data we can start to use on living
species about what tends to trigger
hunting in groups or living in groups, and what data there might be from
stuff like brain sizes or other trackways. Or again, we do
have bite marks indicating prey size. If you start finding
repeated attacks on big prey from relatively small
predators, that would be quite convincing. As you said, maybe we
had bite marks of multiple different sizes. Now, that on its
own, it comes hard, because obviously scavenging, you know,
tyrannosaurs are an exception. Most dinosaurs, most carnivorous dinosaurs have pretty
similarly shaped teeth. So, how easy is it to tell
an adult from a juvenile from an adult from a different species that's
just a bit smaller? Probably pretty tricky. I mean, for me, I think
the kind of gold standard, which I don't think we're ever going to find
but you never know, like, you could, in theory, get a trackway of something like a
herbivore with a whole bunch of carnivore tracks coming
by it. We do have a couple like this, but they don't have what I really want to see, which
is if you trace the footprints of the individual carnivores,
and if A's in... Early on, A's footprints go on top of
B's, but later on, B's go on top of A's, they
must have been there at the same time because there's no way they
could have been even minutes or hours apart. So, if you had
that, then those two must be together, or at least within sight of
each other and one's not turning around and roaring or having a fight. If you can do that,
If you can do that with seven or eight, all converging on one herbivore,
and then everything goes manic, well, that's really pretty convincing.
- It is so fascinating and awesome, the like the Sherlock
Holmes aspect of paleontology, like figuring out, because you have
very little signal-
very little signal and you have to figure out the puzzle of it from that.
And like, that's it's, it's just you're brilliant. You're giving so many brilliant examples of,
yeah, if A steps on top of B, and then B steps on top of A, that's a strong signal that they were walking
together.
- I am a bit of a Sherlock Holmes fan, and he references
Cuvier. So Cuvier was this legendary French anatomist,
Baron Cuvier. He was the first guy to posit that things went extinct,
working on mammoths. And he said, "Well, there's nothing like this alive today, so extinction
happens." Which before that, we didn't really know. And Holmes has a
line about, "Just as Cuvier can restore
an animal from the smallest bone, so I can restore the events from
the smallest detail," or I-
- Damn.
- I'm paraphrasing, but I'm not far off.
- Yeah, there's truth to that.
- You, you have used an analogy that Conan Doyle specifically used for Holmes
going back to paleontology.
- I mean, it's obvious. It's clear. It's right there, yeah.
- That, that's how on the nose you are with that one.
- So, okay. So basically you clarified and showed all the things in
Jurassic got it wrong.
- Yeah, we, we, yeah, we got off-topic before we even got onto Jurassic Park.
- Uh, and just Velociraptor, you said that the, you know, the, yeah, the size, the
pack hunting, all of that.
- The pack hunting, just to round off on that, like, I don't know.
Maybe there's actually been some more recent stuff on Deinonychus looking
at things like isotopes in the teeth and feeding traces and some
other stuff that's hinting that maybe there is more going on there,
which is great. I'm, I'm not anti the idea that this exists,
but you absolutely get this build up of the idea that
velociraptors are a pack hunter comes from Deinonychus and I think the
evidence from Deinonychus is really weak, in exactly the way that...
Okay, lions are group hunters. We know they are. Does that mean
that leopards are? And tigers and
puma? No. So why on earth do you think that just because, even if
Velociraptor. Group hunting has all kinds of
more complicated dynamics going on it than just close relatives tend to do
it. You can flip that around, you know.
African hunting dog, wolves, things like bush dogs. There's
various canids that all hunt in groups, but then you've got things like
maned wolves which are effectively solitary. The hyenas.
Spotted hyenas are, yeah, these super social animals, but the brown
hyena, the striped hyena and the aardwolf are solitary. So you just
So you just can't do group versus solitary off close relatives or anything like that. I am very sure
close relatives or anything like that. I am very sure a ton of dinosaurs were aggregates, lived in groups to some degree,
a ton of dinosaurs were aggregates, lived in groups to some degree, and I'm very sure some of them were social with complex lives
and I'm very sure some of them were social with complex lives and hierarchies and even pack hunting. Which ones, I
and hierarchies and even pack hunting. Which ones, I have very little idea because I think the data is so sparse
have very little idea because I think the data is so sparse that we can't really say it with any confidence for
that we can't really say it with any confidence for anything, in my opinion. I think that can be gotten at.
anything, in my opinion. I think that can be gotten at. I think we need to start getting at it with the sort of stuff I'm talking about.
I think we need to start getting at it with the sort of stuff I'm talking about. Like get a better understanding of what drives sociality in lions
Like get a better understanding of what drives sociality in lions versus tigers versus leopards. You know, relatively close relatives
tigers versus leopards. You know, relatively close relatives who overlap. Don't forget in India, leopards and tigers
who overlap. Don't forget in India, leopards and tigers overlap with lions. The Asiatic lion is still there.
overlap with lions. The Asiatic lion is still there. So you can talk about ecosystem structure and prey size
So you can talk about ecosystem structure and prey size and prey type and all this stuff. Maybe we can start
and prey type and all this stuff. Maybe we can start piecing that together a bit better and then apply that to stuff
piecing that together a bit better and then apply that to stuff like the track ways and the isotopes and all the rest of it.
Bite marks and these mass mortality sites. So I think it can be done, but personally like what were pack hunters? No idea.
but personally like what were pack hunters? No idea.
No idea. I don't think any of them were in the sense that I don't think we've got good evidence for any of them.
I don't think we've got good evidence for any of them. But there probably exists on Earth definitive evidence one way or the other.
- But there probably exists on earth definitive evidence one way or the other.
- Yeah, probably for some of them. I mean, I think it's well within their scope. One of the papers writing about this,
One of the papers writing about this, ironically, arguing against pack hunting in Deinonychus, said that, "Well,
against pack hunting in Deinonychus, said that, "Well, it's probably not the case because you don't really see pack hunting
it's probably not the case because you don't really see pack hunting in birds. And so if you don't see it in birds, then dinosaurs
in birds. And so if you don't see it in birds, then dinosaurs being their ancestor, well, if birds can't evolve it,
being their ancestor, well, if birds can't evolve it, then maybe dinosaurs couldn't have evolved it." Which
I'm not sure is a great logical argument because of the complexities of social behavior anyway. But then there are a couple of birds
of social behavior anyway. But then there are a couple of birds which actively hunt in groups. Things like the giant ground hornbills.
which actively hunt in groups. Things like the giant ground hornbills. Ethiopia and South Africa are a really good example of that.
Ethiopia and South Africa are a really good example of that. So that point is incorrect. And then we see if not true
So that point is incorrect. And then we see if not true sociality, we see cooperation in crocodilians and we're
sociality, we see cooperation in crocodilians and we're seeing degrees of social behavior in things like iguanas.
seeing degrees of social behavior in things like iguanas. So the idea that, "Well, birds are super advanced
So the idea that, "Well, birds are super advanced and dinosaurs can't do it 'cause the stupid reptiles are too stupid,
and dinosaurs can't do it 'cause the stupid reptiles are too stupid, and therefore dinosaurs are more like them," which isn't quite
and therefore dinosaurs are more like them," which isn't quite what they're saying, but it's sort of the unwritten idea, "Well, we have
what they're saying, but it's sort of the unwritten idea, "Well, we have social behavior and cooperation behavior in crocs and in lizards.
social behavior and cooperation behavior in crocs and in lizards. So that really gives you the impression that dinosaurs, theoretically,
So that really gives you the impression that dinosaurs, theoretically, at least, are perfectly capable of that. So there's pack hunting,
- at least, are perfectly capable of that. So there's pack hunting, but there's also sociality, which is such an interesting idea.
but there's also sociality, which is such an interesting idea. It's how did they live? And this is something you look
It's how did they live? And this is something you look at that paleontology doesn't often touch, is like, the lives.
- Yeah, because, you know, animals are doing complicated things. So, in the case of lions, a large part of this is down to
So, in the case of lions, a large part of this is down to territoriality in that the males ultimately are defending the territory,
territoriality in that the males ultimately are defending the territory, and that's effectively protecting the females. But, of course,
and that's effectively protecting the females. But, of course, what they're mostly protecting them from is other males.
what they're mostly protecting them from is other males. So there's a ludicrous bit of self-interest. But that's
self-interest. But that's effectively how it's
operating as a system. But it could just
be predatory type. Cheetahs are my go-to example for
this. So cheetahs are the weird ones compared to the other cats because
females are solitary, but males are social. So brothers
will... when, you know, if the female has five or six cubs, the
brothers will stay together in a group and then the girls will go off on their own.
And if you're the only brother or the only survivor, you will usually hook up,
hook up with a gang of other males. So cheetahs are pack hunters if you're male
and a solitary hunter if you're female. So it's not about
territory defense or occupation for them. It's about prey type.
- Is it possible to know the sex of a T-Rex or any of the
other dinosaurs? What can paleontology show us?
- So in theory, yes. In practice, it's way more complicated.
So unless you get very lucky, we have a handful of specimens that still have
eggs inside them, instant giveaway. But this is like two or three. Um,
what you can look for is both reptiles and birds have a thing
called medullary bone, and when you're laying
eggs and you need a lot of calcium very quickly because the egg
shell goes on basically, like, the last minute during egg development.
So you need a lot of calcium very quickly. So during the laying season, these
animals grow this really weird kind of bone texture on
big things like the femur and the humerus, like really big bones in the
body. And that's... It's got a weird texture because it's full of blood
vessels, and it's full of blood vessels so that you can basically apply a lot of blood
supply to it quickly, suck up some of the calcium from that bone,
take it through the system, put it on the eggs, lay your eggs. We
can find that. So if you have a dinosaur
bone and it's the right kind of thing, so you can't do it on like a finger
or a claw or a bit of rib, but nice big bone, you could cut a chunk of that out,
grind it down to the point that it's virtually transparent, a fraction of a millimeter thick,
put it under a microscope and have a look. And if you see the right bone texture,
that's... there are some exceptions, but that's very probably medullary
bone, and you have yourself a female.
So the instant assumption is, okay, so you can tell female from male. No, we can tell
laying female from everything else. So males
won't have medullary bone. Young females won't have them. Females
outside of the breeding season won't have it. Females inside the breeding season, but
maybe they've been really sick this year, don't have it. Or they laid their eggs early
and now they don't need it anymore, won't have it. So
occasionally, if you cut up a bone, which of course we try not to do that much,
you can get the signal of medullary bone and infer that you have a female in the
breeding season.
- But so there's no like large bone structure differences?
- Well, maybe there is, but we haven't seen it. You look at things like kudu or
blackbuck and all kinds of antelope or even most deer,
and the males have horns or antlers and the females don't.
And then you look at something like Triceratops and all the ceratopsians.
There's a big clade of... oh, must be 40 species by
now. And every single one of them has the frill and has
some kind of horn somewhere. You don't
have the hornless ones or the frill-less ones in the way that we do with
a lot of these.
- I'm trying to figure out, is there, how many of the species is it
obvious that there's like, like pelvis differences, all that kind of stuff?
- So pelvis differences works on like humans and apes and
maybe a couple of other mammals, but it's mostly not very good because we are...
It's because we give birth to such a gigantic baby with a gigantic head
compared to our sizes that women have different pelvises to men.
- And then there's size differences, like the skull is not as reliable as the pelvis.
- It's, it's not. And then again, you just need to look at, you know, humans are always
slightly dodgy with this because of, you know, our evolutionary and cultural history.
But like, you know, there's population differences. You know,
you, you... There are, there are maned female lions in places. There
are maneless male lions in places. Um,
reindeer, female reindeer have antlers in winter.
So Rudolph was a girl, because every illustration of Santa and his reindeer
ever, they all have antlers, and that's that's a female reindeer, not a male if it's winter.
- So basically, we don't know much about the dating and the sex lives of T-rexes.
- Well, not much, but you can make some inferences. So for example, all tyrannosaurs
have at least some kind of crest on the head. The early ones have like this
midline crest. It really doesn't work on a human. They have like a midline crest
running along the top of the nose that sticks up. The later ones
largely don't, but they do have this weird armored structure
along those fused nasals and then they have little horns over the
eyes. Those as far as we can tell, don't really have any
kind of obvious mechanical function and loads, like outside of the feathered
dinosaurs, the vast majority of carnivorous dinosaurs
have some kind of crestal display feature on the head.
- When you say display feature, meaning for sex appeal to attract mates?
- Or something like that. So I've always favored the term
socio-sexual selection to cover both sexual
display and sexual dominance and communication, but also
social ones, because those two things are hard to tell apart. Female
lions find males with darker manes sexier, but
male lions find males with darker manes more
intimidating. So one of them is sex, but one of them is social.
- Nice.
- And then-
- I mean, I guess it goes hand-in-hand, sure. Yeah.
- It can, but then you get things like the other one I go for is black
swans, these beautiful Australian birds. They have these really weird curly
feathers on their wings. And males and females both have them, and
males prefer females with curlier feathers, and females prefer males
with curlier feathers. There's an obvious sexual link, but then females fight
too. Females fight over the best nesting spots, and
the females with the curliest feathers tend to win those fights.
- How does that make sense?
- This gets into classic sexual selection theory. It's what's called an honest
signal. You couldn't have those curly feathers if you weren't able to support them.
Because they're the primary feathers on the wings, and what it actually does is it
makes it harder to fly. So you're basically going, "Look how tough I am. I've grown
this big and I can fly and carry on with my giant curly feathers
because I'm really tough and I'm in good shape." And it's the same with the lion.
The reason you get pale lions in the south is because it's close to the
equator, because it's too hot.
So there's the trade-off, because if you have a really black mane, all the
males know you're rock and all the females know you're super sexy, but
you just die of overheating. The trade-off is if the heat's
going to kill you, you're probably better off being a bit paler
and surviving in order to reproduce than you are being
jet black but just dying instantly as soon as it gets hot.
- So there's trade-offs there, okay.
- Yeah, and that's probably what's happening with the
theropods. All the little crests and
horns, Ceratosaurus, Dilophosaurus, tyrannosaurs, allosaurs
have big crests over the eyes, and all kinds of others. I've
written about this, I think this is the trade-off. You're going for the
sexiest look,
and the sexiest look is the biggest horns or the biggest spikes and whatever's on the
head, probably also then with the brightest colors and the most display
patterns, but also this gives you away to
your prey. If you're trying to hide or you're trying to sneak up on something,
being brightly colored or having stripes or all this extra stuff on your head,
you get spotted. But then that's the trade-off.
is if I'm this big and my horns are, if my horns are this
big and this red and yellow and I can still, whoop,
I can still run those guys down and hunt them and kill them and eat them.
Then look how great I must be. Whereas that little guy, he's
only got weedy little crests and they're really dark
because he's so bad at catching stuff he doesn't have the extra
energy to grow big crests. And that's why. But when you're a
herbivore, you don't have that pressure, particularly something like, this
is Protoceratops, but somebody like Triceratops and these guys, they're living in big groups.
You can't hide from a predator when you're a group of 20 animals that are 10 tons
each, so who cares? You just grow the biggest
signal you can possibly grow, and lo and behold, they have giant frills and
giant horns.
- What can you say about beauty in evolution?
Something that's, maybe you can educate me, but something that's not quite an
honest signal that's just pure beauty like peacock feathers?
- So there are things which we think operate closer to that. So there
are, these are the two classic ideas of sexual selection, and both are
probably true to certain degrees in various different species. One is the honest
signal or the, it's the kind of handicap hypothesis because you're holding
yourself back whilst proving you can still do it. I ran the
marathon, you know, carrying a couple of weights. You're
obviously stronger than the guy who ran the marathon without. And so
that's why it's an honest signal and it's why it's a handicap. But the other one is what's called the
But the other one is what's called the sexy sons hypothesis.
The idea is a female might just find a male attractive for no other reason than random.
There is some component of her brain, or whatever it may be, that just
looks cool, and you can actually sort of get this as a
human. Forget human beauty, you can look at a bottle and
go, "That bottle's kind of nice, and that bottle's kind of ugly."
- Where do you put birds? Birds are interesting with this.
Where do you put peacock feathers?
- So they're probably more of a handicap hypothesis because the
colors that go into them and the sheer size and shape
- Oh, I see. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- ...and these things basically can't fly. They're really vulnerable to predators.
- Can the handicap hypothesis explain just how beautiful peacock feathers get?
- So-
- They go extreme with it.
- So, probably not entirely. There's almost certainly randomness going on in
there as well. And then the eye spots. We know that eye spots are attractive
are probably encoded in some way. But yeah, going back to the sexy sons, the idea
is females prefer something different for whatever reason, and there
might actually be some reasons females prefer things that are different.
Different usually means separate and outside,
and that usually comes with variation inherently.
- Oh, so variation is an evolutionary turn-on?
- Yeah, basically.
- Wouldn't it? Man, you're rolling the dice, though, aren't you?
- Yeah, well, you...
- Right.
- You've got to remember, again, it's really easy to look at that sort of thing with a
human perspective where, at maximum, reproductive
output, I think the record  there's some obscure record  it's something
like 66 children, which is probably apocryphal for a
Russian woman who had loads of triplets and quads. But,
humans don't have many offspring, but most animals
lay dozens of eggs or hundreds of eggs or thousands of eggs at a time.
- So, diversity pays off more there.
- So diversity can pay off. We think that's probably a major part of the reason that sex
evolved in the first place: it gives you
resistance to a changing environment and it gives you resistance to parasites and
diseases which often reproduce way faster than you do.
bacteria can divide in a few hours. We reproduce every 20 years.
That's quite a difference. If we were all asexual clones and
you're vulnerable to some disease, you're probably going to get wiped out.
Look at the Irish Potato Famine, or something like that.
So different may be appealing simply because it is different.
variation. And there's at least some evidence for
that. There's swordtails. So anyone who keeps
little fish  if anyone's a tropical fish keeper,
swordtails are really quite common little tropical fish that you can get in
all kinds of aquarium shops, and they're a very boring fish shape.
their tail has a big spike on it, and that's the name. They're really
close relatives of a group called the mollies, which basically don't have
that. In the wild, these are Amazonian fish; they don't usually
encounter each other, but even if you go and get not even the domesticated form,
because these things have been bred for, you know, decades at this point, you can go and get some wild
mollies and give them a wild male swordtail, and they
think he's so much better than all the male mollies. They
will go for that one, and they will preferentially mate with that one. We don't know the exact
mechanism, but it appears to be, he looks similar enough that I
recognize it as a potential mate but different enough that this is exciting.
And then this is where the sexy sons kick in because the females are now assuming
those animals are successful, and they can hybridize, or maybe it's
just a male who just happens to be a little bit blue or a little bit red or whatever it may
be. Well, the female offspring,
the daughters are probably going to inherit mother's preference, I really like
red, and the males
are probably going to have red in them because their dad had more red. So guess
what the next generation does? There's more red, and the females
like more red, and you don't have to come back much further, and suddenly all
the males are bright red. And that's
closer to beauty than I think almost anything else would be, with still a
naturalistic explanation.
- We kind of started talking about beauty from how much social life
- Yeah, a T-rex might have.
- a T-rex might have, so just to kind of
take that to a place of what we know and what we don't know. So can we
kind of know something about their social life, where they lived, how they lived?
- So the very fact that they have these apparently socio-sexually
selected signals, the little crest and stuff in the
head. So there's a branch of sexual
selection called mutual sexual selection, and the black swans are an
example of this. The classic sexual selection is your peacocks and your lions
and things like this. Males are bigger and more
flamboyant and whatever it is, and they're doing all the competing. But
mutual sexual selection, and this is really common in a whole bunch
of things that people are familiar with but don't know. Loads of seabirds,
starlings, the common starling that we have in Europe and has been introduced into the U.S.,
parrots, various other things, where basically males
and females invest similarly in rearing the
offspring. So the idea generally, both with handicap and
sexy son, but particularly with handicap, is the idea that males are proving their
worth. They're basically saying, "I'm the biggest, strongest, healthiest, I've got the best
genes, I should be the father of your offspring." They go around
showing off and then mate with as many females as possible.
While the females then do all the work and make the nest and look after
the chicks and, yeah, or rear them or give birth or whatever it may be, yada, yada,
yada. So the idea with mutual sexual selection is, what if there's not
much food around?
Things like puffins or, you know, penguins in the Arctic where the male sits with the
egg and the female toddles off, gets food, and then comes back two months later or whatever it
is. On their own, they can't rear the offspring. They have to have
a male investment. Well, suddenly the male's now putting loads of effort in,
so the male's now in the same position that a female would be in under the normal
conditions. You don't want to be the sexiest, toughest, biggest male,
and you can only mate once, all right? There are various cheats, but we
won't get into that just yet. You're only going to mate once and you're going to put all your effort into helping
rearing offspring, rather than chasing down as many girls as possible. Are
you going to go for the biggest, fittest female as well, or are you going to go for the small, weedy
one that doesn't look very well? You go for the best one. Well,
how do you know that? Well, because she's got a crest as well, and so
suddenly you now get mutual ornamentation just like the
black swans where the males are checking out the curliest females, and the
females are checking out the curliest males, and you'll see they mutually pair
up. This is what we see with things like starlings. Males like the brightest females,
females like the brightest males, they tend to form pairs. The darkest
and least bright ones are obviously kind of left with each other at the bottom of the pile.
They tend to pair up. But it means that when you've got signals in both males
and females, like every triceratops or every
tyrannosaurus, it at least hints that they're going down this route,
and that they might cooperate for reproduction.
- Wow. Another like weak signal that tells a powerful story.
- Yeah, and the problem is it's compromised by lots of things. So that goes back to your earlier
question about telling males from females apart. The vast majority of dinosaur
species, like 90 plus percent, are known from a single specimen.
And a specimen is not necessarily very complete at all. It might be a
couple of bones, it might be one bone, it might be a tooth in a couple of
cases. The actual number where we've got a decent number of real
whole skeletons that we can actually compare to each other,
less than 10. Probably more like five or six.
- Can I ask you a weird question? If you were to, let's say,
all humans died right now
...press a button, poof, gone, how much of human civilization would
you be able to reconstruct from just the skeletons that are in the
ground? Like, you just start collecting skeletons. There's a lot of them.
There are billions of them. Would you be able to start telling a
story, like urban centers?
- Yeah, probably, because
- You could probably reconstruct a lot, right?
- And if nothing else, just the, you know, superlative brain cavity
will tell you quite a lot, you know.
- Yeah, the intelligence.
- Must have been very, very smart with...
- You could-
- ...a brain that big.
- You can probably reconstruct some of the behavior, a lot of the behavior, social behavior.
A lot of this stuff.
- And you're going to see stuff like, you know, it's the famous one of... I think it was
a Neanderthal. There was a famous question of like, you know, "At what point do you
think society exists?" And maybe one of the Leakeys but the
answer was basically this skeleton because it was someone with a
real-like a properly busted leg and then it fully
healed. And it's like if that person was on their own, just
dead, someone had to look after them for months
to get that level of healing. You only do that to someone you're really
devoted to and probably a group of people 'cause even one person can't look
after one other person, right? So that's your
society. And yet you think about the pathology of skeletons
in the human race. How, you know, how many of us have broken a bone?
Most adults have probably broken a couple of bones
even if it's just a finger or a nose or
something. But then you think about what medicine has done and you would be able to
see treatments of complete compound fractures of guys
who survived horrific car crashes and treatments of cancer, bone
cancers and stuff like that. You would see that. Well, how is that happening? Either
they're magic or they've got some kind of... In which case, they'd probably cure
it instantly or there's some kind of technology in society supporting that change.
- That just hints at the fact that the evidence collection and
the reasoning mechanisms that paleontology and archaeology uses is really powerful.
- Yeah, it is.
- And so it could be very effective even just with a small amount of data.
I mean you could-
- But it's the right amount of data. That's the thing. We can find dozens of skeletons
that we can't do very much with and then the right one that, you know,
things like stomach contents, you know, that's a super or bite marks is a super powerful bit of
data but it doesn't turn up that often. So it's not like you can get it off every
skeleton. And that's the thing, it's the pool of data and I think
that's what people miss. We, as paleontologists, we get caught up
on single superlative specimens and then try and
treat them as a... like a silver bullet almost.
So Microraptor, I mentioned this before, little flying dinosaur, crow-sized or
gliding dinosaur. Crow-sized thing from China. We've got at least a
dozen good specimens of it by now and multiple ones with stomach
contents. There's one I've described with a little mammal foot inside
it, there's one with a bird inside it, there's one with a lizard inside it and there's
one with a fish inside it. On their own, and this happened for at
least two of the papers describing these things, it's like, "It ate fish.
These are fish-eating animals." No, that one ate one
fish once. That one ate one bird
once, that one ate one mammal once and that one ate one lizard
once. So what have we actually got here?
I suspect we've got a group of generalists and we just happen to have found them eating different things
at different times. But equally, it's also possible, at
least, that, yeah, this is one of these things and it had learned to
eat fish when the others hadn't and actually this was mostly fish eaters and the others
ate whatever they could get. Maybe one caught a bird up a tree in a
nest. Maybe one found it dead on the ground. You don't really know what
one of these things on its own is fascinating, but potentially misleading.
- Well, the way you're describing it now, it seems like, yes, it's potentially misleading, but
there's... in your whole way of being and the way you've been talking about
this stuff I can see that
it's not just the direct evidence you're mentioning. It's like, it's a bunch of
intuitions you build up. It's like you're stitching together a bunch
of little things... It's the Sherlock Holmes thing. Not just this one piece of evidence.
this one piece of evidence-
... it's like, "Okay, what do I know about the general other
dinosaurs that are on the Earth? The different animals-"
... how animals usually behave about this period, about the environment?" And all of that comes
together, and then- ... figuring out which is true.
- And that's... So one thing I've definitely written about is,
yeah, the independent lines of evidence. Can you get
stuff that is as far as possible truly
independent from the other data and does it give you the
same answer? And then when it does-
- That's powerful.
- ... that's incredibly powerful. So Spinosaurus or the-
the spinosaurs as a whole is my go-to example for this are
the... guys with the famous big sail back and the weird crocodile-like
head, though some of them look rather different to that. And if you look across
all the species and specimens that we have, incredibly fragmentary and very badly
known, but they're all basically associated with... When you look at the gestalt,
you see a whole bunch of stuff for these things. So they
do have a surprisingly crocodile-like head and crocodile-like teeth compared to every
other carnivorous dinosaur. And when you do the mechanical analysis, you
see they function in a very similar way. And indeed,
teeth, here's a spinosaur tooth with very nearly circular
cross section, really distinctive, similar to crocodiles, similar
to dolphins, similar to fish-eating fish.
So points to fish. Crocodile-like head, points to
fish. Crocs eat other stuff too, but still. Um,
they're usually found in or near aquatic systems now.
Fossils in general tend to turn up in aquatic systems because you've got to be buried to become a fossil.
So water association is common, but even so, that's true.
They turn up in places where lots of other dinosaurs don't tend to turn up,
including carnivores, which suggests they're eating something
else. If you look at the isotopic signature of the
teeth, often it correlates with crocodiles, fish,
turtles, and stuff that lives in water, and doesn't correlate well
with other land-living dinosaurs that lived in the same time and same place.
So you put all of that together, and it's really hard to
argue... Oh, in addition to the tiny detail of Baryonyx, the British
one was found with fish scales inside its chest cavity. So you put all of
that together, and yeah, I'm not saying it only ate fish.
I'm sure it ate big shrimp and turtles. And we know they were
predating on terrestrial dinosaurs and pterosaurs because, again, stomach
contents and teeth and stuff. But fundamentally, this is an
animal or a group of animals doing something different to the other carnivorous
dinosaurs, and it's probably linked to water, and it's probably linked to
fish as a predominant way of living.
- We should mention that you're working on a book out in early 2026?
- In the UK it will be out in November. In North America, January or February 2026.
- It's called Spinosaur Tales: The Biology and Ecology of the Spinosaurus. And...
- Written with Mark Witton, who did that picture.
- It's a beautiful creature.
- Which I think is in there. Mark's done a ton of new artwork. He helped write
the book, but he's also the artist.
- I mean, can you describe a little bit more about this creature? There's a bunch of stuff like
what you just mentioned. There's some debate. Like where-
Is it... To what degree is it aquatic? So what-
- Not very is my take.
- So does it live in the water? Does it-
- I... Yeah. So I think it's basically a big wader.
It's a poor analogy, but it's a very weird, giant stork.
- Oh. Got it.
- Or heron.
- Was giant.
- Yeah. So potentially bigger than T-Rex. Linearly, not in
mass. Again, really quite narrow chest versus that T-Rex
barrel. But potentially 15 meters long, so bigger than any
T-Rex we've found, at least in terms of length.
- Can you describe what it looks like? The... I mean, there's some iconic features to it, right?
- Yeah. So this really quite long head,
with a kind of wavy jawline. Like, animals have
You know, most carnivores have straight jaws. This one has a kind of
somewhat wiggly jawline. It really narrows at the front and then opens up
again into a like a little... It's called a rosette. So you've got like a little
semicircle, and then a dip, and then the jaws go back, and then the teeth
line waves up and down. These really conical teeth, which doesn't
sound very exciting, but it makes them
different to every other carnivorous dinosaur. No other thing has a conical
tooth, which is a classic fish thing, or at least biting hold of
something that wriggles. The nostrils are not at
the tip of the nose. They're pushed back, at least somewhat. It has a bunch of crests on the
head. It's got quite a long neck. Spinosaurus and at
least a couple of the other closest relatives to it, a thing called Ichthyovenator.
from... I can't remember if it's Thailand or Laos. I think it's Laos. It has this
giant elongated bit to the top of the vertebrae, so it gives it
this giant sail along the back. Spinosaurus,
at least, possibly Ichthyovenator, probably not any of the others, then
has this weird, thin, newt-like
expanse to the top of the tail, giving it kind of like a giant oar paddle
appearance. Mostly they have very large arms with
giant claws on the hands. And Spinosaurus
at least appears to have really quite short legs, but the others
don't. But again, so
Spinosaurus is totally iconic, but if you look at something like Baryonyx from the
UK or Suchomimus from Niger,
it's still got the same head, neck, and arms, but it doesn't have this
sail, and it doesn't have this tail, and it probably doesn't have short legs. So Spinosaurus
is super weird and exaggerated version of what
was already a kind of super weird group of theropods.
So Spinosaurus is properly strange. And then, as you kind of
hinted at, super controversial as well, because various papers have
claimed it's a diver or a really good swimmer, and I think the evidence for that is
very weak at best.
- So your book is going to be... You're going to start some shit with your book. It's going to be all contro-
- I think... I think I already have, to be honest. I've written...
I've written three major papers, and one in particular with my colleague,
Tom Holt, where we frankly savaged the idea that it's a good swimmer. And then-
- Oh.
- ...other people have since, including some of the authors who were on the original paper
claiming it did swim well, have now effectively reversed their position and said it
didn't.
- So the Jurassic Park 3 fight between the two-
- Yeah.
- ...who's famous. In a real-life encounter, who wins?
- Probably still T-Rex. I mean, the Jurassic Park Spinosaurus was pretty good for its
time because some of the stuff that I've just talked about,
particularly the short legs were suggested way back in 1910,
1912, but it was really uncertain.
Now it appears to be more likely the case than not. The tail was unknown at
this point, so it was just given a very generic tail. But
the crocodile-like head is pretty good. The neck's a bit short.
The sail is a bit too... It's almost just like a semicircle stuck on the
back, and it's a bit more complicated than that. But personally, I'm quite a
big fan of the Jurassic Park 3 Spinosaurus. I think for its era, it's
really quite good. It is massive. There is this... They're from, I'm going to say,
Morocco, because Spinosaurus is found throughout North Africa, Morocco,
Algeria, Egypt. There's a massive pair of jaws or
snout that's in a collection in Milan
that's absolutely outsized. It's like an absolute giant. And that points
to a truly monumentally sized Spinosaurus, which is where all these upper
estimates of 15-plus meters come from, is just this one set of jaws. But
yeah, it's about right, but it's just a bit too muscly and a bit
too bulky. But in gross appearance, it's pretty good.
- Does it have a chance against a T-Rex?
- No. Because it's got this unbelievably long, thin
jaw, which whilst much stronger than something like
Baryonyx, is fundamentally not that strong. The jaws are very long and thin, and then the teeth are...
The jaws are very long and thin, and then the teeth are... Yeah. They're
big, but they're not... big, big.
You know, the whole, like, it grabs the T-Rex neck and
then, like, snaps it. Well, Spinosaurus
actually, its neck is really strong going up and down and is
very weak rotating or going side to side. So it's got the
weakest kind of possible neck to, like, rotate and snap the T-Rex, and
then T-Rex has got, like, the strongest neck of anything. So you've got, like,
the weakest jaw with the weakest spin versus the strongest neck.
So no, I don't buy it.
- So that brings it back to the topic we touched on a little bit. What are... You've
mentioned a bunch of the stuff that the Jurassic Park...
...series gets wrong? Maybe you could speak to more
things, but also, what does it get right?
- So a lot of, like, very, in some level generic, but quite important things it gets
right. T-Rex is about the right size and shape and is
massive, and you don't actually see it run. You see it power walk. If you watch the Jeep chase again,
you'll see it only ever has one foot on the ground.
The weird thing for me is how much some of them vary. So, like, I'm a big
pterosaur guy. I do lots of work on pterosaurs, the flying reptiles. The
Pteranodons in Jurassic Park Two: The Lost
World, you see them very, very briefly in one of the last shots and they're okay, but
they're not great, but it's clearly a bit of a throwaway shot. The ones in Jurassic
Park Three, I think are mostly excellent. Really, really
good. And then the ones in Jurassic World are terrible. Like, a
massive regression. There's loads and loads of details that are right in
JP3 that are completely wrong in Jurassic World, and you're like, "Why did you take a
really good model and make it much, much worse and less
accurate?" I don't understand. And I...
Again, it's fiction. At one level, who cares? But, like, as you said, like,
I don't think... So, see, the weird thing for me is,
I don't think it would affect how they're perceived
by the public. Some things I get. Like, for example, in
Jurassic World, the Pteranodons pick people up with their feet and fly off with
them. Pteranodon's feet don't work like that. It would never be able to do that, and it would
never have the lift. But I get for dramatic purposes, you might want to show that.
Okay, fine. You know, this is your big sequence. You need that. But for
the rest of the animal, it's weirdly inaccurate,
and I don't think the public would know and
they might well care if it was much more accurate.
And I don't think it would be any harder to make it accurate than to make it
inaccurate. I've spoken to a colleague of mine who I won't
name, just in case I get him into trouble.
who's a big dinosaur nerd, but also a big creature creator
and designer, and has done a whole bunch of proper Hollywood
A-list movie stuff. And I asked him about this, and I
went, "Okay, but, like, is it just easier to
take the model that you've got and mess around with it than to, if I came in
and said, 'You need to fix that, and you need to fix this, you need to fix this, you need to fix that?'"
And he basically went, "No, it's about the same amount of effort." It's not like
we don't have the director or the producer or the lead designer going, "No, I want that arm
a bit longer. I want that tail a bit brighter. Can you add a few more bits there? I don't like
those scales." So he said, "We're doing that constantly anyway. So doing
it to one set of design specs versus another set of design specs is no
more hassle." In other words, he said, "It's no harder to make it accurate than to make
it inaccurate." And it's like, if that's truly the case,
then just make it right. And then you can claim a level of accuracy
and engagement that you can. I mean, it's interesting.
There's a thing called the Jurassic Foundation. After the first Jurassic Park
made an absolute fortune. I think it was Spielberg directly, may have been through
Universal, but anyway, they set up the Jurassic Foundation, and it's a small fund of
money for research on dinosaurs and related animals, and academics can apply for
it. One of my PhD students got some money from the Jurassic
Foundation. That's great. He didn't have to do that. He went,
"Paleontology's helped give me this. I'm going to give back a bit." And after
what must be, what, 30 years now, it's probably funded an awful lot of research and
helped young researchers get a start. So
there's a level of engagement there that I think hasn't been
in subsequent films, which you can kind of see
once it goes from being a one-off to being a
franchise, and it's changed hands. I mean, how many different directors has it had
now? You know, Spielberg did the first two, and
then don't know about the next five. Must be two, if not another three more
people, you know, and 30 years later, it's all changing.
- Yeah, but that's the path of creating a legendary film.
The depth of accuracy, and it's not that difficult to work, but it's also...
It does something to the whole artistic creation
if you create a culture where the details really, really matter.
- Matter. Yeah, and again, there are some oddities, so like
Gallimimus, I mentioned it earlier, so one of the ornithomimosaurs. The model for
gallimimus in Jurassic World is nearly
identical to that from Jurassic Park. One of the differences, which you
can barely see on film, but I know this is true because I
found it in like, a Jurassic World kids book cause I flicked through it when it came out, is a
closeup of the head with an arrow to the teeth. Gallimimus doesn't have
teeth. It's got a beak. So someone has taken the original model
and actively spent time adding teeth to an animal that didn't
have them. I would understand it. I'm not saying I agree with it, but I'd
understand if it was a rule of cool and like, "Yeah, but it would look so
much better with all these gnarly big teeth and whatever." And it's like, you can't
even see it in the final thing. They've got tiny little heads. In the film, all they
do is like, run past the camera briefly. It's not like they're a big
carnivore and they're engaged in like, one of the big battles. Like, why? Why?
It's not like... You can barely even see them.
- Well, yeah, again, just to linger on it. There is a lot of value to
authenticity in all walks of life, and one of them is
...accuracy. When you're talking about dinosaurs, it's so
valuable and so worthy, and it's respectable for the long life of a film to be
accurate. I just wish, I hope they do that. There are certain directors that really
dogmatically push that. Alex Garland comes to mind. You know,
he did, whenever he integrates quantum computing or AI into a film...
- Mm-hmm. Nolan with the black hole in Interstellar.
...ended up publishing a paper on the calculation to visualize that.
- I mean, that's legendary.
- Yeah.
- That's great. That's really...
And like, you think that has nothing to do with the story, the narrative of the film, but it
does. It, like, permeates everything. If you get that black hole right, that...
...everybody else steps up their game, and really,
really tells a story in this way that reverberates through time, and it, like,
really moves people. So,
- Yeah. I, I, yeah, I mean, as I say, I, I wish it was
better. I mean, the only thing I'd flip it around is a joke I've made
more than once, but like, just don't take it as a documentary. No
one watches James Bond and goes, "That's how international espionage works."
You know, he's got the laser watch and the exploding car, and he's like,
maybe treat it a bit as fiction. I've heard from a friend of mine
who worked at the Royal Tyrrell Museum, which I've mentioned before, in
Alberta, which is an absolutely phenomenal place, and
she said after the first one, genuinely, like, it was not
common, but more than once, people were annoyed
that they didn't have the real dinosaurs out back, because they'd seen them, and
they knew that the real ones were out there. Which is a testament to
Industrial Light & Magic and Stan Winston, but also...
- Wow.
- ...slightly horrifying that anyone watched Jurassic Park
and literally thought that. Also, why would you go to a museum? You go to the zoo if
it's alive.
- There you will also meet what is it, King Kong and Godzi-
I don't think we quite touched on this. I really want to ask you
about intelligence. What we know about
...the intelligence of, let's say, T-Rex. We talked about his big head. What do we know
about-
- Not much. So there's a T-Rex brain, or at least a very rough cast of part of one.
- That's the actual look of-
- Yeah, this is
...so dinosaurs, in fact, most reptiles. I don't know if you can see it on the
velociraptor. Not really, unfortunately. Um-
- It's elongated.
- Yeah, but it's more that they have... we are weird in
that we have a brain that basically fills the inside of our
skull. What most animals have is actually a little kind
of sub-skull inside the main skull, which is called the
endocast or endocranium, and the brain is in that. And even then, it's
not, like, full of brain because we've packed an awful lot of brain into a limited
space, and they then have quite a lot of goo and fat and other stuff around
it. But it means for dinosaurs, and then deep reptiles and birds in
general, in the old days you could basically cut one
open, but now we'll CT scan through them, you can take an internal mold of the
endocranium or the brain case, and then whatever
filled that would've been the brain and its surrounding tissues. And that's how
you get something like this. In this case, someone literally cracked open an old
skull-
...and basically took an internal mold in the same way that you do an external mold for the
skulls. And that tells you quite a lot about
certain things. So for example, they've got a bulb at the
front, which is the olfactory bulb. So brains are very stereotyped, again, ours are super
weird, so you have the olfactory bulb at the front and behind that you have the optic bulb or the
optic lobe. So roughly how big they are will tell you roughly how
much of the brain is devoted to, for example, sight and smell. So if
it's a lot, it's pretty good. If there's not much, it's not very
good. That goes quite a long way already.
One thing we've done in the last few years is you can also get into the,
it's not shown here, it wouldn't be part of this, but the inner ear.
We can CT scan into the structure of the bony inner ear, and from
that you can actually get an idea of what frequency of sounds
the inner ear was structured ...to be pitched to.
- Wow.
- Which doesn't actually tell you very much, but it's phenomenally cool that you
can do it.
- We should say you also have quite a bit of a background in biology. So you're trying to
reconstruct biology from, go from paleontology to biology.
- Yeah, my go-to one-liner is, "I'm a zoologist
but I work on dead stuff." My degree was zoology. My
official job title now is Reader of Zoology. I teach zoology. I don't teach
Paleo. So yeah, living animals
was always actually my primary interest, and I kind of fell into
paleo, but then I wanted to drag that with me because I'd been
trained in behavior and ecology and it's what I was most interested in, so then applying that
knowledge and understanding to these animals.
- So to some degree it is possible to reach towards the biology?
- Absolutely, yeah.
- So with the ear, that's interesting. The brain.
- Yeah.
- So we can know something about the brain?
- Yeah, but then when you get into intelligence is when it gets really awkward
because working out exactly which bits of this are
probably linked to, like, the main fundamental processing and what
you'd link to actual intelligence is tough.
On top of that, we don't really know what's been the big challenge of the last couple of years of this
question, was T-Rex and other dinosaurs super intelligent? Like, neuron
density. How many basically nerve cells can you pack in per
bit of volume? Because birds have some weird tricks which means they get a lot more
brain per volume. Just how much of
the brain case was brain and how much was, like, goop around it,
we know varies, so you're getting kind of fairly big upper and lower
band, and then the other big thing we always have to do is factor in
size. Big animals need bigger brains to operate them. So
whales have really big brains, but whales weigh tens of tons. They're
not smarter than us. So you have the classic thing is a thing called
the encephalization quotient, which is at a very
simple level, it is the volume of brain scaled against the size of the animal.
We have huge brains compared to how big we are, so we're massively up
the chart. And then you do have a few things with, like, worms. I should probably
stick to vertebrates, because there's some stupid stuff which has a
surprisingly small brain for its size. Most things that
aren't primates, and things like crows and parrots, sit
very neatly on a couple of different curves. There's a curve for reptiles, a curve for birds, a
curve for mammals, and things like this. And
basically that's it. But also, actually, our understanding with mass estimates for
dinosaurs is good but not great, and so you could easily be out by,
you could easily be out by like 20 or 30% on the volume of the
brain inside the brain case, and then you could be out by 20 or 30% on your
mass estimate. Well, now suddenly, it's very
easy to make the brain too big and the animal too light and it's
super smart, or make the brain too small and the animal too heavy and it's super
dumb. So that's awkward, unfortunately.
- So apparently there's a, some controversial paper that suggests that T-Rex is a pri-
has primate-level intelligence.
- Yeah, and then that was shot down within a few months by a
team of paleontologists and a couple of other neurologists who really
went to town on it.
- Just counting the number of... Trying to estimate the number of neurons.
- Yeah, it was the neuron density thing, and yeah
I've unsurprisingly support the revised
one which was done by a whole bunch... Yeah, the Casper paper. I've spoken
to Casper about it, couple of the other authors.
- So, they scaled down the number of neurons from three billion
down to 250 million to 1.7 billion.
- Yeah, much, much lower.
- Which is similar to crocodiles and other primates.
- Yeah, which is kind of what you'd expect. I mean, a couple of other people at
various times have suggested they're really smart. And again, you know, birds
have this thing of, they have this weird thing of neuron folding, and they
can basically pack in a lot more than you'd expect. You know, that's why crows are that
smart despite having
tiny brains, relatively even compared to their overall size. But
I'm being obviously overly facetious, but if
ultimately part of your scaling is how big is the animal
versus how big is its brain, that's most of a T-Rex
brain. It's a fraction of the size of a chimp brain, and
chimps don't weigh seven tons. So,
you know, it's a kind of Hitchens-like extraordinary claims
require extraordinary evidence, but you just look at it and go
that's about the proportion we'd expect for a croc. Now, crocs are smarter than
people think, but they're sure as hell not monkeys. Um,
you're going to have to really come up with something much more
convincing than, "Oh well, if you just pack 'em in, if you scale 'em this way."
- A bit of a ridiculous question, but is it possible to find evidence of tool use?
- I mean, in theory, it depends quite how you define a
tool, so birds building nests is arguably tool use to a certain degree.
I'm aware of... I suspect it's turned out not to be the case. I was, I was
shown a very rough, not very well-prepared fossil
20 years ago now, no, 15 years ago now, where someone said, "We
think this might be an early bird nest and therefore potentially
even a dinosaur nest," and nothing's ever been published, so my guess is
once they excavated it and had a good look at it, they went, "Nah, it's nothing
really." I mean, I guess the question is, how would you know?
- Yeah, it would be difficult unless it's obvious, widespread, primate-like...
- Yeah, but even then, like, you know...
- ...sapient-like almost.
- Chimps make loads of tools, but it's mostly made of wood, and they're mostly just
breaking stuff, and then the odds of that preserving are very
low. You do get things like chimps and otters, sea otters,
you know, they have their favorite anvil and hammer stones to break stuff open.
But again, the reason they picked that stone is 'cause it's really heavy and good at
breaking oysters or breaking nuts. It's not gonna leave, or
probably not gonna leave stereotypical points on the rock. And even then,
you could just go, "Well, maybe it, you know,
just got bashed up in a river or something."
- So, in your book "Uncovering Dinosaur Behavior," you conclude that there's a lot
we might not know. What's a particular lost behavior
that we don't know about that you think might be out there?
- Something like midden use, so a whole bunch of animals and
birds who basically crap in the same spot. They
have their spot, and that's where they go. So, rabbits do this,
sloths do this, aardvarks, even things like wildebeest and zebra, not zebra, impala
will tend to go back to the same place every day.
But the fossil record of sarcoplites, fossilized feces and
fossilized waste from dinosaurs, it exists, but it's extremely
rough because of course, this is the stuff that's already been digested and broken
down. It's already kind of gooey and broken up and doesn't have a lot going for it.
If they do it in water, it's going to dissipate instantly. If it rains, it's
probably going to fall apart. Things like dung beetles and flies will break it
down. Even if it gets covered by sand or whatever from a sandstorm, it's probably
still going to compress and separate. So, are you ever going to find it?
Maybe going back to our trackway stuff, but even if you do, what species
left that? We know a big herbivore did this, but was it
Triceratops, or was it an Ankylosaur? Those animals are very different things
doing very different things, and it would tell you different things about their behavior
- Yeah, so one piece of behavior I forgot to ask you about.
So, T-Rex engaging cannibalism.
- Yeah, almost certainly. Well, certainly. I think we've got
there's a T-Rex bone with a T-Rex embedded tooth in it. With overgrowth.
I think it's, I want to say it's an Albertosaur rather than T-Rex, but there is
there is a tyrannosaur jaw in Alberta with a
T-Rex tooth stuck in it, and you can pull the little tooth out.
And then there's a T-Rex foot bone with these
distinctive feeding traces on them. And this actually goes back to that early
point about T-Rex being weird, being the only big carnivore in its environment,
because if this was even Mongolia at that time, but anywhere else, there's
three or four or five big carnivores. And so you find a bone and it's chewed
up by a big carnivore, we don't know who did it. But when you see a
big bone chewed up in a T-Rex ecosystem,
well, you know, if it's anything bigger than this, you know it was
T-Rex. And so when it's a T-Rex bone with T-Rex bite marks,
- Yep, it's pretty obvious.
- QED. Yeah, so it must have been.
- That's fascinating, isn't it? That they would attack themselves, their own species.
- Cannibalism turns up in a whole bunch of stuff. Um,
but it's very rare as like a fairly habitual behavior.
- So, but there's several reasons you might be engaging in,
or rather teeth marks might tell various stories.
So it could be just fighting for dominance, right?
- It, it could, but it's unlikely, and in this case, so again, we see there are
loads of facial injuries in tyrannosaurs, in carnivorous dinosaurs generally, but
particularly tyrannosaurs. They have really beaten up heads, like half
or even two-thirds of adults have scarring and facial
injuries. But you see healing on it, whereas this foot does not show
healing and it's got multiple different bites. The idea that
you'd bite a foot whilst fighting someone and then go back and bite that one
foot again? That's pretty unlikely.
- So, looks like it's eating, not fighting.
- Yeah, and they're more like the feeding scrape traces than they are the big puncture wounds, so
again, not impossible, but very weird for that to occur as a fight.
- So fascinating.
- So yeah, they're- they're fighting, they're fighting probably quite a lot, but
whether or not you actually eat something that you've
killed or that you stumble across as a body, it definitely happens occasionally.
Otherwise, we wouldn't have the record of that, but there's a reason carnivores
often don't eat carnivores, and particularly don't eat their own
species, which is parasitism. Carnivores in
general are loaded with parasites because they spend their whole
lives eating food which has parasites and stuff in it.
And so they tend to accumulate a lot of them. What's the one thing that's
definitely gonna have the most parasites in it that can infect you as, for
example, a lion? It's another lion that eats the exact same stuff
that you do. So whilst it is food and particularly if you've
just won a big fight, you might want to eat.
In general, cannibalism's pretty rare because it's
generally not a good idea if there's other food available. But yeah, if
you're starving to death or, you know, the other guy ripped your leg half off and you
don't think you're gonna walk for six weeks, not that you'd think, but you know what I mean.
Like, and now there's a body in front of you, it's two tons of meat, well,
maybe you should tuck in.
- This is so fascinating, like, once again, figuring out this puzzle.
And like, what does cannibalism tell you? You're piecing together the
story of T-rex, their life, their hunting life, their social life from
their evolution to their biology to their behavior. That's so fascinating.
- Yeah, we try to. But the thing is, it's always getting better which is
So that's what I try to finish on in my book on behavior is,
I felt I'd written a couple of hundred pages of, "We keep
screwing this up, we've overstated this, I think people have misunderstood this, this-"
You know, like the track ways stuff, and like, this is not as confident as we think,
you need to look at these alternate explanations. This behavior shows that that behavior probably
doesn't correlate the way you said it does, yada, yada, yada. And it's like, and now I feel like I've just written a
book trashing my entire field and all my colleagues, or at least many of my
colleagues. And then, but then you flip it on its head and
going, "We've got techniques that were undreamed
of ten years ago. We've got data streams that were undreamed
of ten years ago. And we've actually got a much better understanding of living
species." And then on top of that we're just constantly finding new animals, you
you know, we have not just
new species, which are often, I think, a lot less important, but just new specimens of ones
we know, because again, it's building up that database. You know, we drifted off talking
about sexual selection, but like, yeah, if you want to know growth, one or two
animals doesn't tell you how an animal, a species, grows. 50 or 100
does. And then that reveals a hell of a lot more about things like sexual
dimorphism and growth rate and how vulnerable juveniles are and population structure
and maybe how they're reproducing. So I'd
like to think I knocked down, I think, a few towers that probably a few people were
fond of, but I think we have the raw materials to build much
better, stronger edifice of behavior.
But as you say, it's always going to be based around
often very piecemeal evidence and
like possibilities and probabilities rather than certainties.
- Let's talk about a sad topic: extinction.
- Yep.
- How did the dinosaurs go extinct?
- Mostly, probably, pretty quickly, but it really is
the answer that I think most people are now probably familiar with, which is, it's an
asteroid impact or some kind of extraterrestrial body hit
just off the coast of the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico about 66 million years
ago that basically atomized the
asteroid, but also importantly, the bit of the ground it hit, or
below the sea bed that it hit, was basically the worst kind of rock.
And so it put up this enormous ash cloud and basically you
have a nearly instantaneous nuclear winter. I mean, immediate
devastation. You know, and anything immediately
next to it is obviously just vaporized. But you know, this is the sort of thing that's
hot enough to set fire to the atmosphere. I think the one I read was,
it's something like a piece of rock about the size of Mount Everest
traveling at something like 10 times the speed of sound. So just
the momentum between that speed and mass thing is just, you know,
beyond extraordinary.
- But I think what does a lot of damage is the change in the climate, and-
- Yeah, and so every... There are five recognized mass
extinctions in the history of life on Earth, and all of them are ultimately some form of climate
change, whether it's volcanic eruptions or
hyper-oxygenation, or an ice age or whatever. It's climate
changing too quickly for things to adapt to. And that starts, you know, that
just cripples entire populations and entire species. And then if you do
enough damage to enough things, you start getting ecosystem
collapse. You know, this moth has died out. Well, it turns out that
moth is the primary pollinator of this tree. Well, that tree produced nuts, and
that was the entire winter survival store for this squirrel. Well, that squirrel
was the main food of this cat, and now
suddenly the moth going has killed four other things and everything that's attached to that.
And so that's really what did for them.
- And sadly, the big things... Well, everything
dies, but the big things have a lot of trouble recovering.
- Yeah. So, I mean, this is, you know, a classic
example. So, oh well, you know, what is paleontology good for? Well, actually, really, it's
extinction, which is very relevant right now in that we have a very good
handle on when you have extreme climate stress, what
tends to suffer more and what tends to suffer less. And as we say,
big things fundamentally do. They require more
resources, they require more area of land. You need to roam
further, which means, you know, if you're a mouse and you
happen to have a little bit of land and that bit doesn't get hit, you're fine; whereas if you're an
elephant and you need all of this land and even a chunk of it goes
wrong, well, that's probably maybe not enough for you to survive anymore.
So, yeah, big things suffer disproportionately badly from these things, and
mostly as well we think terrestrial things generally do worse than
things in water because water's a great equilibrating
medium, you know, it takes ages to heat up, it takes ages to cool
down. Yes, if you live in specific coastal conditions or something, maybe
you can't travel that easily, but, you know, whales can go from
pole to pole quite happily, and plenty of other fish do too. So if it's too hot
or too cold or too nasty here, you can just swim somewhere else,
whereas if you're an animal and you hit a desert or you hit a mountain range or you hit a
river, you stop moving and you're trapped, and then you die.
So dinosaurs were, yeah, the worst possible
combination. They were mostly big and they were mostly on
land, and yeah, it's not really surprising they did very badly out of it.
- And then some species did survive. I
guess I think you've said that it's very possible that some dinosaurs even
survived for a time.
- Oh, w-
- ...that we might be able to discover down the line.
- I'd be amazed if they didn't. I mean, there's been various reports over the
decades of the- the
K-Pg or K-T extinction, the Cretaceous- Paleogene or Cretaceous-Tertiary
extinction of dinosaurs surviving and none of them have held up. It's
usually been bioturbation, so literally things like
prairie dogs digging, and of course they'll dig a tooth up and then move it through
the layers, or things like this, or plant roots can move stuff.
Or just soils can get churned up. But
I would be shocked if they didn't. Not like, "Oh, yeah, the
dinosaur survived, and the Loch Ness Monster, and stuff like that." But like,
yes, it was a global devastation. Yes, it's what ultimately killed the
dinosaurs, but I'd be amazed if there wasn't some equivalent of Hawaii or New
Zealand or some other tucked away island or valley where
actually dinosaurs were fine for anything from a few hundred thousand to a
couple of million years. But on a global scale, it's a dot on a
map and the odds that we'll ever uncover
any rocks, fossiliferous rocks of that age that we then have
access to that we then find a dinosaur in that we can then date properly,
I think, is almost non-existent. But it would just be weird if
they didn't survive somewhere for a bit, or even quite a few of them in places.
- So a small, local population.
- We see it all the time, you know, the lemurs in Madagascar,
all the stuff in New Zealand. There's tons of weird archaic stuff hanging around.
in Hawaii, you know, Galapagos finches and tortoises, the
tortoises that you don't see anywhere else. In Australia, with the marsupials, they're
almost, and then the monotremes are almost unknown outside of there.
This is a pretty normal bit of biology. For animals that were so dominant globally
we know there were patches that were largely unchanged, otherwise we wouldn't have had the mammals
surviving and the crocodiles surviving and the birds surviving and ever- and newts
and frogs and everything that did survive. I'm sure a few of those
patches had some dinosaurs in them, but it is ultimately what killed them.
- What do you think is the chance that they would have survived? So you take some local
populations and they flourish.
- It's happened. Look at Australia. You know, the
marsupials have done pretty well there for a very long
time. You can imagine if the next mass
extinction, you know, flattens a large chunk of
Indonesia, for example, kangaroos could island
hop pretty easily, make it to mainland Asia.
- But then, I mean, to then lead... You take the
dinosaurs... a small fraction survives and then they eventually
repopulate the earth again.
- I mean, that's extraordinarily unlikely, because once your population's been crashed like
that, you do have the problems of things like inbreeding, or maybe you're
a great specialist to a certain area, or you're surviving because you're
isolated, you're in a valley, or you're on an island, and then
dispersing again becomes really, or breaking out into those areas
becomes much, much harder.
- So like the great predators like the... Even though the T-rex is such a great
predator, that doesn't give you...
- Yeah, because you still had the extinction event, and the
environment is no longer what it was that you evolved into.
- Right.
- And once those systems start to recover, those other animals are going to adapt
much better to them.
- How does that make you feel that, that this stupid asteroid from nowhere?
- Well, I mean, at one level I probably wouldn't be here if it hadn't.
- So, I mean, that's an interesting question. I mean, do you think... There's several ways of asking that
question, but if dinosaurs didn't go extinct, do you think
humans would still be able to evolve?
- I mean, my guess is probably not. I don't think it's quite
the... What was it? Oh, Simon Conway
Morris had that book. What was it? Inevitability of Man. That like even if you
rewound it, everything would come back. I'm not...
I don't think it's that far. I certainly don't think it's
anything quite like the butterfly effect of, you know, if
one mammal had been trodden on by one T-rex, then humans would never have
evolved either.
- We should say that the ancestor of the primates, or the
closest... There's a lot of debate around this, it's a kind of tiny
creature, Purgatorius, that was our
ancestor. Yeah, so this is us. This is what we evolved from.
- Yes. Scandentia, I think, is the group.
- Basically a rodent.
- Yeah, I mean there were probably primates around in the Cretaceous. Some
of the molecular clock stuff suggests that primates were around
alongside the dinosaurs, but we've never found any
osteological evidence of that. But yeah, there's been a
back and forth about were dinosaurs already on their way out, or were they a bit
limited by the very end Cretaceous. I think the more recent
analyses have shown that's probably not the case, because in other words, they were basically doing
fine right up to the extinction event. And so,
yeah, if the asteroid hadn't hit, there's no reason to think that they were on
some kind of terminal decline. Something else may have hit. There may have been,
you know, some other environmental disaster or something may have happened,
or maybe they're more vulnerable to stuff than we know of,
but there's no... I don't think there's any really good reason to think
they wouldn't have carried on relatively well. I mean, even
post-dinosaur extinction, you had a window where the mammals and the birds were
pretty competing. There was a lot of big birds getting going and various big
carnivorous, terrestrial, kind of hyper-predatory
ostrich-like things, like the phorusrhacids. So there's no
guarantee that mammals would have even taken over post the dinosaur
extinction, since initially they were in a fair bit of competition.
- So is it just going to... Based on current scientific understanding, human evolution would be
highly improbable if dinosaurs hadn't gone extinct 66 million years ago,
because dinosaurs dominated ecological niches.
- For everything, basically.
- Wide-bodied mammals.
- I mean, that's the thing. You look through the Mesozoic, the late
Triassic, dinosaurs are there alongside a whole bunch of other
big and unusual and interesting reptiles and some other
early pre-mammal-like things that are closer to mammals than the reptiles.
But once you've gotten into the Jurassic, you've now got a solid
like 120, 130 million years where almost anywhere on Earth, if you saw an animal
bigger than like a raccoon, it was probably a dinosaur. That's how
incredibly dominant they... You know, as dominant, if not more dominant than
modern mammals.
- But is it fair to say that they were mostly dumb?
- I don't think so, 'cause I think that comes down to
A) that bit of kind of classic, almost Victorian
speciesism, and you get these insane hypotheses
like dinosaurs as a species or as a lineage became senile, so they
forgot to breed. I know it's literally a suggested idea.
You know, the mammals ate their eggs and all of this kind of stuff. Dinosaurs only lived
alongside mammals for 100 million years. It'd be weird if they all went extinct at the
same time because suddenly egg eating evolved. You know, you've
got problems like this. But also, again, that general
speciesism, which, you know, even goes back to Linnaeus and his taxonomic
ranks, and even arguably stuff like Aristotle, you've got like, you know,
humans are superior in some way and we're superior to the
other mammals. And of course, mammals are closest to us, so they must be quite
good. And then they've got to be better than lizards, and then
lizards have to be better than frogs, and frogs have to be better than fish. So
that gets you into the, "Well, reptiles must be stupid." And they're not.
- I wonder if a human intelligence level organism could have evolved from the
dinosaurs.
- I mean, it's... That's been hypothesized plenty of times. Dale Russell, a
Canadian paleontologist, the famous guy who came up with this human-like
troodontid that was done for a TV
documentary. I think the one that Christopher Reeve narrated. That, I think is
a remake, but I've seen the original that Dale had made for his TV show
and it's still... It's sitting in the collections of the
National Museum of Nature in Ottawa, for Canada. It's really,
really cool. It's like this five-foot tall dinosauroid. That was it there on the
screen.
- "Model of the hypothetical dinosauroid and display at the dinosaur museum in Dorchester."
- Oh, Dorchester. That's in England. Yeah, I knew there were a couple of copies of it.
Troodon always comes back as the most intelligent dinosaur because it has really quite a
big brain for its size. It does have a high encephalization
quotient, so it's always been tagged as a very good candidate
for being the smartest dinosaur. And basically, he just hybridized that with a
human. But of course, why would these things end up as plantigrade
quadrupeds, and why would they go back to five fingers and... Actually, I think he's only got three, to be
fair, but he's got very human-like feet. Why has it got no tail? Why would those
things suddenly disappear? There's no real reason other than just kind of
human exceptionalism. But like, I mean, you could argue some parrots, some crows are
phenomenally intelligent and show extremely clever
behaviors on par with apes. So at
some level, some dinosaurs were extremely intelligent.
- I mean, yeah, this is a whole other conversation, but all the tiny details that lead
to the explosion that is in our evolutionary
tree that is Homo sapiens. Like what is it? Opposable thumbs,
right? Is it the invention of fire and the meat-eating? Is it-
... is it some other-
- And fighting and sociality and-
- So many-
- predation pressure, and then the changing environment. I mean, the shrinking of the
forest, pushing apes out of the trees into the environment, or into
the open environment.
- And probably the same kind of story could be told about the dinosaurs or about anything
really.
- Yeah, I mean, you...
- There's no reason...
- I mean, if you have 160 million years and a global
domination. But I mean, this is the thing. You talked about lost behaviors, but
like the lost lineages. I wrote about this in one of my books, and like, you want to
find... You want a weird animal, you go to a volcanic
island. You go to New Zealand, you go to Hawaii, you go to the
Galapagos, and yet those are the places that basically don't really form fossils.
So you think the dinosaurs we know about are strange. What
was the stuff knocking around there? We're never going to
know, sadly. But for everything you think
weird... You know, you think birds are cool. Think about penguins compared to your
average bird. They live on an ice shelf for six months of the year and can't
fly, and massively modified skeletons. You know, compared to your average bird,
penguins are unbelievably weird. So yeah, take an average
dinosaur and take it to penguin level or ostrich
level or hummingbird level evolution.
There's going to be weirder stuff out there than we've found. Much weirder.
- If you travel back in time, your mind will probably be blown by the weirdness.
- Yeah.
- Because those things are almost always in small, isolated
places that don't preserve fossils very well, and so the odds of
us ever coming across them... I mean, you see it to a degree. So you've got,
the stuff that comes out of what is modern Transylvania,
what was Transylvania Hateg. That's that
was a series of islands in the Mediterranean at the end of the Cretaceous,
and some of the weirdest dinosaurs are from that chain of islands. And
that's not very isolated compared to, again, something like Hawaii or New
Zealand. But it's fitting the exact pattern. You get dinosaurs on
islands, they turn weird. We see that. So again, dinosaurs were real animals.
Again, it sounds really painfully obvious, but they weren't monsters. They followed
the same... Rules might be pushing it, but certainly, like, guidelines.
Ecology operates in certain ways. If you're bigger, you need more
food. But you're more efficient. You just are. That's pretty
much just physics and scaling. So big dinosaurs are going to follow
the rules of bigger animals, and small dinosaurs are going to follow the rules of smaller animals.
They just will. Quite how they violate it in certain
ways, by having unusually long necks or
unusual physiology, or eating an unusual diet, or because there was a
weird plant that was alive then that isn't now, or whatever it may be. There's
obviously a huge amount of variation and uncertainty. But
fundamentally, we know what makes animals and ecosystems
work, and dinosaurs were animals in ecosystems. They're
not that strange at some level, and therefore reconstructing their actual biology
is challenging, but far from impossible.
- Strange question. As everybody knows, dragons are obviously real.
- I've been asked that on live TV before. Only not with the sarcastic tone, so...
- Do you dare disagree? ...with this notion?
- Yes, I do. They don't.
- Well...
- And again, I...
- They're real to me, so...
- That's fine. But again, you know, we kind of touched on it, but
I think there's probably very little of any kind
of paleontological law that ended up in
things like Chinese culture, with the Chinese dragons and all of that stuff. That one comes up
repeatedly. The only one I do know of, again, from Alberta,
is buffalo stones that the...
apparently some of the Native Americans had, which are actually bits of
ammonites. So ammonites, they're curly, spiral-shelled
cephalopods that are related to octopus and squid. So they have all these
little segments to the shells, and the right species... And when they break
open, they have, like, two little pairs of legs and
then a bulge and then a little bulge, and it looks very roughly like a
bison. And apparently these were
thought to be, like, somehow miniature bison. They're very rare
because ironically, although the dinosaur bones are extremely common,
it was very swampy, so you didn't actually have a lot of sea coming in,
so you didn't tend to get things like ammonites and ocean-going animals. And then the shell would
have to break in the right way. But apparently for the local tribes, like
Sptilh, I don't remember who it is in that bit of Canada... But yeah, these were
quite valued. If you've got a buffalo stone. And I've seen a
couple of them, and yeah, you have to squint a bit, but as a little buffalo, it's not
far off. But yeah, but that whole, like, were they
finding mammoth legs and were they finding T-rexes, and was this inspiration
for this animal or this mystical animal? I don't think they were,
because you just don't tend to find them like that.
- So where do you think, like... You know, 'cause dragons show up in a bunch of different myths.
- Well, right. But that's the thing, they turn up in British mythology, and we've barely got any
dinosaurs here at all. You only find them when you start digging for
coal mines, which we weren't doing in...
- Is it basically a dramatization of like of snakes and lizards and stuff like this?
- Yeah, and just general exaggeration and welding stuff together.
I mean, that's one thing you could, I guess, potentially argue is
that, you know, yeah, we find tyrannosaurs in North America and in East
Asia. In fact, there's a whole bunch of stuff in the Early Cretaceous, which is often very common,
'cause it's all relatively recent in the grand scheme of things in the history of the
world. The fauna of East Asia:
China, Mongolia, Eastern Russia, is very similar to what you get in Canada or in the
USA and down in Mexico. And so
you find the same rough stuff. They may not be exactly the same, but you get
ceratopsians, you get tyrannosaurs, you get the big-edged archosaurs, you get
ankylosaurs, the armored ones, this, that, and the other. So if
these were influencing all those different cultures
...why don't Chinese dragons look like Mexican dragons or
equivalent thunderbirds or whatever? Well, because it probably wasn't influencing
them. If they were all seeing the same skeleton, they'd probably all
produce the same kind of mythical animals. They all produce
- Well, uh
- ...different ones.
- You have to understand, paleontology's not perfect, so they were just misinterpreting it.
- Misinterpreting, yeah.
- I mean, dragons aside, I'm sure, like we said with weirdness, there would
be creatures
that would be remarkable, right? That you look at it and you might as well
be seeing a dragon. It could be
And I mean, there are creatures alive in the sea today.
- Yeah, I mean if you dredged up a colossal squid, I think you'd have
You know, or even just dugongs and manatees. I mean, they're really quite strange.
- And if you allow yourself to marvel at the small things on Earth, like I was in the
Amazon jungle, like the insects, they're just like, "What is"
...happening there? There are so many things going on.
Oh, they're like hairy and colorful, and probably
poisonous, and they have teeth, and what? And they're just And they're long and
- Well, and all the little weirdos. I've, I've
several times I've pitched a book to publishers where I want to write a book
that basically makes the point that there is almost
nothing I mean, you can always dream up something totally ludicrous There is basically
nothing in science fiction that doesn't already exist on Earth in some way, shape, or
form.
- Yeah, that is why I'll think about alien civilizations and aliens out there, and
I'm very, very certain that there are aliens everywhere
throughout the observable universe. It's very strange we haven't seen
them, but it's fun to marvel at what they
possibly look like, because there's a huge variety
of organisms and species here on Earth, and you just expand that out
...to like more and more Earths, and you can just imagine there's a lot of weird
- Well, that's the thing. I think most people, you know, understandably...
I'm a biologist, and I particularly pride myself on finding out about
particularly weird animals. But yeah, I think people would be stunned
about some of the weird stuff that's out there that they just wouldn't
realize are real. You know, things like velvet worms.
You know, it's just, it'll blow your mind. You know,
caecilians and stuff like this and their reproductive behavior. It's just
jaw-dropping. I mean, I love teaching about them. I do a class on diversity of
life, and it's about eight weeks of vertebrate diversity, and I love
just dropping things in, and the students are like, "What do you mean that exists?
What do you mean something like that's normal for this group?" Yeah, they do that.
- Well, what from that class, but everything you've studied with the
dinosaurs, what have you learned about the
evolution of life on Earth, that mechanism?
- It's really good. It sounds obvious, but it's... I think
the bit that still fries my brain is just like the raw numbers, because
I think we're very bad at considering... Like, I
regularly talk about, "Oh, this is 70 million years old, but this is 78, and this is
104." And people are just like, "Oh my God, how on Earth do you deal with
those numbers?" And I don't. They're just numbers,
because I can't conceive of it really any better than you
can. They are astronomical. Yeah, last Thursday was quite a long time ago.
66 million years is mind-boggling. I can't fathom it.
I can't fathom it. But that's it. I think
the evolution thing is, A, my suspicion is quite a lot of it
happens... It's not quite Stephen Gould's punctuated equilibrium, but I think
stressful events probably prompt a lot more than
less stressful events. You know, population crashes and all these
things that then...
Odd things survive, and then that's changing your genetic component and all the rest of it.
But you've just got to remember that it's almost a numbers
game. You know, it's that bad analogy of like, "Oh yeah,
evolution is just rolling dice and hoping you get all sixes." And it's like, no, a friend of mine said,
"No, it's rolling dice, but it gets to keep the sixes." And then suddenly getting a
hat full of sixes isn't that hard, but also you're in the context
of even rare species, you know, ultra-rare,
short of stuff that like we've nearly killed off, but very rare
species have populations in the thousands or hundreds of thousands.
And are probably around for hundreds of thousands of years.
Very few, other than a few things like whales and apes and
elephants, mostly have dozens or thousands of offspring at a
time. So a few thousand animals that have a few thousand
offspring aligned for a few hundred thousand years... Yeah, it's billions and
billions and billions of them. And that's the
rare stuff. You look at Mola mola, the ocean sunfish, though I
think Mola has just been split up into like five species. It's one of the
weirdest-looking animals. I love it, love it, love it.
I mean, what a fish that is. Swims with a giant dorsal and
I think it's a giant anal fin, and then they flap alternatingly.
- Does it have a face? Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. Little one at the front. Ate jellyfish. Super
open-oceanic. And they get really big. You can see that one with the diver.
But I think these are the record breeders for animals, and they have something like 100
million eggs at a time.
- Whoa.
- Don't quote me on that, but it is something in those kinds of numbers.
So yeah, you don't need a very large population of
sunfish to start having an awful lot
of numbers. Are you gonna Google it and see if you can
find it? Number of eggs or something? Yeah. 300 million. Oh, I under- I-
- A single fe-
- I undercut it.
- A single female can release up to 300 million eggs at one time during a
spawning event. Boy. These eggs are incredibly small, measuring
about 1.3 millimeters in diameter.
- That's still a lot of egg size when you think about it.
- It's not that small.
- Yeah. 300 million of one mil is still quite a bit.
- Fertilization is external.
- Yeah, it's-
- Females release their eggs into the water, where males then fertilize
them. Wow. Man, there's a lot of different ways to have sex, I guess. This is-
- Yeah. But that's the bit of evolution that I
think, I understand why people don't get it. We are
mostly talking about millions in population
times millions of years times thousands of offspring.
Yeah. It's kind of a numbers game. Well, how could this evolve?
With the right selective pressure, and when you've got 100 billion offspring,
probably a few of them have that.
- And when you focus in on a single species and trace its history,
you can see how effective evolution is, natural selection is. And then you just have to,
like, go across species and you're gonna realize-
- Yeah, but it's also a massive compromise, which is the bit that people always miss.
You know, it's Darwin's line, "It's descent with
modification." Yes, over time, you can end up
with extraordinarily weird things, but mostly what's happening is you're changing
something fairly simple.
- Yeah.
- You're making edits to the existing plan,
which is why you don't have animals with tentacles.
They have legs, which have joints, which have fingers, and they all have one bone,
then two bones, then a bunch of little blocky bones, and then a few more,
and then the little ones that make up the digits for hands and feet, and basically everything has that-
... because you're modifying that pattern. And occasionally you'll get something weird,
like most of the modern lungfish have basically reduced those down to-
well, they had a more simple plan to begin with, but reduced it down to a stump, and then they've got something
like a flaily tentacle. But
yeah, you know, snakes have gotten rid of them, all of the various legless lizards and things like that,
and again, caecilians, and all the rest. But yet, you're- you're
subtly changing certain things in certain ways is mostly what's going on, and then
those build up over time. But also, again, it's that compromise of
there's things that do and don't work. There's things that are interlinked, so you can't
modify A without modifying B. Modifying A will kill
you, therefore B never modifies, because the two are genetically
linked in some way. Or yeah, like the compromise of the
lion's mane. Making it darker makes you sexier, but more likely to kill you.
I think people think evolution is like,
perfecting things in some way. And they're not. They're bodge
jobs, you know? That's why we have a blind spot in our eye, but
things like squid don't.
- But that process, nevertheless, does have inventions in it. You have Tiktaalik. You
have a fish that learns to breathe, that crawls out.
- Yeah, but it already had a swim bladder that it was probably processing a minimal amount of
oxygen through, and the swim bladder evolved for a certainly different function.
- Yeah, but that's one of the powerful things... ...About evolution.
... evolution. It switches the function.
It develops it for one function, but once you once you get there, you're like, "Oh, okay, this
could be used for another function," that- that leads to something that
we, in retrospect, can see as a major invention, which is-
... a fish that's able to crawl on land, and all of a sudden-
- Yep, absolutely.
- ...we have- we have cities and... ...And rockets, and yeah. Tiktaalik specifically,
like, there's something really, like, mind-boggling about a
fish that crawls out of the sea, and you just the image of that.
- Yeah, but again, you've got stuff that's not a million miles away from that.
You have things like frogfish, which are fully marine,
but kinda clamber through seaweed and stuff, and they've
got pseudo-functional limbs. It's again, it's that
...Tiktaalik is not a weirdly derived frogfish, but it's not like
it's a fish that suddenly came on land or a fish that suddenly evolved legs. There was already
that selective pressure that was pushing it into a new opportunity, which gave it an-
and then on and on and on, and that's what keeps going. But it also brings up another thing, going
back to dinosaurs and the behavior stuff, which, again, I think has been a
problem, is the functionality thing,
and how there's always been, I think, this big perception
of single traits having single functions,
which isn't how a huge amount of biology works. For some, yeah. Like, eyes
are used for seeing. They don't really do anything else. But I
think there's a lot of- again, it comes down to a lot of the sexual selection stuff, but things like
horns on Triceratops. That's probably quite good for fighting off predators, but it's
also quite good for fighting other Triceratops.
And then things like elephants dig with their tusks as well as fight other elephants,
as well as fight lions, as well as stripping the bark off trees. So,
you've got to be very careful about how you think of functionality in
two different ways. One way is, what possible things
could that thing do and what possible things could
have been the main selective pressure before. So, you think
about elephant tusks. As I say, they do all these different things. But when an elephant's just
got the tiniest-
little nubs, like the first elephant whose teeth are growing the wrong
way and have pushed out of its jaw, and now it's got a couple of little
spikes, it can't really dig a hole
with them. It's certainly not digging for water. They're
probably not great against a predator, because you'd basically have to get on your knees to try and lean
over and try and stab it a bit. But you can show off to the girls,
and you can immediately find another elephant who's head-to-head the same height as
you, and you've got a massive advantage. So,
evolutionarily, they probably started as some kind of
sexually selected feature. But now,
functionally, they are probably compromised by the fact that
having the best fighting tusks, but also having the tusks that are best at
digging up water to keep you alive during a drought,
is putting selective pressure on that.
And those are, are those selections, sexual selection appears in both
ends. Those are two different things. Digging for water is
critical, but it's probably not what started it. And I think that's where we get
trapped with things
like, say, the paddle tail of Spinosaurus or stuff like, or you know, or T-rex
arms. It's like, well, why are T-rex arms like that? Well, maybe we
need to consider what a slightly longer arm is like or what it was being functioned for in its
ancestors or how it works in other species or what else it might
do, rather than every paper is like, "Did it do this," or,
"Did it do this," or, "Did it do this?" It's like, you know, it could be all of them.
That's-
a very different question to try and answer, but people don't tend to think of it.
And it ends up being very binary. And again, biology is not like that,
because it's a compromise.
- And it may be wiser to then look at the evolutionary origins, how it first
sprung up.
- Yeah, if you, yeah. You know, what does a
miniaturized version of this look like, and what might that function for? Or,
how does it function in ancestral forms? You know, a really good example of that is
giraffe necks, which have been argued about, you know, forever and a day. It
was, "Giraffe necks are to help them feed up high." And then in the late
'90s, early 2000s, there's a couple of papers coming out going, "Actually, maybe it's
sexual selection and competition." And then that drove down into
arguments about, "Well, what does a short neck look like? And the okapi is the nearest
relative. And what do short legs look like, and how do they work?" And plus a whole bunch of
other studies. And ultimately, it came out that we were right the first time. This is all about
feeding. But it's a really interesting way of thinking about it and looking at it.
- Gotta ask you the ridiculous question. We do have dinosaurs here on Earth today.
They're birds.
- Yep. 10 and a half, 11,000 species of dinosaur.
- Are birds dinosaurs?
- Yes.
- Yeah, there's not...
- It's, it's-
- Wild?
- It's just a yes. Yeah.
- How many people know this, by the way?
- So there's, there's an interesting one. I did a radio show, oh, it's probably
seven or eight years ago now, with a couple of prese- you know, drive time
afternoon, nothing serious, nothing science, or anything like that. I mentioned something like this.
And one presenter was, "Oh my God, what do you mean birds are dinosaurs?"
And the other one is, "What do you mean you don't know birds are dinosaurs?"
So it's hitting that tipping point of common knowledge, I think, where...
Does everyone know? No. But I think an awful lot of people know and are now used to it.
as an idea.
- So what's the evolutionary connection between birds and dinosaurs?
- They literally are, in the same way that we are apes and mammals. Birds are
dinosaurs. The direct, if you trace back the
evolution of all the birds, so hummingbirds and
albatross and ostrich and kiwi and parrots and pelicans and penguins
and whatever else, and take them down to their ancestral point, and then
go back quite a few more million years, the nearest
relatives to them is a dinosaur. It is actually something very close to
Velociraptor or at least a small version of Velociraptor.
So birds have literally descended from dinosaurs, therefore
they are dinosaurs. We have literally descended from other apes, we are apes.
It is that form of evolutionary connection.
- Throughout that whole process, did they have feathers, or did feathers come and go?
- Feathers are in tyrannosaurs. Feathers go back at least...
So, ironically, because the fossil record is very incomplete, most of the things
that are closest to birds we know from the early and late Cretaceous,
so the last kind of 50 million years of dinosaur evolution,
up to the extinction. And actually, birds almost certainly go back another
50 million years. So birds did not appear as a result of the dinosaurs going
So birds did not appear as a result of the dinosaurs going
extinct. Birds lived alongside the dinosaurs for 100 million years. This was, the
birds were not new on the scene. It's not like, "Oh, the dinosaurs died, and from
the ashes rose the birds." No, they've been knocking around forever.
No, they've been knocking around forever.
- They just survived 'cause they're small.
- In a very large part, yeah. That's almost certainly what really
helped them. Birds took a kicking in the KT extinction.
So did mammals. Loads of bird lineages went extinct, and only a handful got over the
line, but they did. We have feathers, as I said, we've got Middle Jurassic
tyrannosaurs that are 165 million years.
old, so 100 million years before the extinction, that have
feathers. Simple feathers, they'd be like those you get on most baby chicks,
so they're not with the big kind of
classic pick up a feather in, you know, in the street or on a field, the big vein
up the middle and then the kind of paired flat pieces. This
would be much more like a hair. But we have them.
We've got something which is very close to a bird, but might not quite be a
bird, with modern feathers. In
the Middle Jurassic, we've got definitive stuff like Archaeopteryx in the Late
Jurassic, and then into the early Cretaceous we have a series of fossil beds in
China which are just heaving with them. So yeah, and
tyrannosaurs have feathers. Velociraptor and the
Dromaeosaurs had feathers. Troodontids had feathers. Ornithomimosaurs, we've
mentioned, they had feathers, and so did a whole bunch of other groups as well.
There's about eight or nine major
groups, kind of the size of something like, yeah, literally like
carnivores or deer. You know, some
massive groups. About eight or nine of them were fully feathered, as far
as we can tell. So feathers massively predate bird
origins, but it was a major part of their evolution.
- Do I understand why feathers evolved with the function,
the, the sexual selection, the signaling?
- Yeah, it's probably a fundamental twofold one, which is feathers
insulate you. They keep you warm. And most dinosaurs were,
it's an archaic term, but it's what most people know, warm-blooded. So they were
much more like us and birds. They had a stable high body temperature regardless
of the environmental conditions. So if you're burning a lot of calories to stay warm,
you want to kind of keep that heat, and feathers really help you do that.
And then the other thing is, yeah, the obvious thing is sexual selection
and communication. Feathers do stuff that scales can't. You can
shed them in winter and change color and come back as another one. That's
quite a handy trick. You can change them between juveniles and adults. So baby
birds have one type of feather, adults have a different one. We know of dinosaurs
that do that, where we've got adults and juveniles with different feather types
preserved in the fossils. Yeah, you can produce all kinds of weird colors
and displays. You can erect feathers. You can hold them up and fan them out
like a peacock or a pheasant. Whereas scales, you can't really do that, or
you need a huge amount of bone like Protoceratops. So
there's two good reasons that they would probably evolve, and
exactly pulling them apart or which is more important. And again-
they're probably bifunctional. As soon as you start making feathers and making
them more colorful, well, you're staying warmer. So that's an advantage. Or as soon
as you start making feathers to make them warmer, it probably won't be long until
someone evolves them to be a bit brighter red. And then we're back to, "Oh my God, red."
Right? But that's what's happening.
And then they're probably gonna push each other potentially.
- I mean, it is true that the birds went real crazy with the
feather and the colors and the prettiness and all that.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. They absolutely do.
- I mean, maybe there's something about feathers that allows for that efficient
sort of diversification of fashion.
- I think, yeah, I think it gives them opportunities that...
...scales and solid structures simply don't.
- Yeah, it could be a material for it.
- The sole ability, I mean, I say peacocks and pheasants, they are at a massive
disadvantage, and males have got these extra plumes because they're so big and heavy.
Peacocks can barely fly. But the fact is, you can still kind of fold them up into a
fairly neat package and kind of hide if you really wanted to. Whereas if you're
something like a Triceratops, that billboard stuck on the top of your
head is not only enormous but also
bone. It's massive, it's heavy, and you've got to...
- No hiding.
- ...hide it around the whole year. Whereas peacocks at least can go, "Well, all the
girls have settled down on their nests now, I'm just going to get rid of all this extra
weight and dump it."
- Just looking at the entire history of Earth, what has studying
hundreds of millions of years of evolution, studying
this epic age of the dinosaurs, what has that done for your
appreciation of what makes Earth beautiful? Do you ever just
like sit back and think, "Holy shit, this is incredible, this whole thing"?
- Yeah, yeah, I do. But I guess maybe not much more so than I would anyway.
As in, I already... because again, I don't really think of
myself as a paleontologist in a lot of ways. Um,
it's not that I don't love my work, but it's,
I'm a biologist, and this is what I'm looking at. But I'm fascinated and
amazed by lungfish and flying frogs and
caterpillars and onychophorans and butterflies and a million and one
other hagfish and things that I think are cool and interesting and fascinating, and I could
happily read about them or watch them in a zoo or a documentary or
whatever it may be, almost every bit as much
as I would with dinosaurs. I probably appreciate the dinosaurs and pterosaurs
in a very different way because I have such a greater intimate knowledge of the
science, in a way that I try and read the lion literature because I'm really
interested in predation dynamics, but I can't keep up with it whilst doing all the other
stuff as well.
- Predation dynamics. Awesome.
- Well, right, so like the difference of what prey are they taking? Why? At what
percentage? What influences? How are they competing with leopards and...
- Wait, there's a body of literature on this?
- Yeah, people are studying lions, what they hunt, what they eat, and where they do it, and
there's a whole bunch of stuff on particularly the
African carnivores, because there are so many of them and they're so big, and their
populations aren't terrible compared to like
South America or North America or a lot of Asia, for example. Um,
But yeah, going back to your question, I can appreciate all of it. It's all
cool. Some of it is definitely more awesome than others. I work on some
of the giant pterosaurs, the ones with 10-meter wingspans.
Yeah, and it's, it's hard. My partner's family is from Uganda.
We were in Uganda last year. I was watching marabou storks
circle overhead and you're like, "Wow, these things are huge and amazing."
And then I'm like, "Their wingspan is about a fifth of the stuff I work on."
Their wingspan is about a fifth of the stuff I work on."
Actually, these are quite piddly in the grand scheme, you know,
this thing being like an airliner going overhead. And when you think about it
in that context, yeah, I mean,
because that's it with the... you know, I know people tend to be obsessed with size.
You kind of get it. Like blue whales are...
fundamentally cooler than smaller humpback whales, even if humpback whales are cool.
It's hard not to be impressed by Patagotitan or
Tyrannosaurus or Triceratops or Quetzalcoatlus or any of these
ultimate giants. There's a reason we love great white sharks, there's a reason we love
giant squid. There's a reason we love lions and grizzly bears and stuff.
But the dinosaurs do kind of do it better than anyone else
or, you know, marine reptiles and the flying reptiles, because it's just so insane.
- Yeah, both size and diversity.
- Yeah, and longevity as well. I mean, you look
at, you know, elephants have come and gone, and the whales,
okay, the whales have reached superlative sizes, but they're relatively new on the
scene. Could easily have gone extinct in the last
century. But yeah, you know, there's truly
titanic dinosaurs for at least 100 million years.
- It's a long time. It's hard sometimes, and as you said, it's very hard to
load in just how long that is. They really dominated Earth for a very long time.
- Yeah, and almost absolutely everywhere. There's a handful of places that we've
found where it appears that dinosaurs didn't really get in, and something else
kind of took over, you know, like Australia with the marsupials versus the
other eutherians. But yeah, fundamentally, it was a dinosaur planet for...
After the Triassic, less so the end of the Triassic when they're first getting going.
But yeah, Jurassic and Cretaceous, yeah, it's 140-ish million years
of, yeah, just absolute dominance.
- I think it's hilarious and just perfect that there's a giant
dinosaur head next to you, and you didn't mention it once during this conversation.
- Because I thought we'd get it. Well, I mean, giant is an absolute diddy one.
Yeah, so this is Protoceratops andrewsi. I've done loads
of work on Protoceratops. It's from Mongolia. This is a latest
so I've got a big head, and the big head's kind of like this, but I really
but I really couldn't fit it in the bag.
- So this is a to-scale juvenile.
- This is a cast. This is not original, but someone
has molded and copied it. So it's not even, it's not carved.
It's a cast and a mold taken. So yeah,
this is 100% accurate to the original specimen, or at least extraordinarily accurate to
the original specimen.
- So it's a young guy.
- Yeah. But yeah, at full size, it's going to be like
pig or sheep size, so big but not massive.
But I've got it partly because it's affordable, cause I can't afford to buy the
big skeletons and skulls. But I've done a huge amount of work on it, and in part
it goes back to those earlier conversations about
populations. If you really want to understand animals, you need
an understanding of what a real population and a
growth of what these animals looks like. And
Protoceratops is, I would argue, probably the only dinosaur
where we can really do that, or at least as close as possible as
you could get to any modern animal as an analog. We've
got well over 100 good skeletons, though
probably only about 70 or 80 in really accessible
museums, but that's still a hell of a lot. We have everything from, "Here's a tiny baby
one." This is a really cheap and nasty 3D print I had
made but that's a hatchling sized one, or not much bigger than a
hatchling sized one,
all the way up to the big adults. We've now got embryos as well,
which we didn't have until about 10 years ago. So
we've got embryonic animals all the way up to big adults. They're all
pretty much from one place in
Mongolia. And they are, as far as we can tell, from a relatively
narrow window in time, only about 100,000 years, which in the grand scheme of things is very
close.
So you've got one population from one place from one time, with 100 animals from
embryos up to big adults.
- That's okay.
- So now if you want to look at, as I do, something like sexual
selection, and when does growth of the signal kick in and at what size,
and what evidence for dimorphism, well, suddenly you've got a population. You've got
something you can work with. And that's why
Protoceratops is so important, and I think way more important
than even a lot of my fellow paleontologists realize, and I genuinely think
we should be pouring a lot more research into them, because they can tell us
stuff that pretty much no other dinosaur can.
- Because you have the population data, so you can...
...you can ask them a lot more questions.
- And we can treat it as a population. So going way, way back to a
conversation about telling males and females apart, and I said the big
problem is population data, or at least the number of
specimens that you have when mostly you've only got one, two, or three.
I did a big study on this a few years ago on gharials, the really long-snouted
crocodilians from Nepal, India, and Pakistan with a giant
bulge on the end of the nose. And even though the males are all bigger than the
females, and the males all have this weird nose growth
that's mostly soft tissue, but they have a weird depression in the jaw, in the
end of the snout where the nostrils sit. We got a sample size
of something like about 110 animals. So these are very,
very rare animals, so we had to ransack every museum worldwide.
I was sending my students sending emails to huge numbers of
people, "Have you got one sitting in your collection lost? Can you get
it for us? Can you take these photos or these measurements? We can measure it." We put the dataset
together, and then we found that actually, apart from
the very biggest males, it's really hard to tell males and
females apart, and this actually really closely matched
some modeling data that I'd done with a colleague, Jordan Malin in Ottawa,
looking at this for alligators and trying to compare it
to dinosaurs. Because we talked about mutual sexual selection before,
neutral sexual selection in particular, you tend to get things that are extremely similar.
Males and females are very hard to tell apart. But there's
also a gradient, you know, all the way up to things like
peacocks, all the way down to you can't tell them apart, like parrots.
And for some features, when they take time to get growing,
or because dinosaurs grow over a very long window and are
sexually mature over a very long window, you run into the problem that
a big female will look like a small male.
And we can't sex them, and lo and behold, this is what you get with the gharials.
The really big males are obvious because they're so much bigger and they've got this big depression in
the snout, but medium-sized and big females look like medium
sized, or smaller males and very small males. And so, yeah,
that's basically what we have with dinosaurs. Even with Protoceratops, where
we've got a dataset of like a hundred,
papers have come out saying there's very mild sexual dimorphism or there isn't
sexual dimorphism. Sexual dimorphism could
be very strong in Protoceratops, but we can't find it because
we can't tell the males from the females because we haven't ID'd
enough through something like medullary bone.
And so you're in this horrible situation where, because going back to the T-Rex thing, is like
well, maybe it's mutual sexual selection and therefore they're cooperating, and
that would be cool. But also, maybe males are much bigger
but we can't tell because our dataset's too small.
- Oh, that's frustrating.
- In which case, they're not under mutual sexual selection, and we've got it all wrong.
Argh! It- It's maddening because it's so
if these were living animals, you'd just watch them or you'd just genotype them
or you'd sex them and you'd just know, and we just
don't. But on the other hand, we do have the mechanism to do it. There
are a handful of places where you get a bunch of Protoceratops together, where it's a mass
mortality site. Well, let's go and drill every bone, because if that's the
breeding season, we might find seven or eight females, and then the others are
pretty much by default males if we know it's the middle of the breeding season because all the
middle of the breeding season because all the others have medullary bone.
Now, let's analyze those two data sets.
And then maybe we'll see a difference and maybe we won't.
- I love how that frustration is a catalyst for figuring it out.
You're searching for a place, a piece of evidence that just shows you clearly.
- There are ways in.
- Yeah, there's ways in.
- This is the thing.
- There's always ways in.
- Yeah, there are ways in. And maybe we got to get lucky
because maybe it's not the breeding season.
Or maybe that was just a group of all males, and therefore
we're not going to get the signal we're looking for.
But there's enough of them, and they're common enough, and yet, still digging in
Mongolia, we keep finding new species. We keep finding new, cooler stuff.
But I'm like, "Can we dig up some more Protoceratops?"
Because actually, however cool these new things are,
genuinely, if you want to know what dinosaurs are and how they worked,
another hundred Protoceratops will actually probably tell us a lot more
than 50 new species, however cool 50 new species might be.
- Paleontology is an incredible discipline. It really is Sherlock Holmes
territory. This was an incredible
conversation. I'm really grateful for all the work you write,
that you put out there.
- Thank you.
- The podcast is incredible. I just, thank you for being you
and thank you for talking today.
- Well, thank you very much for having me. I hope I haven't worn out my
welcome with dinosaur...
- No.
- stories.
- Oh, we could talk for many more hours. Thank you, brother. Thank you, Dave.
- Thank you.
- Thank you for listening to this conversation with Dave Hone.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description and consider
subscribing to this channel. And now, let me leave with some
words from Carl Sagan, "Extinction is the rule. Survival is the exception."
Thank you for listening. I hope to see you next time.