- No one anywhere who's serious believes
that cookie banners does anything good for anyone,
yet we've been unable to get rid of it.
This is the thing that really gets me
about cookie banners too.
It's not just the EU.
It's the entire world.
You can't hide from cookie banners anywhere on this planet.
If you go to goddam Mars on one of Elon's rockets
and you try to access a webpage,
you'll still see a cookie banner.
No one in the universe is safe from this nonsense.
It sometimes feels like we're barely better off.
Like webpages aren't that different
from what they were in the late '90s, early 2000s.
They're still just forms.
They still just right to databases.
A lot of people, I think, are very uncomfortable
with the fact that they are essentially CRUD monkeys.
They just make systems
that create read, update or delete row in a database,
and they have to compensate
for that existential dread by overcomplicating things.
That's a huge part of the satisfaction
of driving a race car
is driving in at the edge of adhesion, as we call it.
Where you're essentially
just a tiny movement away from spinning out.
Doesn't take much,
then the car starts rotating.
Once it starts rotating,
you lose grip and you're going for the wall.
That balance of danger and skill
is what's so intoxicating.
- The following is a conversation
with David Heinemeier Hansson, also known as DHH.
He is a legend in the programming and tech world,
brilliant and insightful, sometimes controversial,
and always fun to talk to.
He's the creator of Ruby on Rails,
which is an influential web development framework
behind many websites used by millions of people,
including Shopify, GitHub, and Airbnb.
He is the co-owner and CTO
of 37signals that created Basecamp, HEY and ONCE.
He is a "New York Times" bestselling author,
together with his co-author,
Jason Fried of four books,
"Rework," "Remote," "Getting Real,"
and "It Doesn't Have to Be Crazy at Work."
And on top of that, he's also a race car driver,
including being a class winner
at the legendary 24-hour Le Mans Race.
This is a Lex Fridman Podcast.
To support it,
please check out our sponsors in the description
and consider subscribing to this channel.
And now, dear friends, here's DHH.
For someone who became a legendary programmer,
you officially got into programming late in life,
and I guess that's because you tried
to learn how to program a few times and you failed.
So can you tell me the the full story, the saga
of your failures to learn programming?
Was Commodore 64 involved?
- Commodore 64 was the inspiration.
I really wanted a Commodore 64.
That was the first computer I ever sat down in front.
And the way I sat down in front of it
was I was five years old
and there was this one kid on my street
who had a Commodore 64.
No one else had a computer,
so we were all the kids just getting over there
and we were all playing "Yie Ar Kung-Fu."
I dunno if you've ever seen that game.
It was one of the original fighting games.
It's really a great game.
And I was playing that for the first time
at five years old.
And we were like seven kids
sitting up in this one kid's bedroom,
all taking our turn to play the game.
And I just found that unbelievably interesting.
And I begged and I begged and I begged my dad,
could I get a computer?
And he finally comes home.
He's like, "I got your computer."
I was like, yes, my own Commodore 64.
And he pulls out this black green and blue keyboard.
That's an Amstrad 464.
I was like, dad, what's this?
- The disappointment.
- This is not a Commodore 64.
But it was a computer.
So I got my first computer at essentially six years old
that Amstrad 464.
And of course, the first thing I wanted to do,
I wanted to play video games.
And I think the computer, which he by the way,
had traded for TV and a stereo recorder
or something like that.
Came with like two games.
One was this "Frogger" game
where you had to escape from underground.
It was actually kind of dark.
Like this frog, you're trying
to get it out from underground.
And I was pretty bad at it.
And I only had those two games.
And then I wanted more games.
And one way to get more games
when you're a kid who don't have a lot of money,
I can't just buy a bunch of games,
is to type them in yourself.
Back in '84, '85,
magazines would literally print source code
at the back of their magazines
and you could just sit and type it in. So I tried to do that
and it would take like two hours
to print this game into the Amstrad.
And of course I'd make some spelling mistake along the way
and something wouldn't work,
and the whole thing.
I wasn't that good of English.
I was born in Denmark.
So I was really trying to get into it
because I wanted all these games.
I didn't have the money to buy 'em.
And I tried quite hard for quite a while to get into it,
but it just never clicked.
And then I discovered the magic of piracy.
And after that I kind of basically just took some time off
from learning to program
because, well, now suddenly
I had access to all sorts of games.
So that was the first attempt,
like around six, seven years old.
And what's funny is I remember these fragments.
I remember not understanding the purpose of a variable.
If there's a thing and you sign something,
why would you assign another thing to it?
So for some reason, I understand it constants.
A constants made sense to me, but variables didn't.
Then maybe I'm 11 to 12,
I've gotten into the Amiga at this point.
The Amiga, by the way,
still perhaps my favorite computer of all time.
I mean, this is one of those things
where you're like, people get older and they're like,
"Oh, the music from the '80s amazing."
To me, even as someone who loves computers,
who loved new computers,
the Amiga was this magical machine
that was made by the same company
that produced the Commodore 64.
And I got the Amiga 500, I think in '87.
- Look at this sexy thing
that is a sexy machine right there.
- This is from an age by the way,
where computing wasn't global in the same sense.
The different territories
had different computers that were popular.
The Amiga was really popular in Europe,
but it wasn't very popular at all in the US
as far as I understand it. It wasn't popular in Japan.
There were just different machines.
The Apple II was a big thing in the US.
I'd never even heard of Apple
in the '80s in Copenhagen.
But the Amiga 500 was the machine
that brought me to want to try it again.
And you know what's funny?
The reason I wanted to try it again
was I remembered the first time to learn.
And then there was this programming language
that was literally called EasyAMOS,
like the easy version of AMOS.
I'm like, if it's EasyAMOS, how hard can it be?
I gotta be able to figure this out.
And this time I tried harder.
I got into conditionals,
I got into loops, I got into all these things
and I still, I couldn't do it.
And on the second attempt,
I really got to the point of like,
maybe I'm not smart enough,
maybe programming is just not for me,
maybe it's too much math.
Like I like math in this sort of superficial way.
I don't like it in the deep way.
That's some on my perhaps slightly nerdier friends did
who I had tremendous respect for.
Like I'm not that person.
I'm not the math geek who's gonna figure it all out.
So after that attempt with EasyAMOS
and failing to even get, I don't even think
I completed one even very basic game.
I thought the program's just not for me.
I'm gonna have to do something else.
I still love computers.
I still love video games.
I actually at that time had already begun making friends
with people who knew how to program,
who weren't even programming EasyAMOS.
They were programming freaking assembler.
And I would sit down and just go, how do you,
the moves and the memories and the copies,
how do you even do this?
I don't even understand how you go from this
to Amiga demos, for example.
That was the big thing with the Amiga.
It had this wonderful demo scene in Europe.
It's this really interesting period of time
in Amiga's history
where you had all these programmers
spread out mostly all over Europe
who would compete on graphic competitions,
where you could probably bring
one of these different... - On that thing?
- On this thing,
they would make these little almost like music videos,
combining some midi music, combining some cool graphics.
And they would do all of it in like 4K, four kilobytes.
That is not 4Ks of revolution,
four kilobytes of memory.
And I just thought that was such a cool scene.
This was obviously pre-internet.
It was even pre BBS, bulletin board systems
to some extent.
It was you swap your demo software with someone else
by sending them a disk in the mail, like the 3.5s.
And I was enamored with that whole scene.
I was enamored with what they were able to create
and I just wanted to be a part of it
even though I kind of didn't have any skills to contribute.
And that's how I got into running BBSs.
I didn't learn programming then
and I wouldn't learn programming until much later,
until I was almost 20 years old.
The bulletin board systems existed in this funny space
where they were partly a service to the demo scenes
allowing all these demo groups
to distribute their amazing demos.
And then it was also a place
to trade piracy software, pirated software.
And I ended up starting one of those
when I was 14 years old
in my tiny little bedroom in Copenhagen.
I had my, at that point, Amiga 4000.
I had three telephone lines coming in into my tiny room.
- [Lex] Nice.
- Which is funny because again, I'm 14 years old.
By the time I was in Sterling, my third line,
you had to get someone from the telephone company
to come do it.
I get this guy and he's just looking around like,
"What is this?
Why the hell is a 14-year-old
having three phone lines into their tiny little bedroom?
What's going on here?
Why are all these modems blinking red and black
and making funny sounds?"
- Did your parents know?
- They did and they didn't.
They knew I had the phone lines.
They knew I had the computer.
I don't think they really understood
that I was trading pirated software
that was both illegal, and whatever else was going on.
- Oh, we should probably say that in Europe,
maybe you can comment on this
in, especially in Eastern Europe, but Europe in general,
piracy I think was more acceptable
than it was in the United States.
I don't know there maybe it's just my upbringing.
- Even that conversation wasn't present.
I never spoke to anyone growing up in Denmark.
- The piracy is wrong. - Had any moral qualms
whatsoever about piracy.
It was just completely accepted that you're a kid,
you won a lot of games.
You don't have a lot of money, what do you do?
You trade. - Yeah.
- Some people would occasionally buy a game.
I mean, I once bought a second Master System,
and I bought one game.
Because that was what I could afford.
I got "After Burner II."
I dunno if you've ever played that game.
It's pretty bad implementation
on the second Master System,
but it was like 600 crowners.
And I was making money at that time
doing newspaper delivery.
I had to do that for a month to afford one game.
I like video games way too much
to wait a month just to get one game.
So piracy was just the way you did it.
And that was how I got into running
this bulletin board system,
being part of the demo scene,
being part of the piracy scene to some extent.
And then also at some point realizing,
oh, you can actually also make money on this
and this can fund buying more phone lines
and buying more modems and buying more Amigas.
Oh yeah, that was one of the demo parties.
These were amazing things.
- What am I looking at? - Isn't that amazing?
- Look at all those CRT monitors.
- All these CRT monitors.
Again, when I was 14,
I don't understand fully why my parents allowed this.
But I traveled from Copenhagen,
the capital of Denmark to Aarhus this tiny little town
in Jutland on the train with a bunch of dudes
who were like late teens and their 20s.
I'm 14 years old.
I'm lugging my 14-inch CRT monitor
with my computer in the back to go to the party.
That was what it was called.
That was the biggest demo scene party at that time.
And it was exactly as you see in that picture,
thousands of people just lining up with their computers,
programming demos all day long,
and trading these things back and forth.
- That's kind of awesome.
Not gonna lie.
It's a little ridiculous.
- It's totally awesome.
And I miss it in ways
where the internet has connected people in some ways,
but the connection you get from sitting
right next to someone else
who has their own CRT monitor
who's lugged at halfway around the country to get there
is truly special.
Because it was also just this burst of creativity.
You're constantly running around.
You're constantly surrounded by people
who are really good at what they could do.
They're really good at programming computers.
It's infectious.
It was part of that pang I felt then going like,
oh man, why can't I figure this out?
I mean, why can't I even figure out EasyAMOS?
It's kind of frustrating.
- But on your third attempt,
you a little more successful?
- So third attempt is when I start getting it,
this is when I start helping out,
let's say build things for the internet.
So around '95, I think it is, or '96,
I discovered the internet.
Actually, in ninth grade.
That was my first experience.
I went to some university in Denmark.
And in ninth grade, we had this excursion
and they sat us down in front of a computer
and the computer had Netscape Navigator, the first version,
or maybe it was even the precursor to that.
And they had a text editor.
And us kids just got like,
"Hey, built something on the internet."
And it was just HTML and the first thing you do is like,
oh, I can make the text blink
by just putting in this tag and saving it.
That moment, that was actually when I reawaken the urge
to wanna learn the program
because I got a positive experience.
All the other experiences I had with programming
was I'd spend hours typing something in,
I'd click Run and it wouldn't work.
And I'd get an error message
that made no sense to me as a kid,
either at six or seven or at 12.
And here I am sitting in front of a computer
connected to the internet and I'm making text blink.
I'm making it larger.
I'm turning it into an h1 or an h2.
And these guys out here,
"We just did it for like an hour and a half."
And suddenly I go, oh, I can make things for the internet
that someone in Germany can be able to access and see,
and I don't have to ask anyone for permission.
This is super cool.
I gotta do more of this.
So I got into to the internet.
I got into working with HTML
and I still had all these friends from these demo parties.
And I started working with them
on creating gaming websites.
I'd rather buy the video games, I'd review him.
This was another good way of getting new video games
was to walk down to some store
and say like, hey, I'm a journalist.
I'm like this 15-year-old kid.
And they're looking at you, "You're a journalist?"
Yeah, can I borrow some games?
Because this was when games moved on
to the PlayStation and these other things.
You couldn't just as easily pirate, at least not at first.
So I went down there, did all that,
and that started the journey of the internet for me.
It started working on these gaming websites,
working with programmers,
figuring out that I could do something,
I could work on the HTML part. It's not really programming,
but it kind of smells like it.
You're talking to a computer.
You're making it put text on the screen
and you're communicating
with someone halfway around the world.
So that became my pathway back into programming.
And then slowly I picked up more and more of it.
First website I did with someone,
one of these programs from the demo scene
that was dynamic was ASP.NET.
I wasn't even actually called .NET.
That was what we started on.
And then we moved on to PHP,
and PHP was when I finally got it.
When it finally clicked.
When conditionals and loops and variables
and all of that stuff started to make sense enough to me
that I thought I can do this.
- So would it be fair to say
that we wouldn't have DHH without PHP,
and therefore you owe all of your success to PHP?
- 100% that's true.
And it's even better than that
because as PHP to me didn't just give a start
in terms of making my own web applications,
it actually gave me a bar.
In many ways, I think the pinnacle of developer,
web developer ergonomics is late '90s PHP,
you write this script,
you FTP it to a server and instantly it's deployed.
Instantly it's available.
You change anything in that file and you reload.
Boom, it's right there.
There's no web servers, there's no setup.
There's just an Apache that runs mod PHP.
And it was essentially the easiest way
to get a dynamic webpage up and going.
And this is one of the things I've been chasing that high
for basically the rest of my career.
That it was so easy to make things for the internet
in the mid to late '90s.
How did we lose the sensibilities
that allowed us to not just work this way
but get new people into the industry
to give them that was success experiences that I had.
Adding a freaking blink tag to an HTML page,
FTPing a PHP page to an Apache web server
without knowing really anything about anything,
without knowing anything about frameworks,
without knowing anything about setup.
All of that stuff have really taken us to a place
where it sometimes feels like we're barely better off.
Like webpages aren't that different
from what they were in the late '90s, early 2000s.
They're still just forms.
They still just write to databases.
A lot of people, I think are very uncomfortable
with the fact that they are essentially CRUD monkeys.
They just make systems
that create read, update or delete row in a database,
and they have to compensate
for that existential dread by overcomplicating things.
Now that's a bit of a character.
There's more to it.
And there's things you can learn
from more sophisticated ways of thinking about this.
But there's still an ideal here,
which is why I was so happy you had Pieter Levels on,
because he still basically works like this.
And I look at that and go like,
man, that's amazing.
- Yeah, you're chasing that high.
He's been high all along
using PHP, jQuery and SQLite.
- I think it's amazing because he's proving
that this isn't just a nostalgic dream.
He's actually doing it.
He's running all these businesses.
Now some of that is, as he would admit up first upfront,
is that he's just one guy.
And you could do different things when you just one guy.
When you're working in a team,
when I started working on the team,
when I started working with Jason Fried on Basecamp,
we at first didn't use version control together.
I used version control for myself.
And then I thought, do you know what?
Designers, ah, they probably not smart enough
to figure out CBS.
And therefore I just like, no, no, no, you just FTP it up.
You just FTP it.
I knew they knew how to do FTP.
And then after the third time
I had overridden their changes.
I was like, goddammit.
I gotta teach Jason CBS to not do that again.
But I think there's still way more truth
to the fact that we can work the way we did in the '90s,
work the way Pieter works today, even in the team context.
And that we've been far too willing
to hand over far too much of our developer ergonomics
to the merchants of complexity.
- And you've been chasing that with Rails 8.
So how do you bring all the cool features
of a modern framework and make it no build,
make it as easy to create something
and to ship it as it was in the '90s with just PHP?
It's very difficult for me
to beat the Pieter Levels approach.
It's so easy to just ship some PHP.
- And it should be.
Why should it be harder than that?
Our computers today are almost infinitely faster
than what they were in the '90s.
So shouldn't we be able to work in even easier ways?
We should be looking back on the '90s ago,
like, oh, that was way too complicated.
Now we have more sophisticated technology
that's way faster and it allows us to work
in these easier to use ways.
But that's not true.
But now you can see the line I draw
in my work with Ruby on Rails,
and especially with Rails 8.
No build to me is reaching back to that '90s feeling
and going, now we can do
some of those things without giving up
on all the progress.
Because I do think you can get too nostalgic.
I do think you can start just fantasizing
that everything was better in the '90s.
It wasn't.
I mean, I was there.
There was a lot of things that sucked.
And if we can somehow find a way to combine
the advantages and advances we've had over the past 20 years
with that ease of developer ergonomics, we can win.
No build is a rejection of the part of web development
I've hated the most in the past 10, 15 years,
which is the JavaScript scene.
And I don't say that as someone who hate JavaScript.
I mean, I often joke that JavaScript.
It's my second favorite program language.
It's a very distant second.
Ruby is by far and away number one,
but I actually like JavaScript.
I don't think it's a bad language.
It gets a lot of flack.
People add a string of two plus a one
and it gives something nonsense.
And I just go like, yeah,
but why would you do that?
Just don't do that.
The language is actually quite lovely,
especially the modern version.
ES6 that really introduced a proper class syntax to it.
So I could work with JavaScript in many of the same ways
that I love working with Ruby made things so much better.
But in the early 2010s until quite recently,
all of that advancement happened in pre-processing,
happened in built pipelines.
The browsers couldn't speak a dialect of JavaScript
that was pleasant to work with.
So everyone started to pre-filing their JavaScript
to be able to use more modern ways of programming
with a browser that was seen as stuck
with an ancient version of JavaScript
that no one actually wanted to work with.
And that made sense to me,
but it was also deeply unpleasant.
And I remember thinking during that time,
the dark ages, as I refer to them with JavaScript,
that this cannot be the final destination.
There's no way that we have managed
to turn the internet into such an unpleasant place to work.
Where I would start working on a project in JavaScript
using webpack and all of these dependencies.
And I would put it down for literally five minutes
and the thing wouldn't compile anymore.
The amount of churn that the JavaScript community,
especially with its frameworks
and its tooling went through
in the decade from 2010 to 2020 was absurd.
And you had to be trapped inside of that asylum
to not realize what an utterly perverse situation
we had landed ourselves in.
Why does everything break all the time?
I mean, the joke
wouldn't be just that the software would break,
that would annoy me personally.
But then I'd go on Hacker News
and I'd see some thread
on the latest JavaScript release of some framework.
And the thread would be like, someone would ask,
"Well, aren't we using the thing
we just used three months ago?"
And people would be like, "That thing is so outdated.
That's so three months ago.
You gotta get with the new program.
We're completely rewriting everything
for the oomph-teen time."
And anything you've learned in the framework
you've been spending the last amount of time on,
it's all useless.
You gotta throw everything out and you gotta start over.
Why aren't you doing it, stupid idiot?
- Is that a kind of mass hysteria
that took over the developer community you think?
Like where you have to keep creating new frameworks
and new frameworks.
And are we past that dark age?
- I think we're getting out of it,
and we're getting out of it
because browsers have gotten so much better.
There was a stagnation in browser technology.
Some of it was an overhang all the way back from IE5.
So IE5 essentially put the whole internet development
experience into a deep freeze,
because Microsoft won the browser wars in the mid 2000s,
and then they basically disbanded
their browser development team.
'Cause they're like, "All right, job done.
We don't need any more innovation on the internet.
Can we just go back to writing Windows forms
or something now that we control everything?"
And it really wasn't until obviously Firefox
kind of kindled a little bit of something.
Then Chrome got into the scene
and Google got serious about moving to web forward.
That you had a kindling
of maybe the browser could be better.
Maybe the browser wasn't frozen in time in 2005.
Maybe the browser could actually evolve
like at the development platform that it is.
But then what happened was you had a lot of smart people
who poured in to the web
because the web turned out to be the greatest
application development platform of all time.
This was where all the money was being made.
This was where all the billionaires were being minted.
This was where the Facebooks
and whatever of the world came to be.
So you had all of this brain power
applied to the problem of how to work with the web.
And there were some very smart people
with some, I'm sure very good ideas
who did not have programmer happiness
as their motivation number one.
They had other priorities
and those priorities allowed them to discount
and even rationalize the complexity
they were injecting everywhere.
Some of that complexity
came from organizational structure.
When you have a company like Facebook, for example,
that does depend on the web and wanna push it forward,
but have sliced the development role job
into these tiny little niches.
I'm a front-end glob pipeline configurator.
Oh yeah, well, I'm a front-end whatever engineer.
And suddenly the web developer was no longer one person.
It was 15 different roles.
That in itself injected a ton of complexity.
But I also wanna give it the bold case here,
which was that some of that complexity
was necessary to get to where we are today.
That the complexity was a bridge.
It wasn't the destination,
but we had to cross that bridge
to get to where we are today,
where browsers are frankly incredible.
The JavaScript you can write in a text file
and then serve on a web server
for a browser to ingest is amazing.
It's actually a really good experience.
You don't need any pre-processing.
You could just write text files,
send them to a browser,
and you have an incredible development.
- And we should also say that it can kind of be broken,
at least the HTML, but even the JavaScript
could be a little bit broken and it kind of still works
like maybe a half-ass works.
But like, just the amount of mess of smelly code
that a browser has to deal with is insane.
- This is one of the hardest problems in computing today
is to parse the entire internet.
Because thankfully for us as web developers,
but perhaps not so much for the browser developers,
every webpage that has ever been created
minus the brief period with Flash still runs today.
The webpage I did in ninth grade would render
on a modern browser today,
30 years later. - That's crazy.
- That is completely crazy.
When you think about the amount of evolution
we've had with the web, how much better we've made it,
how many more standards browsers have adopted.
It's essentially an Apollo project today
to create a new browser,
which is why it doesn't happen very often,
which is why even companies like Microsoft
had to throw into towel and say, "We can't do it."
Now I actually don't think that's good for the web.
There is the danger of the monoculture
if we just get a single browser engine
that runs everything,
and we are in danger of that.
I love the fact that the Ladybird project, for example,
is trying to make a new browser engine from scratch.
I've supported that project.
I would encourage people to look into that.
It's really a wonderful
- Nice. - thing.
It's staffed by a bunch of people
who worked on other browser projects in the past.
- Truly independent web browser.
- We really need that.
But I can hold that thought in my head.
At the same time, I hold the thought in my head
that Google's Chrome was pivotal
to the web surviving
as the premier web development platform.
If it had not been for Google and their entire business
depending on a thriving open web,
Apple, Microsoft, I think would've been just as fine
to see the web go away to disappear
into being something that's just served
native web applications or native mobile applications
and native desktop applications
that they could completely control.
So I have all sorts of problems with Google,
but it's not Chrome.
Chrome is a complete gift to web developers everywhere,
to the web as a development platform.
And they deserve an enormous amount of credit,
I think for that.
Even if it's entangled with their business model
and half of Chrome is code that spies on you
or informs targeted ads.
And a bunch of things, I'm not a big fan of.
I can divorce that from the fact
that we need champions in the corner of the web
who have trillions of dollars of market cap value
riding on the open web.
- We're gonna take tangents
upon a tangents upon a tangents.
So let's go to Chrome.
I think Chrome positive impact on humanities
is immeasurable for reasons that you just described.
On the technology front,
the features that present the competition they created,
it's spurred on this wonderful flourishing
of web technologies.
But anyway, I have to ask you about
the recent stuff with the DOJ,
trying to split up Chrome and Google.
Do you think this is a good idea?
Do you think this does harm?
- It's a disaster.
And I say that as someone who's been very sympathetic
to the antitrust fight, because I do think
we have antitrust problems in technology.
But the one place where we don't have them, by and large,
is with browsers,
is with the tools we use to access the open web.
First of all, we have Firefox.
Now Firefox is not doing all that great.
And Firefox has been propped up by Google for many years
to deter from exactly what's going on with the DOJ
that they were the only game in town.
Apple has Safari.
I have a bunch of problems with Apple too,
but I love Safari.
I love the fact that we have a premier browser
running on a premier operating system
that people can't turn the web
into just a Chrome experience.
But I also think that the open web
needs this trillion dollar champion,
or at least benefits from it.
Maybe it doesn't need it,
but it certainly benefits from it.
And of all the things
that are wrong with monopoly formation in technology,
Chrome is the last thing.
And this is why I get so frustrated sometimes
about the anti or the monopoly fight
that there are real problems.
And we should be focusing on the premier problems first.
Like the toll booths on our mobile phones.
They're far bigger problems.
It's not the open web.
It's not the tools that we use to access the open web.
If I don't want to use Chrome,
if my customers of my businesses that run on the internet
don't wanna use Chrome, they don't have to.
We're never forced to go through it.
The open internet is still open.
So I think it's a real shame that the DOJ
has chosen to pursue Google in this way.
I do think there are other things you can nail Google for
and their ad monopoly maybe,
or the shenanigans done
in controlling both sides of the ad ledger
that they both controlled the supply and the demand.
There are problems.
Chrome, isn't it?
And you end up making the web much worse.
And this is the thing we always gotta remember
when we think about legislation,
when we think about monopoly fights
is you may not like how things look today.
And you may wanna do something about it,
but you may also make it worse.
The good intentions behind the GDPR in Europe
currently has amounted to what?
Cookie banners that everyone on the internet hates.
That helps no one do anything better,
anything more efficient that saves no privacy
in any way, shape or form
has been a complete boondoggle
that has only enriched lawyers
and accountants and bureaucrats.
- Yeah, you said that the cookie banner is a monument
for why Europe is losing is doing the worst
of all the regions in tech.
- It's a monument to good intentions
leading straight to hell.
And the Europe is actually world class
in good intentions leading straight to hell.
- So hell is the cookie accept button
that you have to accept all cookies.
That's what hell looks like over and over.
You don't actually ever get to the web page.
- Just on a human scale,
try to imagine how many hours every day are wasted
clicking that away.
And how much harm we've done to the web as a platform
that people enjoy because of them.
The internet is ugly in part because of cookie banners.
Cookie banners were supposed to save us from advertisement,
and advertisement can make the web ugly.
There's plenty of examples of that,
but cookie banners made the entire internet ugly
in one felt swoop.
And that's a complete tragedy.
But what's even worse,
and this is why I call it out as a monument
to everything the EU gets wrong,
is that we have known this for a decade.
No one anywhere who's serious believes that cookie banners
does anything good for anyone.
Yet we've been unable to get rid of it.
There's this one piece of legislation
that's now I think 10 or 12 years old.
It's complete failure on every conceivable metric.
Everyone hates it universally,
yet we can't seem to do anything about it.
That's a bankruptcy declaration for any body of bureaucrats
who pretend or pretend
to make things better for not just citizens,
but people around the world.
This is the thing that really gets me
about cookie banners too.
It's not just the EU.
It's the entire world.
You can't hide from cookie banners anywhere on this planet.
If you go to goddamn Mars on one of Elon's rockets
and you try to access a webpage,
you still see a cookie banner.
No one in the universe is safe from this nonsense.
- Probably the interface
on the rocket. - It'll be slower.
You'll have basically 150 second ping time.
So it'll take you 45 seconds
just to get through the cookie banners from Mars.
- All right, let's walk back up the stack
of this recursive tangents we've been taking.
So Chrome, we should say,
at least in my opinion, is not winning unfairly.
It's winning in the fairway by just being better.
- It is, if I was gonna steal man the other side
just for a half second,
people would say, well, maybe yes,
most people do sort of begrudgingly agree
that is a pretty good browser.
But then they'll say the reason it
got dominance was distribution.
And the reason it got distribution
was because Google also controls Android,
and therefore can make Chrome the default
browser on all these phones.
Now I don't buy that.
And the reason I don't buy that
is because on Android, you are actually allowed
to ship a different browser
that has a browser engine that's not the same as Chrome.
Unlike on iOS, where if you wanna ship a browser,
Chrome, for example, ships for iOS,
but it's not Chrome, it's Safari wrapped in a dress.
And every single alternative browser on iOS
have to use the Safari web engine.
That's not competition.
That's not what happened on Android.
Again, I think there are some nuances to it,
but if you zoom out
and you look at all the problems
we have with big tech, Chrome is not it.
Chrome won on merits.
I begrudgingly have switched to Chrome
on that realization alone.
As a web developer, I just prefer it.
I like Firefox in many ways.
I like the ethos of it,
but Chrome is a better browser than Firefox full stop.
- And by the way, we've never mentioned Edge.
Edge is also a good browser
- Because it's also Chrome in a dress.
- But it never gets to love.
I don't think I've ever used Bing,
and I'm sure Bing is really nice.
- Maybe you have, because you know what?
Is Bing in a dress?
- What? - DuckDuckGo.
Which is actually - What?
- the search engine that I use.
DuckDuckGo gets its search results from Bing,
or at least it used to.
If they change that, that would be news to me.
- Well, maybe everything
is just a wrap or a dress.
Everything is wearing a dress underneath.
There's some other. - There's some of that.
- Turtles, all the dress is all the way down.
Okay, what were we talking about?
They, we got there from JavaScript
and from you learning how to program.
So eventually, the big success story
is when you built a bunch of stuff with PHP
and you were like actually shipping things.
And that's when the Ruby story came.
So what your big love affair
with programming began there?
So can you take me there?
What is Ruby?
Tell the story of Ruby.
Explain Ruby to me.
- PHP was what converted me
from just being able to fondle HTML
and turn out some web pages
to actually being able to produce web applications myself.
So I owe a tremendous gratitude to PHP in that regard.
But I never thought of PHP as a calling.
I never thought, I'm a professional programmer
who writes PHP, that's who I am
and that's what I do.
I thought of PHP as a tool
I needed to smack the computer with
until it produced web applications I wanted.
It was very much a means to an end.
I didn't fall in love with PHP.
I'm very grateful that it taught me
the basics of programming.
And I'm very grateful that it set the bar for the economics.
But it really wasn't until Ruby
that I started thinking of myself as a programmer.
And the way that came about
was that the first time I ever got hired
as a professional programmer to write code
was actually by Jason Fried, my business partner still.
All the way back in 2001,
I had been working on these gaming websites in PHP
for essentially 18 months at that point.
No one had been paying me to do code in that regard.
And I connect with Jason Fried
over an email sent from Copenhagen, Denmark
to Chicago, Illinois to a person who didn't know who I was.
I was just offering solicited advice.
Jason had asked a question on the internet
and I had sent him the answer and he was asking in PHP.
And I'd sent him the answer to that question.
And we started talking and then we started working.
Which by the way, is a miracle
of what the internet can allow.
How can a kid in Copenhagen
who's never met this guy in Chicago
connect just over email and start working together?
And by the way, we're still working together now
24 years later.
That's incredible.
But we started working together
and we started working together on some client projects.
Jason would do the design, 37signals would do design,
I would bring the programming PHP.
And after we'd work on I think two or three
client projects together in PHP,
we kept hitting the same problem.
That whenever you work with a client,
you start that project off an email.
Oh yeah, let's work together.
Here's what we're building.
And you start trading more and more emails.
And before a few weeks have passed,
you gotta add someone to the project.
They don't have the emails.
They don't have the context.
You send it, where's the latest file?
Oh, I've uploaded on the FTP.
It's like finalfinal_v06_2.0, right?
That's the one to get.
It's just a mess.
A beautiful mess in some ways,
a mess that still runs the vast majority of projects
to this day.
Email is the lowest common denominator.
That's wonderful.
But we had dropped the ball a couple of times
in serious ways with customers
and we thought we can do better.
We know how to make web applications.
Can't we just make a system
that's better than email for managing projects?
It can't be that hard.
We've been doing blogs.
We've been doing to-do lists.
Let's put some of these together
and just make a system
where everything that anyone involved in the project needs
is on one page.
And it has to be simple enough
that I'm not gonna run a seminar
teaching you how to use the system.
I'm just gonna give you the login code.
You're gonna jump into it.
So that's Basecamp.
And when we started working on Basecamp,
I for the first time in the experience I had with Jason
had the freedom of technology choice.
There was no client telling me,
"Yeah, PHP, that sounds good.
We know PHP.
Can you build it in PHP?"
I had free reigns.
And at that time I'd been reading IEEE magazine
and a couple of other magazines back from the early 2000s
where Dave Thomas and Martin Fowler
had been writing about programming patterns
and how to write better code.
And these two guys, in particular,
were both using Ruby to explain their concepts
because Ruby looked like pseudo code.
Whether you were programming in C or Java or PHP,
all three constituencies could understand Ruby
because it basically just read link English.
So these guys were using Ruby to describe the concepts.
And first of all, I would read these articles
for just the concepts they were explaining.
And I'd be like, what is this programming language?
I mean, I like the concept you're explaining,
but I also wanna see the programming language.
Why haven't I heard of this?
So I started looking into Ruby
and I realized at that time,
Ruby might not be known by anyone,
but it's actually been around for a long time.
Matz, the Japanese creator of Ruby
had started working on Ruby back in '93.
Before the internet was even a thing.
And here I am in 2003, 10 years later,
picking up what seems like this hidden gem
that's just laying in obscurity in plain sight.
But Dave Thomas and Martin Fowler,
I think successfully put me and a handful of other people
on the trail of a programming language
that hadn't been used much in the west, but could be.
So I picked up Ruby and I thought,
this is very different.
First of all, where are all the semicolons?
I'd been programming in PHP, in ASP,
I'd even done some Pascal, I'd looked at some C.
There were semicolons everywhere.
And that was the first thing that struck me
is where are the damn semicolons?
And I started thinking,
actually, why do we have semicolons in programming?
They're to tell the interpreter
that there's a new line of instructions,
but I don't need 'em as a human.
How? Oh,
someone is looking out for the human here,
not for the machine.
So that really got me interested.
And then I thought to myself, do you know what?
I know PHP quite well.
I'm not an amazing programmer.
I haven't been working in programming for all that long,
but maybe I can figure it out.
I'm gonna give myself two weeks.
I'm gonna write a proof of concept
where I talk to a database,
I pull some records, I format them a bit,
and I display 'em on an HTML page.
Can I figure that out in a couple weeks?
It took about one weekend
and I was completely mesmerized.
I was completely mind blown
because Ruby was made for my brain
like a perfect tailored glove by someone I'd never met.
Like, how is this even possible?
- We should say maybe like paint the picture
of the certain qualities that Ruby has,
maybe even compared to PHP.
We should also say that there's a ridiculous thing
that I'm used to that I forget about
that there's dollar signs everywhere.
PHP. - Yes, yes,
there's line noise.
That's what I like to call. - There's line noise.
Line noise, that's such a beautiful phrase.
Yeah, so there's all these things
that look like programs.
And with Ruby,
I mean there's some similarities in Python there.
It just looks kind of like natural language.
You can read it normally.
- Here's a wild loop that does a five iterations.
You can literally type
the number five, dot,
now I'm calling a method under number five.
By the way, that's one of the beautiful aspects of Ruby
that primitives like integers are also objects.
And you can call 5.times, start brackets.
Now you're iterating over
the code in that bracket five times, that's it.
- [Lex] Okay, that's nice.
- That's not just nice, that's exceptional.
There's literally no other programming language
that I know of that has managed to boil away the line noise
that almost every other programming language would inject
into a five time iteration
over a block of code to that extent.
- Wow, that's a really nice,
well, thank you for giving that example.
That's a beautiful example.
Wow, I don't think I know
what programming language that does that.
That's really nice.
- Ruby is full of that.
So let me dive into a couple of examples.
Because I really think it helps paint the picture.
And let me preface this by saying I actually,
I like the ethos of Python.
I think the Ruby and the Python community
share a lot of similarities.
They're both dynamic interpreted languages.
They're both focused on immediacy and productivity
and ease of use in a bunch of ways.
But then they're also very different in many other ways.
And one of the one ways
they're very different is aesthetically.
Python, to me, I hope I don't offend people too much.
I've said this before, it's ugly.
And it's ugly in its space,
because it's full of superfluous instructions
that are necessary for legacy reasons
of when Guido made Python back in '87
that are still here in 2025.
And my brain can't cope with that.
Let me give you a basic example.
When you make a class in Python,
the initialize a method, the starting method is def.
Okay, fair enough.
That's actually the same as Ruby,
D-E-F, definition of a method.
Then it is underscore, not one,
underscore, two, init, underscore, underscore,
parentheses start, self, comma,
and then the first argument.
- [Lex] Yeah, the whole self thing.
- I look at that and go, I'm sorry I'm out.
I can't do it.
It's everything about it
offends my sensibilities to the core.
Here you have the most important method
that all new objects or classes have to implement.
And it is one of the most aesthetically offensive ways
of typing initialized that I've ever seen anywhere.
And you guys are okay with this?
- Hey, you're making me, you know,
where you're like talking about my marriage
or something like this,
and I'm not realizing
I've been in a toxic relationship all along.
Yet, I just get used to it.
- That to me, by the way, was the magic of Ruby.
It opened my eyes
to help beautiful program could be.
I didn't know I'd been working in ASP.
I'd been working in PHP.
I didn't even have the concept
that aesthetics beautiful code
was something we could optimize for that.
Something we could pursue.
And even more than that,
that we could pursue it above other objectives.
That Ruby is as beautiful as it is.
It's not an accident and it's not easy.
Ruby itself is implemented in C.
It's very difficult to parse Ruby code,
because Ruby is written for humans
and humans are messy creatures.
They like things in just the right way.
I can't fully explain why the __init___ make me repulse,
but it does.
And when I look at the Ruby alternative,
it's really instructive.
So it's def, same part, D-E-F, space,
initialize, parentheses.
Not even parentheses.
If you don't need to call it within the arguments,
there's not even a parentheses.
That in itself is actually also a major part.
If the human doesn't need the additional characters,
we're not just gonna put them in
because it'd be nicer to parse for the computer.
We're gonna get rid of the semicolons.
We're gonna get rid of the parentheses.
We're gonna get rid of the underscores.
We're gonna get rid of all that ugliness,
all the line noise
and boil it down to its pure essentials.
And at the same time, we're not gonna abbreviate.
This is a key difference in the aesthetics
between Ruby and Python as well.
init, short of type, it's only five characters.
Initialize is a lot longer, but it looks a lot better
and you don't type it very often.
So you should look at something pretty.
If you don't have to do it all the time,
it's okay that it's long.
Those kinds of aesthetic evaluations
are rife all over the Ruby language.
But let me give you an even better example.
The if conditional.
That's the bedrock of all programming languages.
They have the if conditional.
If you take most programming languages,
they all have if.
That's basically the same in almost every language.
Space, start parentheses, we all do that.
And then you have perhaps,
let's say you're calling a object
called user.isadmin, close parentheses, close parentheses,
start brackets, and here's what we're gonna do
if the user is an admin, right?
That would be a normal programming language.
Ruby doesn't do it like that.
Ruby boils almost all of it away.
We start with the if.
Okay, that's the same.
No parenthesis necessary
because there's no ambiguity for the human
to distinguish that the next part
is just a single statement.
So you do if, space, user, dot,
admin, question mark.
No open brackets, no parentheses, no nothing.
Next, open line.
Here's your conditional.
That question mark means nothing to the computer,
but it meets something to the human.
Ruby put in the predicate method style
purely as a communication tool between humans.
It's actually more work for the interpreter
to be able to see that this question mark is there.
Why is this question mark in here?
Because it just reads so nicely.
If user.admin?
That's a very human phrase, but it gets better.
You can turn this around.
You can have your statement
you want to execute before the conditional.
You can do user.upgrade.
Say you're calling an upgrade method on a user.
Space, if, space, user.admin?.
We do the thing if the thing is true.
Instead of saying, if the thing is true, do the thing.
But it gets even better.
This is why I love this example with the conditional,
because you can keep diving into it.
So let's flip it around.
user.downgrade if !not user.admin, right?
That'd be a typical way of writing it.
Ruby goes, that exclamation point is light noise.
Why do we have if
and then an exclamation point, that's ugly.
We could do user.downgrade unless user.admin?
That to me is an encapsulation of the incredible beauty
that Ruby affords the programmer through ambiguity
that is only to serve the human reader and writer.
All of these statements we've just discussed,
they're the same for the computer.
It'll combine down to the same C code.
That'll compile down to the same assembly code.
It makes no difference whatsoever.
In fact, it just makes it harder to write an interpreter.
But for the human who gets to choose
whether the statement comes before the conditional
or the predicate method has, it's just incredible.
It reads like poetry at some point.
- It's also incredible that, you know,
one language designer's creating that, you know,
Guido van Rossum also, it's like one person
gets to make these extremely difficult decision
because you have to think about
how does that all get parsed?
And you have to think about the thousands,
if it's a popular language that millions of people
that end up using this.
And what they feel, what that question mark
for the if statement, what does that feel like
for the user? - That's what Matz
thought about because he started his entire mission
off a different premise
than almost every programming language designer
that I'd heard, at least articulate the vision.
That his number one goal was programmer happiness.
That his number one goal was the affordances
that would allow programmers to articulate code
in ways that not just execute it correctly,
but were a joy to write and were a joy to read.
And that vision is based on a fundamentally
different view of humanity.
There's no greater contrast between Matz
and James Gosling, the designer of Java.
I wanted to listen to James talk about the design of Java.
Why was it the way it was?
Why was it so rigid?
And he was very blunt about it,
which, by the way, I really appreciate.
And I think Gosling has done a tremendous job with Java.
But his view of humanity is rather dark.
His view of humanity was programmers
at the average are stupid creatures.
They cannot be trusted,
which sophisticated programming languages
because they're gonna shoot their foot off or their handoff.
And that would be kind of inconvenient
to the regional development office
of a mid-tier insurance company
writing code that has to last for 20 years.
Now it's actually a very Thomas-Sowell view
of constrained capacity in humans
that I've come to appreciate much later in life.
But it's also a very depressing view of programmers
that there are just certain programmers
who are too dumb to appreciate code poetry.
There are too ignorant to learn how to write it well.
We need to give them a sandbox
where they just won't hurt themselves too much.
Matz went the completely opposite direction.
He believes in humanity.
He believes in the unlimited capacity of programmers
to learn and become better.
So much so that he's willing to put the stranger
at his own level.
This is the second part I truly appreciate about Ruby.
Ruby allows you to extend base classes.
You know how we just talked about 5.times
is a way to iterate over a statement five times?
That five is obviously a base class.
It's a number.
Do you know what?
You can add your own methods to that.
I did, extensively.
In Rails, we have something called active support,
which is essentially my dialect of Ruby
for programming web applications.
And I'll give you one example.
I've added a method called days to the Number.
So if you do 5.days,
you get five days in seconds.
Because seconds is the way we set cache expiration times
and other things like that.
So you can say cache expires in 5.days.
And you're gonna get
whatever's five times - That's nice.
- 24 times 60 times 60 is,
or whatever the math is, right?
Very humanly readable.
In a novel programming language,
you would type out the seconds
and then you would have a little comment above it
saying this represent five days.
In Ruby, you get to write five days.
But even better than that,
Matz didn't come up with it.
Matz didn't need the five days.
I needed that because I needed to expire caches.
I was allowed by Matz to extend his story
with my own chapters unequal footing,
such that a reader Ruby could not tell the difference
between the code Matz wrote and the code that I wrote.
He trusted me as a complete stranger from Denmark
who had never met to mess with his beautiful story.
That level of trust is essentially unheard of.
I know there are other program languages that allow things
with macros and so forth.
But none do it in a way like Ruby does it.
None does it with an articulated vision of humanity,
a trust in humanity like Matz does,
that is the opposite end of the spectrum of Java.
- Yeah, I mean for my aesthetic sensibilities,
just the way you describe 5.days,
that's really pleasant to me.
Like I could see myself sitting alone,
sleep deprived, and just writing that.
It's just an easy thing.
You can write it in a long way with a comment.
You can write multiple lines.
You could do, and now with AI,
I'm sure it's gonna generate it correctly,
but there's something really pleasant
about the simplicity of that.
I'm not sure what that is.
But you're right,
there is a good feeling there.
And I'm sure we'll talk about happiness
from all kinds of philosophical angles,
but you know, that is what happiness is made of.
That little - Exactly.
- good feeling there.
- It's the good feeling that come out of a concept
compressed to its pure essence.
There's nothing you can take away
from that statement that's superfluous.
- But see, I also wanna push back a little bit
'cause I also a program named Perl a bunch.
Just be cool.
So like it's not all about compression.
- No, you can compress it too far.
Perl golf is a thing
where you can turn programs into something
that's unreadable for humans.
Now the great thing about Perl
was that it came out before Ruby.
Matz was a great student of Wall,
was a great student of Perl,
was a great student of Python
and Smalltalk and Lisp.
He took inspiration from all of these prior attempts
at creating good programming languages
and really edited down the very best bits into this.
So he was able to learn from his lessons.
But what I found incredible about Ruby
is that here we are 2025,
Ruby has been worked on for over 30 years,
and essentially the first draft
is 90% of what we're still using.
There was almost a sense of divine inspiration
possible in wherever Matz was writing
that initial version of Ruby
that transcended time to such a degree
that no one has still even begun to reach it.
This is the other thing I always find fascinating.
I generally believe in the efficient market theory
that if someone comes up with a better mousetrap
or better idea, others will eventually copy them
to such an extent that perhaps the original mousetrap
is no longer even remembered.
No one has been able to copy that essence of Ruby.
They borrowed elements, that's totally fine,
but Ruby still stands taller than everyone else
on these metrics, on this trust in humanity and programmers.
- And we should also say like, you know,
maybe the perfect programming language
that metric and then there's the successful language
and those are often different.
There's something wonderful about
the Brendan Eich story of creating JavaScript.
There's something truly beautiful
about the way JavaScript took over the world.
I've recently got to visit the Amazon jungle
and just one of my favorite things to do
is just to watch the ants take over anything, everything.
And it's just like it's a nice distributor system.
It's a messy thing that doesn't seem to be ordered,
but it just works
and the machinery of it. - Worse is Better.
Worse is Better.
I mean that's actually the name of a pattern
in software development
and other ways of how do is the pattern of Linux.
Linux was quantifiably worse
than I think it was Minx at the time.
Other ways of it that were more cathedral less bizarre
and it's still one that there's something to it
that the imperfections can help something go forward.
It's actually a trick I've studied
to the degree that I now incorporated
in almost all open source that I do.
I make sure that when I release the first version
of any new thing I work on, it's a little broken.
It's a little busted in ways
that invite people to come in and help me.
Because there's no easier way
to get the collaboration of other programmers
than to put something out
that they know how to fix and improve.
- Yeah, that's awesome. - But Ruby is somehow,
or was at least a little bit different in that regard.
Not in all regards.
Matz got the ethos of the language,
the design of language just right.
But the first versions of Ruby were terribly slow.
It's taken, I mean hundreds of man years
to get Ruby to be both this beautiful
yet also highly efficient and really fast.
- And we should say that the thing
that made you fall in love
with this particular programming language
is metaprogramming?
- Yes, so that takes all of these elements
we've just talked about and turned them up to 11.
I'll explain metaprogramming
real quick. - Yeah, please.
- Metaprogramming is essentially
a version of the 5.days.
You get to add keywords to the language.
Active record is the part of Rails
that communicates with the database.
This is a system where every table in the database
is represented by a class.
So if we take the user example, again,
you do class user descends from active record base,
and then the first line you can write is this.
I want my users to have many posts or have many comments.
Let's do that.
We're making some system where users can make comments.
The very next line is has_many, space, colon comments.
Now you've set up a dependency
between users and comments
that will give your whole host of access and factory methods
for users to be able to own comments,
to create comments, to update comments
in that line alone has many looks like a keyword.
It looks like it's part of the Ruby language.
That's metaprogramming.
When Rails is able to add these elements
to how you define a class
and then that runs code that adds a bunch of methods
to the use of class, that's metaprogramming.
And when metaprogramming is used in this way,
we call it domain specific languages.
You take a generic language like Ruby
and you tailor it to a certain domain like describing
relationships in a database at a object level.
And this is one of those early examples
where you can do, user has many comments.
Belongs _two_ :account.
Now you've set up a one-to-one relationship
before we had a one-to-many relationship.
Rails is rife with all these kinds
of domain specific languages
where at sometimes it doesn't even look like Ruby.
You can't identify Ruby keywords.
You can just identify
what looks like keywords in its own programming language.
Now again, I know that Lisp and others also do this stuff.
They just do it with the maximum amount of line noise
that can ever be crammed into a programming language.
And Ruby does it at a level where you cannot tell
my metaprogramming from Matz's keywords
and with zero line noise.
- Yeah, I should say that my first love was Lisp.
So there's a slow tear that you can't see.
- I've actually never written any real Lisp myself.
- Well, how can you judge it so harshly then?
- 'Cause I have two eyes and I can look at code,
and my aesthetic sensibilities forbid me
to even go much further.
Which is a limitation, I know.
I should actually dive into Lisp
because I've found that I've learned a lot
just diving into, maybe I'm insulting Lisp again here,
but the past of programming languages
with Smalltalk, for example.
I think Smalltalk is a incredible experiment
that also worked but isn't suitable
for today's programming environments.
- I love that we're talking about Ruby
so much and what beautiful code is
and what a beautiful programming language is.
So one of the things that is I think implied
maybe you made explicit in your descriptions there
is that Ruby is dynamic typing versus strict typing.
And you have been not just saying that it's a nice thing,
but that you will defend dynamic typing to the death.
Like that freedom is a powerful freedom to preserve.
- It's the essence of what makes Ruby Ruby.
This is why I don't fully understand
when people call for Ruby to add static typing.
'Cause to me, it's the bedrock of what this is.
Why would you wanna turn one of the most beautiful languages
into something far uglier?
This is one of my primary objections to static typing.
It's not just that it limits you in certain ways.
It makes metaprogramming harder.
I write a bunch of metaprogramming.
I've seen what it takes to do metaprogramming TypeScript.
That was actually one of the things
that just really sent me on a tear of getting meta
or getting TypeScript
out of some of the projects that I'm involved with.
We pulled TypeScript out of turbo.
One of the front-end frameworks that we have,
because I tried to write to metaprogramming
in TypeScript and I was just infuriated.
I don't want that experience,
but I also don't want it from an aesthetic point of view.
I hate repetition.
We've just talked about how much I love that Ruby boils
all of these expressions down to its essence.
You can't remove one dot.
You can't remove one character without losing something.
This moment you go for static typing that you declare,
at least I know there are ways
to do implied typing and so forth.
But let's just take the stereotypical case
of a example, for example.
Capital U, user,
I'm declaring the type of the variable;
lowercase user, I'm now naming my variable;
equals uppercase user or new uppercase user.
I've repeated user three times.
I don't have time for this.
I don't have sensibilities for this.
I don't want my Ruby polluted with this.
Now I understand all the arguments
for why people like static typing
when the primary arguments is that it makes tooling easier.
It makes it easier to do auto complete
in editors, for example.
It makes it easier to find certain kinds of bugs
because maybe you're calling methods that don't exist
on an object and the editor
can actually catch that bug before you even run it.
I don't care.
First of all, I don't write code with tools.
I write them with text editors.
I chisel them out of the screen with my bare hands.
I don't auto complete.
And this is why I love Ruby so much,
and this is why I continue to be in love
with the text editor rather than the IDE.
I don't want an IDE.
I want my fingers to have to individually
type out every element of it
because it will force me to stay in the world
where Ruby is beautiful.
Because as soon as it gets easy
to type a lot of boilerplate, well guess what?
You can have a lot of boilerplate.
Every single language basically
that has great tooling support has a much higher tolerance
for boilerplate because the thinking is, well,
you're not typing it anyway,
you're just auto completing it.
I don't want that at all.
I want something where the fabric I'm working in,
it's just a text file.
There's nothing else to it.
So these things play together.
There's the aesthetic part, there's the tooling part,
there's the metaprogramming part.
There's the fact that Ruby's ethos of duck typing,
I dunno if you've heard that term before.
It's essentially not about, can I call this method,
if a object is of a certain class.
It is, can I call this method if the method responds?
It's very out of Smalltalk in that regard.
You don't actually check
of whether that class has the method,
which allows you to dynamically add methods at runtime
and do all sorts of really interesting things
that underpin all the beautiful metaprogramming
that we do in Ruby.
I don't wanna lose any of that.
And I don't care for the benefits.
One of the benefits I see touted over and over again
is that it's much easier to write correct software.
You can have fewer bugs.
You're gonna have less null pointer exceptions.
You're gonna have less all of this stuff.
Yeah, I don't have any of that.
It's just not something
that occurs in my standard mode of operation.
I'm not saying I don't have bugs, of course I do,
but I catch those bugs with unit testing,
with integration testing.
Those are the kinds of precautions
that will catch logical bugs.
Things that compile but are wrong
along with the uncompilable stuff.
So I've never been drawn into this world,
and part of it is because I work
on a certain class of systems.
I fully accept that.
If you're writing systems
that have five, 10, 50 million lines of code
with hundreds, thousands,
or tens of thousands of programmers,
I fully accept that you need different methods.
What I object to is the idea
that what's right for a code base
of 10 million lines of code
with a hundred thousand programmers working on it
is also the same thing I should be using in my bedroom
to create Basecamp, because I'm just a single individual.
That's complete nonsense.
In the real world,
we would know that that makes no sense at all.
That you don't, I don't know,
use your Pagani to go pick up groceries at Costco.
It's a bad vehicle for that.
It just doesn't have the space.
You don't wanna muddy the beautiful seats.
You don't wanna do any of those things.
We know that certain things
that are very good in certain domains
don't apply to all.
In programming languages,
it seems like we forget that.
Now, to be fair, I also had a little bit perhaps
of a reputation of forgetting that.
When I first learned Ruby,
I was so head over heels in love
with this programming language
that I almost found it unconceivable
that anyone would choose any other programming language
at all to write web applications.
And I kind of engaged the evangelism of Ruby on Rails
in that spirit as a crusade,
as I just need to teach you the gospel.
I just need to show you this conditional code
that we just talked about
and you will convert at the point of a sharp argument.
Now, I learned that that's not the way.
And part of the reason
it's not the way is the programmers think differently.
Our brains are configured differently.
My brain is configured perfectly for Ruby.
Perfectly for a dynamically duck typed language
that I can chisel code out of a text editor with.
And other people need the security of an IDE.
They want the security of classes
that won't compile unless you call the methods on it.
I have come to accept that, but most programmers don't.
They're still stuck in, essentially, I like static typing.
Therefore, static typing is the only way
to create reliable correct systems,
which is just such a mind blowing, to be blunt,
idiotic thing to say in the face of evidence,
mountains of evidence to the contrary.
This is one of the reasons I'm so in love with Shopify
as the flagship application for Ruby on Rails.
Shopify exists at a scale
that most programmers will never touch.
On Black Friday,
I think Shopify did 1 million requests per second.
That's not 1 million requests of images.
That's of dynamic requests
that are funneling through the pipeline of commerce.
I mean, Shopify runs something like 30%
of all e-commerce stores on the damn internet.
A huge portion of all commerce in total
runs through Shopify and that runs on Ruby on Rails.
So Ruby on Rails is able to scale
up to that level without using
static typing in all of what it does.
Now I know they've done certain experiments in certain ways
because they are hitting some of the limits
that you will hit with dynamic typing.
And some of those limits you hit
with dynamic typing are actually, by the way,
just limits you hit when you write 5 million lines of code.
I think the Shopify monolith
is about 5 million lines of code.
At that scale, everything breaks
because you're at the frontier
of what humans are capable of doing
with programming languages.
The difference in part
is that Ruby is such a succinct language
that those 5 million,
if they had been written in, let's just say Go or Java
would've been 50 or 25.
Now that might have alleviated some of the problems
that you have when you work on huge systems
with many programmers.
But it certainly would also have compounded them
trying to understand 25 million lines of code.
- So the thing does scale.
That's a persistent myth that it doesn't scale
Shopify and others.
But Shopify thinks a great example.
By the way, I love Shopify and I love Tobi, amazing.
- You gotta have Tobi on. - Yeah, for sure.
- Just talking to him this morning.
- For sure, he's a brilliant.
I got to hang out with him
in the desert somewhere, I forget in Utah.
He's just a brilliant human.
And Shopify, shopify.com/lex has been supporting
this podcast for the longest time.
I don't think actually Tobi knows
that they sponsor this podcast.
I mean this is a big company, right?
- It's a huge company.
I think just under 10,000 employees,
market cap of 120 billion,
GMV of a quarter of a trillion every quarter.
- And he's involved with the details though.
- He is, very much so.
Funny story about Tobi.
Tobi was on the Rails core team
back in the mid 2000s.
Tobi himself wrote Active Merchant,
which is one of the frameworks for creating shops.
He wrote the Liquid templating language
that Shopify still uses to this day.
He has a huge list of contributions
to the Rails ecosystem, and he's the CEO of the company.
Yeah, I think it's just...
It's very inspiring to me
because it's such at the opposite end of what I like to do.
I like to chisel code with my own hands most of the day.
He runs a company of almost 10,000 people that is literally
like world commerce depends on it.
A level of criticality I can't even begin to understand.
And yet we can see eye to eye
on so many of these fundamental questions
in computer science and program development.
That is a dynamic range
to be able to encompass Rails being a great tool
for the one developer
who's just starting out with an idea
who don't even fully know everything.
Who is right at the level where PHP
would've been a good fit in those late '90s
because yeah, I could probably upload
something to an FTP server, and so on.
Rails does have more complexity than that,
but it also has so much longer runway.
The runway goes all the way to goddamn Shopify.
That is about the most convincing argument I can make
for sort of dynamic range that we can do a lot of it.
And even having said that,
Shopify is the outlier of course.
I don't think about Shopify
as the primary target when I write Rails.
I think of the single developer.
Actually, I do think about Shopify.
But I don't think about Shopify now.
I think of Shopify when Tobi was writing Snow Devil,
which was the first e-commerce store to sell snowboards
that he created, that was the pre-Shopify Shopify.
He created all by himself.
And that was possible because Ruby on Rails
isn't just about beautiful code.
It's just as much about productivity.
It's just as much about the impact
that an individual programmer is able to have.
That they can build system
where they can keep the whole thing in their head
and be able to move it forward
such that you can go from one developer
sitting and working on something
and that something is Shopify
and it turns into what it is today.
When we talk about programming languages
and we compare 'em,
we often compare 'em at a very late stage.
Like what is the better programming language
for let's say Twitter in 2009
when it's already a huge success.
Twitter was started on Ruby on Rails.
They then hit some scaling problems.
It was a big debacle at the time.
They end up then I think writing it in some other language,
which by the way I think is the best advertisement
ever for Ruby on Rails,
because nothing fucking happened
for 10 years after they switched over, right?
Essentially zero innovation.
Some of that was because they were doing a long conversion,
and all of the early success
in part came because they had the agility
quickly change and adopt and so forth.
That's what startups needs.
That's what Shopify needed.
That's what Twitter needed.
That's what everyone needs.
And that's the number one priority for Ruby on Rails.
To make sure that we don't lose that.
Because what happens so often when development tools
and program language driven by huge companies
is that they mirror their org chart.
React and everything else needed to use that
is in some ways a reflection of how Meta builds Facebook.
'Cause of course it is.
Because of course it's an destruction of that.
I'm not saying React isn't a great tool
and that can't be used by smaller teams.
Of course it can.
But it's born in a very different context
than something like Ruby on Rails.
- Let me say this a small aside
because I think we might return to Shopify
and celebrate it often.
Just a sort of personal note.
This particular podcast has way more sponsors
and sponsors that want to be sponsors
than I could possibly ever have.
And it's really, really important for me
to not give a shit,
and to be able to celebrate people.
Like I celebrate people.
I celebrate companies.
And I don't care that they're sponsoring.
I really don't care.
I just wanna make that very explicit
'cause we're gonna continue saying
positive things about Shopify.
I don't care.
Stop sponsoring.
It doesn't really matter to me.
But yeah, I just wanna make that explicit.
So, but to linger on the scaling thing
with the Twitter and the Shopify,
can you just explain to me
what Shopify is doing with the YJIT?
What did they have to try to do to scale this thing?
Because that's kind of an incredible story, right?
- Yeah, so one of the great contributions
that Shopify has made to the entire Ruby ecosystem,
not just Rails but in particular Rails is YJIT.
So YJIT is their compiler for Ruby.
That just makes everything a lot more efficient
and at Shopify scale eking out even a five,
10% improvement in Ruby's overhead and execution time
is a huge deal.
Now, Shopify didn't need YJIT.
Shopify was already running
on the initial version of Ruby
that was, I think 10 times slower than what we have today.
If you look back upon the Ruby 186,
that Tobi probably started on just as I started on,
and that was enough to propel Shopify
to the scale that it has today.
A lot of the scaling conversation
in is lost in a failure to distinguish two things.
Scale is kind of one package we talk about
when there are really multiple packages inside of it.
One is runtime performance, latency.
How fast can you execute a single request?
Can it happen fast enough that the user
will not notice?
If your Rails request takes a second and a half to execute,
the user's gonna notice.
Your app is gonna feel slow and sluggish.
You have to get that response time down below,
let's say at least 300 milliseconds.
I like to target a hundred milliseconds as my latency.
That's kind of performance.
How much performance of that kind of latency
can you squeeze out of a single CPU core,
that tells you something about
what the price of a single request will be.
But then whether you can deal
with 1 million requests a second
like Shopify is doing right now.
If you have one box
that can do a thousand requests a second,
you just need X boxes to get up to a million.
And what you'll actually find
is that when it comes to programming languages,
they're all the same in this way.
They all scale largely beautifully horizontally.
You just add more boxes.
The hard parts of scaling a Shopify
is typically the program language.
It's the database.
And that's actually one of the challenges
that Shopify has now is how do you deal with MySQL
at the scale that they're operating at?
When do you need to move to other databases
to get worldwide performance?
All of these things.
The questions about scaling Ruby are economic questions.
If we are spending so and so much on application servers,
if we can get just 5% more performance out of Ruby,
well we could save 5% of those servers
and that could filter down into the budget.
Now that analysis concludes into basically one thing.
Ruby is a luxury language.
It's a luxury, the highest luxury in my opinion.
It is the Coco Chanel of programming languages.
Something that not everyone can afford.
And I mean this in the best possible way.
There are some applications on the internet
where each request has so little value,
you can't afford to use a luxurious language
like Ruby to program in it.
You simply have to slum it with a C or a Go
or some other low level language or Rust,
talk about line noise there for...
- It's like the thrift store of languages.
- Exactly, where you need kind of just...
you need a very low level to do it.
You can't afford to use a luxury language
to use to build it with.
That's not true of Shopify.
It wasn't true of Basecamp even back in 2004.
It's not been true of 99%
of all web applications ever created
because the main cost component
of 99% of web applications,
it's not CPU course.
It's wet course.
It's human course.
It's human capacity to understand and involve systems.
It's their personal productivity.
I did a calculation once
when someone had for the 400th time said that,
"Oh, if you switch from Ruby to some faster language,
you could save a bunch of money."
And I calculated it out that at the time,
and I think the last time I did this calculation
was almost a decade ago.
We were spending about 15% of our operating budget
on Ruby application service.
So for me to improve my cost profile of the business
by seven percentage points,
I'd have to pick something twice as fast.
That's quite hard.
Versus if Ruby and Ruby on Rails
was even 10% more productive than something else,
I would move the needle far more
because making individual programmers more productive
actually matters a lot more.
This is why people are so excited about AI.
This is why they're freaking out
over the fact that a single programmer in Silicon Valley
who makes $300,000 a year
can now do the work of three or five, at least in theory.
I haven't actually seen that fully in practice,
but let's just assume the theory is correct
if not now, then in six months.
That's a huge deal.
That matters so much more
than whether you can squeeze a few more cycles
out of the CPU,
when it comes to these kinds of business applications.
If you're making unreal engine rendering stuff
like Tim Sweeney you had on.
Yeah, he needs to really sweat all those details.
The Nanite engine can't run on Ruby.
It's never going to.
It would not meant for that, fine.
These kinds of business applications absolutely can
and everything that people are excited
about AI for right now,
that extra capacity to just do more.
That was why we were excited about Ruby
back in the early 2000s.
That was be because I saw
that if we could even squeeze out
a 10% improvement of the human programmer,
we'd be able to do so much more for so much less.
- Probably argue about this,
but I really like working together with AI,
collaborating with AI.
And I would argue that the kind of code you want AI
to generate is human readable, human interpretable.
If it's generating Perl golf code,
it's not a collaboration.
So it has to be speaking the human.
It's not just you're writing the prompts in English.
You also want to read the responses
in the human interpretable language like Ruby, right?
So that's actually is beneficial for AI too.
'Cause you've kind of said that for you the sculptor,
the sort of the elitist Coco Chanel sculptor,
you want to on your fancy keyboard
to type every single letter
yourself of your own fingers.
But it's also that the benefit
of Ruby also applies in once some of that is written by AI
and you're actually doing
with your own fingers the editing.
Because you can interact with it
because it's human interpretable.
- The paradigm I really love with this
was something Elon actually said on one of your shows
when you guys were talking about Neuralink,
that Neuralink allows the bandwidth
between you and the machine to increase.
That language either spoken or written
is very low bandwidth.
If you are to calculate just how many bits
we can exchange as we are sitting here, it's very slow.
Ruby has a much higher bandwidth
of communication revealed conveys
so much more concept per character
than most other programming languages do.
So when you are collaborating with AI,
you want really high bandwidth.
You want it to be able to produce programs with you,
whether you're letting it write the code or not,
that both of you can actually understand really quickly
and that you could compress a grand concept,
a grand system into far fewer parts
that both of you can understand.
Now, I actually love collaborating with AI too.
I love chiseling my code
and the way I use AI is in a separate window.
I don't let it drive my code.
I've tried that.
I've tried the cursors and the wind surfaces
and I don't enjoy that way of writing.
And one of the reasons I don't enjoy
that way of writing is I can literally feel competence
draining out of my fingers.
Like that level of immediacy
with the material disappears.
And the where I felt this the most was I did this remix
of Ubuntu called Omakub when I switched to Linux,
and it's all written in Bash.
I'd never written any serious
amount of code in Bash before.
So I was using AI to collaborate,
to write a bunch of Bash with me,
'cause I needed all this.
I knew what I wanted.
I could express it in Ruby.
But I thought it was an interesting challenge
to filter through Bash because what I was doing
was setting up a Linux machine.
That's basically what Bash was designed for.
It's a great constraint.
But what I found myself doing was asking AI
for the same way of expressing a conditional,
for example, in Bash over and over again.
That by not typing it, I wasn't learning it.
I was using it, I was getting the expression I wanted,
but I wasn't learning it.
And I got a little scared.
I got a little scared like,
is this the end of learning?
Am I no longer learning if I'm not typing?
And the way I, for me, recast that
was, I don't wanna give up on the AI.
It's such a better experience as a programmer
to look up APIs, to get a second opinion on something,
to do a draft.
But I have to do the typing myself
because you learn with your fingers.
If you're learning how to play the guitar,
you can watch as many YouTube videos as you want.
You're not gonna learn the guitar.
You have to put your fingers on the strings
to actually learn the motions.
And I think there is a parallel here to programming
where programming has to be learned in part
by the actual typing.
- I'm just really, this is fascinating.
Listen, part of my brain agrees with you.
100% part doesn't.
I think AI should be in the loop of learning.
Now current systems don't do that,
but I think it's very possible for cursor to say,
to basically force you to type certain things.
So like if you set the mode of learning,
I don't want to be this sort of give up on AI.
I think vibe coding is a skill.
So for an experienced programmer
it's too easy to dismiss vibe coding as a thing.
- [DHH] I agree, I wouldn't dismiss it.
- But I think you need to start building that skill
and start to figure out
how do you prevent the competency from slipping away
from your fingers and brain.
Like how do you develop that skill in parallel
to the other skill?
I don't know.
I think it's a fascinating puzzle though.
I know too many really strong programmers
that just kind of avoid AI,
'cause it's currently a little too dumb.
- Yes, it's a little too slow.
It's actually my main problem.
It's a little too dumb in some ways,
but it's a little too slow in other ways.
When I use Claude's code,
the terminal version of a Claude,
which is actually my preferred way of using it,
I get too impatient.
It feels like I'm going back to a time
where code had to compile
and I had to go do something else.
A boil some tea while the code is compiling.
Well, I've been working in Ruby for 20 years.
I don't have compiled weight in me anymore.
So there's that aspect of it.
But I think the more crucial aspect
for me is I really care about the competence.
And I've seen what happens to even great programmers
the moment they put away the keyboard.
Because even before AI,
this would happen as soon as people would get promoted.
Most great programmers who work in large businesses
stop writing code on a daily basis
because they simply have too many meetings to attend to.
They have too many other things to do.
And invariably they lose touch with programming.
That doesn't mean they forget everything.
But if you don't have your fingers in the sauce, source,
you are going to lose touch with it.
There's just no other way.
I don't want that because I enjoy it too much.
This is not just about outcomes.
This is what's crucial to understand
programming for programmers who like to code
is not just about the programs they get out of it.
That may be the economic value.
It's not the only human value.
The human value is just much in the expression.
When someone who sits down on a guitar
and plays "Stairway to Heaven,"
there's a perfect recording
of that that will last in eternity.
You can just put it on Spotify.
You don't actually need to do it.
The joy is to command the guitar yourself.
The joy of a programmer, of me as a programmer,
is to type the code myself.
If I elevate myself,
if I promote myself out of programming,
I turn myself into a project manager.
A project manager of a murder of AI crows
as I wrote the other day.
I could have been become a project manager my whole career.
I could have become a project manager 20 years ago
if I didn't care to write code myself.
And I just wanted outcomes.
That's how I got started in programming.
I just wanted outcomes.
Then I fell in love with programming
and now I'd rather retire than giving it up.
Now that doesn't mean
you can't have your cake and needed to.
I've done some vibe coding
where I didn't care that I wasn't playing myself.
I just wanted to see something.
There was an idea in my head.
I wanted to see something.
That's fine.
I also use AI all day long.
In fact, I'm already at the point
where if you took it away from me,
I'd be like, oh my god,
how do we even look things up on the internet anymore?
Is Stack Overflow still around?
Or I'm still a thing?
Like how do I even find answers
to some of these questions I have all day long.
I don't wanna give up AI.
In fact, I'd say the way I like to use AI,
I'm getting smarter every because of AI.
Because I'm using AI to have it explain things to me.
Even stupid questions.
I would be a little embarrassed
to even enter into Google.
AI is perfectly willing to give me the ELI5 explanation
of some Unix command.
I should have known already,
but I don't, I'm sorry,
can you just explain it to me and now I know the thing.
So at the end of the day of me working with AI all day long,
I'm a little bit smarter.
Like 5%, sorry, not 5%, half a percent maybe.
That compounds over time.
But what I've also seen,
when I worked on the Omakub project
and I tried to let AI drive for me,
I felt I was maybe half a percent dumber
at the end of the day.
- Okay, you said a lot of interesting things.
First of all, let's just start at the very fact
that asking dumb questions.
If you go to Stack Overflow
and ask a dumb question
or read somebody else's dumb question and the answer to it,
there's a lot of judgment there.
AI sometimes to an excessive degree has no judgment.
It usually says, oh, that's a great question.
- [DHH] To a fault.
- Yeah, oh, that's wonderful.
Yeah, I mean, it's so conducive to learning.
It's such a wonderful tool of learning
and I too would miss it.
And it's a great basically search engine
into all kinds of nuances
of a particular programming language,
especially if you don't know it that well
or like APIs you can load in documentation.
It's just so great for learning.
I, for me personally...
I mean, on the happiness scale,
it makes me more excited to program.
I don't know what that is exactly.
Part of that is the, I'm really sorry.
Stack Overflow is an incredible website,
but there is a negativity there.
There's a judgment there.
It's just exciting to be out like with a hype man
next to me, just like saying, yeah, that's a great idea.
And I'll say, no, that's wrong.
I'll correct the AI,
and the AI will say, "You're absolutely right.
How did I not think about that?"
You know, rewrite the code.
I'm like, holy shit, I'm having, that's like a buddy.
That's like really being positive
and is very smart and is challenging me to think.
And even if I never use the code it generates,
I'm already a better programmer.
But actually the deeper thing is for some reason
I'm having more fun.
That's a really, really important thing.
- I like to think of it as a pair programmer
for exactly that reason.
Pair programming came a vogue in like the 2000s.
Where you'd have two programmers in front of one machine
and you'd push the keyboard between you.
One programmer would be driving, they'd be typing in.
The other programmer would essentially sit
and watch the code,
suggest improvements, look something up.
That was a really interesting dynamic.
Now unfortunately, I'm an introvert,
so I can do that for about five minutes
before I want to jump off a bridge.
So it doesn't work for me as a full-time occupation.
But AI allows me to have all the best
of that experience all the time.
Now I think what's really interesting,
what you said about it makes it more fun.
I hadn't actually thought about that,
but what it's made more fun to me is to be a beginner again.
It made it more fun to learn Bash
successfully for the first time.
Now I had to do the detour
where I let it write all the code for me
and I realized I wasn't learning nearly as much
as I hoped I would
and that I started doing once I typed it out myself.
But it gave me the confidence that, you know what?
If I need to do some iOS programming myself,
I haven't done that in probably six years
was the last time I dabbled in it.
I never really built anything for real.
I feel highly confident now that I could sit down with AI
and I could have something in the app store
by the end of the week.
I would not have that confidence
unless I had a pair of programming body like AI.
I don't actually use it very much for Ruby code.
I'm occasionally impressed
whenever I try it, they're like,
oh, it got this one thing right.
That is truly remarkable and it's actually pretty good.
And then I'll ask you two more questions
and I go like, oh yeah, okay.
If you were my junior programmer,
I'd start tapping my fingers
and going like, you gotta shape up.
Now the great thing of course
is we can just wait five minutes.
The Anthropic CEO seems to think that 90% of all code
by the end of the year is gonna be written by AI.
I am more than a little bit skeptical about that,
but I'm open-minded about the prospect
that programming potentially
will turn into a horse when done manually.
Something we do recreationally
is no longer a mode of transportation to get around LA.
You're not gonna saddle up
and go to the grocery store
and pick up stuff from whole foods in your saddlebacks.
That's just not a thing anymore.
That could be the future for programming,
for manual programming entirely possible.
I also don't care.
Like even though we have great renditions
of all the best songs, as I said,
there are millions of people who love to play the guitar.
It may no longer have as much economic value as it once did.
I think that I'm quite convinced is true
that we perhaps have seen the peak.
Now I understand the paradox,
when the price of something goes down,
actually the overall usage goes up
and total spend on that activity goes up.
That could also happen maybe.
But what we're seeing right now
is that a lot of the big shops, a lot of the big companies
are not hiring like they were five years ago.
They're not anticipating they're gonna need
tons more programmers.
Controversially, Tobi actually put out a memo
inside of Shopify asking everyone
who's considering hiring someone
to ask the question, could this be done by AI?
Now, he's further ahead on this question than I am.
I look at some of the coding trenches
and I go like, I'd love to use AI more,
and I see how it's making us more productive,
but it's not yet at the level
where I just go like, oh, we have this project.
Let me just give it to the AI agent
and it's gonna go off and do it.
- But let's just be honest.
You're like a Clint-Eastwood type character cowboy
and on a horse seeing cars going around
and you're like, well.
- That's part of it.
And I think that's, it is important to have that humility
that what you are good at
may no longer be what society values.
This has happened a million times in history
that you could have been exceptionally good
at saddle making, for example.
That's something that a lot of people used to care about
because everyone rode a horse.
And then suddenly riding a horse became this niche hobby
that there's some people care about it,
but not nearly as many.
That's okay.
Now the other thing of this
is I've had the good fortune to...
I've been a programmer for nearly 30 years.
That was a great run.
I try to look at life in this way
that I've already been blessed
with decades of economically viable,
highly valuable ways of translating what I like best
in the working world to write Ruby code.
That that was so valuable
that I could make millions and millions of dollars doing it.
And if that's over tomorrow,
I shouldn't look at that with regret.
I should look at it with gratitude.
- But you're also a highly experienced, brilliant
and opinionated human being,
so it's really interesting to get your opinion
on the future of the horse
because it, you know,
there's a lot of young people listening to this
who love programming or who are excited
by the possibility of building stuff with software,
with Ruby on Rails, that kind of language.
This and now the possibility.
- But is it a career? - Is it a career?
And if indeed a single person can build
more and more and more with the help of AI,
like how do they learn that skill?
Is this a good skill to learn?
I mean, that to me is the real mystery here,
because I think it's still absolutely true
that you have to learn how to program
from scratch currently.
But how do you balance those two skills?
Because I too, as I'm thinking now,
there is a scary slipping away of skill that happens.
In a matter of like really minutes
on a particular piece of code.
It's scary.
Not the way driving, you know,
when you have a car drive for you
doesn't quite slip away that fast.
So that really scares me.
So when somebody comes up to me
and asks me like, how do I learn to program,
I don't know what the advice
is because I think it's not enough
to just use cursor or copilot to generate code.
- It's absolutely not enough.
Not if you wanna learn,
none of you want to become better at it.
If you just become a tap monkey,
maybe you're productive in a second.
But then you have to realize,
well, can anyone just tap?
If that's all we're doing
is just sitting around all day long tapping?
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
That's not a marketable skill.
Now, I always preface this both to myself
and when I speak to others,
it is rule number note one, nobody fucking knows anything.
No one can predict even six months ahead.
Right now, we're probably at peak AI future hype
because we see all the promise,
because so much of it is real
and so many people have experienced it themselves.
This mind boggling thing
that the silicon is thinking in some way
that feels eerily reminiscent of humans.
I'd actually say the big thing
for me wasn't even ChatGPT.
It wasn't even Claude.
It was DeepSeek.
Running DeepSeek locally
and seeing the think box
where it converses with itself
about how to formulate the response.
I almost wanted to think, is this a gimmick?
Is it doing this as a performance for my benefit?
But that's not actually how it thinks.
If this is how it actually thinks,
okay, I'm a little scared.
This is incredibly human how it thinks in this way.
But where does that go?
So in '95, 1 of my favorite movies,
one of my favorite B movies came out,
"The Lawnmower Man." - Great movie.
- Incredible movie about virtual reality.
Being an avatar and living in VR,
like the story was a mess.
But the aesthetics the world had built up was incredible.
And I thought, we're five years away.
I'm gonna be living in VR now.
I'm just gonna be floating around.
I'm gonna be an avatar.
This is where most humans can spend most of the day
that didn't happen.
We're 30 years later,
VR is still not here.
It's here for gaming.
It's here for some specialized applications.
My oldest loves playing Gorilla Tag.
I dunno if you've tried that.
That's basically the hottest VR game.
Wonderful, it's great.
It's really hard to predict the future
'cause we just don't know.
And then when you factor in AI
and you have even the smartest people go like,
I don't think we fully understand how this works.
- But then on the flip side,
you have Moore's Law that seems to have worked
for many, many, many years
in decreasing the size of transistor, for example.
So like you know, Flash didn't take over the internet,
but Moore's Law worked.
So we don't know
which one AI is. - Which one it is.
And this is what I find so fascinating too.
I forget who did this presentation,
but someone in the web community,
this great presentation on the history of the airplane.
So you go from the Wright brothers flying in, what?
1903 or something like that.
And 40 years later you have a jet flight.
Just an unbelievable amount of progress in four decades.
Then in '56, I think it was,
the halt the sign for the Boeing 747
essentially precursor was designed
and basically nothing has happened since.
Just minor tweaks and improvements
on the flying experience since the '50s.
Somehow, if you were to predict where flying
was gonna go, and you were sitting in 42
and you'd seen, you'd remember
the Wright brothers flying in '03,
and you were seeing that jet engines coming,
you're like, we're gonna fly to to the stars
in another two decades.
We're gonna invent super mega hypersonic flights
that's gonna traverse the earth in two hours.
And then that didn't happen.
It tapped out.
This is what's so hard about predicting the future.
We can be so excited in the moment
because we're drawing a line through early dots on a chart,
and it looks like those early dots
are just going up into the right,
and sometimes it's just flatten out.
This is also one of those things
where we have so much critical infrastructure, for example,
that still runs on COBOL.
That about five humans
around the world really understand truly, deeply
that there's a lot, it's possible
for society to lose a competence.
It's still needs because it's chasing the future.
COBOL is still with us.
This is one of the things I think about
with with programming.
Ruby on Rails is at such a level now
that in 50 years from now,
it's exceedingly likely that there's still a ton
of Ruby on Rail systems running around.
And very hard to predict
what that exact world is gonna be like.
But yesterday's weather tells us
that if there's still COBOL code from the '70s
operating social security today,
and we haven't figured out a clean way to convert that,
let alone understand it,
we should certainly be humble about predicting the future.
I don't think any of the programmers
who wrote that COBOL code back in the '70s
had any damn idea that in 2025,
checks were still being cut off the business logic
that they had encoded back then.
But that just brings me to the conclusion on the question
for what should a young programmer do?
You're not gonna be able to predict the future.
No one's gonna be able to predict the future.
If you like programming, you should learn programming.
Now, is that gonna be a career forever?
I don't know, but what's gonna be a career forever?
Who knows?
Like a second ago,
we thought that it was the blue collar labor
that was gonna be extracted first.
It was the robots that were gonna take over.
Then GenAI comes out,
and then all the artists suddenly look like,
"Holy shit, is this gonna do all animation now?
Is gonna do all music now?"
They get real scared.
And now I see the latest Tesla robot going like,
oh, maybe we're back now to blue collar being in trouble.
Because if it can dance like that,
it can probably fix a toilet.
So no one knows anything,
and you have to then position yourself for the future
in such a way that it doesn't matter
that you pick a profession or path
where if it turns out that you have to retool and re-skill,
you're not gonna regret the path you took.
That's a general life principle.
For me, how I look at all endeavors I involve myself in
is I want to be content with all outcomes.
When we start working on a new product at 37signals,
I set up my mental model for its success.
And I go, do you know what?
If no one wants this, I will have had another opportunity
to write beautiful Ruby code,
to explore Greenfield domain,
to learn something new,
to build a system I want, even if no one else wants it.
What a blessing.
What a privilege.
If a bunch of people want it, that's great.
We can pay some salaries, we can keep the business running,
and if it's a blow away success, wonderful.
I get to impact a bunch of people.
- I think one of the big open questions to me
is how far you can get with vibe coding,
whether an approach for a young developer to invest
most of the time it's into vibe coding
or into writing code from scratch.
So vibe coding, meaning,
so I'm leaning into the meme a little bit,
but the vibe coding, meaning you generate code,
you have this idea of a thing you want to create,
you generate the code and then you fix it
with both natural language to the prompts and manually.
You learn enough to manually fix it.
So that's the learning process.
How you fix code that's generated,
or you write code from scratch
and have the LMS kind of tab, tab, tab, tab,
add extra code.
Like which part do you lean on?
I think to be safe, you should find the beauty
and the artistry and the skill
in both right from scratch.
So like there should be some percent
of your time just writing from scratch
and some percent vibe coding.
- There should be more of the time writing from scratch.
If you are interested in learning how to program,
unfortunately you're not gonna get fit
by watching fitness videos.
You're not gonna learn how to play the guitar
by watching YouTube guitar videos.
You have to actually play yourself.
You have to do the sit ups.
Programming, understanding,
learning almost anything requires you to do.
Humans are not built to absorb information
in a way that transforms into skills
by just watching others from afar.
Now ironically, it seems AI is actually quite good at that,
but humans are not.
If you wanna learn how to become a competent programmer,
you have to program.
It's really not that difficult to understand.
Now I understand the temptation.
And the temptation is there
because vibe coding can produce things.
Perhaps in this moment,
especially in a new domain you're not familiar with,
with tools you don't know perfectly well,
that's better than what you could do.
Or that you would take much longer to get at,
but you're not gonna learn anything.
You're gonna learn in this superficial way
that feels like learning,
but is completely empty calories.
And secondly, if you can just vibe code it,
you're not a programmer.
Then anyone could do it, which may be wonderful.
That's essentially what happened with the Access database.
That's what happened with Excel.
It took the capacity of accountants
to become software developers
because the tools became so accessible to them
that they could build a model
for how the business was gonna do next week.
That required a programmer prior to Excel.
Now it didn't because they could do it themselves
by coding enables non-programmers
to explore their ideas
in a way that I find absolutely wonderful.
But it doesn't make your a programmer.
- I agree with you, but I wanna allow for room
for both of us to be wrong.
For example, there could be,
vibe coding could actually be a skill.
That if you train it, and by vibe coding,
let's include the step of correction,
the iterative correction.
It's possible if you get really good at that,
that you're outperforming the people that run from scratch,
that you can come up with truly innovative things,
especially at this moment in history.
While the LLMs are a little bit too dumb
to create super novel things and a complete product,
but they're starting to creep close to that.
So if you are investing time now
into becoming a really good vibe coder,
maybe this is the right thing to do
as if it's indeed a skill,
we kind of meme about vibe coding,
just like sitting back and it's in the name.
But if you treat it seriously,
a competitive vibe coder
and get good at riding the wave of AI
and get good at the skill of editing code
versus writing code from scratch, it's possible
that you can actually get farther in the long term.
Maybe editing is a fundamentally different task
than writing from scratch
if you take that seriously as a skill that you develop.
To me that's an open question.
I just think, I personally, now you're on another level,
but just me, just personally,
I'm not as good at editing the code that I didn't write.
- No one is. - That's one different.
- No one is of this generation,
but maybe that's a skill.
Maybe if you get on the same page as the AI,
'cause there's a consistency to the AI.
It's like it really is a pair programmer
with a consistent style and structure and so on.
Plus with your own prompting,
you can control the kind of wrote code you write.
I mean, it could generally be a skill like.
- That's the dream of the prompt engineer.
I think it's complete pipe dream.
I don't think editors exist
that aren't good at writing.
I've written a number of books.
I've had a number of professional editors.
Not all of them wrote their own great books,
but all of them were great writers in some regard.
You cannot give someone pointers
if you don't know how to do it.
It's very difficult for an editor
to be able to spot what's wrong with a problem
if you that it couldn't make the solution themselves.
Editing, in my opinion, is the reward,
the capacity to be a good editor
is the reward you get from being a good doer.
You have to be a doer first.
Now that's not the same as saying that vibe coding,
prompt engineering won't be able to produce
fully formed amazing systems even shortly.
I think that's entirely possible,
but then there's no skill left,
which maybe is the greatest payoff at all.
Wasn't that the whole promise of AI anyway,
that it was just all natural language
that even my clumsy way of formulating a question
could result in a beautiful, succinct answer.
That actually to me is a much more appealing vision
that there's gonna be these special
prompt engineering wizards
who know how to tickle the AI
just write to produce what they want.
The beauty of AI is to think that someone
who doesn't know the first thing about
how AI actually works is able to formulate their idea
and their aspirations for what they want,
and the AI could somehow take that messy clump of ideas
and produce something that someone wants.
That's actually what programming has always been.
There's very often been people
who didn't know how to program, who wanted programs,
who then hired programmers,
who gave them messy descriptions of what they wanted
and then when the programmers delivered that back said,
"Oh no, actually that's not what I meant.
I want something else."
AI may be able to provide that cycle.
If that happens to the fullest extent of it,
yeah, there's not gonna be
as many programmers around, right?
But hopefully presumably someone still,
at least for the foreseeable future,
have to understand whether what the AI is producing
actually works or not.
- As a interesting case study,
maybe a thought experiment.
If I wanted to vibe code Basecamp or HEY,
and some of the products you've built,
like what would be the bottleneck?
Where would I fail along the way?
- What I've seen when I've been trying to do this,
trying to use vibe coding to build something real
is you actually failed really early.
The vibe coding is able to build a veneer
at the current present moment
of something that looks like it works, right?
But it's flawed in all sorts of ways.
There are the obvious ways, the meme ways
that it's leaking all your API keys,
it's storing your password in plain text.
I think that's ultimately solvable.
Like it's gonna figure that out
or at least it's gonna get better at that,
but its capacity to get lost in its own labyrinth
is very great right now.
It code something and then you wanna change something
and it becomes a game of whack-a-mole.
Real quick, Pieter Levels who've been doing this wonderful
flight simulator was talking to that
where at a certain scale,
the thing just keeps biting its own tail.
You wanna fix something
and it breaks five other things,
which I think is actually uniquely human
because that's how most bad programmers are.
At the certain level of complexity with the domain,
they can't fix one thing
without breaking three other things.
So in that way I'm actually
in some way it's almost a positive signal
for that the AI is gonna figure this out
because it's done an extremely human trajectory right now.
The kind of mistakes it's making
are the kind of mistakes the junior programmers
make all the time.
- Yeah, can we zoom out and look at the vision,
the manifesto, the doctrine of Rails?
What are some of the things
that make a programming language a framework great?
Especially for web development.
So we talked about happiness.
The underlying objective of Ruby.
What else?
- So you're looking at the nine points I wrote out
in I think 2012.
And first, before we dive into 'em,
I wanna say the reason I wrote it down
is that if you want a community to endure,
you have to record its values
and you have to record its practices.
If you don't, eventually you're gonna get enough
new people come in who have their own ideas
of where this thing should go.
And if we don't have a a guiding light
helping us to make decisions, we're gonna start flailing.
We're gonna start actually falling apart.
I think this is one of the key reasons
that institutions of all kinds start falling apart.
We forget why Chesterton's Fence is there.
We just go like, why is that fence there?
Let's yank it out.
Oh, it was to keep the wolves out.
Now we're all dead, oops.
So I wanted to write these things down.
And if we just take them quick one by one,
you talked about optimizing for programmer happiness.
I put that at number one in homage of Matz,
and that's a lot about accepting
that there is occasionally a trade off
between writing beautiful code
and other things we want out of systems.
There could be a runtime trade off,
there can be a performance trade off,
but we're gonna do it nonetheless.
We're also going to allow ambiguity
in a way that many programmers, by default,
are uncomfortable with.
I give the example actually here
of in the interactive Ruby shell
where you can play with the language
or even interact with your domain model.
You can quit it in two ways, at least that I found.
You can write exit.
Boom, you're out of the program.
You can write quit.
They do the same thing.
We just wrote both exit
or the people who built that wrote both exit and quit
because they knew humans were likely
to pick one or the other.
Python is the perfect contrast to this.
In the Python interactive protocol,
if you write exit, it won't exit.
It'll give you a lesson.
It'll basically tell you to read the fucking manual.
It says use exit parentheses
or Ctrl-D i.e. end of file to exit.
I'm like, one is very human and another is very engineer.
And I mean that both of them in the best possible way.
Python is pedantic.
Python is the value from the start stated
is that there should be preferably one
and only one way to do a certain thing.
Ruby is the complete opposite.
No, we want the full expression
that fits different human brains,
such that it seems like the language
is guessing just what they want.
- And part of that is also described
the principle of least surprise,
which is a difficult thing to engineer into a language
because you have to kind of, it's a subjective thing.
- Which is why you can't do it in one way,
which is why I used the example of both exit and quit.
The principle of least surprise
for some people would be like, "Oh, exit.
That's how I get out of the prompt."
For other people it'd be quit.
Why don't we just do both?
- Okay, so what's the convention over configuration?
That's a big one.
- That's a big one.
That's a huge one.
And it was born out of a frustration
I had in the early days with especially Java frameworks
where when you were setting up a web application framework
for Java back in the day,
it was not uncommon to literally
write hundreds if not thousands of lines
of XML configuration files.
Oh, I need this.
I want the database to use the foreign keys
as post_id.
No, no, no, I wanted as post capital ID.
Oh, no, no, no, you have to do it capital PID.
There are all these ways
where you can configure how foreign relation keys
should work in a database and none of them matter.
We just need to pick one, and then that's fine.
And if we pick one and we can depend on it,
it becomes a convention.
And if it's a convention, we don't have to configure it.
And if we don't have to configure it,
you can get started with you actually care
about much quicker.
So convention over configuration
is essentially to take that idea
that the system should come preassembled.
I'm not just handing you a box of fucking Legos
and asking you to build the Millennium Falcon.
I'm giving you a finished toy.
You can edit, you can change it,
it's still build out a Legos.
You can still take some pieces off
and put in some other pieces,
but I'm giving you the final product.
And this cuts against the grain
of what most programmers love.
They love a box of Legos.
They love to put everything together from scratch.
They love to make all these detailed little decisions
that just don't matter at all.
And I want to elevate that up
so that hey, I'm not trying to take the decisions
away from you.
I just want you to focus on decisions
that actually matter that you truly care about.
No one cares about whether it's post_id
or post ID or PID.
- Yeah, great defaults. - Yes.
- It's just a wonderful thing.
You have all these aspirations,
they're gonna do some kind of custom,
most beautiful Legos castle
that nobody's ever built from these pieces.
But in reality to be productive in most situations,
you just need to build the basic thing.
And then on top of that is where your creativity comes.
- Absolutely, and I think this is one of those,
part of the doctrine that a lot of programmers
who get to use Ruby on Rails
begrudgingly will acknowledge it's a nice thing,
even if they don't really like it.
Like it's hard to beat the sort of attraction
to building with Legos from scratch out of programmers.
That's just what we like.
This is why we're programmers in the first place
because we'd like to put these little pieces together,
but we can direct that instinct
towards a more productive end of the stack.
- Okay, what are some of the other ones?
- The menu is omakase.
It actually comes out of the same principle
that great defaults really matter.
If you look at everything
that's wrong with the JavaScript ecosystem right now,
for example, it is that no one is in charge of the menu.
There are a billion different dishes
and you can configure just your tailored specific
configuration of it,
but no one done the work to make sure it all fits together.
So you have all these unique problems
in the JavaScript ecosystem, for example,
there's probably 25 major ways
of just doing the controller layer.
And then as many of how to talk to the database.
So you get this permutation of n times n times n
of no one is using the same thing.
And if they are using the same thing,
they're only using the same thing for about five minutes.
So we have no retained wisdom.
We build up no durable skills.
Rails goes the complete opposite way of saying,
do you know what?
Rails is not just a white framework.
It's a complete attempt at solving the web problem.
It's a complete attempt at solving everything you need
to build a great web application.
And every piece of that puzzle
should ideally be in the box
pre-configured, preassembled.
If you want to change some of those pieces later,
that's wonderful.
But on day one you'll get a full menu
designed by a chef who really cared
about every piece of ingredient and you're gonna enjoy it.
And that's again, one of those things
where many programmers think like I know better.
And they do in some hyper local sense of it.
Every programmer knows better.
This is what Ruby is built on.
That every programmer knows better
in their specific situation.
Maybe they can do something dangerous.
Maybe they think they know better
and then they blow their foot off
and then they truly will know better
because they've blown their foot off once
and won't do it again.
But the the menu of omakase is that.
- So you in general
see the value in the in the monolith?
- Yes, the integrated system.
- Integrated. - That someone thought
of the whole problem.
This is one of the reasons why I've been on a crusade
against microservices since the term was coined.
Microservices was born out of essentially a good idea.
What do you do at Netflix scale
when you have thousands of engineers working
on millions of lines of code?
No one can keep that entire system
in their head at one time. You have to break it down.
Microservices can be a reasonable way to do that.
When you're at Netflix scale,
when you apply that pattern to a team of 20 programmers
working on a code base of half a million lines of code,
you're an idiot.
You just don't need to turn method invocations
into network calls.
It is the first rule of distributed programming.
Do not distribute your programming.
It is makes everything harder.
All the failure conditions
you have to consider as a programmer
just becomes infinitely harder
when there's a network cable involved.
So I hate the idea of premature decomposition
and microservices is exactly that.
The monolith says.
Let's try to focus on building a whole system
that a single human can actually understand
and push that paradigm as far as possible
by compressing all the concepts
such that more of it will fit into memory
of a single operating human.
And then we can have a system
where I can actually understand all the Basecamp.
I can actually understand all of HEY.
Both of those systems
are just over a hundred thousand lines of code.
I've seen people do this that maybe twice,
maybe three times that scale
and then it starts breaking down.
Once you get north of certainly
half a million lines of code,
no individual human can do it
and that's when you get into maybe some degree
of microservices can make sense.
- Basecamp and HEY are both a hundred thousand?
- A hundred thousand lines of code thereabouts.
- Wow, it's small.
- It is.
Considering the fact that Basecamp
I think has something like 420 screens,
different ways and configurations.
- Ah, do you include the front end in that?
- No, that's the Ruby code.
Well, it's front end in the sense
that some of that Ruby codes.
It's beneficial to the front,
but it's not JavaScript for example.
Now the other thing we might talk about later
is we write very little JavaScript actually
for all of our applications.
HEY, which is a Gmail competitor.
Gmail ships I think 28 megabytes
of uncompressed JavaScript.
If you compress it,
I think it's about six megabytes, 28 megabytes.
Think about how many lines of code that is.
When HEY launched, we shipped 40 kilobytes.
It's trying to solve the same problem.
You can solve the email client problem
with either 28 megabytes of uncompressed JavaScript
or with 40 kilobytes if you do things differently.
But that comes through the same problem essentially.
This is why I have fiercely fought
splitting front end and back end apart.
That, in my opinion, this was one of the great crimes
against web development.
That we are still atoning for.
That we separated and divided
what was and should be a unified problem solving mechanism.
When you are working both on front end and back end,
you understand the whole system.
And you're not going to get into these camps
that decompose and eventually you end up with like GraphQL.
- Okay, let's fly through the rest of the doctrine.
No one paradigm.
- No one paradigm goes to the fact that Ruby
is a fiercely object-oriented programming language
at its core, but it's also a functional program language.
This five times I told you about,
you can essentially do these anonymous function calls
and you can chain 'em together very much in the spirit
of how true functional programming languages worked.
Ruby has even moved closer
towards the functional programming
and of the scale by making strings immutable.
There are ideas from all different disciplines
and all different paradigms
of software development that can fit together.
Smalltalk, for example.
With only object oriented,
and that was just it.
Ruby tries to be mainly object oriented,
but borrow a little bit of functional programming,
a little bit of imperative programming,
be able to do all of that.
Rails tries to do the same thing.
We're not just gonna pick one paradigm
and run it through everything.
Object orientation is at the center of it,
but it's okay to invite all these other disciplines
and it's okay to be inspired.
It's okay to remix it.
I actually think one of the main benefits of Rails
is that it's a remix.
I didn't invent all these ideas.
I didn't come up with active record.
I didn't come up with the NBC
way of dividing an application.
I took all the great ideas
that I had learned and picked up from every different camp
and I put it together.
Not because there was gonna be just one single
overarching theory of everything,
but I was gonna have a cohesive unit
that incorporated the best from everywhere.
- Is that idea a bit at tension
with the beauty of the monolith system?
- I think the monolith can be thought of as quite roomy,
quite as a big tent that the monolith needs actually
to borrow a little bit of functional programming
for the kinds of problems that that excels,
that discipline excels at solving,
and that paradigm excels at solving.
If you also want object orientation at its core.
I actually think when I've looked
at functional programming languages,
there's a lot to love.
And then I see some of the crazy contortions
they have to go through
when part of the problem they're solving calls
for mutating something.
And you go like, holy shit,
this is a great paradigm from 90% of the problem.
And then you're twisting yourself completely out of shape
when you try to solve the last 10.
- Ooh, exalt beautiful code is in the next one.
- We've talked about that at length
and here's a great example that really summarizes
the domain specific language quality of Ruby on Rails
that you can make code actually pleasant to write and read.
Which is really funny to me
because as we talked about
when I started learning programming,
it wasn't even a consideration.
I didn't even know that that could be part of the premise,
that could be part of the solution.
That writing code could feel as good as writing a poem.
- class Project, ApplicationRecord
belongs_to :account has many participants.
Class_name, Person, validates_presence_of :name.
- See, you could read it out.
You didn't even change.
- Anything like a haiku or something.
- Right? Isn't that beautiful?
- Yeah, it's nice.
It's really nice.
There's an intuitive nature to it.
Okay, so I have specific questions there.
I mean ActiveRecord, just to take that tangent.
That has to be your favorite feature.
- It's the crown jewel of Rails.
It really is.
It is the defining characteristic
of how to work with Ruby on Rails.
And it's born in an interesting level of controversy,
because it actually uses a pattern
that had been described by Martin Fowler
in the "Patterns of Enterprise Application Architecture."
One of the greatest books
for anyone working on business systems.
And if you had not read it, you must pick it up immediately.
"Patterns of Enterprise Application Architecture,"
I think it was published in 2001.
It is one of the very few programming books
that I have read many times over.
It's incredible.
In it, Martin describes a bunch of different patterns
of how to build business systems essentially.
And ActiveRecord is a little bit of a footnote in there.
The pattern is literally called active record.
You can look it up. - Nice.
- It's called active record.
I wasn't even creative enough
to come up with a name of my own.
But it allows the creation,
the marriage of database and object orientation
in a way that a lot of programmers
find a little off-putting.
They don't actually want to pollute
the beautiful object-oriented nature
of that kind of programming with SQL.
There was a rant by Uncle Bob the other day about
how SQL is the worst thing ever.
Baba, okay fine, whatever, I don't care.
This is practical.
We are making CRUD applications.
You're taking things out of an HTML form
and you're sticking 'em into a damn database.
It's not more complicated than that.
The more abstractions you put in
between those two ends of the spectrum,
the more you're just fooling yourself.
This is what we're doing.
We're talking to SQL databases.
By the way, quick aside, SQL was one of those things
that have endured the onslaught
of NoSQL databases structured list data
for a better part of a decade
and still reign supreme.
SQL was a good thing to invest your time in learning.
Every program I'm working with the web
should know SQL to a fair degree.
Even if they're working with an ORM,
an optic relational map or as active record.
You still need to understand SQL.
What Active record does
is not so much try to abstract the SQL away
behind a different kind of paradigm.
It's just making it less cumbersome to write.
Making it more amenable to build
domain models on top of other domain models
in a ways that you don't have to write
every damn SQL statement by hand.
- We'll just say the active record is an ORM,
which is a layer that makes it intuitive
and human interpretable to communicate with a database.
- Even simpler than that.
It turns tables into classes and rows into objects.
I actually think SQL is very easy to understand most of it.
You can write some SQL golf too.
That's very hard to understand.
But SQL at its base,
and much of the criticism against SQL
was it was written for human consumption.
It's actually quite verbose,
especially if you're doing things
like inserts over and over again.
It's quite verbose insert into table parentheses,
enumerate every column you want to insert, values,
parentheses, every value that fits with that column.
It gets tedious to write SQL by hand,
but it's actually very humanly readable.
Active record just takes that tedious away.
It makes it possible to combine things in a way
that a humanly describable language just doesn't.
It composes things into methods
and you can combine these methods
and you can build structures around them.
So I don't dislike SQL,
I dislike a lot of things in programming.
I try to get rid of them.
SQL wasn't really one of them.
It was just a sense of I don't wanna write
the same thing over and over again.
It was a, can we be a little more succinct?
Can we match it just slightly better
to the optic orientation
without trying to hide away the fact
that we're persisting these objects into a database.
That's where I think a lot of ORMs went wrong.
They tried to live in the pure world of objects.
Never to consider that those objects
had to be consistent into a SQL database
and then they came up with convoluted way
of translating back and forth.
Active record says, do you know what?
Just accept it.
This record, this object is not gonna get saved
into some NoSQL database.
It's not gonna be saved.
It's gonna be saved into SQL database.
So it's just structure the whole thing around that.
It's gonna have attributes.
Those attributes are gonna respond
to columns in the database.
It's not more complicated than that stuff making it so.
- Yeah, but I should say, so I personally love SQL
because I'm an algorithms person
and so I love optimization.
I love to know how the databases actually work
so I can match the SQL queries
and the design of the table such that there is, you know,
optimal, squeeze the optimal performance out of the table.
Okay, based on the actual way that that table is used.
So I mean, I think that pushes to the point
that like there is value in learning in understanding SQL.
I wonder, because I started looking at active record
and it looks really awesome.
Does that make you lazy?
Not you, but a person that rolls in
and starts using Rails you can probably get away
with never really learning SQL, right?
- As long as you wanna stay
at the entry level of competence.
And this is actually my overarching mission with Rails
is to lower the barrier of entry so far down
that someone can start seeing stuff
on their browser without basically understanding anything.
Yeah, they can run Rail's new blog,
run a couple of generators, they have a whole system,
they don't understand anything.
But it's an invitation to learn more.
Where I get fired up,
and this ties back to the AI discussion,
is when that's turned into this meme,
that programmers no longer have to be competent.
I mean the AI is gonna figure it out.
The generators is gonna figure it out.
I don't need to know SQL,
active record is gonna abstract it away from me.
No, no, no dude, hold up.
The path here is competence.
I'm trying to teach you things.
I understand I can't teach you everything in five minutes.
No one who's ever become good at anything worthwhile
could be taught everything in five minutes.
If you wanna be a fully
well-rounded web application developer,
that takes years.
But you can actually become somewhat productive
in a few days. You can have fun in a few days for sure.
You're gonna have fun in a a few minutes and a few hours.
And over time, I can teach you a little more.
Active record says like, yeah, yeah.
All right, start to here
and then like next week we'll do a class on SQL.
- And actually you have this beautiful expression
that I love that that a great programming language.
Like Ruby has a soft ramp, the ramp goes to infinity.
- That's exactly right. - So yeah.
It's super accessible, super easy to get started.
- And it never stops.
There's always more to learn.
This is one of the reasons I'm still having fun programming.
That I'm still learning new things.
I can still incorporate new things.
The web is deep enough as a domain.
You're never gonna learn all of it.
- Provide sharp knives. - This is a good one,
because another way of saying this,
the opposite way of saying this,
the Java way of saying is do not provide foot guns, right?
I don't wanna give you sharp knives.
You're a child.
You can't handle a sharp knife.
Here's a dull butter knife.
Cut your damn steak, right?
That's a very frustrating experience.
You want a sharp knife
even though you might be able to cut yourself.
I trust humans in the same way that Matz trust humans.
Maybe you cut off a finger.
All right, you're not gonna do that again.
Thankfully it was a virtual think finger.
It's gonna grow back out.
Your competence is gonna grow.
It's more fun to work with sharp tools.
- And that actually contributes
to the the ramp that goes to infinity.
- Yes, to the learning
- Value integrated systems. - We kind of hit on that one.
This is Rails is trying to solve the whole problem
of the web, not just one little component.
It's not leaving you a bunch of pieces.
You have to put together yourself.
- Progress over stability.
- You know what?
If there's one that's dated,
it's probably that one.
At this stage, Rails has been incredibly stable
over many, many generations.
The last major release Rails 8
was basically a no upgrade
for anyone running Rail 7.
Rail 7 was almost a no upgrade
for anyone running Rail 6.
I used to think it required more churn
to get progress to stay on the leading edge of new stuff.
And I wrote this before I experienced the indignity
of the 2010s in the JavaScript community.
Where it seemed like stability was not just unvalued,
it was actually despised
that churn in and of itself was a value
we should be pursuing.
If you were still working with the same framework
three months later you were an idiot.
And I saw that and I actually recoiled.
And if I was gonna write the doctrine today,
I'd write that differently.
I wouldn't say progress over stability.
- Well maybe it'd be a function of the age
of the programming language also.
- Maybe, or a deeper understanding of the problem.
I think part of what's so fascinating about technology
is that we have this perception
that everything constantly moves so fast.
No, it doesn't.
Everything moves at a glacial pace.
There is occasionally a paradigm shift
like what's happening with AI right now.
Like what happened with the introduction
of the iPhone in 2007,
like what happened with the internet in '95.
That's basically the total sum of my career.
Three things changed.
Everything else in between
was incremental small improvements.
You can recognize a Rails application written in 2003.
I know because the Basecamp I wrote back then
is still operating, making millions of dollars in ARR,
servings in customers on the initial version
that was launched back then.
And it looks like the Rails code
if I squint a little that I would write today.
So most things don't change even in computing.
And that's actually a good thing.
We saw with the JavaScript ecosystem.
What happens when everyone
gets just mad about constant churn?
Things don't change that often.
- By the way, on that small tangent.
You just sort of visibly, verbally changed your mind
with the you of 15 years ago.
- Yes. - That's interesting.
Have you noticed yourself changing your mind
quite a bit over the years?
- I would say, oh yes.
And then also, oh no,
in the sense that there are absolutely fundamental things
both about human nature,
about institutions, about programming,
about business that I've changed my mind on.
And then I've also had experiences
that are almost even more interesting
where I thought I had changed my mind
and I tried it a new way,
realized why I had the original opinion in the first place
and then gone back to it.
So it happens both ways.
An example of the later part, for example,
was managers at 37signals.
For the longest time,
I would Rail against engineering managers
as an unnecessary burden
on a small or even medium sized company.
And at one point I actually started
doubting myself a little bit.
I started thinking like, do you know what?
Maybe all programmers do need a one-on-one therapy session
every week with their engineering manager
to be a whole individual.
So we tried that for a couple years
where we hired some very good engineering managers
who did engineering management
the way you're supposed to do it,
the way it's done all over the place.
And after that I thought like, no, no, I was right.
This was correct.
We should not have had managers.
Not every programmer needs a therapy session
with an engineering manager every week.
We don't need these and least scheduled huddles.
We don't need all these meetings.
We just need to leave people the hell alone
to work on problems that they enjoy
for long stretches of uninterrupted time.
That is where happiness is found.
That's where productivity is found.
And if you can get away with it, you absolutely should.
Engineering management is a necessary evil
when that breaks down.
- What's the case for managers then?
- The case for managers
is that if you do have a lot of people.
There's a bunch of work that kind of just crops up.
The one-on-one is one example
that programmers need someone to check in with.
There's another idealized version that someone needs
to guide the career of juniors, for example,
to give them redirecting feedback
and all this other stuff.
And it's not that in the abstract,
I don't agree with some of those things,
but in practice I've found
that they often create more problems that they solve.
And a good example here is can you get feedback
from someone who's not better at your job than you are?
You get some feedback.
You can get feedback on how you show up at work.
Are you being courteous to others?
Are you being a good communicator?
Okay, yes. But you can't get feedback on your work
and that's more important.
It's more important that you work
under and with someone who's better at your job
than you are if you wish to progress in your career.
And every single programmer I've ever worked with
was far more interested in progressing
in their career on that metric,
getting better at their craft
than they were in picking up pointers
that a middle manager could teach them.
That's not saying that there isn't value in it.
It's not saying there isn't value
in being a better person or a better communicator.
Of course there is all those things.
But if I have to choose one or the other,
I value competence higher.
Like that's again, I caveat this a million times
because I know what people sometimes hear.
They hear the genius asshole
is just fine and that's great
and you should excuse all sorts of malicious behavior
if someone's just really good at what they do.
I'm not saying that at all.
What I am saying is that the history of competence
is a history of learning
from people who are better than you,
and that relationship should take precedence over all else
and that relationship gets put aside a bit
when engineering managers introduced.
Now the funny thing is this conversation
ties back to the earlier things we were talking about.
Most engineering managers are actually former programmers.
They at least no program to some extent,
but what I've seen time and again
is that they lose their touch,
their feel with it very, very quickly
and turn into pointy haired bosses very, very quickly
who are really good at checking for updates.
Just seeing where we are on project A here
if you need anything or we ready to deliver.
Okay, yes.
And also, no.
Shut up, leave me the hell alone.
Let me program and then I'll come up for error.
I'll talk with other programmers
who I can spar with that we can learn something with.
I can turn the problems over with and we can move forward.
If you look back on the history of computer industry,
all the great innovation that's happened,
it's all been done by tiny teams
with no engineering managers.
Just full of highly skilled individuals.
You've had John Carmack on here.
I used to look up to its software so much.
Not just because I loved quick,
not just because I loved what they were doing,
but because he shared a bit about how the company worked.
There were no managers or maybe they had one business guy
doing some business stuff, but that was just to get paid.
Everything else was basically
just designers and programmers.
And there were about eight of them
and they created goddamn "Quake II."
So why do you need all these people again?
Why do you need all these managers again?
I think, again, at a certain scale it does break down.
It's hard to just have a hundred thousand programmers
running around wild without any
product mommies or daddies telling them what to do.
I understand that.
And then even as I say that, I also don't understand it.
Yeah, because if you look at something
like Gmail, for example,
there was like a side project done by Buchheit
at Google at the time.
So much of the enduring long-term value
of even all these huge companies
were created by people who didn't have a manager.
And that's not an accident,
that's a direct cause and effect.
So I've turned in some way even more militant
over the years against this notion of management,
at least for myself
and knowing who I am and how I wanna work.
Because the other part of this
is I don't want to be a manager,
and maybe this is just me projecting the fact
that I'm an introvert who don't like to talk
to people on one-on-one calls every week.
But it also encapsulates
how I was able to progress my career.
I did not really go to the next level with Ruby
or otherwise until I had a door I could close
and no one could bother me for six hours straight.
- So in companies probably one of the reasons
is it's very easy to hire managers,
and managers also delegate responsibility from you.
So if you just have a bunch of programmers running around,
you're kind of response like it's work,
it's intellectual work to have to deal
with the the first principles
of every problem that's going on.
So managers like you can like relax,
oh I'll be taken care of.
But they then hire their own managers
and it just multiplies and multiplies and multiplies.
I would love it if some of the great companies
would have in the United States,
if there was like an extra side branch
that we could always run,
maybe physicists can come up how to split the simulation
to where just all the managers are removed.
Also just in that branch,
just the PR and the comms people also.
And even the lawyers, just the engineers
and let's just see and then we merge it back.
- I've essentially run that branch
at 37signals for 20 years.
And I've experimented with forking back on the other side.
I've experimented with having a full-time lawyer on staff.
I've experimented with having engineering managers.
And I can tell you life is much better
at 50, 60 people when none of those individuals
or none of those roles.
It's never about the individuals.
It's about the roles.
None of those roles are in your organization fulltime.
Occasionally you need a manager.
Occasionally you need a lawyer.
I can play the role of manager occasionally, fine.
And then I can set it back down to zero.
It's almost like a cloud surface.
I wanna a manager service
I can call on for seven hours this week
and then I wanna take it down to zero
for the next three months.
- Yeah. I read. I don't know if this is still the case,
that Basecamp is an LLC and doesn't have a CFO,
like a full-time accountant.
Was that upgrade? - So the funniest.
These days, we do have a head of finance.
We did not for the first 19 years of life, I think.
We got away with basically
just an accountant do our books
in the same way you would do a small ice cream shop,
except we would over time have done
hundreds of millions of dollars in revenue.
The scale seemed quirky.
And at some point, you can also fall in love
with your own quirkiness
to a degree that isn't actually healthy.
And I've certainly done that over time
and we should have had someone mount
or count the beans
a little more diligently, a little earlier.
This was part of a blessing
of just being wildly profitable and selling software
that can have infinite margins basically
that you kind of can get away with a bunch of stuff
that you perhaps shouldn't.
What partially taught me this lesson
was when we realized we had not been collecting sales tax
in different US states where we had Nexus.
And it took us about two years
and $5 million in settlements
and cleanups to get out of that mess.
And after that I went like,
okay, fine, we can hire a finance person.
And we now have a wonderful finance person, Ron,
who actually ended up replacing something else.
We used to have a full-time data analytics
person who would do all sorts of insight mining
for why are people signing up for this thing.
We ran that for 10 years
and realized, you know what?
If I can have either a data analytics person
or an accountant, I'm picking the accountant.
- I love this so much on so many levels.
Can we just linger on that advice that you've given
that small teams are better?
I think that's really less.
Less is more.
What did you say before?
Worse is better.
Okay, I'm sorry.
- Worse better on adoption with technology
a lot of times.
And I think actually comes out at the same thing.
It comes out of the fact
that many of the great breakthroughs
are created by not even just tiny teams but individuals.
Individuals writing something.
And an individual writing something on some parameter,
what they do is worse.
Of course it's worse when one person has to make something
that a huge company have hundreds
if not thousands of developers
that they can have work on that problem.
But in so many other parameters
that worseness is the value,
that less is the value.
In getting real, which we wrote back in 2006.
We talk about this notion of less software.
When we first got started with Basecamp back in 2004,
people would ask us all the time,
aren't you petrified of Microsoft?
They have so many more resources.
They have so many more programmers.
What if they take a liking to your little niche here
and they show up
and they just throw a thousand programmers at the problem?
And my answer perhaps partly
because I was like 24 was first of all,
no, no care in the world.
But the real answer
was they're not gonna produce the same thing.
You cannot produce the kind of software that Basecamp is
with a team of a thousand people.
You will build the kind of software
that a thousand people builds.
And that's not the same thing at all.
So much of the main breakthrough
in both end user systems
but also in open source systems
and fundamental systems,
they're done by individuals or very small teams.
Even all these classical histories of Apple
has always been like, well it was a big organization
but then you had the team
that was actually working on the breakthrough.
It was four people.
It was eight people.
It was never 200.
- And large teams seems to slow things down.
- Yes. - It's so fascinating
and part of it's the manager thing.
- Because humans don't scale.
Communication between humans certainly don't scale.
You basically get the network cost effect
every time you add a new node, it goes up exponentially.
This is perhaps the key thing
of why I get to be so fond
of having no managers at Basecamp,
because our default team size is two.
One programmer, one designer, one feature.
When you're operating at that level of scale,
you don't need sophistication.
You don't need advanced methodologies.
You don't need multiple layers of management
because you can just do.
The magic of small teams is that they just do.
They don't have to argue
because we don't have to set direction,
we don't have to worry about the roadmap.
We can just sit down and make something
and then see if it's good.
When you can get away with just making things,
you don't have to plan.
And if you can get out of planning,
you can follow the truth
that emerges from the code, from the product,
from the thing you're working on in the moment.
You know far more about
what the great next step is,
when you're one step behind
rather than if you try 18 months in advance
to map out all the steps.
How do we get from here to very far away?
You know what?
That's difficult to imagine in advance
because humans are very poor at that.
Maybe AI one day will be much better than us,
but humans can take one foot
or put one foot in front of each other.
That's not that hard and that allows you
to get away with all that sophistication.
So the process has become much simpler.
You need far fewer people, it compounds.
You need much less process.
You need to waste less time in meetings.
You can just spend these long glorious days
and weeks of uninterrupted time
solving real problems you care about and that are valuable
and you're gonna find
that's what the market actually wants.
No one is buying something
because there's a huge company behind it.
Most of the time.
They're buying something because it's good.
And the way you get something good
is you don't sit around and have a meeting about it.
You try stuff.
You build stuff.
- It really is kind of incredible what one person,
honestly one person can do in 100 hours
of deep work of focused work, even less.
- So I'll tell you this,
I tracked exactly the number of hours
I spent on the first version of Basecamp.
And I was doing this because at the time
I was working on a contract basis for Jason,
he was paying me, I was gonna say $15 an hour.
That's what I got paid when we first got started.
I think he had bumped my pay to a glorious 25.
But I was billing him
and I know that the invoice
for the first vision of Basecamp was 400 hours.
That's what it took for one sole individual in 2004
to create an entire system that has then gone
on to gross hundreds of millions of dollars
and continues to do extremely well.
One person just me setting up everything.
Part of that story is Ruby.
Part of that story is Rails.
But a lot of it is also just me plus Jason,
plus Ryan, plus Matt.
That was the entire company at the time.
And we could create something of sheer sustaining value
with such a tiny team, because we were a tiny team.
Not to spite off.
Small is not a stepping stone.
This is the other thing that people get into their head.
This is one of the big topics of "Rework."
That it gave entrepreneurs
the permission to embrace being a small team.
Not as a way point, not as like I'm trying
to become a thousand people.
No, I actually like being a small team.
Small teams are more fun.
If you ask almost anyone,
I'm sure Tobi would say this too,
even at his scale,
the sheer enjoyment of building something
is in the enjoyment of building it with a tiny team.
Now you can have impact at a different scale
when you have a huge company.
I fully recognize that and I see the appeal of it.
But in the actual building of things,
it's always small teams, always.
- How do you protect the small team.
Basecamp has successfully stayed small.
Has been the dragon, and you had to fight off.
That like basically you make a lot of money.
There's a temptation to grow.
So how do you not grow?
- Don't take venture capital.
- Okay, that's step one. - That is point number one.
- First of all, - Point number two
everybody takes venture capital.
So you already went.
- I mean that's been the answer for the longest time.
Because the problem isn't just venture capital,
it's other people's money.
Once you take other people's money,
completely understandably, they want a return
and they would prefer to have the largest return possible.
'Cause not them sitting in the code.
It's not them getting the daily satisfaction
out of building something.
Chiseling beautiful code poems out of the editor, right?
They don't get that satisfaction.
They get the satisfaction maybe of seeing
something nice put into the world, that's fair.
But they certainly also get a satisfaction
of a higher return.
And there is this sense certainly in venture capital,
stated in venture capital
that the whole point of you taking the money
is to get to a billion dollars or more.
Now the path to that
usually does go through running established playbooks
and then when it comes to software,
the enterprise sales playbook is that playbook.
If you're doing B2B software SaaS,
you will try to find product market fit.
And the second you have it,
you will abandon your small and medium sized accounts
to chase the big whales with a huge sales force
and by then you're a thousand people and life sucks.
- That said, I mean people are just curious about this.
I've gotten a chance to get to know Jeff Bezos.
He invested in Basecamp, not controlling?
- He bought secondaries.
So this was the funny thing
is that when investing have these two dual meanings.
Normally when people think about investing,
they think you're putting in growth capital
because you want the business to hire more people
to do more R&Ds so they can grow bigger.
Bezos didn't do that actually.
He bought a ownership stake directly from Jason and I,
and 100% of the proceeds of that purchase
went into my and Jason's bank account,
personal bank account.
Not a single cent went into the account of the company
'cause we didn't need the money to grow.
What we needed or what we certainly enjoyed
was to some extent maybe the vote of confidence,
but more so the security
of taking a little bit off the table
is that we dare turn down the big bucks
from venture capitals.
It was essentially a vaccine
against wanting to take a larger check
from people who then wanted to take the company
to something enormous that we didn't want to go with it.
So Jeff gave Jason and I just enough money
that we were comfortable turning all these people down
in a way where if it had turned belly up
like six months later,
we wouldn't have been kicking ourselves
and going, we had something here that was worth millions
and now we have nothing
and I have to worry about rent and groceries again.
- It is a vote of confidence.
I wonder from, I'd love to hear Jeff's side of the story
of like why, 'cause he doesn't need like the money.
So it's really,
I think it probably is just believing in people
and wanting to have cool stuff be created in the world
and make money off of it, but not like.
- 100% the motivation for Jeff wasn't a return,
because he actually has a team.
He's private office that runs these investments
who did the calculus on the investment pitch we gave him,
which was so ridiculous
that Jason and I were laughing our asses off
when we were writing down our metrics.
I was like, no one's gonna pay this.
No one is gonna give us this multiple
of this amount of revenue.
And that's fine.
I mean we took the call
essentially out of kind of an awe
that Jeff Bezos even wanted to look at us and like,
do you know what?
We don't want venture capital.
We don't need other people's money,
but like let's just give him a bullshit number
that no sane person would actually say yes to.
And then I mean, we can each go our own way.
And his investment team said like, "Jeff, no way.
This makes no economic sense at all.
They're asking for way too much money
with way too little revenue."
And Jeff just went like, "I don't care.
I wanna invest in this guy."
Because to him at the time it was chump change, right?
Like Jason and I each got a few million dollars.
I mean whatever the currency swing
between the yen and the dollar
that day probably moved 10 x
that for his net worth than our investment did.
Jeff seemed genuinely interested
in being around interesting people,
interesting companies, helping someone go to distance.
And I actually look back on that relationship
with some degree of regret,
because I took that vote of confidence for granted
in ways that I'm a little bit ashamed of
over the years I've been more critical about
some of the things that Amazon had done
that I feel now is sort of justified.
So that's just sort of part of that processing of it.
But on the economic sense,
he gave us that confidence.
He gave us the economic confidence,
but then he also gave us the confidence of a CEO running
perhaps at the time the most important
internet business in the US.
Showing up to our calls,
which we would have with him like once a year
and basically just going like, yeah,
you guys are doing awesome stuff.
You should just keep doing awesome stuff.
I read your book, it's awesome.
You launched this thing, it's awesome.
You should just do more of that.
I don't actually know how to run your business.
You guys know it.
- So the book goes out.
I'm just so, from a fan perspective,
I'm curious about how Jeff Bezos was able to see,
'cause to me, you and Jason,
like especially humans in the space of tech.
And the fact that Jeff was able to see that, right?
How hard is it to see that?
- He certainly saw it very early.
And I think this is something that Jeff does better
than almost anyone else.
He spots that opportunity so far in advance
of anyone else even opened their eyes to it,
or certain he is willing to bet on it
far early and far harder than anyone else is.
And he's just right time and again.
I mean, we were not the only investment that he made.
And certainly Amazon had a extremely long-term vision.
So far longer than I have ever had the gumption to keep.
Like I think of myself as a long-term thinker.
I am playing a child's game
compared to the game that Jeff is playing.
Like when I looked at Amazon's economics
around the dot-com boom and bust, they looked ridiculous.
Like they were losing so much money.
They were so hated by the market they were...
no one believed that it was gonna turn
into what it is, but Jeff did.
In a way that that level of conviction I really aspire to.
And I think that's one of the main things
I've taken away from that relationship
is that you can just believe in yourself
to that degree against those odds.
That's ridiculous.
He did that at so many times our level
that it's pathetic if I'm doubting myself.
- Yeah, I think Amazon is one of those companies.
I mean, it's come under a bunch of criticism
over the years.
This is something about humans
that don't appreciate so much
that we take for granted the positive
that a thing brings real quick
and then we just start criticizing the thing.
It's the Wi-Fi and the airplanes.
- [DHH] That's exactly it.
- But I think Amazon,
there could be a case made that Amazon
is one of the greatest companies
in the last a hundred years
- For sure, I think it's an easy case to make.
What I also think is that the price you pay
to be one of the greatest companies
in the last a hundred years
is a lot of detractors, a lot of pushback,
a lot of criticism
that this is actually order restored in the universe.
One of my favorite teachers in all the time
I've been on the internet is Kathy Sierra.
I don't know if you know her work,
but she was actually Vern a few short years
before the cruel internet ran her off.
But she wrote a blog called Creating Passionate Users
and she carved into my brain
this notion of balance in the universe.
If you are creating something of value
that a lot of people love, you must create an equal
and opposite force of haters.
You cannot have people who love what you do
without also having people who hate what you do.
The only escape from that is mediocrity.
If you are so boring
and so uninteresting that no one gives a damn
whether you exist or not, yeah, you don't get the haters,
but you also don't get the impact of people
who really enjoy your work.
And I think Amazon is that just at the massive scale, right?
They brought so much value and change
to technology to commerce
that they must simply have a black hole size of haters,
otherwise the universe is simply gonna tip over.
- Let me ask you about small teams.
So you mentioned Jason a bunch of times, Jason Fried,
you have been partners for a long, long time.
Perhaps it's fair to say he's more
on the sort of the design business side
and you're like the tech, the engineering wizard.
How have you guys over all these years
creating so many amazing products, not murder each other?
It's a great story of like partnership.
What can you say about collaboration?
What can you say that about Jason that you love
that you've learned from?
Why does this work?
- So first I'll say we have tried
to murder each other several times over the years,
but far less, I think in the last decade.
In the early days,
our product discussions were so fierce
that when we were having them in the office
and there were other employees around,
some of them were legitimately worried
that the company was about to fall apart.
Because the volume coming out of the room
would be so high and sound so acrimonious,
that they were legitimately worried
the whole thing was gonna fall apart.
But you know what's funny
is that it never felt like that in the moment.
It always felt like just a peak vigorous search
for something better.
And that we were able to stomach
that level of adversity on the merits of an idea
because it was about the idea.
It wasn't about the person
and it never really got personal.
Not even never really, it didn't get personal.
It wasn't like, Jason, you're an asshole.
It was like, Jason, you're an idiot.
And you're an idiot
because you're looking at this problem the wrong way.
And let me tell you the right way to do it.
- As a small tangent, let me say this.
Some people have said, oh, probably return to this,
that you're sometimes can have flights of temper
on the internet and so on.
I never take it that way
because it is the same kind of ilk.
Maybe I haven't seen the right kind of traces of temper,
but usually it's about the idea
and it's just excited, passionate human.
- That's exactly what I like to think of it as.
It doesn't always come across as that.
And I can see why spectators in particular sometimes
would see something that looks like I'm going after
the man rather than the ball.
And I do think I've tried to get better at that.
But in my relationship with Jason,
I think it's worked so well
because we have our own distinct areas of competence
where we fully trust each other.
Jason trusts me to make the correct technical decisions.
I trust him to make the correct design
and product direction decisions,
and then we can overlap and share on the business,
on marketing, on writing, on other aspects of it.
So that's one thing is that if you're starting a business
with someone where you do exactly the same as they do
and you're constantly contesting
who's the more competent person,
I think that's far more difficult and far more volatile.
So if you're starting a business
and you're both programmers
and you both work on the same kind of programming,
ah, good luck.
I think that's hard.
I tried to pick an easier path
working with a designer where I knew
that at least half of the time
I could just delegate to his experience and competence
and say like, do you know what?
I may have an opinion,
I have an opinion all the time on design.
But I don't have to win the argument because I trust you.
Now occasionally we would have overlaps
on business or direction
where we'd both feel
like we had a strong stake in the game
and we both had a claim to competence in that area.
But then for whatever reason,
we also both had a long-term vision
were I would go, do you know what?
I think we're wrong here.
But as I learned from Jeff Bezos, by the way,
I'm gonna disagree and commit.
That was one of those early lessons
he gave us that was absolutely crucial
and perhaps even instrumental
in ensuring that Jason and I have been working together
for a quarter of a century.
Disagree and commit
is one of the old time Jeff Bezos greats.
- I'm just surprised that Yoko Ono hasn't come along.
You know what I mean?
Like there's so many Yokos in this world.
- It might have happened.
If not in part because we don't sit on each other's lap
all the time.
Most of our careers,
we haven't even lived in the same city.
Like I lived in Chicago for a couple of years
while we were getting going
after I'd moved to the US in 2005.
But then I moved to Malibu and then I lived in Spain
and then I lived in Copenhagen.
And Jason and I from the foundation of our relationship
learned how to work together
in a remarkably efficient way
where we didn't have to actually talk that much.
On any given week, I'd be surprised
if Jason and I spent more than two hours
of direct exchange and communication.
- Yeah, sometimes it's the basic human frictions
that you just accumulate. - Yes, I think you rub up
against another person,
that person well better be your spouse
if it's too much for too long.
- Yeah, but even there. - Even there.
- COVID has really test the relationship.
It's fascinating to watch.
- It has, and I do think that having some separation,
which is kind of counterintuitive
because I think a lot of people think
the more collaboration you can have, the better.
The more ideas that can bounce back and forth, the better.
And both Jason and I, for whatever reason,
came to the conclusion early on in careers.
Absolutely not, that's complete baloney.
This is why we were huge proponents of remote work.
This is why I enjoy working in my home office
where I can close the door and not see another human
for like six hours at the time.
I don't wanna bounce ideas off you all the time.
I wanna bounce ideas off you occasionally
and then I wanna go off and implement those ideas.
There's way too much bouncing going on
and not enough scoring, not enough dunking.
And I think this is one of the great traps
of executive rule.
Once a founder elevates themselves
all the way up to an executive
where what they're doing
is just telling other people what to do,
that's the realm they live in 24/7.
They just live in the idea realm.
Oh, I can just tell more people
more things what to do and we can just see it happen.
If you actually have to be part of implementing that,
you slow your horse.
You think like, do you know what?
I had a good idea last week.
I'm gonna save the rest of my good ideas
until next month.
- And there is a temptation for the managers
and for the people in the executive layer
to do something,
which that's something usually means a meeting, right?
And so that's why you say...
- Their job is telling other people what to do.
- Yeah, and the meeting,
so this is one of the big things you're against
is meeting... - Meetings are toxic.
And this really I think ties
into this with Jason and I.
If I had to count out the total number of meetings
we've had in 24 years of collaborations
where we in person sat in front of each other
and discussed a topic,
I probably it'd be less than whatever,
three months at a fan company.
We just haven't done that that much.
We haven't worn it out.
One of this funny metaphors
that Trump came up with at one point
was a human has like a limited number of steps
in their life, right?
Like that's the longevity argument here.
You could do so much activity and then you run out.
There's some kernel in that idea
that can be applied to relationship.
There's some amount of exchange we can have.
There's some amount of time we can spend together
where you can wear it out.
Jason and I were diligent about not wearing each other out.
And I think that is absolutely key
to the longevity of the relationship
combined with that level of trust.
And then just combining with the level
that we really like the work itself.
We don't just like the brainstorming.
The say where we just come up with good ideas.
No, we like to do the ideas
and we like to be part of that process directly ourselves.
I like to program, he likes to do design.
We could go off and do our little things
for long stretches of time.
In case you, come together
and go like, hey, let's launch a great product.
- This might sound like I'm asking you to do therapy,
but I find myself to sometimes
want or long for a meeting because I'm lonely.
Like 'cause it remote work is just sitting by yourself.
I don't know, it can get really lonely
for long stretches of time.
- Let me give you a tip, get a wife.
- Yes, oh, goddammit.
- Get a couple kids.
- [Lex] All right.
- Like family really is the great antidote to loneliness.
And I mean that as sincerely as I can possibly say it.
I certainly had exactly that feeling you described
early in my career
when I was working remotely and I was just a, like
me living in an apartment.
A total stereotype where for the longest time
when I first moved to Chicago,
all I had on the floor was a mattress
and then I bought this big TV and I didn't even mount it.
And then I had a stack of DVDs.
And I was basically,
I was working a lot of time
and then I would just go home and do that.
And it wasn't great.
It really wasn't.
Like I do think that humans need humans.
And if you can't get them at work
and I actually sort of kind of don't want them at work,
at least I don't want 'em for 40 hours a week.
That's not what I prefer.
You need something else.
You need other relationships in your life,
and there's no greater depth of relationship
if you can find someone
that you actually just wanna spend a lot of time with.
That's key to it.
And I think it's key for both Jason and I
that we've had families for quite a long time
and it grounds you two in a way
where the sprint of a startup
can get traded in for the marathon
of an enduring company.
And you get settled in a way.
We talked briefly about sometimes I get fired up.
I mean a lot of times,
maybe even most of the times I get fired up about topics,
but I don't get fired up in the same way now
as I used to when I was 24.
I'm still extremely passionate about ideas
and trying to find the right things,
but having a family meeting, my wife,
building a life around that
has just mellowed everything out
in a completely cliche way.
But I think it's actually key.
I think if we could get more even younger people
not to wait until they were in the late goddamn 30s
or early 40s to hitch up with someone,
we'd be better off
and we'd have more stable business relationships as well
because folks would get that nurturing human
relations somewhere else.
Now when I say all of that,
I also accept that there are plenty of great businesses
that's been built over the years
that have not been built remote,
that have been built by a gang of hooligans
sitting in an office for immense hours of time.
I mean, both John Carmack
and Tim Sweeney talked about that in the '90s
with their careers that that was just basically work, sleep,
hang out with the guys at the office, right?
A totally fair.
That never appealed to me.
Both Jason and I saw eye to eye on the idea
that 40 hours a week dedicated to work was enough
that if we were gonna go to distance
for not just the five to seven years
it takes to build a VC case up to an exit.
But for potentially 10 years, 20 years or further,
we needed to become whole humans.
Because the only that whole humanness
was gonna go to distance,
which included building up
friendships outside of work, having hobbies,
finding a mate and having a family.
And that entire higher existence,
those legs of the stool
that work is not the only thing in life
is completely related to the fact
that we've been around for 25 years.
There's way too much,
especially in America of false trade-offs.
Oh, you wanna build a successful business?
Well, you can either have money enjoyment
or family or health pick one.
What? Why do we have to give up all of this?
Now again, I'm not saying,
and there are moments of payers in life
where you can sprint.
But I am saying if that sprint turns into a decade,
you're gonna pay for it.
And you can pay for it in ways.
I've seen time and again
seem like a very bad trade that even if it works.
And by the way, most of the time it does not.
Most of the time startups go bust.
Most of the time people spend five, seven years
or something that does not pan out
and they don't get the payout
and then they just sit with regret of like,
what the fuck happened to my 20s?
Early on, Jason and I basically made the pact
that working together
was not gonna lead to that kind of regret.
That we were gonna allow ourselves and each other
to build a whole life outside of work.
And the fact that that worked
is something I feel is almost like forbidden knowledge,
certainly in technology circles in the US.
It's something that we've tried to champion for 20 years
and we still get slack.
For just two days ago, I had another Twitter beef
with someone saying like,
"Oh, well okay, maybe it worked,
but you didn't turn into Atlassian.
So you're a failure.
Basecamp isn't Jira, so why are you even bothering?"
And it's such a fascinating winner-takes-all mentality
that unless you dominate everyone else
in all the ways you've lost.
When so much of life is far more open to multiple winners
where we can end up with a business
that have made hundreds of millions of dollars
over the years,
and we've kept much of that to do whatever we want
and that's enough.
That's good, that's great.
That's actually something worth aspiring to.
Certainly it should be a path
for someone to consider choosing
rather than the VC unicorn of bust mentality
that dominates everything.
- Yeah, I'd love to ask you about this exchange
so you can explain to me the whole saga,
but so just to link on that a little bit
is I think there's a notion
that success for a tech founder
is like work for a few years all out
and then exit, sort of sell your company for, I don't know,
hundreds of millions of dollars.
That's success.
When it seems in reality,
when you look at who the people like you,
like really smart, creative humans,
who they actually are and what happiness entails.
It actually entails working your whole life a little bit.
It's like because you actually love the programming,
you love the building, you love the designer
and you don't want to exit.
And that's something you've talked about
really eloquently about.
So like you actually want to create a life
where you're always doing the building
and doing it in a way
that's not completely taken over your life.
- Mojito Island is a mirage.
It always was.
There is no retirement for ambitious people.
There is no just sitting back on the beach
and sipping a mojito for what?
For two weeks before you go damn crazy
and wanna get back into the action?
That's exactly what happens to most people
who have the capacity to build those kinds of exits.
I've never seen, I shouldn't say never.
I've almost never seen anyone be able to pull that off.
Yet so many think that that's why they're doing it.
That's why they're sacrificing everything.
Because once I get to the finish line, I'm golden.
I've won, I can retire, I can sit back, I can just relax.
And you find out
that that kind of relaxation is actually hell.
It's hell for creative people to squander
their God-given creative juices and capacities.
And I was really lucky to read the book "Flow"
by Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi
early on - Nice,
the pronunciations, spot on. - You know what?
I had to practice that
with AI over the last few days
because I knew I was gonna cite him
and I butchered his name several times.
So AI taught me how to pronounce that,
at least somewhat correctly.
But his main work over his career
was essentially the concept of flow
that came out of a search for understanding happiness.
Why are some people happy?
When are they happy?
And what he learned was quite illuminating.
He learned that people aren't happy
when they sit on Mojito Island.
They're not happy when they're free
of all obligations and responsibilities.
No, they're happy in these moments
where they're reaching and stretching their capacities
just beyond what they can currently do.
In those moments of flow,
they can forget time and space.
They can sit in front
of the key board program a hard problem,
think 20 minutes have passed
and suddenly it's been three hours.
They look back upon those moments
with the greatest amount of joy.
And that is what peak happiness is.
If you take away the pursuit of those kinds of problems,
if you eliminate all the problems from your plate,
you're gonna get depressed.
You're are not gonna have a good time.
Now there are people who can do that,
but they're not the same kind of people
who built these kinds of companies.
So you have to accept the kind of individual you are.
If you are on this path, don't bullshit yourself.
Don't bullshit yourself into thinking,
I'm just gonna sacrifice everything,
my health, my family, my hobbies, my friends,
but in 10 years I'm gonna make it all up
because in 10 years I can do it.
It never works out like that.
It doesn't work out on both ends of it.
It does not work out
if you're successful and you sell your company,
because you'll get bored out of your mind
after two weeks on retirement.
It doesn't work out if the company is a failure
and you regret the last 10 years spent for nothing.
It doesn't work out if it all works
and you stay in the business
because it never gets any easier.
So you're gonna fail on all metrics if you just go,
there's only work and nothing else.
And I didn't want that.
I wanted the happiness of flow.
I understood that insight was true,
but I wanted to do it in a way
where I could sustain the journey for 40 or 50 years.
- And there's another other interesting caveat
that I've heard you say
is that if you do exit and you sell your company
and you wanna stay in, you wanna do another company
that's going to usually not be as fulfilling.
Because really your first baby, like.
- You can't do it again or most people can't do it again.
A, because their second idea
is not gonna be as good as the first one.
It is so rare to capture lightning in the bottle
like we have, for example, with Basecamp.
I know this from experience
because I've been trying to build
a lot of other businesses since.
And some of them have been moderate successes,
even good successes, none of them have been Basecamp.
It's really difficult to do that twice.
But founders are arrogant pricks, including myself.
And we like to think that, do you know what?
We succeeded in large part because we're just awesome.
We're just so much better than everyone else.
And in some ways that's true some of the time.
But you can also be really good at something
that matters for a hot moment that door is open.
The door closes now you're still good at the thing,
but it doesn't matter.
No one cares.
There's that part of it.
And then there's the part of it that going back
to experience things for the first time
only happens the first time.
You can't do it again.
I don't know if I have it in me
to go through the of the early days again.
And I say bullshit in the sense of the most endearing sense.
It's all great to do it.
I know too much.
This is one of the reasons why,
whenever I'm asked the questions,
if you could tell your younger self
something that would really,
what would you say to your younger self?
I would fuck not say a thing.
I would not rob my younger self
of all the life experiences that I've been blessed
with due to the ignorance of how the world works.
Building up the wisdom about how the world works is a joy.
And you gotta build it one break at a time
if you just handed all the results.
It's like, oh, should we watch your movie?
Here's how it ends.
I don't wanna fucking watch the movie now.
You spoiled it.
I don't want you to spoil my business experience.
I don't wanna spoil any of my ignorance.
The greatest blessing half the time
when you're starting something new is A,
you don't know how hard it's gonna be;
B, you don't know what you don't know.
Like the adventure is to pay off,
the responsibility is to pay off.
This is something Jordan Peterson
has really taught me to articulate.
This notion that responsibility is actually key to me.
"Man's Search for Meaning,"
Viktor Frankl talks about this as well,
that we can endure any hardship if there's a reason why.
Now he talked about it in truly life altering
concentration can't waste.
But you can also apply at a smaller scale
with less criticality
of even just your daily life
that all that hardship in building the original business
that is responsibility
you take upon yourself the appeal.
The reason you take that on you
is in part because you don't know fully what it entails.
If you had known upfront, if I had known upfront,
how hard it would be?
How much frustration there'd be along the way?
If you just told me that in a narrative
before I got started, I would've been like, eh,
maybe I should just go get a job.
- You said so many smart things there.
Just to pick one.
It's funny that sometimes the advice givers,
the wisdom givers have gone through all the bullshit.
And so there is a degree
to which you wanna make the mistake.
So I think I would still give the advice of you
want to have a stretch of your life
where you work too hard, including a thing that fails.
I don't think you can learn the lessons
why that's a bad idea in any other way except by doing it.
There is a degree like, but of course you don't.
- I think you should stretch.
Should you have to stretch for a decade?
I'm not so sure.
- Yeah, the decade thing is 20s is a special time.
- It's a lot to trade.
You don't get your 20s back.
Yeah, you don't get your 30s back.
You don't get your 40s back.
You really, I would've regretted personally
if I hadn't done the other things I did in my 20s,
if I hadn't had the fun I had,
if I hadn't had the friends I had,
if I hadn't built up the hobbies that I did,
if I hadn't started driving race cars
at an early enough age to actually get really good at it,
if I had just gone all in on business
because I would've got the same out in the end.
This is something Derek Sivers really taught me
is he has this great essay
about how when he went for a bike ride,
he could go really hard all out
and he could do the ride I think in whatever 19 minutes.
Or he could enjoy the ride, go 5% slower,
do the ride in 21 minutes
and realize there's only two minutes apart.
Either I go all in all the time, there's nothing else,
I'm completely exhausted at the alt.
Or I travel the same distance
and I arrive maybe two minutes later,
but I got to enjoy the scenery,
listen to the birds, smell the flowers.
That journey is also valuable.
Now I say that while accepting and celebrating
that if you wanna be the best at one thing in the world,
no, you have to sacrifice everything.
You have to be obsessed with just that thing.
There is no instant
of someone who's the best in the world at something
who's not completely obsessed at.
I didn't need to be the best at anything.
This was a rare blessing of humility
I had early on is like, do you know what?
I am not that smart.
I'm not that good.
I'm not that talented.
I can do interesting things
by combining different aspects and elements that I know,
but I'm not gonna be the best at anything.
And that released me from this singular obsession
with just going,
I'm gonna be the best programmer in the world.
Eh, I know I'm not.
I failed at it twice
before I even got how conditional it's worked.
I'm not smart enough to be the best at anything.
I'm not dedicated enough to do that.
That's a bit of a blessing.
And I think as a society, we have to straddle
both celebrating peak excellence,
which we do all the time
and celebrating the peak intensity
of mission it takes to become that.
And then also going like, do you know what?
We don't all need to be Michael Jordan.
There's only gonna be one of those.
- Well, we should say that there's certain pursuits
where a singular obsession is required.
Basketball is one of them.
By the way, probably racing.
If you wanna be the best at F1 in the world...
- If you wanna be Senna, you gotta be a maniac.
- But I would argue
that there's most disciplines like programming
allows if you want to be, quote, unquote, "the best,"
whatever that means,
I think that's judged at the end of your life.
And usually if you look at that path,
it's gonna be an nonlinear one.
It you're not gonna look like the life
of an Olympic athlete who's singular focus.
There's gonna be some acid there in the 20s
or there's going to be a several detours,
which the true greats.
There's gonna be detours.
And sometimes they're not gonna be
Steve Jobs asset type of situation.
There'll be just different companies
you've worked for different careers
or different sort of efforts
you allocated your life to.
But it's gonna be non-linear.
It's not gonna be a singular focus.
- The way I think about this sometimes
is I want a good bargain on learning.
I can become in the top 5%
of whatever I defined as good at something
much, much easier.
Perhaps it's 20 times easier, 100 times easier
to get into the top 5% than it is to get into the top 0.1%.
That's almost impossibly hard to get into that.
But if I'm content just being in the top 5%,
I can be in the top 5% on like five things at once.
I can get really good at writing.
I can get decent at driving a race car.
I can become pretty good at programming.
I can run a company.
I can have a family.
I can do a lot of things at the same time.
That gives me sort of that variety
that almost was idealized Karl Marx has this idea,
"Oh, I'm gonna fish in the morning
and hammer in the evening
and paint on the weekends, right?"
That there's a sense for me at least
where his diagnosis of alienation was true.
That just that tunnel vision.
There's just this one thing I'm just gonna focus on that
gives me a sense of alienation I can't stomach.
When I'm really deep on programming
and sometimes I go deep for weeks,
maybe even in a few cases months,
I have to come up for air
and I have to go do something else.
Like, all right, that was programming for this year.
I've done my part and I'm gonna go off riding
or annoy people on the internet
or drive some race cars to do something else.
And then I can do the programming thing
with full intensity again next year.
- Speaking of annoying people on the internet,
you gotta explain to me this drama.
Okay, so what is this guy that said,
imagine losing to Jira but boasting
that you have a couple million dollars per year.
So this had to do with this almost now a meme decision
to leave the cloud.
DHH left the cloud.
I think that's literally a meme,
but it's also a fascinating decision.
Can you talk through the full saga of DHH
leaves the cloud?
- Yes. - Of leaving AWS saving money.
And I guess the case this person is making now.
- Is that we wasted our time optimizing a business
that could've been a hundred times bigger
if we'd just gone for the moon.
- And for the moon includes?
- Venture capital. - But also...
- And other things in not caring about cost.
- But also because AGIs are on the corner,
you should have been investing into AI, right?
Is this just part of? - Sort of tank ginger?
I think it's a bit of a muddy argument,
but if we just take it at it's peak ideal,
which I actually think is a reasonable point,
is that you can get myopically focused on counting pennies
when you should be focused on getting, right?
That I've optimized our spend on infrastructure
by getting out of the cloud
and that took some time and I could have taken that time
and spend it on making more features
that would've attract more customers
or spend even more time with AI or done other things.
Opportunity cost is real.
I'm not denying that.
I'm pushing back on the idea that for a company of our size
saving $2 million a year on our infrastructure bill,
which is about somewhere between half to two thirds
goes directly to the bottom line,
which means it's return to Jason or I as owners
and our employees part of our profit sharing plan,
is totally worth doing.
This idea that costs don't matter
is a very Silicon Valley way of thinking
that again, understand at the scale of something maybe,
but I also actually think it's aesthetically unpleasing.
I find an inefficient business
as I find an inefficient program full of line noise
to just be a splinter in my brain.
I hate looking at an expense report
and just seeing disproportionate waste.
And when I was looking at our spend
at 37signals a while back, a few years back,
I saw bills that did not pass my smell test.
I remembered how much we used to spend
on infrastructure before the cloud
and I saw numbers I could not recognize
in proportion to what we needed.
The fact that computers had gotten so much faster over time,
shouldn't things be getting cheaper?
Why are we spending more and more money
servicing more customers?
Yes, but with much faster computers,
Moore's Law should be lowering the costs
and the opposite is happening.
Why is that happening?
And that started a journey of unwinding
why the cloud isn't as great as the deal
as people like to think that.
- Yeah, can we look at the specifics
just for people who don't know the story
and then generalize to what it means about
the role of the cloud and the tech business.
So the specifics is you were using AWS S3 for...
- We were using AWS for everything.
HEY.com launched as an entirely cloud app.
It was completely on AWS for compute,
for databases, for all of it.
We were using all the systems
as they're best prescribed that we should.
Our total cloud bill for Basecamp,
our total spend with AWS was I think 3.2 million
or 3.4 million at its peak.
That's kind of a lot of money.
3.4 million, I mean we have a ton of users and customers,
but still that just struck me as unreasonable.
And the reason why it was so unreasonable
was because I had the pitch for the cloud
ringing in my ears.
Hey, this is gonna be faster.
This is gonna be easier.
This is gonna be cheaper.
Why are you trying to produce your own power, right?
Like, do you have your own power plant?
Why would you do that?
Leave the computers to the hyperscalers.
They're much better at it anyway.
I actually thought that was a compelling pitch.
I bought in on that pitch for several years
and thought, do you know what?
I'm done ever owning a server again.
We are just gonna render our capacity
and Amazon is gonna be able to offer us services
much cheaper than we could buy 'em themselves
because they're gonna have these economies of scale.
And I was thinking Jeff's word ringing.
My competitors margin is my opportunity.
That was something he used to drive amazon.com with.
That if he could just make 2%
when the other guy was trying to make 4%,
he would end up with all the money.
And on volume, he would still win.
So I thought that was the operating ethos for AWS.
It turns out that's not true at all.
AWS by the way operates its almost 40% margin.
So just in that, there's a clue
that competitors are not able to do the competitive thing
we like about capitalism,
which is to lower costs and so forth.
So the cloud pitch in my optics,
it's fundamentally false.
It did not get easier first of all.
I dunno if you've used AWS recently,
it is hella complicated.
If you think Linux is hard,
you've never tried to set up IAM rules
or access parameters or whatever for AWS.
- AWS is always difficult.
It was always complicated.
- Well, I think it's gotten even more difficult.
But yes, now some of that is it's difficult
because it's very capable
and you have a bunch of capacity on tap.
And there are reasons I don't think they're good enough
to justify how complicated
the whole jing-a-ma-jing has become.
But what's certainly true is that it's no longer easier.
It's not easier to use AWS
than it is to run your own machines,
which we learned when we pulled out the cloud
and didn't hire a single extra person.
Even though we operate all our own hardware,
the team stayed exactly the same.
So you have this three-way pitch, right?
It's gonna be easier,
it's gonna be cheaper.
Certainly wasn't cheaper.
We've just proved that
by cutting our spend on infrastructure
by half to two thirds.
And it's gonna be faster.
The last bit was true,
but way too many people overestimated
the value of that speed.
If you need a thousand computers online
in the next 15 minutes, nothing beats the cloud.
How would you even procure that?
If we just need another 20 servers,
it's gonna take a week or two
to get boxes shipped on pallets
delivered to a data center and unwrapped and racked,
and all that stuff, right?
But how often do we need to do that?
And how often do we need to do that
if buying those servers is way, way cheaper
so we get vastly more compute
for the same amount of money.
Could we just buy more servers
and not even care about the fact
that we're not hyper optimized on the compute utility?
That we don't have to use things like automatic scaling
to figure things out because we have to reduce costs?
Yes, we can.
So we went through this journey over a realization
in early 2023
when I had finally had enough with our bills.
I wanted to get rid of them. I wanted to spend less money.
I wanted to keep more of the money ourselves.
And in just over six months,
we moved seven major applications out of the cloud
in terms of compute caching databases
to works onto our own servers.
A glorious, beautiful new fleet bought
from the king of servers, Michael Dell,
who really, by the way, is another icon
on my, I saw he just celebrated 41 years in business.
41 years this man has been selling awesome servers
that we've been using for our entire existence.
But anyway, these pallets arrive in a couple of weeks
and we rack 'em up and get everything going.
And we were out.
At least with the compute part.
We then had a long multi-year commitment to S3
because the only way to get decent pricing
in the cloud, by the way,
is not to buy on a day-to-day basis,
not to rent on a database basis,
but to bind yourself up to multi-year contracts
with computes often a year.
That was in our case and with storage is was four years.
We signed a four-year contract
to store our petabytes of customer files in the cloud,
to be able to get something just halfway decent affordable.
So all of these projects came together to the sense
that we're now saving literally millions of dollars,
projected about 10 million over five years.
It's always hard.
How do you do the accounting exactly,
and TOC this, that and the other thing.
But it's millions of dollars.
But it's not just that.
It's also the fact that getting out of the cloud
meant returning to more of an original idea of the internet.
That the internet was not the sign
such that three computers should run everything.
It was a distributed network
such that the individual nodes
could disappear and the whole thing would still carry on.
DARPA had designed this such that the Russians
could take out Washington
and they could still fight back from New York,
that the entire communication infrastructure
wouldn't disappear because there was no hub and spoke.
It was a network.
I always found that an immensely beautiful vision.
That you could have this glorious internet
and no single node was in control of everything.
And we've returned to much more of a single
node controlling everything
idea with these hyperscalers.
When US-East-1, the main and original region
for AWS goes offline,
which has happened more than a few times over the years.
Seemingly a third of the internet is offline.
Like that in itself is just an insult to DARPA's design.
It just detract from the fact
that what AWS built was marvelous.
I think the cloud has moved so many things so far forward,
especially around virtualization, automation setup.
It's all those giant forward for system administration
that's allowing us now
to be able to run things on-prem in a way
that smells and feels much like the cloud
just at half the cost or less,
and with the autonomy
and the satisfaction of owning hardware.
I don't know what the last time you looked at
like an actual server and took it apart
and looked inside of it.
These things are gorgeous.
I mean, I posted a couple of pictures
of our racks out in the data center
and people always go crazy for 'em
because we've gotten so abstracted
from what the underlying metal looks like
in this cloud age that most people have no idea.
They've no idea how powerful a modern CPU is.
They have no idea
how much RAM you can fit into a one U rack.
Progress in computing has been really exciting,
especially I'd say in the last four to five years
after TSMC with Apple's help really pushed the envelope.
I mean, we kind of sat still there for a while
while Intel was spinning their wheels going nowhere.
And then TSMC with Apple propelling them
really moved things forward.
And now servers are exciting again.
Like you're getting jumps year over year and the 15, 20%
rather than the single digit we were stuck with for a while.
And that all means that owning your own hardware
is a more feasible proposition than it's ever been.
That you need fewer machines to run ever more
and that more people should do it.
Because as much as I love Jeff and Amazon,
like he doesn't need another whatever,
40% margin on all the tech stuff
that I buy to run our business.
And this is just something I've been focused on.
Both because of the ideology
around honoring DARPA's original design,
the practicality of running our own hardware,
seeing how fast we can push things
with the latest machines and then saving the money.
And that has all been so enjoyable to do,
but also so counterintuitive for a lot of people
because it seemed,
I think for a lot of people in the industry
that like we'd all decided
that we were done buying computers,
that that was something we would just delegate to AWS
and Azure and Google Cloud,
that we didn't have to own these things anymore.
So I think there's a little bit of whiplash
for some people that, "Oh, I thought we agreed.
We were done with that."
And then along come us
and say, "Ah, do you know what?
Maybe you should have a computer."
- Is there some pain points to running your own servers?
- Oh, plenty.
There's pain points to operating computers of all kind.
Have you tried just like
using a personal computer these days?
Half the time when my kids or my wife
have a problem, I go like,
have you tried turning it just off and on again.
Computers are inherently painful to humans.
Owning your own computer though
kind of makes some of that pain worth it.
There's a responsibility
that comes with actually owning the hardware that to me,
at least make the burden of operating
that hardware seem slightly more enjoyable.
Now there are things you have to learn,
certainly at our scale too.
I mean, we're not just buying a single computer
and plugging into an ethernet.
We have to have racks and racks with them
and you gotta set it up with network cabling
and there is some specialized expertise in that,
but it's not like that expertise
is like building nuclear rockets.
It's not like it's not widely distributed.
Literally the entire internet
was built on people knowing
how to plug in a computer to the internet, right?
Oh, ethernet cable goes here, power cable goes here,
let's boot up Linux.
That's how everyone put anything online
until 10, 12 years ago
when the cloud sort of took over.
So the expertise is there and can be rediscovered.
You too can learn how to operate a Linux computer.
- Yeah, and it's, you know, when you get a bunch of them,
there's a bunch of flashing LEDs
and it's just so exciting. - Oh, they're beautiful,
calming, amazing.
Computers are really fun.
This is actually something I've gotten into even deeper
after we moved out of the cloud.
Now my next kind of tingle
is that if you could move out of the cloud,
can you also move out of the data center?
Personal servers have gotten really scarily
quick and efficient
and personal internet connections
rival what we connected data centers with
just a decade or two ago.
So there's a whole community
around this concept of home lapping,
which is essentially installing server hardware
in your own apartment, connecting it to the internet,
and exposing that directly to the internet.
That harks back to those glorious days of the '90s
when people building for the internet
would host the actual website
on their actual computer in the closet.
And I'm pretty fired up about that.
I'm doing a bunch of experiments.
I've ordered a bunch of home servers
from my own apartment.
I marvel at the fact
that I can get a five gigabit, five connection now,
I think, do you know what five gigabit
that could have taken Basecamp
to multiple millions of MRR
in the way that back then,
I ran the whole business on a single box
with 2004 technology or probably a hundred megabit cable.
Like the capacity we have access to
both in terms of compute and connectivity
is something that people haven't readjusted to.
And this happens sometimes in technology
where progress sneaks up on you.
This happened with SSDs.
I love that, by the way.
We designed so much of our technology
and storage approach and database design
around spinning metal disks
that had certain seek rate properties.
And then we went to NVMe and SSDs,
and it took quite a while for people to realize
that the systems had to be built
fundamentally different now.
That the difference between memory and disk
was now far smaller
when you weren't spinning these metal plates around
with a little head that had to read off them.
You were essentially just dealing
with another type of memory.
I think we're a little bit in that same phase
when it comes to the capacity of new businesses
to be launched literally out of your damn bedroom.
- So you can get pretty far with a large user based
with home labing?
- Absolutely. - That's exciting.
That's like the old school.
That's really exciting, right?
- It's bringing back the startup in the garage
in the literal physical sense of the word.
Now some of that is do we need to,
you can get relatively cheap cloud capacity
if you don't need very much.
- Hell yes, we need to.
I mean the feeling of doing that by yourself
of seeing LED lights in your own home.
I mean there's nothing like that.
- There's just an aesthetic to it
that I am completely in love with
and I wanna try to push on.
Now it's not gonna be the same
thing as getting out of the cloud.
I'm not sure our exit out of the cloud
was not the exit out of the data center.
We basically just bought hardware,
shipped it to a professionally managed data center
that we didn't even actually touch.
This is the other misconception people have about
moving out of the cloud.
That we have a bunch of people
who are constantly driving to a data center somewhere
to rack new boxes and change dead RAM.
That's not how things happen in the modern world at all.
We have a company called Summit, previously Deft,
that is what we call white gloves.
They work in the data center
when we need something like,
"Hey Deft, can you go down and swap the dead SSD
in box number six?"
They do it.
And what we see is akin to what someone working
with the cloud would see.
You see IP addresses coming online.
You see drives coming online.
It's not that different,
but it is a whole heck of a lot cheaper
when you are operating at our scale.
And of course it is.
Of course it's cheaper to own things
if you need those things for years
rather than it is to rent it.
In no other domain would we confuse those two things
that it's cheaper to own for the long duration
than it is to rent.
- There is some gray area, like I've gotten a chance
to interact with the xAI team a bunch.
I'm probably going back out there in Memphis
to do a big podcast associated with the Grok release.
And those folks, in order to achieve the speed
of building up the cluster
and to solve some of the novel aspects
that have to do with the GPU, with the training,
they have to be a little bit more hands on.
It's a less white glove.
- Oh, and I love that, right?
They're dealing with a frontier problem
and they're dealing with it not by renting a bunch of GPUs
at a huge markup from their main competitor.
They're going like, "No, screw that.
We're gonna put a hundred thousand GPUs
in our own tents," right?
And build it in absolute record time.
So I think if anything, this is testament to the idea
that owning hardware can give you an advantage
both at the small scale, at the medium scale
and at the pioneer levels of computing.
- By the way, you know, speaking of teams,
that those are xAI,
Tesla are large companies, but all those folks,
I don't know what it is about,
you said Jeff is really good at finding good people,
at seeing strength in people.
Like Elon is also extremely,
I don't know what that is.
Actually, I've never actually seen,
maybe you could speak to that.
He's good at finding greatness.
- I don't think he's finding as much as he's attracting.
He's attracting the talent
because of the audacious of his goals and his mission.
The clarity by which he states it.
He doesn't have to go scour the earth
to find the best people.
The best people come to him
because he is, talking about Elon here,
one of the singular most invigorating figures.
In both the same order of the universe here,
haters and lovers, right?
Like he's having such an impact at such a scale
that of course he's gotta have literally
millions of people think
he's the worst person in the world
and he's also gonna have millions of people thinking
he's the greatest gift to humanity.
Depending on the day.
I'm somewhere in between.
But I'm more on the greatest gift to humanity
end of the scale than I'm on the other end of the scale.
And I think that really inspires people in a way
that we've almost forgotten
that that level of audacity is so rare that when we see it,
we don't fully know how to analyze it.
We think of Elon as finding great talent
and I'm sure he is also good at that.
But I also think that this beacon of the mission,
we're going to fucking Mars.
We're gonna transform transportation
into using electricity.
We're gonna cover the earth in internet
is so grand that there are days where I wake up and go like,
what the fuck am I doing with these to-do lists?
Like Jesus, should I go sign up for something like that?
Yeah, that sounds invigorating in a sense.
I can only imagine like a biking back
in 10, 50 going like, should we go to Normandy?
You may die along the way,
but oh boy, does that sound like a journey
and an adventure.
- There's a few components.
There's one definitely this bigger than life mission
and really believing it.
You know, every other sentence is about Mars,
like really believing it.
It doesn't really matter what,
like anybody else, the criticism, anything.
There's a very singular focused big mission.
But I think it also has to do a bunch
of the other components.
Like being able to hire well once the people,
once the beacon attracts.
And I've just seen people that don't necessarily on paper
have a resume with the track record.
I've seen really who now turned out
to be like legendary people.
He basically like tosses 'em the ball of leadership.
Sees something in them and says like, "You go."
And gives them the ownership and they run with it.
And that happens at every scale.
That there's a real meritocracy.
And like there's something,
there's just like, you could see the flourishing
of human intellect in these meetings,
in these group getting together where they're like,
the energy is palpable.
It's like exciting for me to just be around that.
There's not many companies I've seen that
in because when a company becomes successful and larger,
it somehow suffocates that energy.
I guess you see in startups at the early stages.
But like it's cool to see it at a large company
that's actually able to achieve scale, you know?
- I think part of the secret there
is that Elon actually knows things.
And when you know things,
you can evaluate the quality of work products.
And when you can evaluate the quality of work products,
you can very quickly tell who's full of shit
and who will actually take you to Mars.
And you can fire the people who's full of shit
and you can bet on the people who get us to Mars.
That capacity to directly evaluate
the competency of individuals,
it's actually a little bit rare.
It's not widely distributed
amongst managers, hiring managers.
It's not something you can easily delegate
to people who are not very skilled at the work itself.
And Elon obviously knows a lot about a lot
and he can smell who knows stuff for real.
And is this at our tiny scale,
something I've tried to do in the same order
where when we hire programmers, for example,
it's gonna be interesting now with AI
as the new challenge.
But up until this point,
the main pivot point for getting hired
was not your resume,
was not the schooling you've had,
it was not your grades, was not your pedigree,
it was how well you did on two things.
A, your cover letter.
Because I can only work with people remotely
if they're good writers.
So if you can't pen a proper capital letter
and can't bother to put in the effort
to write it specifically for us, you're out.
Two, you have to be able to program really well
to the degree that I can look at your code
and go like, yeah, I wanna work with that person.
Not only I wanna work with that person,
I wanna work on that person's code
when I have to see it again in five years
to fix some damn bug.
So we're gonna give you a programming test
that simulates the way we work for real
and we're gonna see how you do.
And I've been surprised time and again
where I thought for sure this candidate is a shoe-in,
they sound just right, the CV is just right
and then you see the code getting turned in.
I'm like, no way.
No way are we hiring this person.
And the other way has been true as well.
I've go like, I don't know about this guy or this woman.
Eh, I dunno.
And then they turn in their coach stuff
and I'm like, holy shit,
can that person be on my team tomorrow, preferably?
The capacity to evaluate work product
is a superpower when it comes to hiring.
- There's a step that I've seen Elon do really well,
which is be able to show up and say,
this can be done simpler.
- [DHH] Yes.
- But he knows what he's talking about.
And then the engineer,
because Elon knows enough,
the engineer who's first reaction,
you can kind of tell like,
it's almost like rolling your eyes
if your parent tells you something.
This is not, no, we've I've been working
on this for a month, you don't...
But then when you have that conversation a little more,
you realize no, it can be done simpler.
Find the way.
So there's a good, when two engineers are talking,
one might not have perfect information.
But if the senior engineer has like good instinct
that's like been battle earned,
then you can say simplify.
And it actually will result in simplification.
- And I think this is the hallmark of the true greats.
That they not only have the insight
into what's required to do the work,
but they also have the transcendent vision
to go beyond what the engineer would do,
the programmer would do.
I think if we are looking at these rarities,
obviously the myth of Steve Jobs was also this.
Even though perhaps he was less technical
than Elon is in many ways,
he had the same capacity to show up to a product team
and really challenge them
to look harder for the simplification
or for making things greater
in a way that would garner disbelief
from the people who are supposed to do it.
Like this guy is full of shit.
Like this is crazy.
We can never, and then two months later it is.
So there is something of this
where you need the vision,
you need it anchored by the reality
of knowing enough about what's possible,
knowing enough about physics,
knowing enough about software,
that you're not just building bullshit.
There are plenty of people who can tell
a group of engineers.
No, just do it faster.
Like that's not a skill.
It's gotta be anchored in something real,
but it's also gonna be anchored in, it's a tired word,
but a passion for the outcome to a degree
where you get personally insulted if a bad job is done.
This is what I've been writing about lately with Apple.
They've lost that asshole
who would show up and tell engineers
that what they did was not good enough
in ways that would actually perhaps
make them feel a little small in the moment,
but would spark that zest to really fix it.
Now they have a logistics person
who's very good at sourcing components
and lining up production Gantt charts,
but you're not getting that magic.
Now what's interesting with that whole scenario
was I actually thought how well Tim Cook ran things
and has run things at Apple for so long
that maybe we were wrong.
Maybe we were wrong about the criticality of Steve Jobs
to the whole mission.
Maybe you could get away with not having it.
I think the bill was going to come later and now it has.
Apple is failing in all these ways
that someone who would blow up Steve's ghost
and really insult him would say like, see?
This is what's happening now.
So the other thing here too, of course,
is it's impossible to divorce.
Like your perception of what's a critical component
of the system and the messy reality
of a million different moving parts
in the reality of life.
And you should be skeptical about your own analysis
and your own thesis at all time.
- Since you mentioned Apple, I have to ask
somebody in the internet submitted the question.
Does DHH still hate Apple?
I believe the question is.
So there was a time
when Basecamp went to war with Apple over the 30%.
Can you tell the saga of that battle?
- Yes, but first I'll tell you,
I fell in love with Apple,
which was all the way back in also early 2000s
when Microsoft was dominating the industry
in a way we now see Apple
and Google dominate mobile phones.
Microsoft was just everything
when it came to personal computers,
and I really did not like the Microsoft of the '90s.
The Microsoft of the '90s was the cutoff the air supply
to Netscape kind of characters
was the Bill Gates sitting defiant
in an interview with the DOJ
asking about what the definition of what is.
And just overall unpleasant, I think.
You can have respect for what was achieved,
but I certainly didn't like it.
And as we've talked about,
I came begrudgingly to the PC after Commodore fell apart
and I couldn't continue to use the Amiga.
So I already had a bit of a bone to pick with PCs
just over the fact that I love my Amiga so much.
But then in the early 2000s,
Apple emerged as a credible alternative
because they bet the new generation of Macs
on Unix underpinnings.
And that allowed me to escape from Microsoft,
and suddenly I became one of the biggest boosters of Apple.
I was in my graduating class
at the Copenhagen Business School.
I started with the first white iBook,
first person using Mac.
And by the time we were done in graduating,
I had basically converted half the class
to using Apple computers,
'cause I would evangelize them so hard
and demonstrate them
and do all the things that a super fan would do.
And I continued that work over many years.
Jason or I actually in I think 2004, 2005,
did an ad for Apple
that they posted on the developer side
where we were all about like Apple is so integral
to everything that we do and we look up to them
and we are inspired by them.
And that love relationship actually
continued for a very long time.
I basically just became a Mac person for 20 years.
I didn't even care about looking at PCs.
It seemed irrelevant to me, whatever Microsoft was doing,
which felt like such a relief.
Because in the '90s,
I felt like I couldn't escape Microsoft
and suddenly I had found my escape.
And now I was with Apple and it was glorious
and they shared so many of my sensibilities
and my aesthetics and they kept pushing the envelope,
and there was so much to be proud of,
so much to look up to.
And then that sort of started to change with the iPhone,
which is weird because the iPhone is what made modern Apple.
It's what I lined up in 2007 together
with Jason for five hours to stand in the line
to buy a first generation product
where Apple staff would clap at you
when you walked out the store.
I don't know if you remember that. It was a whole ceremony
and it was part of that myth and mystique and awe of Apple.
So I wasn't in the market for other computers.
I wasn't in the market for other computer ideas.
I thought perhaps I'd be with the Mac
until the end of days.
But as Apple discovered the gold mine,
it is to operate a toll booth
where you don't have to innovate,
where you don't actually even have to make anything,
where you can just take 30%
of other people's business.
There was a rot that crept into the foundation
of Apple and that started all the way back
from the initial launch of the app store.
But I don't think we saw at the time,
I didn't see at the time
just how critical the mobile phone
would become to computing in general.
I thought when the iPhone came out that like,
oh, it's like a mobile phone.
I've had a mobile phone since the early '90s.
Well, it wasn't a mobile phone.
It was a mobile computer.
And even more than that,
it was the most important computer
or it would become the most important computer
for most people around the world.
Which meant that if you liked to make software
and wanted to sell it to people,
you had to go through that computer.
And if going through that computer meant
going through Apple's toll booth
and not just having to ask them permission,
which in and of itself was just an dignity.
When you're used to the internet
where you don't have to ask anyone permission
about anything, you buy a domain
and you launch a business
and if customers show up, boom, you're success.
And if they don't, well you're a failure.
Now suddenly before you could even launch,
you'd have to ask Apple for permission.
That always sat wrong with me.
But it wasn't until we launched HEY in 2001
that I saw the full extent of the rot
that has snug into Apple's apple.
- For people who don't know
and we'll talk about it,
HEY is this amazing email
sort of attempt to solve the email problem.
- Yes, I like to pitch it as what Gmail
would've been with 20 years of lessons applied
in a way where they could actually ship.
Gmail was incredible when it launched in 2004.
And it still is a great product
but it's also trapped in its initial success.
You can't redesign Gmail today,
it just has way too many users.
So if you want fresh thinking on email,
I wanted fresh thinking on email.
I needed to build my own email system.
And not just my own email client.
That's what a lot of people have done over the years.
They build a client for Gmail,
but you're severely constrained
if you don't control the email server as well.
If you really wanna move the ball forward with email,
you have to control both the server and the client.
And that was the audacious mission
we set out to do with HEY.
And that was what's funny,
I thought our main obstacle here would be Gmail.
It's the 800 pound gorilla in the email space.
Something like 70% of all email in the US
is sent through Gmail.
I think their world rates
are probably in that neighborhood as well.
They're just absolutely huge
and trying to attack an enormous established competitor
like that who's so actually still loved
by plenty of people.
And is free seems like a suicide mission.
And it was only a mission we signed up for
because we had grown ambitious enough
after making Basecamp for 20 years
that we thought we could tackle that problem.
So I thought, hey, this is dumb.
I would not advise anyone to go head to head with Gmail.
That seems like a suicide mission.
We're gonna try anyway, because you know what?
If we fail it's gonna be fine.
We're just gonna build a better email experience
for me and Jason and the people at the company
and our cat, and that'll be okay
'cause we're gonna afford to do so.
But when we got ready to launch,
after spending two years building this product,
millions of dollars in investment to it.
We obviously needed mobile apps.
You're not gonna be a serious contender with email
if you're not on a mobile phone
and you need to be there with a native client.
So we had built a great native client
for both iOS and for Android.
And as we were getting ready to launch,
we submitted both of them to the app stores,
got both of them approved on I think Friday afternoon
for the iOS app.
And we then went live on Monday.
And we were so excited.
Hey world, we've been working on this new thing,
I'd love for you to check it out.
And of course as with anything,
when you launch a new product, there are some bugs.
So we quickly found a few in the iOS client
and submitted a new build to Apple.
Hey, here's our bug faces, can you please update?
And that's when on help broke loose.
Not only were they not gonna prove our update,
they said, oh wait a minute,
we gave you permission to be in the app store,
but I'm sorry that was a mistake.
We see that you're not using our in-app payment system,
which means that we don't get 30% of your business.
You will have to rectify that
or you can't be in the app store.
And first I thought like, well it got approved already.
We're running on the same model.
We've run Basecamp on in the app store for a decade.
If you're not signing up through the app
and we're signing up our own customers on our own website
and they're just going to the app store
to download their companion app, we're gonna be fine.
That was the truth, right?
That was why I never got so fired up about the app store.
Even as Apple started tightening the screws
was like my business was okay.
Now suddenly my business wasn't okay.
Apple was willing to destroy HEY if we did not agree
to give them 30% of all the signups
that came through the iOS app.
And it wasn't just about the 30%.
It was also about splitting
and not longer having a direct relationship
with our customers.
When you sell an app in the app store,
you're not selling an app to a customer.
You're selling an app to inventory at Apple,
and then Apple sells an app to that customer.
That customer has a purchasing relationship with Apple.
So if you wanna give discounts or refunds or whatever,
it's complete hell.
If you want to easily support multi-platform
that's complete hell if someone signs up
for HEY on their iPhone and they wanna switch to Android.
But that billing relationship, it's tied to Apple,
it's complete hell.
For a million reasons,
I did not want to hand my business over to Apple.
I did not want to hand 30% of our revenue over to Apple.
So we decided to do something
that seemingly Apple had never heard before.
We said no, we're not gonna add the in-app payment.
I don't care if you're threatening us.
this is not fair,
this is not reasonable, please approve.
And of course they didn't and it escalated.
And after a couple of days we realized, you know what?
This isn't a mistake.
This isn't going away.
We're gonna be dead if they go through with this.
If we're not gonna yield and give them the 30%,
they're gonna kick us off unless we make such a racket
such noise that they will regret it.
And that's exactly what then happened.
We were blessed by the fact that we launched HEY
one week before the WWDC,
their Worldwide Developer Conference.
Where Apple loves to get up on stage
and harp on how much they do for developers,
how much they love them
and why you should bill for their new devices
and so on and so forth.
And then we also just happened
to have a platform on the internet,
which is very convenient when you need to go to war
with a $3 trillion company.
So I started kicking and screaming
- Oh boy. - And essentially
turning it up to 11 in terms of the fight
and going public with our or denial to be in the app store.
And that turned into a prolonged
two week battle with Apple
that essentially ended in the best possible outcome
we could have gotten as David fighting Goliath,
which was a bit of a truce.
We wouldn't hand 30% over to Apple.
They do wouldn't kick us out of the app store,
but we had to build some bullshit dummy account
such that the app did something when you downloaded it.
That was a rule that Phil Schiller seemingly made up
on the fly when pressed for the fifth time
by the media about why we couldn't be in the app store
when a million other companion apps could.
But we just happened to be able to create so much pain
and noise for Apple that it was easier for them
to just let us be than to keep on fighting.
- What do you think about Tim Sweeney's victory
with Epic over Apple?
- I think it is incredible
and the entire developer ecosystem.
Not just on iOS but on Android as well,
owe Epic, Tim Sweeney
and Mark Rein, an enormous debt of gratitude
for taking on the only battle
that has ever inflicted a series wound on Apple
in this entire sorted campaign of monopoly enforcement.
And that is Epic's fight versus them.
Tim recently revealed
that it has cost well over a hundred million dollars
in legal fees to carry on this battle against Apple.
We, for a hot moment, considered suing Apple
when they were threatening to kick us out.
We shopped the case around with a few law firms
and perhaps of course they would tell us
you have a good case.
I mean they're trying to sell a product here,
but they would also tell us.
- It's gonna cost a minimum of $10 million
and it's gonna take five
to seven years through all the appeals.
Now we now learned the actual price tag
was 10 times higher, right?
Epic spend over 100 million.
It would've destroyed us
to take on Apple in the legal realm.
Only a company like Epic could do it
and only a company run by founders Like Tim,
like Mark could risk the business
in the way that they did,
the audacity they had to provoke
the fight in the first place,
which I thought was just incredible.
And to stick with it for the long term,
no board would've signed off on this lawsuit
to a professional CEO, no freaking way.
So the fact that they've been able to beat Apple
in also the most hilarious way possible,
I think it's just incredible.
'Cause remember their first victory
in the case was actually not much of a victory.
There were about 11 counts in the trial.
Apple basically won 10 of them
and the judge awarded Epic this one little win
that Apple couldn't tell 'em not to link out to the internet
to be able to do the payment processing.
So they won this one little thing.
And Apple, instead of just taking the 10 out of 11 wins
and going fine, you can have your little links
but all these other rules stay in place
decided to essentially commit criminal contempt of court
as they've now been referred to for prosecution
and angered the judge to such a degree
that the rule of law in the US now
is that you can launch an app in the app store.
And you don't have to use in-app payment,
but you can have a direct billing relationship
with a customer if you just link out to the open internet
when you take the credit card
and then hop back into the app.
And we owe all of that to Tim and Mark.
We owe all of that to Epic.
We're gonna launch new apps any minute now,
I hope actually next week to take advantage of this
that revamp the hey apps so that people
who download the Hey app off the Apple app store
can sign up in the app and can then use the web
to put in their credit card so we don't have to pay 30%.
Instead we have a direct billing relationship
and such that they can take that subscription to Android,
to PCs, whatever without any hassle.
And we have Tim and Mark to thank for it.
- Yeah, Tim, I mean, like you said founders
but also specific kind of founders.
'Cause I think maybe you can educate me on this,
but Tim is somebody who maintains.
to this day sort of the unreasonableness of principles.
Yes, that's what I love.
I think sometimes maybe even
with founders you can get worn down.
It's a large company.
There's a lot of smart, quote, unquote,
people around you lawyers and just whispering
your ear over time
and you're like, well just be reasonable being a, you know,
this is a different thing.
And to be the sort of maintain,
I mean Steve Jobs did this.
Still are the asshole.
Who' says, "No,
I'll sink this whole fucking company over this."
- That's the exact language basically I used
in our original campaign.
I will burn this business down
before I hand over 30% of it to Apple.
And that sort of indignation,
that actual rage is something I try
to be a little careful about tapping into
because it is a little bit of a volatile compound.
Because I mean I have a bunch of employees,
we have a bunch of customers.
It would be pretty sad if the journey of 37 signals
after 25 years would come to an end
because Apple would burn us down
or I would burn the business down
over this fight with Apple.
But I think you also need that level of conviction
to be able to even drive the day-to-day decisions.
One of the other Apple examples,
and I know we're racking on Apple a little bit here,
and I don't actually hate them.
I really don't.
I am tremendously disappointed
at the squandered relationship that did not need
to be sold away for so little.
Now I understand that the app store toll booth
is actually a pretty big business.
It's multiple billions,
but Apple is a trillion dollar company.
And I think in the lens of history,
this is gonna come off as a tremendous mistake
and I think it's already coming off as a tremendous mistake.
The flop that was the Vision Pro
was partly because Apple had pissed off
every other developer.
No one was eager to come build the kind of experiences
for their new hardware
that would perhaps have made it a success.
So when you're on top and you have all the cards,
you can dilute yourself into thinking
that you can dictate all terms at all times
and there are no long term consequences.
Apple is learning finally,
the fact that there are long-term consequences
and that developers actually
are important to Apple's business.
And the relationship is not entirely one sided.
We don't owe our existence to Apple and Apple alone.
We've built our own customer bases.
Apple has been beneficial to the industry.
I'm glad the iPhone exists, da da da da.
It's not that it doesn't go both ways,
but Apple wants it only one way.
And I think that is a mistake,
and it's a mistake that was avoidable.
And A, that's disappointing.
Certainly disappointing for me.
I've literally spent 20 years
evangelizing this shit, right?
I've spent so much money buying Apple hardware,
excusing a bunch of things they've done over the years.
And then for what?
For the fact that you wanted 30% of something
that I created in the most unreasonable way possible?
Couldn't we have found a better way to do this?
I think they're going to get forced to do a better way.
But did you also have to go through the indignity
of having a criminal contempt charge
against you getting referred to prosecution?
It just seems so beneath Apple,
but it also seems so in line
with what happens to huge companies
who are run by, quote, unquote, "professional managers"
rather than founders and unreasonable people.
- Well, we should probably also say
that the thing you love about Apple,
the great spirit of Apple I think still persists
and there's a case to be made that this 30% thing
is a slice, a particular slice of a company,
not a defining aspect of the company.
And that it Apple is still on top in the hardware
that it makes and a lot of things that it makes.
And you know this is, that could be just a hiccup
in a long story of a great company
that does a lot of awesome stuff for humanity.
So like Apple is a truly special company.
We mentioned Amazon, there is no company like Apple.
- I agree, this is why the disappointment
is all greater.
Because we had such high aspirations
and expectations to Apple
that they were the shining city on the hill
and they were guiding the industry
in a million positive ways.
I think as we talked about earlier,
hardware is exciting again
in large part because Apple bought PA Semi
and pursued a against all odds
mission to get ARM up to the level it is today.
And we have these incredible M chips now because of it.
And the design sensibilities
that Apple bring to the table are unparalleled.
No one has taste certainly at the hardware level
like Apple does, even at the software level.
I'd say there's a lot of taste left in Apple,
but there's also some real sour taste now.
So they have to wash that off first I think
before they find their wear back.
But Apple's been in a mirage before,
I mean Wozniak and Steve Jobs
started this thing in the garage,
has great success with the Apple II.
He hands the company over to a sugar drink salesman
who tanks the company into the '90s.
He doesn't learn the lesson,
spends the next 20 years building up this amazing company,
then hands the company over again to a logistics person
who presumably had more redeeming qualities
than the first guy who put in charge,
but still ends up leading the company astray.
Now this is the norm.
The norm is that great companies don't last forever.
In the long arc of history,
almost no company lasts forever.
There are very few companies around
that was here 100 years ago,
even fewer 200 years ago.
And virtually nothing that are 1000 years old
outside of a handful of Japanese sorts makers
or something like that, right?
So you can get diluted into thinking
that something is forever when you're in the moment.
And they seem so large.
Apple could absolutely stumble
and I think they have more reason to stumble now than ever.
They're behind on AI, terribly behind.
Their software quality is faltering in a bunch of ways.
The competition is catching up on the hardware game
in part because TSMC is not an Apple subsidiary,
but a foundry that services a MD and NVIDIA and others
who are now able to use the same kind of advanced processes.
This is something I learned
after not looking at PC hardware for the longest time,
that holy smokes, AMD actually makes CPUs
that are just as fast, if not faster than apples.
They're not quite as efficient yet
because ARM has some fundamental efficiencies over x86,
but they're still pretty good.
So Apple should have reason to worry.
Apple's shareholders should have reason to be concerned.
Not just about all these stumbles,
but also by the fact that Apple is run by old people.
Apple's board has an average age of, I think, 75.
Their entire executive team is above 60.
Now that sounds horribly ageist.
And in some ways, it a little bit is.
In the same way, I'm ageist against myself.
Like I'm 45 now and I sort of kind of have to force myself
to really get into AI because it is such a paradigm shift
and a lot of people when they reach a certain age
are just happy to stay with what they know.
They don't wanna go back to being a beginner.
They don't wanna go back to having to relearn everything.
And I think like, ah, this is a little hard for me at 45.
How the hell do you do that at 75?
- I have to come back to, you mentioned it earlier,
you're a parent.
Can you speak to the impact that becoming a father
has had on your life?
- I think what's funny about fatherhood is that for me,
I wasn't even sure it's something I wanted.
It took meeting the right woman
and letting her convince me
That this was the right idea before we even got started.
I didn't have starting my own family
on the list of priorities
in my late 20s or even early 30s.
It was really the impetus of meeting my wife Jamie
and her telling me this is what I want.
I wanna have a family.
I wanna get married.
I wanna have kids.
I wanna have three.
And me going for a second like whoa, whoa, whoa.
And then eh, all right, let's do it.
And I think that's the kind of happy accident
where some parts of my life have been very driven,
where I knew exactly what I wanted
and how to push forward to it
and what the payoff was going to be.
But when it comes to having a family,
that always felt like a very fuzzy abstract idea
that sure, someday, maybe.
And then it became very concrete
because I met a woman who knew what she wanted.
And looking back on it now,
it almost seems crazy.
Like there's this fork in the road of reality.
Where if that hadn't happened
and I had been sitting here now,
not being a father, not having a family,
the level of regret knowing what I know now about
the joys of having that family
would've been existential, would've been...
I don't know if they would've been devastating.
I think men have a little bit of a longer window
to pursue these things than women do.
There are just certain biological facts.
But ending up with the family I have now,
ending up with my three boys have been
just a transformative experience in the sense
that here's something that turned out
to be the most important thing.
And it was an open secret.
Not even an open secret.
It was an open truth through all of history.
You listen to anyone who's ever had children,
they will all say,
"My children are the most important to me."
Yet somehow that wisdom couldn't sink in
until you were in the situation yourself.
I find those truths fascinating
when you can't actually relay them with words.
I can tell you, Hey Lex, what are you doing?
Get a wife,
make some kids,
get a move on it.
And these are just words.
They're not communicating the gravity
of what it actually feels to go through the experience.
And you can't really learn it without going through it.
Now of course you could be influenced and whatever,
we can all help contribute and little sparks
and little seeds can grow in your your mind about it.
But it still has to happen.
And now that I am in this situation
and just the sheer joy on a daily basis
where you think your level of life satisfaction
is on a scale of one to 10,
and then the satisfaction
of seeing your children understand something,
accomplish something, learn something,
do something, just be.
Just goes like, oh my god,
the scale doesn't go from one to 10.
It goes from one to 100.
And I've been playing down here
in the one to 10 range all this time.
And there's a one to 100
that has been humbling
in a way that is impactful in and of itself.
This whole idea that I thought I had a fair understanding
of like the boundaries of life in my early 30s,
like what is this about?
I mean, I've been on this earth long enough now
here to know something.
And you realize, I don't know, I did not know.
I did not know that the scale was much broader.
And I've often talked about joys of having kids
and just seeing your own DNA,
which is remarkable to me
because literally that's been the pursuit of humans
since the dawn of time.
I am here today because whatever, 30,000 years ago,
some Neanderthal had the same realization
that I should procreate
and I should continue my bloodline.
And that that all amounts to me sitting here now.
But it didn't become a practical reality to me
before meeting the right woman.
And I think that that's sometimes
not part of the conversation enough
that there's something broken at the moment
about how people pair up in the western world.
And it's at the source of why
we're not having enough children
because there's not enough couples,
there's not enough marriage.
There's not a lot of these...
There's not enough of all these traditional values
that even 50, 60, 70 years ago
was just taken for granted.
We're in this grand experiment
of what happens if we just remove a bunch of institutions?
What happens if we no longer value marriage
as a something to aspire to?
What happened if parenthood is now seen in some camps?
It's almost something like weird
or against your own self-expression.
It's a grand experiment
that I'm kind of curious how it turns out.
I prefer to watch it as a movie
like the "Children of Men," I'm like, that was a good show.
I kind of wish that wasn't reality.
But we're seeing that reality play out
while I'm sitting here in a very traditional
two parent loving household with three children,
and going, this is now at the top.
I've done a lot of things in my life.
I've built software, I've built companies,
I've raced cars, I've done all sorts of things,
and I would trade all of it in a heartbeat for my kids.
That's just a really fascinating human experience
that the depth of that bond
is something you can't appreciate before you have it.
But I also think there is a role to play, to talk it up.
Because we're being bombarded constantly
with reasons why not to.
Oh, it's too expensive.
Well, you could get divorced and then you might lose half.
There's all these voices
constantly articulating the case against marriage,
the case against having children
that those of us who've chosen to do the traditional thing
to get married and to have children have an obligation
to kind of talk it up a little bit,
which would've seen ridiculous again 50 years ago
that you'd have to talk up
something so fundamental of that.
But I have become kind of obligated
in that sense to do just that.
To talk it up, to say, you know what?
You can look at everything that I've done
and if you like some of those parts
realize that to me in this situation,
the kids, the family, the wife
is more important than all of it.
And it sounds like a cliche
because you've heard it a thousand times before.
And by becoming a cliche,
maybe you start believing it's not true
that it's just something people say, but it is reality.
I know almost no parents
that I have personal relationships with
that don't consider their children
to be the most important thing in their life.
- So there's a lot of interesting things you said.
So one, it does seem to be,
I know a lot of parents,
perhaps more interestingly,
I know a lot of super successful people who are parents
who really love their kids
and who say that the kids even help them
to be more successful.
Now the interesting thing,
speaking to what you're saying
is it does seem for us humans,
it's easier to articulate the negatives
because they're sort of concrete, pragmatic, you know,
it costs more, it takes some time, you know,
they can be, you know, crying all over the place.
They're, you know, tiny narcissists
running around or whatever.
- Which is all true.
- Yeah, pooping everywhere, that kind of stuff.
But to articulate the thing you were speaking to
of there's this little creature
that you love more than anything
you've ever loved in your life.
It's hard to convert that into words.
You have to really experience it.
But I believe it and I want to experience that,
but I believe 'cause just from a scientific method,
have seen a lot of people
who are not honestly not very capable of love,
fall completely in love with their kids.
Like, you know, very sort of...
let's just call it what it is, engineers
that are very like boop bop.
They just fall in love.
And it's like, all right, people who just like you said,
they don't really want, they don't really care
or don't really think about having kids that kind of stuff
once they do it changes everything.
So, you know, but it's hard to convert it into words.
- One of the reasons I think
is also difficult is, I mean, I like kids.
Not that I actively disliked them,
but when I was around other people's kids,
I didn't have a emotional reaction.
Some women have, right?
They see a baby and they go, "Oh."
I never had any emotion of that.
I mean, I could appreciate,
I'm glad for you that you have children.
It did not provoke anything in me.
The emotions that are provoked in me
when I look at my own children,
this doesn't exist in the same universe.
So you don't have something,
you don't have a complete parallel,
or at least a lot of men,
or at least me, I didn't have sort of a framework
to put it into what would it be like to have my own child?
And then you experience it.
It's like the poof.
And it happens so quickly too.
This is what I found fascinating.
It happens before that little human
is even able to return any words to you
that the love you develop to an infant,
it happens quite quickly.
Not necessarily immediately, I don't know,
different people have different experiences,
but it took me a little bit.
But then once it hit, it just hit like kick of a horse.
And I love that it's also just such a universal experience.
That you can be the most successful person in the world.
You can be the poorest person in the world.
You can be somewhere in the middle.
And we share this experience that being a parent,
for most of them,
turns out to be the most important thing in their life.
- But you know, it is really nice
to do that kind of experience with the right partner.
But I think because I'm such an empath,
the cost of having the wrong partner is high for me.
But then I also like realized, man,
I have a friend of mine who's divorced happily
and he still loves the shit out of his kids.
And it's still beautiful.
It's a mess, but there's all of that love is still there
and it's, you know, you just have to make it work.
It's just that, I don't know,
that kind of like divorce would destroy me.
- You should listen to The School of Life.
He has this great bit on YouTube.
You'll marry the wrong person.
If you accept upfront that you will marry the wrong person,
that every potential person you can marry
is gonna be the wrong person on some dimension.
They're gonna annoy you.
They're gonna be not what you hoped in certain dimensions.
The romantic ideal
that everything is just perfect all the time
is not very conducive to the reality
of hitching up and get making babies.
Because I think as you just accounted,
even when it turns to shit,
I find that most of the people I personally know
where things have fallen apart
and have turned to shit,
never in a million years would they go like, "I regret it."
"I would rather, my children did not exist
because a relationship turned sour."
I mean, I think you should try very hard.
And I think this is also one of those things
where we didn't fully understand those fences.
And when we pulled them up
and celebrated how easy it is to get divorced, for example,
that that wasn't gonna have some negative consequences.
I'm not saying you shouldn't have divorces.
I'm not saying return to times past.
I'm saying though that civilization
over thousands of years developed certain technologies
for ensuring the continuation of its own institutions
and its own life that perhaps we didn't fully appreciate.
I mean, again, this is something Jordan Peterson
and others are far more articulate to speak about,
and that I've learned a lot
to just analyze my own situation.
Why is it that this incredible burden,
it is to be responsible for someone else's life
that you brought into this world
is also the most rewarding part of existence?
That's just curious.
Before I heard Peterson articulate the value
of taking on the greatest burden you know how to carry,
I always thought about burdens as a negative things.
Why would I want the burden of a child?
I might screw it up.
I might be a bad parent.
They might have bad... all this stuff, right?
All the reasons why you shouldn't.
And so few voices articulating why you should.
- Yeah, but there I should also add
on top of that thing you mentioned
currently, perhaps in the west,
the matchmaking process is broken.
Is broken and technology made it worse.
Yeah, it's fascinating.
This whole thing that that hasn't been solved.
So hiring great teams,
that's probably been solved the best out of matchmaking.
Finding great people to hire.
Second, finding great friends.
That's like, that's also hasn't been solved.
- And it's breaking down. - It's breaking down.
And third is matchmaking
for like relationships.
That's like the worst.
And in fact, technology made it even worse.
It's fascinating.
- It is.
It's a great example again
of how all the greatest intentions
still led us straight to hell.
I really enjoyed Louis Perry's analysis
of the sexual revolution not being an unqualified good,
which was something I hadn't thought about at all
before she articulated it.
That of course women
should be able to have freedom and self determination
and abortions and all of these things.
And Louise Perry is not arguing
against that either, of course.
But there are second order facts
that we don't appreciate at the time
and we may not have ready-made solutions for.
And that's just interesting.
You make life better in a million different ways
and somehow we end up more miserable.
Why is that?
Why is it that humans find meaning in hardship?
And I think some of that
is that it's a difficult question
to answers through science.
And again, Peterson articulates well
this idea that you have to find some of it through art,
some of it through authors,
some of it through different...
I was just about to say modes of knowing
before I stopped myself,
because that sounds like woo bullshit.
But there are different ways
to acquire those deep lessons
that sort of paper is not gonna tell you.
- I mean, this is really,
the point also applies to religion, for example.
If you remove from society the software of religion,
you better have a good replacement.
- And we've had a bunch of bad replacements,
especially over the last few decades.
Religion is one of those things I've struggled with a lot
because I'm not religious.
I sort of wish I was.
I can now fully appreciate the enormous value
having an operating system like that
brings not just at the individual level,
but rather at a societal level.
And it's not clear at all what the answer is.
I think we've tried a lot of dead ends
when it came to replacements
and people have been filling that void
in a million different ways that seem worse
than all the religions,
despite their faults in a myriad of ways
have been able to deliver.
- Yeah, religions like the cobalt code.
It's just... - Yes,
it's the institutions
where we don't fully understand the rules
and why they're there
and what's gonna happen if we remove them.
Yeah, some of them seems obvious to me
are just bullshit of the time.
Oh, you should need whatever shellfish,
because in that region of the world.
There was something, something, something, okay, fine.
But there's a bunch of other things
that are pivotal to keeping society functioning
for the long term,
and we don't fully understand which is which.
What's the bullshit
and what's the load-bearing pillars of society.
- Can you speak to the hit on productivity that kids have?
Did they increase your productivity, decrease it,
or is that even the wrong question to ask?
- I think it's one of the reasons
why ambitious people are often afraid of having children
because they think I have so much more to do
and I barely have enough time now.
How would I possibly be able to accomplish the things
I wanna accomplish if I add another human into the mix?
Now, A, we've always worked 40 hours a week,
not 80 or 100 or 120.
I think that's very beneficial.
B, kids don't exist in this vacuum
of just them alone being entered into your life.
Hopefully there's a partner.
And in my life, I'm married to a wonderful woman
who decided to stop working her corporate job
when we got together
and have been able to carry
a huge part of that responsibility.
I was just about to say burden.
And I think that's exactly how it often gets presented,
especially from a feminist perspective,
that carrying for your own children
is some sort of unpaid labor
that has to be compensated for in some specific way
beyond the compensation
of what bringing life into this world,
racing wonderful humans.
There's something screwy about that analysis
that I actually think the modern trad movement
is a reply against.
Whether they have all the answers,
I'm certainly not sure of either.
But there's something that's just not right
in the analysis that children are a burden
and that if woman chooses to stay at home with the kids,
that that some sort of failure mode of feminist ambition.
I think that's actually a complete dead end.
Now depends on different people, different circumstances.
I can just speak to my life
being married to a wonderful woman
who have decided to be home with the kids,
at least at their early age
and taking on a lot of those responsibilities.
Now it doesn't mean there isn't plenty of ways
that I have to be part of that and have to chip in,
but it's allowed me to continue
to work the 40 hours a week that I've always worked.
But it's made the 40 hours more strict.
I have a schedule where I wake up, whatever, 6:30
and we have to get out of the door a little before 8:00.
I usually have to play
at least one or two rounds of "Fortnite"
with my youngest and sometimes middle child.
Then take the kids to school,
get in, start work at, I don't know, 8:39.
Didn't work until 5:00, 5:30, sometimes six o'clock.
But then it's dinner and I have to be there for that.
And then I have to read to the kids
and by the time that's done,
I don't want to go back to work.
So my work time really is 9:00 to 5:00, 9:00 to 6:00,
depending of whatever is going on.
Sometimes there's emergencies
and you have to tend to them,
but it's made it more structured.
And I found some benefit in that
and I've found some productivity in that,
that I can't goof around quite as much
that the day will end at around 5:36.
That's just if I didn't accomplish
what I wanted to do today,
if I get to that time, it's done.
I'm over, I have to try again tomorrow.
Whereas before having a family and before having kids,
I could just like not do it
and just make it up in the evening.
So in that way it's made me more structured,
but it hasn't really changed
my volume of work all that much.
I still work about the same amount of hours.
And that's, by the way, enough.
This is one of the key points we make in.
It doesn't have to be crazy at work.
The latest book we wrote is that there's enough time.
40 hours a week is actually a ton
if you don't piss it away.
Most people do piss it away.
They piss it away in meetings.
They piss it away on just stuff that doesn't matter
when even three hours, four hours
of concentrated uninterrupted time every day
would move to goals they truly care about
way down the field.
- I think kids do make you more productive
in that way for people who need it,
especially people like me.
They create their urgency.
Lik if you have to be done by 5:00,
it's a maybe counterintuitive notion,
but for people like me who like to work,
you can really fill the day with fluff of work.
And if you have to be done by 5:00,
you're going to have to do the deep work and get it done.
Like really focus singular work.
And then you're just gonna cut off all the pressure.
- It keeps you honest.
It keeps you honest because you can squander one day,
you can squander two days.
But if I squander a whole week, I feel terrible.
Now that's just some drive I have in me
where I feel content and full meaning
if I actually do stuff that matters,
if I can look back upon the week
and go like that was a nice week, really.
We moved forward.
Maybe we didn't get done,
but we moved forward and everything got better.
And I think kids really helped
just time box things in that way.
And a lot of people need that
because I find just so much of the celebration
of overwork to be so tiresome.
Oh, I work 60 hours or 80 hours or 100 hours a week
and just like, first of all, no, you don't.
No, you don't.
Like those 80 hours are full
of all sorts of fluff that you label work,
but that I would laugh at
and that most people laugh at.
That you would laugh at if you actually did the analysis
of where's that time going.
Most of the important stuff that has to be done
is done in these uninterrupted chunks
of two hours here or four hours there or five hours there.
The hard part is making sure
you get them in the whole piece.
So don't give me that.
There's time enough.
And also what's so important that it ranks
above continuing your lineage.
I think there's just some ancient honor
in the fact that, again,
this DNA that's sitting on this chair
traveled 30,000 years to get here
and you're gonna squander all that away
just so you can send a few more emails.
- There is something that's also hard
to convert into words of just the kind of fun
you can have just playing with your kids.
I don't know what that on the surface it's like,
I can have that kind of fun
just playing video games by myself.
But no, it's like there's something magical about it, right?
- I have a thousand hours logged in "Fortnite"
since 19, I think,
all of it with my kids.
I'd never be playing "Fortnite."
Well, I don't know if I never would be.
I wouldn't be playing a thousand hours of "Fortnite"
if it wasn't for my kids.
The enjoyment for me is to do
something with them that I also happen to enjoy.
I really love "Fortnite."
It's a phenomenal game.
I don't have to force myself to play that with them.
I often ask like, hey, do you wanna play "Fortnite?"
But still, it's an activity that I get to share with them.
It's a passion that I get to share with them.
I've started doing go-karting with my oldest.
I've been driving race cars for a long time
and now they're getting into go-karting
and just being at the go-kart track,
seeing them go around,
seeing them get faster, seeing them learn that skill,
you just go look at like,
what else would I be doing with my life?
At my age, 45, I'm standing here truly enjoying life.
I brought into this world.
What else was so important at this stage
that I would otherwise be spending my time on?
- All right, like you mentioned, you like to race cars
and you do it at a world class competitive level,
which is incredible.
So how'd you get into it?
What attracts you to racing?
What do you love about it?
- The funny thing about getting into racing
is I did not get my driver's license until I was 25.
I grew up in Copenhagen, Denmark,
where the tax on cars is basically over 200%.
So you pay for three cars and you get one.
And I didn't even have the money for one car,
let alone three.
So I could not afford a car growing up.
We did not have a car growing up,
but Copenhagen is a nice city
to be able to get around on a bike or with a bus,
or as I did for a long period of time, on roller blades.
But when I was 25,
I realized I wanted to spend more time in the US.
I wasn't sure yet that I was gonna move there.
That turned out later to be true.
But I knew that if I wanted to spend time in the US,
I needed to have a driver's license.
I was not gonna get around very
well if I didn't know how to drive a car.
So I got a driver's license at 25.
Then ended up moving to the US later that year
and I'd always been into video games, racing video games,
"Metropolitan Street Racer" on the Dreamcast
was one of those games that really sucked me into.
It was the precursor to Project Gotham,
which was the precursor
to essentially, Forza Horizon, I think.
- Oh, okay, interesting.
- I think that's how the lineage goes.
Just a great game.
I actually just fired it up on an emulator
a few weeks ago.
And it still sort of kind of holds up
because it has enough real car dynamics
that it smells a little bit like driving a real car.
It's not just like an arcade racer
like Sega Rally or something like that.
But I'd always been into that.
Then I got my driver's license at 25 and moved to the US,
and then two years later,
a friend that I'd met in Chicago
took me to the Chicago Autobahn Country Club,
which is this great track,
about 45 minutes from Chicago.
And I sat in a race car
and I drove a race car for the first time.
And I had the same kind of pseudo religious experience
I did as when I started working on Ruby,
where I did maybe 20 laps
in this basically a Mazda race car
from, I think, it was like the '90s or something,
like a pretty cheap race car, but a real race car.
Single seat, manual gearbox,
but exposed slick wheels, all the stuff.
And after having had that experience,
first of all it was just the most amazing thing ever.
Like the physical sensation of driving a race car
is really unique.
And I think if you've driven a car fast,
you have a maybe a 2% taste of it.
The exposure to the elements
that you get in a single seat race car,
especially one like that where your head
is actually out in the elements,
you can see the individual wheels
and you sensation of speed
is just so much higher is at a completely different level.
- So can you actually speak to that?
So even at that Mazda, so you can feel,
what can you feel like the track
reverberating you see? You feel the grip?
- Oh yeah, not only can you see the bumps
because you're literally looking straight at the wheel,
you can feel all the bumps
because you're running a slick tire.
It's a really stiff setup.
It's nothing like taking a fast street car
out on a racetrack and try to driving a little bit around.
- So can you feel like the slipping,
the traction? - Yeah, you feel the slipping.
hat's a huge part of the satisfaction
of driving a race car
is driving in at the edge of adhesion as we call it.
Where the car's actually sliding a little bit.
A couple of percent of slip angle
is the fastest way to drive a race car.
You don't wanna slide too much that looks great,
lots of smoke, but it's not fast.
How you want to drive it is just at the limit of adhesion
where you're rotating the car
as much as your tires can manage.
And then slightly more than that and playing at it,
keeping it just at that level.
Because when you're at the level
or at the limit of adhesion,
you're essentially just a tiny movement away
from spinning out.
I mean, it doesn't take much.
Then the car starts rotating.
Once it starts rotating,
you lose grip and you're going for the wall.
That balance of danger and skill
is what's so intoxicating.
And it's so much better than racing video games too,
because the criticality is taking up two notches.
I often think about people who really like gambling,
where I think like, aren't you just playing poker?
Like no, the point is not poker.
Pokers may be part of it,
but the point is that I could lose my house, right?
Like that's the addiction that some people get to gambling,
that there's something real on the line.
When you're in a race car,
there's something very real on the line.
If you get it wrong,
at the very least,
you're gonna spin out and properly hit a wall
and it's gonna be expensive.
At the very worst, you're not getting out alive.
And even if modern race cars have gotten way safer
than they used to be.
There is that element of danger that's real.
That there are people who still get seriously hurt
or even killed in a race car.
It's mercifully rare compared to what it used to be
when those maniacs in the '60s
would do Formula 1 and whatever,
13% of the grid wouldn't make it to the end of the year
because they'd just die in a fiery flaming fireball.
But there's still some of it there.
And I think that since that there's something on the line
really contributes to it.
But it's more than that.
There's just a physical sensation.
There's activation of all your forces.
There's the flow.
And I think that really cements like why I got addicted,
'cause I always, I love that flow
I got out of programming,
but getting flow out of programming
is a very inconsistent process.
I can't just sit down in front of a keyboard
and go like, all right,
let's get the flow going.
It doesn't happen like that.
The problem has to be just right.
It has to meet my skills in just a right moment.
It's a bit of a lottery.
In a race car is not a lottery at all.
You sit down in that car, you turn the ignition,
you go out on track,
and I get flow virtually guaranteed.
Because you need, or I need at least
100% of my brain processing power
to be able to go at the speed I go without crashing.
So there's no time to think about the other night
or the meeting next week or product launch.
It's completely zen
in actually the literal sense of the word.
I think of someone who's really good at meditation,
that's probably kind of state they get
into where it's just clear you're in the now,
there's nothing but you and the next corner.
That's a really addictive experience.
So after I've had that, I couldn't get enough.
I kept going to the track every opportunity I got.
Every single weekend for about four years,
I would go to the track.
And by the end of that time,
I'd finally worked up enough skill
and enough success with the company
that I could afford to go, quote, unquote, "real racing."
So I started doing that.
I started driving these Porsches,
and then as soon as I got into that,
as soon as I got into, quote, unquote, "real competition,"
I was like, I wonder how far you can take this.
And it didn't take that long
before I decided, you know what?
I can take this all the way.
My great hero in racing is Tom Kristensen, fellow Dane.
The Mr. Le Mans, as they call him.
The greatest endurance race in the world.
The 24 hours of Le Mans has been won more times
than any other by Tom Kristensen.
He won the race nine times.
So Tom just really turned me onto Le Mans.
I've been watching Le Mans since I think the '80s.
I have my earliest memories of watching that on TV.
The race has been going since I think 20s.
But in the '80s I got kind of into it.
And then in the late '90s,
early 2000s when Tom started winning,
I like pretty much every other Dane
started watching the race almost religiously.
So I thought, you know what?
I wanna get to Le Mans.
And this is the magic thing about racing,
that if I get into basketball,
like I can't set a realistic expectation
that I'm gonna play in the NBA,
then I'm gonna go to the finals.
Or I get into tennis and I'm gonna play at Wimbledon,
that just doesn't happen.
But racing thing is special in this way
because it requires a fair amount of money
to keep these cars running.
It's really expensive.
It's like having a small startup.
You need to fly a bunch of people around the world
and buy expensive equipment and so forth.
So you need a bunch of capital.
And I had some through the success of the company.
So I could do it, which meant that I could get to Le Mans.
So I set that as my goal.
I wanna get to Le Mans.
And I started racing in real competition 2009.
And three years later in 2012,
I was at the grid of Le Mans for the first time.
- We should say, so Le Mans, 24-hour race endurance.
I mean, this is insane.
- There are three drivers, mind you.
So it's not like one guy just drive for 20 hours,
24 hours straight.
But still, it's a pretty tough race
both physically and mentally, especially mentally.
When you've been up for 24 plus hours,
you're not quite as sharp as when you first wake up.
And this is funny about Le Mans too.
It starts at around four o'clock in the afternoon.
So you've already been up for half a day
by the time the race starts.
And then there's 24 hours to go before you're done.
And you'll be in the car for anywhere
from usually an hour and a half
to a maximum of four hours.
The regulations say four out of six is the max you can do.
I've spent perhaps two and a half hours
in a single stint at Le Mans.
It's pretty taxing.
You're going 200 miles an hour
into some of these turns,
and there's another 60 cars on track.
Whenever I'm in my normal category,
which is the LMP2 category,
I have GT cars, which are more like a Ferrari and a Porsche
that I have to overtake.
And then I have these hypercar,
which is the top class that are overtaking me.
So you got a lot going on and you gotta stay sharp
for two and a half hours straight to do that.
That is just a guaranteed way to get incredible flow
for long, long stretches of time.
That's why you get addicted to it.
That was why I got addicted.
- You gotta talk me through this video.
This video of you in these LMP2s.
- Oh, yes. - This is such a cool.
This is so cool.
- And this was probably my favorite battle of my career.
- [Commentator] And Heinemeier Hansson
has beat past to add five...
- Yeah, so this is me driving against Nico Muller
at the Shanghai International Circuit.
- You're on the outside here? - I'm on the outside in the...
- How cool is it? - Blue and white.
And we go a whole track around
with basically a piece of paper
between a seat down this back straight.
I get so close to him because I wanna force him over
on the other side of the track,
such that he can't just box me in.
And we've been fighting already
at this point for basically 40 minutes straight.
I've been managing to keep this professional driver
behind me for 40 minutes.
And he finally passes me,
but we just keep the battle on for the whole time.
And it really just shows both these kinds of cars.
The Le Mans prototypes.
We don't actually ever touch.
We get within about an inch.
And keep going around
Shanghai circuit too. - What a cool.
How did you get so good? Like what?
I mean that's a fascinating story, right?
That you are able to get so good.
- I'm pretty good for the kind of driver I am,
which is called the gentleman driver,
which means I'm not a professional driver.
And like many good gentlemen drivers,
when we're at our really best,
we can be quite competitive with even professional drivers
who have been doing this their whole life.
The difference between us and the professionals
is the professionals could do it every time
or more or less every time.
So I can't be this good all the time.
When everything is just right,
I can be competitive with professional drivers,
but that's not how you win championships.
That's not how you get paid by factories to drive.
You gotta be good every time you go out.
So that's a huge difference.
But some of it was also just, I really put my mind to it
by the time I realized race cars
is what I want to do as my serious hobby.
I put in thousands of hours.
- Have you crashed?
What's the worst crash?
- I've had a lot of crashes,
but thankfully, knock on wood,
I haven't had any crashes
where I've gotten really seriously hurt.
- Have you like wrecked the car?
- Oh yes, oh yes.
I've wrecked many car.
- So what's that feel like?
Just you wreck a car.
Like how do you get...
- It feels like total shit
if you're in a real race and other people depend on you.
It's not even so much to car,
although it's also sometimes that these cars
are expensive to repair and that sucks
and it feels so wasteful
in a way when you crash some of these cars.
But the sense that you're letting a team down.
Endurance racing is a team sport.
Not only do you have your mechanics,
do you usually have co-drivers.
So when I crash I just feel like,
damn it, I could have avoided this.
- Yeah, but also you could have died.
- Do you know what's funny?
I never think about that.
I don't think you can.
Because I think the moment you start thinking about
being able to die, you can't do it.
You can't go fast.
- Well, I'm sure not to go all Carl Jung and Freud here,
but I'm sure that's always present
in the back of your mind somewhere.
You're not just bringing it to the surface.
- It is in the sense that it's part of the appeal,
it's part of the sense that there's something on the line
that this isn't just virtual.
I can't just hit reset, restart, reboot.
If I crash this car,
we're gonna be out or we're gonna be disadvantaged
or it's gonna get destroyed or I might get hurt.
I've gotten lightly hurt a few times.
I actually had the year we won
24 hours of Le Mans in our class,
I've been training in this formula 3.5 car.
It's a really fast car.
It's a really nice exercise to do,
but it's also, it doesn't have power steering.
So some of these race cars, especially the open-seaters,
they don't have power steering.
Which means that the steering wheel
is basically directly connected to the front wheels.
So if you crash one of those cars
and the front wheel suddenly turn,
you're really gonna hurt your hands
if you don't get your hands off the wheel.
I hadn't raced enough of those cars
to know that I had to get, or to have the instinct,
to have developed the instinct
that I had to get my hands off the wheel.
So I didn't, and I really hurt my hand
and this was just I think a month before the 24 of Le Mans.
So I thought, ah man, I'm gonna have to miss it this year.
I had like a, not a cast, it was just seriously sprained.
And then somehow miraculously
like a week before the event,
I was like, yeah, actually it's okay now.
So got to do it.
And that would've been grave regret
if I would've seen my team go on to win the race
and I would have to sit on the sidelines.
But I really have been quite fortunate
in the sense that most of my crashes
have just been expensive or sporting inconvenient.
They've never been something where I got seriously hurt.
But I've seen plenty of people
who have in fact, my co-driver this year
and for several years, Pietro Fittipaldi
drove a race car at Spa.
Spa is one of the great race tracks of all time.
And it has this iconic corner called Eau Rouge,
which is probably the most famous corner
in all of motorsports.
It has a great compression before you climb uphill.
It's extremely fast, very difficult corner.
And just as he does the compression,
his car basically sets out
and he loses his power steering
and he drives straight into the wall
and breaks both his legs
and basically faced the prospect
that maybe his career was over.
I've had other teammates
and people I know have serious injuries
that's really hurt them.
And yet what's funny, as you say,
you'd think that would sink in.
The year before we won in 2014,
that same car had a Danish driver in it at Le Mans
at the race I was driving who died.
He lost control of the car
when there was a bit of rain on the track
and the track went unfortunately designed
in such a poor way that there was a very big tree
right behind the railing.
And he hit that tree at full speed, pulled 90 Gs
and was dead on the spot,
which was just such an extremely
awful experience to go through.
I finished second that year,
which should have been caused for a bunch of celebration.
But it was just tainted by the fact that
not only did a driver die, a fellow Dane died.
A guy I knew died.
That was pretty tough.
- So that throw that into the pile of the things
that have to be considered is the weather conditions
that you mentioned of the track.
The weather is dry or wet.
- It's a huge part of it.
- Even just last year at Le Mans.
It was raining and I was out,
and I hadn't made a serious mistake
at the 24 hours of Le Mans
since I did the first race in 2012
where I put it in the sand trap
with like four hours to go
and we lost a couple of lap getting pulled out,
but it didn't actually change anything for our result
because that was just how the field was spread out.
I'd made minor mistakes over the years
but nothing that really set us out.
And at the race last year when it was raining,
I first clobbered a Ford Mustang
when I made an overambitious pass
on a damp part of the track and couldn't stop in time
and then felt absolutely awful
as I sat in the gravel pit for two laps
and knew that our race was over.
A race where we were highly competitive.
You're not blessed with a competitive car,
a competitive team and competitive setup every year.
I know how rare that is.
So to know that we had had a chance that year
and I sort of squandered it felt really bad,
but that got compounded.
I got back on track, barely made it another stint
and then put it in the gravel trap
again when it started raining on the entrance into Porsche.
So this is part of why racing is so addicting too
because the highs are very, very high.
When you win a race like the 24 hours of Le Mans.
It feels just incredible.
There's so much emotion.
But if you fuck it up, the lows are very, very low.
- What are the things you're paying attention to
when you're driving?
What are the parameters?
What are you loading in?
Are you feeling the grip?
Are you basically increasing the speed
and seeing what like a constant feedback system
effect that has on the grip
and you're trying to manage that
and try to find that optimal slip angle?
Are you looking around using your eyes?
Are you smelling things?
Are you listening just feeling the wind
or are you looking at the field too?
Like how'd you not hit that guy at all?
You get close with an inches, right?
So you have to pay attention to that too.
It's really interesting about that specific battle
where we're literally a few inches apart.
I can't fully explain it,
but humans can develop an incredible sense of space.
Where I can't see the edge of the back of my car,
but I can know exactly where it is.
I can have a mental model in my head
that gives me the exact dimensions of this car
just that I can run within a few inches
of a competitor car
or within a few inches of the wall
and not hit either when things go well.
The car is about two meters wide
and it's quite long, five meters.
And you can't see everything.
The mirrors are actually kind of shit.
There's no rear view mirror in these cars.
You can't see out the back.
You can only see through your two side mirrors.
But you formed this intuitive mental model
when you get good enough at this.
But what I actually pay attention to most
is I run a program.
What I try to do when I go to a racetrack
is I try to load up the best program I know how
for every single corner.
What's my break point?
What's my acceleration point?
What's my break trailing curve?
And I try to pick up that program in part
just by finding it myself and how fast I can go.
But even more so than that
by copying my professional competitors
or not competitors, co-drivers.
So I usually always race with a pro.
And modern race cars produce an absolute
enormous amount of data,
and you can analyze all that data after each outing.
You can see an exact trace
of how much you pushed the brake pedal,
how much you did in terms of steering inputs.
When you got on the gas,
you can see every millisecond you're losing
is evident in those charts.
So what I try to do is I try to look at the chart
and then I try to load that in
and like that's what I gotta do.
Oh, in this corner 17,
I have to be 10 bar lighter on the brake.
So I try to load that program in
and then I try to repeat it now.
Then there are all the things that changes.
Your tires change quite a lot.
These tires are made to only last
40 minutes in many cases.
Sometimes at Le Mans we can go longer,
but at some racetracks they'll last as little as 40 minutes
before they really fall off.
So you gotta manage that.
That the grip is constantly changing.
So your program have to suddenly fit
those changing circumstances.
And then in endurance racing,
you're constantly interacting with other cars
because you're passing slower classes
or you're getting passed by a faster class.
So that's part of the equation.
And then you're trying to dance the car
around the limit of adhesion.
So you got all those factors playing at the same time.
But above all else for me
is to try to become a robot.
Like how can I repeat this set of steps
exactly as I'm supposed to
for two and a half hours straight
without making 100 milliseconds worth of mistakes?
- Yeah, low latency algorithm.
- That's really a huge part of it actually.
Your latency is enormously important
in terms of being able to catch
when the car starts slipping.
You get this sensation in your body
that the G-force are a little off,
the slip angle is a little off,
and then you have to counter steer.
And obviously the best race car drivers
just feel like an intuition.
I have some intuition.
I don't have all of it,
so I do occasionally spin my car.
But that's the challenge.
- From everything you've studied and understand,
what does it take to achieve mastery in racing?
Like what does it take
to become the best race car driver in the world?
- Obsession is part of it.
When I read and hear about Senna and the other greats,
they were just singularly focused.
Max Verstappen is the current champion of the world
and he is the same kind.
Max has been fascinating to watch.
I mean he is a phenomenal race car driver,
but he also literally does nothing else.
When he is not at the racetrack,
he's driving sim racing.
Like he's literally in video games doing more racing
when he is not doing all the racing he's already doing.
- Is there a specific skill
that have that like stands out to you
as supernatural through all of that obsession?
Is it a bunch of factors or are they actually able to,
like you said, develop a sense?
Is it they're able to get to the very edge of the slip?
- They're able to develop very fine tuned sensibilities
for when the car's sliding.
They can feel just these tiny moments
or movements in the chassis
that transports up usually through their ass.
That's why you call us like a butt meter
that goes up and you feel like the car is loose
or you feel like you're just about to lock up.
You can really hone that tuning.
Then the other thing
is you have to have really good reaction time.
And when you look at great Formula 1 drivers,
they can generally have a reaction time
of just under 200 milliseconds, which is awesome.
And even 10 milliseconds difference makes a huge difference.
You'll see it when the Formula 1 grit, for example,
they do a standing start
and you see the five red lights come on.
And when the last light goes out,
they're supposed to release the clutch
and get going.
And they can time this.
So you can see exactly who has the reaction time.
And even being off by 20 milliseconds
can make the difference
of whether you're in front or behind at the first corner.
- How much of winning is also just the strategy
of jostling for a position?
- There's some of that
and some of it is also just nerve.
Who wants it more?
That's exactly when that sense of danger comes in.
There's a great quote from Fernando Alonso
when he was driving at Suzuka
against Schumacher, I think.
They're coming up to this incredibly fast corner.
It's very dangerous.
And Alonso basically accounts
I was gonna make the pass
'cause I knew he had a wife and kids at home.
- That's so gangster.
- Just absolutely ruthless, right?
- Yeah, wow. - That I knew he valued
life more than I did.
So there's a bit of poker sometimes in that.
Who's gonna yield?
There's a bit of chicken raised in that regard.
And sometimes it doesn't work.
No one yields and you both crash.
But very often one person will blink first.
- Can the pass be both on the inside and the outside?
- You can pass wherever you want
as long as you have just a slight part of the car
on the racetrack.
- And then you just improvise and take risks.
What a sport.
And then Senna, of course, is like a legendary risk taker.
- Yes, and even before him, by the time,
I mean he died in the '90s.
But by the time we got to the '90s,
racing was al already a lot safer
than it was when Niki Lauda raced in the '60s.
That level of danger is no longer there.
There's still just a remnant of it
and it is still dangerous, but nothing like that.
And it's a little hard to compare through the ages,
like who's the greatest driver of all time.
I think there's a fair argument that Senna is,
but we don't have the data.
We don't know who he was up against.
Like how would he fare if we pitted him
against Max Verstappen today.
I do think sometimes that you can have a bit of a nostalgia
for the all time greats, but the world moves forward
and new records are being set all the time
and the professionalism keeps improving.
Sometimes to the detriment of the sport, I think.
There's a lot of professional drivers
who are not only just very good at driving,
but are very good at being corporate spokespeople.
And it used to be quite different.
There used to be more characters in racing
that had a bit more personality
that they were allowed to shine
because there weren't a billion sponsorships
on the line that they were afraid to lose.
- Ridiculous question,
what's the greatest car I ever made,
or maybe what's the funnest one to drive?
- The greatest car for me of all time is the Pagani Zonda.
- [Lex] Okay, I'm looking this up, Pagani Zonda.
- [DHH] So the Pagani Zonda
was made by this wonderful Argentinian
called Horacio Pagani.
- [Lex] My god, that's a beautiful car, wow.
- It's a gorgeous car.
You can look up mine.
It's the Pagani Zonda HH.
So that's a car I had made in 2010
after we visited the factory in Modena.
And by sheer accident ended up with this car,
but it became my favorite car in the world basically.
When I watched an episode of "Top Gear,"
I think in 2005, where one of the presenters
was driving the Pagani Zonda F around.
And I just thought,
that's the most beautiful car in the world.
It is the most incredibly sounding car in the world.
If I one day have the option, this is what I want.
And then I had the option in 2010,
I've had the car ever since.
I'm never ever gonna sell it.
It's truly a masterpiece that stood the test of time.
There's some great cars from history
that are recognized as being great in their time.
This car is still great.
- Have you taken on the racetrack?
- I have, it's terrible at that.
Well, I don't wanna say it's terrible that
that's not what it's designed for.
It's designed for the road and that's why it's great.
There are a lot of fast cars
that are straddling their race car for the road.
You don't actually want a race car for the world.
A race car for the world is a pain in the ass.
It's way too stiff.
It's way too loud.
It's way too uncomfortable.
You can't actually take it on a road trip.
- So this actually feels good driving
normal roads? - Totally, totally.
- And you of course always go to speed limit?
- Always.
This is why I love having this car in Spain
'cause they're a little more relaxed.
Not entirely relaxed, but more relaxed
than they are in a lot of places.
In Denmark, I kid you not, if you are on the highway
and you go more than twice the speed limit,
they confiscate your car and keep it.
You're not getting it back.
They don't even care if it's your car or not.
Like if you were boring my car
and you went twice the speed limit, it's gone.
So they don't do that in Spain.
I mean, in most places except for the German Autobahn,
they get pissy if you go twice the speed limit.
For all sorts of fair reasons, I'm not advocating
that you should be going much more than that.
But there are certain special roads
where you can't open things up and no one's in harm's way.
And that's an incredible sensation.
And I do think that some of those speed limits
actually are kind of silly.
And I'm not just saying that in a vacuum.
In Germany, they have the glorious Autobahn.
And on the Autobahn, there is no speed limit
in a bunch of segments.
And they're so committed to their speed-limitless Autobahn,
which is by the way, very weird of Germans.
They usually love rules.
They usually very precise about it.
And then they have this glorious thing called the Autobahn.
There was a great case a couple of years ago
where a guy took out a Bugatti Chiron;
went 400 kilometers an hour on the Autobahn
and he filled it and put it on YouTube
and a case was brought against him.
Because even though they don't have a speed limit,
they do have rules that you can't drive recklessly.
And he won the case.
He wasn't driving recklessly.
He was just going very, very fast.
I've done the Autobahn a couple of times.
My wife and I went on a road trip in Europe in 2009,
and I got the Lamborghini Gallardo.
We were driving up to 200 miles an hour.
And I'd driven 200 miles an hour
or close to it on a racetrack before.
That feels like one thing.
Driving on a public road, 200 miles an hour
feels really, really fast.
- Scary?
- Actually A little scary, yes.
Because you constantly think like on a racetrack,
you know the road, you know the surface.
You can walk the track most of the time.
You can know if there's a dip.
On a public road,
you can't know if there's suddenly a pothole.
Presumably there's not gonna be a pothole
on the German Autobahn.
but it does feel a little scary, but also exhilarating.
Speed is just intrinsically really fun.
I don't know anyone I've taken out in a fast car.
Well, actually I do know a few people.
Most people I take out in a fast car, they grin.
It's a human reaction to grin when you go really fast.
- Do you know what the fastest you've ever gone?
- I was probably at Le Mans,
I think when the LMP2s were at their maximum power
and had 600 horsepower and really sticky tires,
we were going 340 kilometers an hour,
which is just over 200 miles an hour.
A bit over 200 miles an hour.
That does feel fast.
And it's really interesting with speed
is that the difference between going, let's say 150
and 160 doesn't feel that much
actually those 10 mile an hour.
But the difference between going 190 and 200
feels crazy faster,
which as a percentage change is actually less
than going from 150 to 160.
But there's some sense of exponentiality
once you get up to those limits
where it's just on a complete different level.
- Yeah, 'cause to me like 110, 120 feels fast.
200? that's crazy. - It really is crazy.
- I gotta ask you about the details
of your programming setup, the IDE,
all that kind of stuff.
Let's paint the picture of the perfect programming setup.
Do you have a programming setup that you enjoy?
Are you very flexible?
Like how many monitors?
What kind of keyboard?
What kind of chair?
What kind of desk?
- It's funny because if you'd asked me,
let's see, a year and a half ago,
I would've given you the same answer
as I would've given anyone for basically 20 years.
I want a Mac.
I like the Magic Keyboard.
I like the single monitor.
Apple makes an awesome 6K 32-inch XDR screen
that I still haven't found anyone
who've beaten that I still use,
even though I switched away from Apple computers.
I still use their monitor because it's just fantastic.
But I've always been a single screen kind of guy.
I do like a big screen,
but I don't want multiple screens.
I've never found that that really works
with my perception.
I wanna be able to just focus on a single thing.
I don't want all of it all over the place.
And I've always used multiple virtual desktops
and being able to switch back and forth
between those things.
But the setup I have today is Linux.
I switched to a little over a year ago
after I finally got fed up with Apple enough
that I couldn't do that anymore.
And then I use this low profile mechanical keyboard
called the Lofree Flow84,
which is just the most glorious
sounding keyboard I've ever heard.
I know there are a lot of connoisseurs
of mechanical keyboards
that'll probably contest me on this.
This is too thy or too clicky or too clocky or whatever.
But for me, the Lofree Flow84
is just a delight that I did not even know existed.
Which is so funny because I mean,
I've been programming for a long time.
Mechanical keyboards have been a thing for a long time.
And the keyboard, when you look at it like this,
it just kind of, it looks plain,
it doesn't look extravagant.
But the tactile sensation
you get out of pushing those keys, the talky sound
that you hear when the keys hit the board.
It's just sublime.
And I'm kicking myself
that I was in this Mac bubble for so long
that I wasn't even in the market to find this.
I knew mechanical keyboards existed,
but to be blunt, I thought it was a bit of a nerd thing
that only real nerds that were much more nerdy
than me would ever care about.
And then I got out of the Apple bubble
and suddenly I had to find everything again.
I had to find a new mouse,
I had to find a new keyboard,
I had to find everything.
And I thought like, all right,
let me give mechanical keyboards a try.
And I gave quite a few of them a try.
The Keychron is one of the big brands
in that I didn't like that at all.
I tried a bunch of other keyboards
and then I finally found this keyboard
and I just went like, angels are singing.
Where have you been my whole life?
We spent as programmers so much of our time
interacting with those keys.
It really kind of matters
in a way I didn't fully appreciate.
I used to defend the Apple Magic Keyboard,
like hey, it's great.
It's actually a great keyboard.
And I think for what it is, this ultra-low profile,
ultra low travel is actually a really nice keyboard.
But once you've tried a longer travel
mechanical keyboard, there's no going back.
- You do have to remember in many ways,
both on the software side and the hardware side,
that you do spend a lot of hour behind the computer.
It's worth... - It's worth investing in.
- And also worth exploring
until you find the thing
where the angels starts singing, whatever.
- That's exactly right.
And I actually do regret that a little bit,
especially with this damn keyboard.
I mean, I could have been listening
to these beautiful thocky keys for years and years,
but sometimes you have to get really off
before you open your eyes
and see that something else exists.
I feel the same way about Linux.
So I've been using Linux on the server
since late '90s, probably.
We ran servers on Linux back then.
I never seriously considered it as a desktop option.
I never ran Linux before, directly myself.
I always thought, you know what?
I wanna focus on programming.
I don't have time for all these configuration files
and all this setup bullshit and whatnot.
And Apple is close enough.
It's built on Unix underpinnings.
Why do I need to bother with Linux?
And again, it was one of those things.
I needed to try new things and try something else
to realize that there is other things other than Apple.
And again, it's not 'cause I hate Apple.
I think they still make good computers.
I think a lot of the software
is still also pretty okay.
But I have come to realize that as a web developer,
Linux is just better.
It's closer to what I deploy on.
The tooling is actually phenomenal.
And if you spend a bit of time setting it up,
you can record a reproducible environment
that I've now done with this Omakub concept
or project that I've done,
that I can set up a new Linux machine
in less than 30 minutes.
And it's perfect.
It's not pretty good.
It's not like I still need to spend two hours on.
It's perfect because you can code all aspects
of the development environment into this.
And I didn't know.
I didn't even know, to be fair,
that Linux could look as good as it can.
If you look at a stock Ubuntu or Fedora boot,
I mean, not that it's ugly,
but I'd pick the Mac any day of the week.
You look at Omakub,
I mean, I'm biased here, of course,
'cause I built it with my own sensibilities.
But I look at that and go like, this is better.
This is beautiful.
And then you look at some of those true
Linux rising setups where people go nuts with everything
and you go, oh yeah, I remember when computers
used to be fun in this way,
when there was this individuality and this setup.
And it wasn't just all planned the sameness.
And I think that's the flip side
sometimes of something like Apple,
where they have really strong opinions
and they have really good opinions,
they have very good taste.
And it looks very nice
and it also looks totally the same.
And Linux has far more variety
and far more texture and flavor.
Sometimes also annoyances and bugs and whatever.
But I run Linux now.
It's Ubuntu-based with the Omakub stuff on top.
The low free keyboard.
I use a Logitech, what's it called?
The MX 3 mouse, which I love how it feels in my hand.
I don't love how it looks.
I actually was a Magic Mouse stan for the longest time.
I thought it was genius
that Apple integrated the track pad into a mouse,
and I used that.
And I always thought it was ridiculous
that people would slag it
just because you had to charge it by flipping it over.
'Cause the battery would last for three months
and then you'd charge it for half an hour.
I thought like, that's a perfect
compatibility with my sensibilities.
I don't mind giving up a little inconvenience
if something is beautiful,
and that Magic Mouse is beautiful.
But it wasn't gonna work on Linux.
So I found something else.
The S3 is nice,
but I sometimes do wish like the Magic Mouse.
That's pretty good.
- Yeah, Linux is really great
for customizing everything, for tiling,
for macros, for all of that.
And I also do the same in Windows with AutoHotKey
or just customize the whole thing
to your preferences.
- If you're a developer,
you should learn how to control your environment
with the keyboard.
It's faster, it's more fluid.
I think one of those silly things
I've come to truly appreciate about my Omakub setup
is that I can, in whatever time
it takes to refresh the screen,
probably five milliseconds
switch from one virtual desktop to another.
Even on Windows, you can't get it that smooth.
You can get close,
you can't get it that smooth.
On macOS, for whatever reason,
Apple insists on having this infuriating animation
when you switch between virtual desktops,
which makes it just that you don't want to.
You don't wanna run full screen apps
because it's too cumbersome to switch
between the virtual desktops.
The kind of immediacy that you can get
from a wonderful Linux setup in that regard,
it's just next level.
- Yeah, and it seems like a subtle thing,
but you know, difference in milliseconds and latency
between switching the virtual desktops, for example.
I don't know, it changes...
- It changes how you use the computer.
It really does.
- Similar thing with VR, right?
If there's some kind of latency
or like it just completely takes you all out of it.
- And it's funny, I actually had to watch,
I think it was ThePrimeagen on YouTube
when he was showing off his setup
and I was seeing how quickly
he was switching between those virtual desktops.
And I'd always been using virtual desktops,
but I didn't like switching too much
because just of that latency
and it's like, oh, you can do that on Linux?
Oh, that's pretty cool.
So I run that, and then my editor
of choice now is Neovim.
- Oh good, all right.
Well we're out of time.
No, all right, you did for many, many years.
You used, what is it? TextMate.
- Yes, TextMate. - TextMate, yeah.
- That was actually, that was the main blocker
of moving away from Apple.
Everything else I thought, do you know what?
I can swing it.
But TextMate was and is a wonderful editor.
One, I helped birth into this world.
The programmer Allan Odgaard is a good friend of mine,
all the way back from the party days
when we were lugging our computers around.
And he was a big Mac guy.
And in 2005, he was writing this editor
and I helped him with the project management
of kind of keeping him on track,
keeping him focused on getting something released.
Because I really wanted it for myself.
And I thought, this was the last editor
I thought I was never gonna switch.
- Forgive me for not knowing,
but how featureful as this editor is this?
- It's quite featureful,
but it's a GUI-driven editor in some regards.
It was really early on with ways of recording macros
and having sort of sophisticated syntax highlighting.
And it did a bunch of firsts
and it was just a really pleasant editing experience.
I think these days a lot of people
would just use VS Code.
VS Codes exist in the same universe as TextMate
in some ways.
And actually I think is compatible
with the original TextMate bundles,
the original TextMate format.
So it really trailed a path there,
but it also just didn't evolve.
Now a lot of people saw a huge problem with that.
They were like, "Oh, it needs to have more features.
It needs to have all these things."
I was like, I'm happy with this text editor.
That hasn't changed at all.
Basically when Allan stopped working on it
for a decade or more.
I don't need anything else.
Because as our original discussion went,
I don't want an IDE.
I don't want the editor to write code for me.
I want to text editor.
I want interact with characters directly.
And Neovim allows me to do that in some ways
that are even better than TextMate.
And I love TextMate, but Vi as you know.
Once you learn the commands and it sounds,
I sometimes feel like Vi fans overplay
how difficult it is to learn
because it makes them perhaps seem kind of more awesome
that they were able to do it.
It's not that difficult.
And it doesn't take that long, in my opinion,
to learn just enough combo moves
to get that high of holy shit,
I could not do this in any other editor.
- How long did it take you?
And by the way, I don't know, I haven't yet.
Oh, I know, intellectually.
But just like with kids,
I haven't gone in all the way in.
I haven't used Vim.
- You have a treat in mind.
Well, I switched in about,
I had three days when I switched here about a year ago.
I had three days of cursing
where I thought it was absolutely terrible
and it was never gonna happen.
And I had three days of annoyance
and already the next week I was like, this is sweet.
I'm not going anywhere.
But I also had a bit of a head start about
20 years ago in early 2000s.
I tried Vim for like a summer and it didn't stick.
I didn't for whatever reason love it at the time.
But Neovim is really good.
The key to Neovim is to realize
that you don't have to build the whole editor yourself.
There's a lot of Neovim stans are like,
here's how to write the conflict from scratch.
Over 17 episodes, that's gonna take you three weeks.
Ah, I don't care that much.
I love a great editor.
I love to tailor it a little bit, but not that much.
So you have to pair Neovim with this thing called LazyVim.
Lazyvim.org is a distribution for Neovim
that takes all the drudgery
out of getting an amazing editor
experience right out of the box.
- Ridiculous question, we talked about
a bunch of programming languages.
You told us how much you love JavaScript.
It's your second favorite programming language.
Would TypeScript be the third then?
- TypeScript wouldn't even be in this universe.
I hate TypeScript as much as I like JavaScript.
- So what you hate, oh man,
I'm not smart enough to understand the math of that.
Okay, before I ask about other programming languages,
if you can encapsulate your hatred of TypeScript
into something that could be human interpretable,
what would be the reasoning?
- The JavaScript smells a lot like Ruby
when it comes to some aspects of its metaprogramming.
And TypeScript just complicates that
to an infuriating degree
when you're trying to write that kind of code.
And even when you're trying to write
the normal kind of code,
none of the benefits that accrue to people who like it.
Like auto completion is something I care about.
I don't care about auto completion
because I'm not using an IDE.
Now I understand that that is part
of what separates it and why.
I don't see the benefits.
I only see the costs.
I see the extra typing.
I see the type gymnastics that you sometimes have to do
and where a bunch of people give up
and just do any instead, right?
Like that they don't actually use the type system
because it's just too frustrating to use.
So I've ever only felt the frustration of TypeScript
and the obfuscation of TypeScript in the code
that gave me no payoff.
Again, I understand that there is a payoff.
I don't want the payoff.
So for my situation,
I'm not willing to make the trade
and I'm not willing to take a language that underneath
is as dynamic of a language as rubious
and then turn it into this pretend
statically type language.
I find that just intellectually insulting.
- Do you think it will
and do you think it should die TypeScript?
- I don't wanna take something away
from people who enjoy it.
So if you like TypeScript, all the most part of you.
If you using TypeScript because you think
that's what a professional program is supposed to do,
here's my permission,
you don't have to use TypeScript.
- There's something deeply enjoyable about
a brilliant programmer such as yourself,
DHH is talking shit.
It's like one of my favorite things in life.
What are the top three programming languages
everyone should learn
if you're talking to a beginner?
- I would 100% start with Ruby.
It is magic for beginners
in terms of just understanding the core concepts
of conditionals and loops and whatever,
because it makes it so easy.
Even if you're just making a shell program
that's outputting to the terminal,
getting hello-world running in Ruby
is basically puts, P-U-T-S, space, start quotes,
hello world, end quotes, you're done, right?
There's no fluff.
There's nothing to wrap it into.
There are other languages that does that,
especially in the Perl or Python
would be rather similar.
But Go would not, Java would not.
There's a lot of other languages
that have a lot more ceremony and boilerplate.
Ruby has none of it.
So it's a wonderful starting language.
There's a book called "Learn to Program"
by Pine that uses Ruby
essentially to just teach basic programming principles
that I've seen heavily recommended.
So that's a great language.
- [Lex] How quickly would you go to Rails?
- It depends on what you wanna do.
If you wanna build web applications,
go to Rails right away.
Learn Ruby along with Rails,
because I think what really helps
power through learning programming
is to build programs that you want, right?
If you're just learning it in the abstract,
it's difficult to motivate yourself to actually do it.
Well, some people learn languages
just for the fun of them.
Most people do not.
Most people learn it
because they have a mission.
They wanna build a program.
They wanna become a programmer.
So you gotta use it for something real.
And I actually find that it's easier to learn programming
that way too because it drives your learning process.
You can't just learn the whole thing up front.
You can't just sit down
and read the language specification,
then go like, ooh, like Neo.
Now I know kung fu.
Now I know Ruby.
It doesn't download that way.
You actually have to type it out in anger
on a real program.
- Yeah, yeah, for sure.
- So I would start there.
But then number two, I probably would be JavaScript.
Because JavaScript just is the language
you need to know if you wanna work with the web.
And the web is the greatest application
platform of all time
if you're making business software,
collaboration software, all this kind of stuff.
If you're making video games,
you should probably go off and learn C++ or C
or something else like that.
But if you're in the realm of web applications,
you gotta learn JavaScript.
Regardless of what else you learn,
- So if you're learning Ruby,
what does Ruby not have in terms of programming concepts
that you would need other languages for?
- I dunno if there's any concepts missing,
but it doesn't have the speed or the low level access
of memory manipulation that you would need to build
a 3D gaming engine, for example.
No one's gonna build that in Ruby.
You could build quite low level stuff
when it comes to web technologies in Ruby.
But at some point, you're gonna hit the limit
and you should use something else.
I'm not someone who prescribed just Ruby for everything.
Just once you reach the level of abstraction
that's involved with web applications, Ruby is superb.
But if you're writing, for example, HTTP proxy,
go, it's great for that.
We've written quite a few HTTP proxies
lately at the company for various reasons,
including our cloud exit and so forth.
And Kevin, one of the programs I'm working with,
he writes all of that in Go.
Go just have the primitives
and it has the pace and the speed
to do that really well.
I highly recommend it.
If you're writing an HTTP general proxy, do it in Go.
Great language for that.
Don't ride your business logic in Go.
I know people do, but I don't see the point in that.
- So what would you say the three,
so Go, Ruby plus Rails, JavaScript?
- Yeah, if you're interested in working with the web,
I'd pick those three.
Go, Ruby and JavaScript.
- Go, Ruby and JavaScript, okay.
Functional languages?
- Someone's talking about Ocaml.
- They are always going to show up.
It must be some kind of OCaml industrial complex
or something like this.
But they always say mention OCaml.
- I love that there are people
who love functional languages to that degree.
Those people are not me.
I don't care at all.
Like I care about functional principles
when they help me in these isolated cases
where that's just better than everything else.
But at heart, I'm an object oriented guy.
That's just how I think about programs.
That's how I like to think about programs.
That's how I carve up a big problem space
into a domain language.
Objects are my jam.
- Yeah, me too.
So I program a Lisp a bunch
for like AI applications for basic.
So Othello, chess engines, that kind of stuff.
And I did try OCaml just to force myself
to program just a very basic game of life.
A little simulation.
It's much, you know,
Lisp is just parentheses everywhere.
It's actually not readable at all.
- That's the problem I've had with Lisp.
- OCaml is very intuitive, very readable.
It's nice.
- I really should pick up a language
like that at some point.
I've been programming long enough
that it's a little embarrassing
that I haven't actually done anything real in anger
in a fully functionally programming language.
- Yeah, but like I have to figure out,
I'm sure there's an answer to this.
What can I do that would be useful for me
like that I actually wanna build?
- Yes, yes, that's my problem
- That a functional language is better suited for.
- That's right. - Because I really
wanna experience the language properly.
- [DHH] That's right.
- Yeah, 'cause I'm still, yeah.
At this point, I'm very object-oriented brained.
- Yes, and that's my problem too.
I don't care as much about these low level problems
in computer science.
I care about the high level.
I care about writing software.
I care about the abstraction layer
that really floats well
with web applications and business logic.
And I've come to accept that about myself.
Even though, as we talked about when I was a kid,
I really wanted to become a games programmer.
And then I saw what it took
to write a collision detection engine.
And I go like, yeah, that's not me at all.
I'm never gonna be into vector matrix manipulation
or any of that stuff.
It's way too much math
and I'm more of a writing person
than I'm of a math person.
- I mean, just in the way you were speaking today,
you have like a poetic literary approach to programming.
- Yes. - Yeah.
- It's interesting, that's actually exactly right.
So I did actually a keynote at RailsConf 10 years ago
where I call myself a software writer.
I mean, I'm not the first person to say that software writer
has been in the vernacular for a long time.
But the modern identity that most programmers adopt
when they're trying to be serious is software engineer.
And I reject that label.
I'm not an engineer.
Occasionally I dabble in some engineering,
but the vast majority of the time, I'm a software writer.
I write software for human consumption
and for my own delight.
I can get away with that
because I'm working in a high level language like Ruby,
working on collaboration software
and to-do lists and all the other stuff.
Again, if I was trying to apply my talents
to writing 3D game engines,
no, that's not the right mindset.
That's not the right identity.
But I find that the software engineering identity
flattens thing a little bit,
I'd like to think that we have software writers
and software mathematicians, for example.
And then those are actually richer
ways of describing the abstraction level
that you're working at than engineer.
- Yeah, and I think if AI
becomes more and more successful,
I think we'll need software writer skill more and more.
Because it feels like that's the realm
of which, 'cause it's not writer.
You're gonna have to do the software.
You're gonna have to be a computer person.
But there's a more... I don't know,
I just don't wanna romanticize it,
but it's more poetic, it's more literary.
It's more feels like writing a good blog post than...
- I actually wish that AI
had a bit higher standards for writing.
I find the fact that it accepts my sloppy,
incomplete sentences a little offensive.
I wish there was like a strict mode for AI
where it would snap my fingers.
It was just feeding it key words
and like speak proper,
do pronunciation, do punctuation,
because I love that.
I love crafting a just right sentence
that hasn't been boiled down,
that it has no meat on, it has no character in it.
It's succinct.
It's not overly flowery.
It is just right that writing phase,
to me, is just addictive.
And I find that when programming is the best,
it's almost equivalent exactly to that.
You also have to solve a problem.
You're not just communicating a solution.
You have to actually figure out
what are you trying to say, but even writing has that.
Half the time when I start writing a blog post,
I don't know exactly what arguments I'm gonna use.
They develop as part of the writing process.
And that's how writing software happens too.
You know roughly the kind of problem
you're trying to solve.
You don't know exactly how you're gonna solve it.
And as you start typing, the solution emerges.
- And actually, as far as I understand,
you and Jason are working on a new book.
It's in the early days of that kind of topic.
I think he said,
he tweeted that it's gonna be titled something like,
we don't know what we're doing upfront, something like that.
That kind of topic.
And you figure out along the way.
- That's a big part of it.
Trying to give more people the permission
to trust your own instincts and their own gut
and realizing that developing
that supercomputer in your stomach
is actually the work of a career.
And that you should not discard those feelings
in preference to over comp...
or not even complicated,
to analytics, to intellectualism.
Very often when we look at the big decisions
we've had to make, they've come from the gut
where you cannot fully articulate like,
why do I think this is the right thing?
Well, because I've been in this business for 20 years
and I've seen a bunch of things
and I've talked to a bunch of people,
and that is percolating into this being the right answer.
A lot of people are very skeptical about that
in business or unable to trust it
because it feels like they can't rationalize.
Why are we doing something?
Well, because I feel like it, damn it.
That's a great privilege
of being a bootstrapped independent founder
who don't owe their business to someone else
and doesn't have to produce a return.
Because I feel like a lot of the really creeps in
when you're trying to rationalize to other people
why you do the things you do
and why you take the decisions that you do.
If you don't have anyone to answer to,
you are free to follow your gut.
And that's hell of enjoyable way to work.
And it's also in very often the correct way to work.
Your gut knows a lot, like you can't articulate it,
but it's spot on more times than not.
- Yeah, having to make a plan can be a paralyzing thing.
I've often, I mean,
I suppose there's different kinds of brains.
And first of all,
I can't wait to read that book if it materializes.
I often feel like in the more interesting things
I do in my life,
I really don't know what I'm doing up upfront.
And I think there's a lot of people around me
that care for me that really want me
to know what I'm doing.
They're like, what's the plan?
Why are you doing this crazy thing?
And if I had to wait until I have a plan,
I'm not gonna do it.
They have different brains on this kind of stuff.
Some people really are planners
and it maybe energizes them.
I think most creative pursuits, most really interesting,
most novel pursuits are like,
you kind of have to just take the leap
and then just figure out as you go.
- My favorite essay in "Rework" is the last one,
and it's entitled, Inspiration is Perishable.
And I think that captures a lot of it,
that if you take the time to do a detailed plan,
you may very well have lost the inspiration
by the time you're done.
If you follow the inspiration in that moment
and trust your gut, trust your own competence,
that you will figure it out,
you're gonna get so much more back.
You're gonna go on the adventure
you otherwise wouldn't have.
Whether that's just a business decisions or life decision,
you have to seize that inspiration.
There's a great set of children's books
written by this Japanese author about chasing an idea
and trying to get a hold of it,
and it's beautifully illustrated as an idea
something that's floating around
as something you have to catch and latch onto.
That I really feel captures this notion
that inspiration is perishable, it'll disappear.
If you just put it back on the shelf and say like,
well, I gotta be diligent about this.
I gotta line up a plan.
You may run out and then there's no steam to keep going.
- I have to ask about open source.
What does it take to run a successful open source project?
You've spoken about that.
It's a misconception that open source is democratic.
It's actually meritocratic.
That's a beautiful way to put it.
So there's often is a kind of also a benevolent
dictator at the top often.
So can you just speak to that?
Having run successful open source projects yourself
and being a benevolent dictator yourself.
- Which is gonna be a bit of a biased
piece of evidence here, but I...
- But why monarchy is best. - It's great.
We should definitely have dictators
and they should control everything,
especially when the dictator is me.
Now, well I think I learned very early on
that a quick way to burn out in open source
is to treat it as a business,
as though your users are customers,
as though they have claims of legitimacy on your time
and your attention and your direction.
Because I faced this almost immediately
with Ruby on Rails.
As soon as it was released,
there were a million peoples
who had all sorts of opinions about
where I ought to take it.
And not just opinions, but actually demands.
Unless you implement an Oracle database adaptive,
this is always gonna be a toy.
It was actually more or less that exact demand
that prompted me to have a slide at one
of the early Rails conferences that just said, fuck you.
- [Lex] Yeah, I saw that.
- I'm not gonna do what you tell me to.
I'm here as a bringer of gift.
I am sharing code that I wrote on my own time,
on my own volition.
And you don't have to say thank you.
I mean it'd be nice if you did.
You can take the code and do whatever you want with it.
You can contribute back if you want,
but you can't tell me what to do
or where to go or how to act.
I'm not a vendor.
This is a fundamental misconception
that users of open source occasionally step into,
because they're used to buying software from companies
who really care about their business.
I care about people using my software.
I think it's great,
but we don't have a transactional relationship.
I don't get something back
when you tell me what to do except grief.
And I don't want it, so you can keep it.
So my open source philosophy
from the start has been, I gotta do this primarily for me.
I love when other people find use in my open source.
It's not my primary motivation.
I'm not primarily doing it for other people.
I'm primarily doing it for me and my own objectives
because as Adam Smith said,
it's not for the benevolence of the butcher
that we expect our daily meat.
It's for his self-interest.
And I actually find that to be a beautiful thought
that our comments increase in value
when we all pursue our self-interest.
Certainly in the realm of open source.
This is also why I reject this notion
that open source is in some sort of crisis.
That there's a funding crisis that we have to spend more.
No, we don't.
Open source has never been doing better.
Open source has never controlled more domains
in software than it has right now.
There is no crisis.
There's a misconception from some people making open source
and from a lot of people using open source.
That open source is primarily like commercial software.
Something you buy
and something where you can then make demands as a customer.
And that the customer is always right.
Customer is not always right.
Not even in business, but certainly not in open source.
In open source,
the customer, as it is, is a receiver of gifts.
We are having a gift exchange.
I show up and give you my code.
If you like it, you can use it.
And if you have some code that fits in
with where I'm going with this,
I would love to get those gifts back.
And we can keep trading like that.
I give you more gifts.
You give me some of your gifts.
Together, we pool all the gifts
such that someone showing up brand new,
just get a mountain of gifts.
This is the magic thing of open source
is it increases the total sum value
of what's in the common
when we all pursue our own self-interest.
So I'm building things for Rails that I need.
And you know what?
You want me to do that.
You do not want me to build things
that I don't need on behalf of other people,
'cause I'll do a crap job.
I build much better software
when I can evaluate the quality of that software
by my own use.
I need this feature.
I'm gonna build a good version of that feature
and I'm gonna build just enough just for me.
So I'm not gonna bloat it.
I'm not trying to attract the customer here.
I'm not trying to see some angle.
I'm just building what I need.
And if you go into open source with that mentality
that you're building for you and everything else is a bonus,
I think you have all the ingredients to go to distance.
I think the people who burn out in open source
is when they go in thinking, "I'm making all these gifts.
I don't really need them myself,
but I'm like hoping someone else does
and maybe they'll also give me some money."
That's a losing proposition.
It never basically works.
If you want money for your software,
you should just sell it.
We have a perfectly fine model of commercial software
that people can make that kind
and then they can sell it.
But I find a lot of confusion,
let's just call it that politely,
in open source contributors
who want to have their cake and eat it too.
They like the mode of working with open source.
They maybe even like the status that comes from open source,
but they also would like to earn a living
for making that open source.
And therefore, they occasionally end up
with the kind of grievances
that someone who feels underappreciated at work will develop
when others aren't doing enough to recognize
their great gifts.
- And then they might walk away.
I wish I had more insight into their mind state
of the individual people that are running these projects,
like if they're feeling sad or they need more money
or they're like, it's just such a dark box.
- It can be.
- I mean of course there's some communication,
but I just sadly see too often
they just kind of walk away.
- Right, and I think that's actually
also part of the beauty of open source.
- Is walking away. - You are not obligated
to do this code forever.
You're obligated to do this for as long as you wanna do it.
That's basically your own obligation.
- But there is a, I know, okay...
So you might criticize some pushback.
You did write a blog post on forever,
until the end of the internet with ta-da list.
There is a beautiful aspect
and you found a good balance there.
But I don't know, you're bringing so much joy to people
with this thing you created.
It's not an obligation, but there's a real beauty
to taking care of this thing you've created.
There is and not forgetting.
I think, what I think
what the open source creator is not seeing enough
and I mean there's like,
how many lives you're making better.
There's certain pieces of software
that I just quietly use a lot.
And like they bring my life joy
and I wish I could communicate that well.
There's ways to donate, but it's inefficient.
It's usually hard to donate.
- It is.
There's some ways for some people that made it easier.
GitHub donations is one way of doing it.
I donate to a few people
even though I don't love the paradigm.
I also accept that we can have multiple paradigms.
I accept that I can do open source
for one set of motivations
and other people can do
open source for other motivations.
We don't all have to do it the same way.
But I do want to counter the misconception
that open source is somehow high in a crisis
unless we all start paying for open source.
That model already exists.
It's commercial software.
It works very well and plenty of great companies
have been built off the back of it.
And the expectations are very clear.
I pay you this amount and I get this software.
Open source, once you start mixing money into it,
gets real muddy real fast.
And a lot of it's just from those misaligned expectations.
That if you feel like you're starving artists
as an open source developer
and you are owed X amount of money
because your software is popular, you're delusional
and you need to knock that off.
Just get back on track
where you realize that you're putting gifts into the world.
And if you get something back
in terms of monetary compensation,
okay, that's a bonus.
But if you need that money back
in terms of monetary compensation,
you just charge for software
or go work for a software company
that will employ you to do open source.
There's tons of that.
That is probably actually the primary mode
that open source software
is being developed in the world today.
Commercial companies making open source
that they need themselves and then contributing it back.
- So I'm glad you sort of like
drew some hard lines here.
It is a good moment to bring up
what I think is the, maybe one of the greatest
open source projects ever, WordPress.
And you spoke up in October 24
about some of the stuff that's been going on
with WordPress's founder Matt Mullenweg
in a blog post open source royalty and mad kings.
It's a really good blog post
on sort of just the idea of Benevolent Dictators For Life,
this model for open source projects.
And then the basic implication
was that Matt as the BDFL of WordPress
has lost his way a bit with his battle with WP Engine.
So I should also say that I really love WordPress.
It brings me joy.
I think it's a really...
it's a beacon of what open source could be.
I think it's made the internet better.
It allowed a lot of people to create wonderful websites.
And I also think, now you might disagree with this,
but from everything I've seen,
WP Engine just gives me bad vibes.
I think they're not the good guy in this.
I don't like it.
I understand the frustration.
I understand all of it,
but I don't think that excuses the behavior.
There is a bit of, see this kind of counter
to a little bit what you said,
which is when you have a open source project of that size,
there is a bit of a, like when you're the king
for a project of a kingdom that large,
there's a bit of responsibility.
Anyway, could you speak to your, maybe to your empathy
of Matt and to your criticism
and maybe paint a path
of how he and WordPress can be winning again?
- First echo what you said about
what a wonderful thing it is that WordPress exists.
That there are not many projects
in the open source world or in the world at large
that has had as big of an impact on the internet
as WordPress has.
He deserves a ton of accolades for that work.
So that was my engagement, essentially my premise.
Do you know what?
I had tremendous respect
for what Matt has built with WordPress.
What that entire ecosystem has built around itself.
It's a true marvel.
But there's some principles
that are larger than my personal sympathies
to the characters involved.
I agree.
The Silver Lake private equity company
that's involved with WP Engine is not my natural ally.
I'm not the natural ally of private equity
doing some game with VP Engine.
That's not my interest in the case.
My interest is essentially a set of principles.
And the principles are if you release
something as open source,
people are free to use it as they see fit.
And they're free to donate code or resources
or money back to the community as they see fit.
You may disagree about whether they've done enough,
whether they should do more, but you can't show up
after you've given the gift
of free software to the world
and then say, now that you've used that gift,
you actually owe me a huge slide of your business
because you got too successful
using the thing I gave you for free.
You don't get to take a gift back.
That's why we have open source licenses.
They stipulate exactly what the obligations are
on both sides of the equation.
The uses of open source don't get to demand
what the makers of open source do and how they act.
And the makers of open source
don't get to suddenly show up with a ransom note
to the users and say,
actually you owe me for all sorts of use.
I'm 100% allergic to that kind of interaction.
And I think Matt, unfortunately, for whatever reason,
got so wrapped up in what he was owed
that he failed to realize what he was destroying.
WordPress and Automatic already makes a ton of money.
This is part of the wonder of WordPress.
This is a project
that generates hundreds of millions of dollars,
and Matt didn't feel like he was getting enough of that.
That's not a good argument, bro.
You can't just violate the spirit
and the letter of these open source licensees
and just start showing up with demand letters
even to characters that are not particularly sympathetic.
This goes to the root of my interpretation
of open source in general.
The GPL is a particular license
that actually demands code
from people who use it under certain circumstances.
I've never liked the GPL.
I don't want your shitty code
if you don't wanna give it to me.
What am I gonna do with that?
Some code dump that youve...
I'm not on board with that part of Stallman's vision at all.
I love the MIT license.
To me that is the perfect license
because it is mercifully short.
I think it's two paragraphs, three paragraphs.
Really short, and it basically says, here's some software.
It comes with no warranty.
You can't sue me.
You can't demand anything,
but you can do whatever the hell you want with it.
Have a nice life.
That's a perfect open source interaction in my opinion.
And that license needs to be upheld.
These licenses, in general, even the GPL,
even if I don't like it,
we have to abide by them.
Because if we just set aside those licensees,
when we in a moment's notice
feel like something's slightly unfair,
we've lost everything.
We've lost the entire framework
that allowed open source to prosper
and allowed open source
to become such an integral part of commerce too.
I mean, back when open source was initially
finding its feet,
it was at war with commercial software.
Stallman is at war with commercial software
and always has been.
Bill Gates was in return at war
with open source for the longest time.
The open source licensees
and the clarity that they provide
allowed us to end that war.
Today, commercial software and open source software
can peacefully coexist.
I make commercial software.
I sell Basecamp, I sell HEY,
and then I also make a bunch of open source software
that I give away for free as gifts.
That can't happen
if we start violating these contracts.
No commercial company is gonna go,
"Let me base my next project
off this piece of open source.
If I'm also running the liability
that some mad maker is gonna show up seven years in
and demand, I give them $50 million."
That's not an environment conducive
to commerce collaboration or anything else.
And it's just basically wrong.
I think there's one analysis that's all about
kind of the practical outcomes of this,
which I think are bad.
There's also some an argument that's simply about ethics.
This is not right.
You can't just show up afterwards and demand something.
This is not too dissimilar in my opinion,
to the whole Apple thing we talked about earlier.
Apple just showing up and feeling like they're entitled
to 30% of everyone's business.
No, that's not right.
That's not fair.
So I think Matt unfortunately
kind of steered himself blind
on the indignity
he thought was being perpetrated
against him because there was all this money being made
by VP Engine making a good product
and not giving quite enough back in Matt's opinion,
tough cookie.
- I think there, maybe I'm reading too much into it,
but there might be some personal stuff too,
which they weren't only not giving enough,
but probably implicitly promising that they will give
and then taking advantage of him in that way in his mind,
just like interpersonal interaction.
And then you get like interpersonally frustrated,
that forget like the bigger picture ethics of it.
It's like when a guy keeps saying, you know,
promising you'll do something.
And then you realize you wake up one day
like a year or two later.
Wait a minute, I was being lied to this whole time
and that I don't even know if it's about money.
- I'd get mad too.
It's totally fine to get mad when people disappoint you.
That's not justification for upending decades
of open source licensees
and the essential de facto case law
we've established around it.
This is why I chose to even weigh in on this
because I like WordPress.
I don't use WordPress.
I'm not a part of that community.
I don't actually have a dog in this fight.
I'm biased if anything towards Matt just as a fellow BDFL.
I would like to see him do well with this.
But I also think there's some principles at stake here
that ring much louder.
I don't want Rails to suddenly be tainted
by the fact that it's open source
and whether companies can rely on it
and build businesses on it.
Because wait, maybe one day I'm gonna turn Matt
and I'm gonna turn Matt King
and I'm gonna show up with a demand ransom letter.
No, screw that.
We have way more to protect here.
There's way more at stake than your personal beef
with someone or your perceived grievance
over what you're owed.
- What would you recommend?
What do you think he should do, can do
to walk it back to heal?
- Decide, this is the curious thing.
He could decide to give this up.
That's very, very difficult
for driven, ambitious people to do.
To accept that they're wrong
and to give up and lay down their sword.
So I had a hope earlier on in this that that was possible.
I haven't seen any evidence
that Matt is interested in that
and I find that deeply regretful,
but that's his prerogative.
I continue to speak out
when he's violating the spirit
and ethics of open source,
but I wish he would just accept
that this was a really bad idea.
He made a bad bet and I thought,
I think he thought he'd just get away with it.
That they'd just pay up and that he could put pressure.
I mean, I know that temptation.
When you sit as the head
of a very important project,
you know that that comes with a great degree of power
and you really need a great degree of discipline
to reign that in and not exercise that power
at every step where you feel aggrieved.
I've felt aggrieved a million times over
in the 20 plus years of Ruby on Rails.
I've really tried very hard not to let those...
sometimes petty, sometimes substantial grievances over time
seep in to the foundation of the ecosystem
and risk ruining everything.
- As the king of the Rails kingdom,
has the power gotten to your head over the years?
- I'm sure it has.
I mean, who wouldn't?
- Do you pace around in your chamber angry?
- I do occasionally.
And I do marvel at both what's been built,
what's been possible.
Over a million applications
have been made with Ruby on Rails
by one estimate that I've seen,
businesses like Shopify and GitHub
and a million others have been built
on top of something that I started.
That's very gratifying.
But you really have to be careful not
to smell your own exhaust too much.
And you have to be just as careful
not to listen too much to the haters
and not to listen too much to the super fans either
that you assess the value
and the sort of principles of what you're working towards
on its own merits, on your own scoreboard.
I try to block that out and then just go,
well I'm working on Rails because I love to write Ruby.
I love to use Ruby to make web applications.
That's my north star.
And I'll continue to do that and I'll continue to share
all of the open source gifts
that I uncover along the ways,
and that's it.
That's enough too.
I don't have to get all of it out of it.
This is sometimes just as with the guy
who thought I'd given up on being Jira or something,
instead of doing Basecamp,
there are people over the years who've asked like,
why didn't you charge for Rails?
Like, don't you know how much money
have been made off Rails?
If we just look at something like Shopify,
it's worth billions of dollars.
I'm not a billionaire
and so freaking what?
I got more than enough.
I got plenty of my share.
I will say though, I'm also introspective enough
to realize that if it hadn't panned out as well
as it did for me on my own business,
maybe I would've been more tempted.
Maybe if you see other people build
huge successful companies off the back of your work
and you really don't have a pot to pissed in,
you might be tempted to get a little upset about that.
I've seen that in the Rails world as well,
where there are people who contributed
substantial bodies of work
and then got really miffed
when they didn't feel like they got enough back.
I was fortunate enough that the business
that Jason and I built with Ruby on Rails
was as successful as it was.
And I made the money I needed to make
that I didn't need to chase the rest of it.
- But we should also just make explicit
that many people in your position
chase the money.
It's not that difficult to chase.
Basically you turned away money.
You made a lot of decisions that just turned away money.
- Maybe, I also think of this example with Matt.
He probably thought there was easy money
for the taking.
And it wasn't so easy, was it?
It looked like low hanging dollar bills
and they turned out to be some really sour grapes.
It turned out
he probably destroyed vast sums of money
by undermining the whole WordPress trust
and the ecosystem
and putting question marks in the heads of folks
who would choose to use WordPress
or something else going forward.
So I often think when people think like,
you left money on the table.
First of all, so what?
I don't have to have all the money.
But second of all,
maybe the money wasn't on the table at all.
- And maybe the cost.
Even if you got the money,
maybe the cost in other ways,
like we've talked about,
would outweigh all the money
that you could have possibly gotten.
Meaning like I think you said that the thing
that makes you happy is flow and tranquility.
Those two things.
Beautifully, really beautifully put.
And it, you know, gaining money might assign
to you responsibility of running a larger thing
that takes away the flow
that you gain from being... fundamentally for you
what flow means is programming.
And then tranquility is like,
I think you also have a beautiful post
of like Nirvana is an empty schedule.
- When I look at a upcoming week
and I see that I have no scheduled meetings at all,
which is quite common,
or maybe I just have one thing for one hour on one day.
I think to myself, do you know what?
This could very easily have been very different.
We could have been running a company of hundreds of people
or thousands of people and my entire calendar
would've been packed solid with little Tetris blocks
of other people's demands on my attention and time,
and I would've been miserable as fuck.
And I look at that and go like that,
what more can I ask for?
Which is a really nice state of being I'd actually say.
I didn't have this always.
I did have early on in my career some sense of like,
I need a little more.
A little more security.
And I remember this really interesting study
where a bunch of researchers asked people
who would made certain amounts of money,
how much money would it take for you to feel secure?
They'd ask people who had a million dollars network?
How much money do you need?
Probably need 2 million.
2 million then I'd be good.
Then they'd ask people with a net worth of 5 million,
how much do you need?
Ah, 10, I need 10.
Ask people with 10 million,
what do you need? 20.
Every single time people
would need double of what they did.
I did that for a couple of doublings
until I realized, you know what?
This is silly.
I am already where I wished
I would be and a million times over.
So what less is there to pursue?
Now that doesn't mean
that if more money is coming my way,
I'm gonna say no to it.
Of course not.
But it does mean that I'm free to set other things higher.
And I also do think you realize,
as Jim Carrey would say,
I wish everyone would get all the money they wished for
and they'd realize it wasn't the answer.
That money solves a whole host of problems and anxieties,
and then it creates a bunch of new ones.
And then it also doesn't touch
a huge swath of the human experience at all.
The world is full of miserable,
anxious, hurt, rich people.
It's also full of miserable, anxious, poor people
and I'd rather be a miserable, anxious, rich person
than a poor person.
But it isn't this magic wand that make everything go away.
And that's again, one of those insights
just like having children
that you cannot communicate in words.
I've never been able to persuade a person
who's not wealthy that wealth wasn't gonna solve
all their problems.
- One quote you've returned to often
that I enjoy a lot is the Coco Chanel quote
of the best things in life are free.
And the second best things are very, very expensive.
And I guess the task is to focus
on surrounding yourself with the best things in life
like family and all of this
and not caring about the other stuff.
- I would easily say you can care about the other stuff.
Just know the order of priority.
If you are blessed with a partner that you love,
some children that you adore,
you've already won the greatest prize
that most humans are able to achieve.
Most humans in this world,
if they are of marital age and they have children,
if you ask them what's the most important thing,
they would all say that.
They would all say that.
No matter whether they're rich or poor.
It's easy to lose sight of that
when you're chasing the second best things.
Because do you know what?
They're also very nice.
I really like that Pagani Zonda.
It was a very expensive car
and I would have no chance of acquiring it
if I hadn't become rather successful in business.
So I don't wanna dismiss it either.
It's great fun to have money.
It's just not as fun for quite as long
or as deep as you think it is.
And these other things, having an occupation
and a pursuit that you enjoy,
being able to carry burdens with a stiff up of a lip
and with, again, a sense of meaning is incredible.
To have family, to have friends, to have hobbies,
to have all these things that are actually available
to most people around the world, that's winning.
And it doesn't mean you have to discount your ambitions,
it doesn't mean you can't reach for more,
but it does mean it's pretty dumb
if you don't realize that
it's not gonna complete you
in some hocus-pocus woo sense to make more.
It really isn't.
- What gives you hope about the future
of this whole thing we have going on here?
Human civilization.
- I find it easier to be optimistic than pessimistic,
because I don't know either way.
So if I get to choose,
why not just choose to believe it's gonna pan out?
Like we suffer more in our imagination
than we do in reality.
That's one of the quotes out of stoicism.
And I also think we have a tendency,
a lot of humans have a tendency
to be pessimistic in advance
for things they don't know how it's gonna pan out.
Climate change, for example,
is making a lot of people very anxious
and very pessimistic about the future.
You know nothing.
40 years ago we thought the problem
was that the planet was gonna be too cool.
I happen to believe that it's probably correct
that the planet is getting too hot
and that CO2 has something to do with it.
Whether we have the right measures to fix it in time,
if that's even possible or not,
is completely up in the air
and we don't know.
If you convince yourself with such certainty
that the world is gonna turn to shit, it is.
Right up here, in your head today.
Climate change might wipe out this entire species
in 200 years is not next year.
It's not 10 years from now.
Life might become more unpleasant
and there might be more negative effects, and so on.
Yes, okay, but then deal with that hardship
when it arrives.
Don't take that in advance.
How are you helping earth
by just walking around being depressed?
- I think our whole conversation today
is also an indication.
It's just two humans talking.
There's billions of us,
and there is something about us
that wants to solve problems and build cool stuff.
And so we're gonna build our way out
of whatever we get ourselves into.
This is what humans do.
We create problems for ourselves
and come up,
figure out how to build rocket ships
to get out of those problems.
And sometimes the rocket ships
create other problems like nuclear warheads
and then, I'm sure,
I hope, figure out ways how to avoid those problems.
And then there'll be nanobots
and then the aliens will come
and there'll be a massive war
between the nanobots and the aliens,
and that will bring all of us humans together.
- The funny thing,
just to pick up one of the points you mentioned,
the atom bomb, for example.
When that was first invented,
a lot of people thought
we have essentially ended life on earth, right?
Or maybe we prevented World War III
from happening in the past 80 years
because assured mutual annihilation
kept the superpowers from attacking each other
at least head on
and kept their fighting to proxy wars.
You know what?
Proxy wars are not great,
but they're probably better than World War III
with nuclear weapons.
So it's quite difficult in the moment
to tell what's actually benefit and what's not.
And I think we should be a bit more humble.
I've certainly become more humble over time
of thinking I know which way it's gonna turn.
I think the pandemic was a huge moment
for a lot of people
where there was so much certainty
about whether this intervention worked
or that intervention didn't work.
And most people were wrong.
Certainly a lot of very smart people,
very qualified people got that just utterly
and catastrophe finely wrong.
So just a little intellectual humility,
I think back upon that and go like, you know what?
I'm not a PhD in virology
and I don't claim that like I somehow saw
how it always gonna play out.
But the people who were really experts in it,
they got a bunch of it wrong.
Nobody knows anything.
I keep reminding myself of that every day.
No one knows anything.
We can't predict the economy a month out.
We can't predict world affairs a month.
The world is just too complicated.
- Yeah, when I watched the Netflix
documentary "Chimp Empire"
and you know, there's a hierarchy of chimps,
all of that looks eerily similar to us humans.
We're recent descendants.
So these experts,
some of the chimps are got a PhD, others don't.
Others are really muscular.
Others are like beta male kind.
They're sucking up to the alpha.
There's a lot of interesting dynamics going on
that really maps cleanly to the geopolitics of the day.
They don't have nuclear weapons,
but the nature of their behavior is similar to ours.
So I think we barely know what's going on,
but I do think there's like a basic
will to cooperate.
A basic compassion that underlies
just the human spirit that's there.
And maybe that is just me being optimistic.
But if that is indeed there, then we're gonna be okay.
- The capacity is certainly there.
Whether we choose that capacity or not,
who knows and in what situation?
I think accepting that we all have the capacity
for both ways, for both incredible generosity
and kindness and also cruelty.
I think, Young, with this whole theory
of the shadow is really spot on.
That we all have that capacity in us
and accepting that it's our job
to attempt to cultivate the better parts
of our human nature
is weighed against our propensity
to sometime be the worst of ourselves.
- I'm excited to find out what's gonna happen.
It's so awesome to be human.
I don't wanna die.
I kind of wanna be alive for a while
to see all the cool shit we do.
And one of the cool things
I wanna see is all the software you create
and all the things you tweet.
All the trouble you get yourself into on Twitter.
David, yeah, I'm a huge fan like I said.
Thank you for everything you've done for the world,
for the millions of developers you've inspired,
and one of whom is me.
And thank you for this awesome conversation brother.
- Thanks so much for having me.
- Thanks for listening to this conversation with DHH.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description
and consider subscribing to this channel.
And now let me leave you
with some words from "Rework" by DHH and Jason Fried.
What you do is what matters,
not will you think or say, or plan.
Thank you for listening
and I hope to see you next time.