- For the vast majority of human existence.
We've been nomadic and we've done these kind of wider
or tighter nomadic circles,
depending on the geographic region, but they'd move.
So once humans figured out how to stay in a place,
that's the initial trigger
to what would become civilization.
- I think you said beauty
and blood went hand in hand for the Aztec.
- What I meant by that is they were absolutely comfortable
with human sacrifice and,
you know, ripping people's hearts out.
They had this just, you know, grotesque, violent bent.
But in the same way, they also
absolutely loved flower gardens and poetry
and music and dance.
The same Aztec king who would order the hearts
of a thousand people extracted also would stand up
at dinner parties to recite his own poetry,
but they were really just surgical about it.
They'd use a thick obsidian knife
where they could just break the ribs right along the sternum
and then push the sternum down, pull up and just.
- While the person was alive?
- Yep, while the person was alive.
- The following is a conversation with Ed Barnhart,
an archeologist specializing in ancient civilizations
of South America, Mesoamerica and North America.
This is the "Lex Fridman Podcast," to support it,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Ed Barnhart.
Do you think there are lost civilizations in the history
of humans on Earth, which we don't know anything about?
- Yes, I do, and in fact, you know,
we have found some civilizations that we had no idea about,
just in my lifetime.
I mean, we've got go Gobekli Tepi
and we've got the stuff that's going on in the Amazon
and there's some other less startling things
that we had no idea existed and pushed our dates back
and give us whole new civilizations we had no idea about.
So yeah, it's happened and I think it'll happen again.
- Do you think there's a lost civilization in the Amazon
that the Amazon jungle has eaten up
or is hiding the evidence of?
- Yes, I do, and we're beginning to find it.
There are these huge, what we call geoglyphs,
these mound groups that are in geometric patterns.
I think that the average Joe,
when they hear the word civilization,
they think of something that looks like Rome.
And I don't think we're ever gonna find anything
that looks like Rome in the Amazon.
I think a lot of things there, I mean,
wherever you are on the planet,
you use your natural resources.
And in the Amazon, there's not a whole lot of stone.
What stone is there is deep, deep, deep.
So a lot of their things were built out of dirt
and trees and feathers and textiles.
- But is it possible that all that land that's not covered
by trees is actually hiding stone?
For example, some architecture, some things
that's just very difficult to find for archeologists.
- I think at the base of the Andes where the Amazon connects
to the Andes, there's a lot of potential there
'cause that's where the stone actually starts poking up.
When you get down into the basin, stone is meters
and meters under the ground except for a stray cliff here
and there where the river dug deep.
And even then, only in the dry season
'cause that river rises like
over a hundred feet every year.
- Well, that's one of the things, having visited that area,
just interacting with waterfalls
and seeing the water, I was humbled by the power of water
to shape landscapes
and probably erase history in the context
that we're talking about of civilizations,
as water can just make everything disappear
over a period of centuries and millennia.
And so if something existed a very long time ago,
thousands of years ago,
it's very possible it was just eaten up by nature.
- Absolutely, in fact, in my opinion,
that's almost a certainty in a lot of places.
You know, the Grand Canyon was dug by water.
There's this wimpy little river in it right now,
and you can't possibly imagine that it dug that, but it did.
The power of nature and geology is really kind of magical.
And when it comes to, you know, ancient civilizations
that could be from a long time ago, there's probably a lot
that are just under the ocean.
And just the wave action have destroyed them
and what they haven't destroyed buried deep.
- Under the ocean.
So you think Atlantis ever existed?
- I don't think that Atlantis existed.
I do think it was one
of Plato's many parables talking about, you know,
putting it in an interesting story
as a teaching device in his school.
If one did exist or a shadow of it,
my money would be on Akrotiri.
Akrotiri is what's left of a big city
that was on the island of Santorini.
And when their volcano blew up, it blew up most of the city
and shot chunks of it so fast
that 70 miles away in Crete,
there are chunks of Santorini in their cliff.
So it blasted what was ever there.
But what's left on the side of the crater, Akrotiri,
is strangely advanced for its age.
And so if there's anything that's a model for Atlantis,
as Plato explained it, it's Akrotiri.
- Akrotiri, the ancient Greek city.
So it says the settlement was destroyed
in the Theran eruption sometime in the 16th century BCE
and buried in volcanic ash, which preserved the remains
of the frescoes and many objects and artworks.
So we don't know how advanced that civilization was.
- No, but we can walk around the ruins
and see that it's got streets, it's got plumbing,
it's got little sconces for torches at night.
It was a vibrant city with a lot of, especially
in terms of hydraulic engineering.
It's very advanced for being 3,500 years old.
- So if you check out, here's an image
of the excavation, what a project.
- It's an amazing place.
And you can tell that it's just part of it
because it's pretty close to where the crater begins.
So the city itself was probably much larger.
- So in this case, there's a lot of evidence.
But like we said,
there could be civilizations that there is no,
there's very little evidence of,
because of the natural environment
that destroys all the evidence.
- And I think Akrotiri is actually a great example
of that because here we have the side that did preserve,
that looks amazing,
but we know there was more of the city
that was completely obliterated.
It was shot, chunks of that city are probably
in the walls of Crete 70 miles away.
And you know, Plato says that it sunk,
it was on an island and it sunk.
Well that's exactly what happened to Akrotiri.
- You think this is what Plato was referring to?
- If it does exist, at least the model of it,
I think this is probably what he was talking about.
- And there could be other civilizations
of which Plato has never written?
- Absolutely. - That we have no record of.
And it's humbling to think that entire civilizations
with all the dreams, the hope, the technological innovation,
the wars, the conflicts, the political tensions,
all of that, the social interactions, the hierarchies,
all of that, the art can be just destroyed like that
and forgotten, completely lost to ancient history.
- I reflect upon that often as an archeologist.
I think about this great country that I live in
and love and all the things we've achieved.
But you know, we're a baby historically speaking.
We've been around 200 years.
Heck, a lot of the cities I study in Central
and South America, they had a run of, you know, 800,
a thousand years and now they're ruins.
But we're barely getting started in terms
of historical civilizations.
- So humans, homo sapiens evolved,
but they didn't start civilizations right away.
There's a long period of time
when they did not form these complex societies.
So how do we, let's say 300,000 years ago in Africa
actually go from there to creating civilizations?
- I think that a lot of human evolution
had to do with the pressures
that their environment put upon them.
And you know, a lot of things start changing
right around 12,000 years ago.
And that's when, you know, our last ice age really ended.
And I think there was a whole lot of things
that just pressured them into, especially finding new ways
of subsistence.
Here in the Americas,
a huge thing that happened was all the megafauna went away.
When the climate changed enough, the mammoths died out
and the bison died out.
And there was just, they had to come up
with different ways of doing things.
We were hunters and gatherers
and we had things we got from hunting
and we got things we got from gathering.
And in the Americas when the things
that they were used to hunting went away
and they had to make do with rabbits there, you know,
the gathering started to be a much more important thing.
And I think that led to figuring out,
hey, we could actually grow certain things.
And gardens turned into crops, turned into intensive crops,
and then people were allowed to gather in bigger groups
and survive in a single area.
They didn't have to roam around anymore.
And that's where we get the first sedentary communities,
which means they stayed in the same place all year long.
For the vast majority of human existence,
we've been nomadic and we've done these kind of wider
or tighter nomadic circles,
depending on the geographic region where they'd know, okay,
you know, in the mountains,
we'll be in the summer, in the mountains
'cause there's berries and things.
And then in the winter we'll be down here
and we'll hunt, but they'd move.
So once humans figured out how to stay in a place,
I think that's the initial trigger too,
what would become civilization.
- What do you think is,
there's a lot of questions I wanna ask here.
What do you think is the motivation for societies?
Is it the carrot or the stick?
So you said like, is it, well, like when resources run out,
when the old way of life is no longer feeding everybody,
then you have to figure stuff out.
Or is it more the carrot of like, there's always this kind
of human spirit that wants to explore,
that wants to maybe impress the rest of the village
or something like this with the new discovery they made
in venturing out and coming out with different ideas
or technological innovation, let's call it?
- Well, you know, I have an explorer's heart,
so I'm kind of, you know, I'm biased.
You know, I do think
that we have an innate desire to see what's on the horizon.
And to impress other people
with our achievements, things like that.
We're social beings.
That's really the edge that humans have
is our ability to work together.
So I think that it's much more the carrot than the stick.
When things get ugly, the stick comes out.
But usually the carrot does the job.
- The really interesting story is
how the first people came to the Americas.
I mean, to me that's pretty gangster to go from Asia
all the way potentially during the ice age,
maybe at the end of the ice age
or during that whole period, not knowing
what the world looks like going into the unknown.
Can you talk through that process?
How did the first people come to the Americas?
- Well, first off, I agree with you.
That was pretty gangster.
I mean, that's a hard place to live.
I listened to some of your podcasts.
Is that guy Jordan Jonas?
He cut the mustard,
but I wouldn't have made it crossing there.
- Well there you go,
like the fact that those guys exist,
that somebody like Jordan Jonas exists, people that survive
and thrive in these harsh conditions,
that's an indication that it's possible.
But yeah, so when do you think,
and how did the first people come?
- The traditional theories are still somewhat valid,
or at least you know, on the table that when
that land bridge occurred, that nomadic hunters
just followed the game like they always had
and the game went across there 'cause there was no barrier
and they followed them across.
The thing that has changed is how early that happened.
DNA has been a total game changer for archeology.
You know, we get all these evolutionary tracks
that we could never see before.
When I was a young archeologist,
I would've never dreamed we'd have
the information we have now.
And that information, a lot of it's coming out
of Texas A&M, we see the traditional
like 12,500 years ago that there was a migration.
But now we're seeing one
that's almost certainly happening closer
to 30,000 years ago.
And now the thing that seems like madness,
but might be true is that it could have been as early as 60,
a lot of the DNA things are suggesting
that the very first migration
could have come across as early as 60.
And when I was a younger archeologist,
it was heresy to go beyond this 12,500.
You were a wacko if you said that,
but now it's really very clear that they came over
at least by 30,000 and the bridge opened
and closed and open and closed.
- That's during the ice age. - Right.
- I mean, that's crazy, right, that is crazy.
- Yeah, I mean, you know, they didn't roll in
and immediately make New York, but there were people
and there were definitely not people here
before that, which is fascinating.
When the bridge closed, DNA mutated.
And so we have specific kinds of haplogroup
that are here in the Americas that don't exist otherwise.
And that same haplogroup game has been showing us more
and more that people came across Siberia.
That it's not Africa, it's not Western Europe.
Those are still, you know, they've become kind
of fringe theories, but they're not totally eradicated.
DNA is a developing science as well.
And I think we all need to keep that in mind,
that it's not like they just cracked the code
and now we know all the answers.
And sometimes, like in any science,
a breakthrough puts us two steps backwards, not forwards.
So I think, you know, we don't need to have too much faith
in the models that are now being created through DNA,
but they are pointing in the direction
of everybody came across from Siberia
that all Native American people are
of Asiatic descent.
- Do you think it was a gradual process
if it's like 30 to 60,000 years ago?
Was it just gradual movement of these nomadic tribes
as they follow the animals?
Or was it like one explorer
that pushed the tribe to just go, go, go, go
and go across maybe across a hundred years,
travel all the way
across maybe into North America, into North, North America
where Canada is now, and then sort
of like big leaps in movement versus gradual movement?
- I think it was big leaps
and now this is just, you know, mostly guess,
I'll admit, but I think that it much in the way that a lot
of our evolutionary models talk about
punctuated equilibrium, that there are big moments of change
and then it settles out into a more slow
and steady pattern and then something big will happen again.
I do think that the early people went as far
as they could go, and there were certain colonies
that just got isolated for thousands of years.
One of the fascinating things that DNA is showing us,
which actually blood types were showing us
way before that, is
that the oldest people in the Americas are in South America.
The ones that got separated early
and didn't mix their DNA, like the people in the Amazon,
most of those guys have O blood type
and they're haplogroup D, which is the oldest one
that entered the US and what are they doing down there?
I do believe they came across the Bering Strait,
I don't think it's very, we have no real evidence
to say they came in mass across Oceania.
So they made it probably by boat along the coast,
all the way to South America.
- So there's some kind of cultural engine
that drove them to explore.
So if you had to bet all your money,
it happened like tens of thousands of years ago.
But in a very rapid pace, there's these explorers,
they went all the way to South America
and there established their kind of more stable existence.
And from there, South America, Mesoamerica,
North America was kind of gradually expanded into that area.
- I think the next waves came down
and did North America and Central America.
And the very first wave made it all the way down
to South America and got isolated there,
and then mixed in with the next groups that came.
- That's fascinating. - Kinda like there's,
there's an interesting correlate in Europe
where today everybody feels
like Celtic people are from Ireland,
but actually Celtic people started in Eastern Europe
and it was the entire area.
And when Rome kind of swept everything
and Rome was now the ruler of the day,
it was only that far edge of the Celtic world, Ireland
that they were like, ah, we're not gonna mess
with those guys on that island.
We'll leave them be, so now it looks like that's the heart
of Celtic tradition, but actually it's the fringe.
- So if it is 60,000 years ago,
these are really early humans.
- Yeah, and there were consistent things
that have been coming out for decades
about very old Carbon 14 dates in the Amazon
and in the Andes area that everybody just dismissed.
It's, no, it didn't get a date of 40,000 years,
but I think we're gonna come back around
to start readdressing some of these
based on new evidence at hand.
- And that's the interesting thing is, you know,
the early human spread throughout the world
and then like you said, perhaps have gotten isolated
and then civilization sprung from there
and they all have similar elements
even though they were isolated.
That's really interesting.
That's really interesting that there's multiple cradles
of civilization, not just one, like one good idea,
that those ideas naturally come up.
Those structures naturally come up.
- And I wonder whether, you know, the similarities
that all those cradles have, it could be, you know,
a shared much deeper past that they all have.
Or it could be a more kind of Star Trek thing where,
you know, captain Kirk was always talking
about the theory of parallel human development,
that humans across the universe go through certain stages
of development and that that could be the answer to it.
- Which one do you lean on?
Which one do you lean towards?
- I think it's a case by case thing.
I think if we look globally,
I'd lean much more towards the human parallel development.
But if I look just to the Americas,
and we have a shorter time period where, you know,
the things that become major civilizations,
now I'll say, you know, up to 30,000 years ago,
which is still a blip in the time of humans,
I think that there were shared things
that those people came over with from Asia,
and that as they got separated, that they had core values
that then turned into things like religion
and cultural customs that we can see.
I'm a big proponent that there are commonalities
in all the cultures of the Americas that lead back to
and point to a single distant origin.
- You've spoken about the lost cradle
of civilization, South America.
So South America is not often talked about
as one of the cradles of civilization.
So South America, Mesoamerica, can you explain?
- Well, we have very early stuff in South America.
You're right, I mean, you know, especially,
as an American, our country's so big
and you know, that we are so far removed from these places,
we don't even think about it.
But more and more we're seeing things that predate
the earliest stuff that we like to talk about,
like Egypt and Mesopotamia.
There are things, it's all on the Peruvian coast
that we have these cradles of civilization.
Someday we might start talking about the Amazon more
and more, but right now what we've got are things
that date back into the three thousands BCE
along the coast of Peru.
And there are big stone built pyramids and temples
and they're amazingly isolated,
even now that we've found them.
Some of them, like Caral is one
of the most famous ones just north of Lima.
We've known about it for a couple decades now,
how old it is.
But every time I visit there, it's like I visited the moon,
there's absolutely nobody there.
Not for miles.
It's amazing how such a discovery was made
and yet still nobody goes to see it.
It's not easy to get to.
- So you think there's a bunch of locations like that.
Some may not have been discovered in the Peru area.
- Oh, there are so many, Peru has tons,
that desert gets really ugly quick
and it buries things completely.
There are so many pyramids out there
that are still completely untouched.
You know, when people hear the name pyramids,
they think of Egypt immediately.
But Egypt has got about 140 pyramids,
and we have pretty much found them all.
Peru has thousands, thousands of pyramids.
And now they weren't built of a lot,
not all of them were built of stones.
Some of them were adobe bricks,
which have weathered terribly.
So now they don't look,
they're not exciting places to visit today.
You know what's funny too, you know,
we started off talking about, you know,
whether I think there's a lost civilization out there,
there are definitely things that are still to be discovered,
but there are some things
that were discovered a hundred years ago and archeologists
or back then, they called themselves antiquarians
just kind of passed over.
Caral was one of these sites
because the coast of Peru has some of those pyramids
that were made by the Moche are full of gold
and beautiful ceramics.
And you know, things that you can sell for big money,
but Caral was found a long time ago,
but the archeologist was like, God, no gold,
no ceramics, forget about it.
This place is no good, we can't sell anything here.
And then about the 1970s or eighties,
somebody said, hey, no ceramics,
is that older than the invention of ceramics.
Shit, we better go take another look at that place.
- So what's the dating on Caral?
- Caral I think starts at about 3,200 BCE
and it lasts as a major civilization with a lot
of other cities around it, until about 1800 BCE.
- So what's the story behind,
like looking at some of these images?
What's the story about constructions like that?
What was the idea?
- That thing, isn't that amazing?
Oh that, gosh.
I mean, it should be some sort of, you know,
I'll be a flaky archeologist, like, you know,
this is a place where rituals took place.
So many things we say are so just painfully vague.
And that's about, you know, what we got.
And a place like this.
I know the one we're looking at here,
I've been here a couple of times.
In the pyramid behind it, the rubble's built in a way
where the building won't rock apart.
This is a very earthquake prone place,
but the buildings haven't fallen
because they make these net baskets
of rocks inside that all kinda wiggle around
and don't allow the building to fall down.
And inside these, we've also found a couple of things
that were babies, that were human babies
that were buried in there.
And I don't think, there's a lot of people
that see that and go, oh, look at that.
They were sacrificing babies, these monsters.
I think a lot of the things that are interpreted
as baby sacrifices, Caral's evidence being one of them,
I think it's more about the tragic nature
of infant mortality,
in the past it was a lot more common.
There were cultures that didn't even really
properly name their kid until they got to five
because chances were they were gonna die.
And so I think a lot of these babies
that we find in these ceremonial contexts
that are interpreted as sacrifices,
I think they're putting them in special places
because they mourn the death of their kids
and it just happened a lot more frequently then.
- One of the things you said that really surprised me is
that pyramids were built in Peru, possibly hundreds of years
before they were built in Egypt.
Is that true?
- Absolutely, absolutely, in fact, there's.
- That's crazy. - There's one
that's now pushing 6,000 BCE,
like that's thousands of years before the stuff in Egypt
and that one's called Huaca Prieta.
And it was not a, it was not an Egyptian pyramid.
But it was a pyramid
and it was thousands of years before.
- What do you think is the motivation to build a pyramid?
The fact that it can withstand the elements structurally,
that kind of thing, is it?
Why do humans build pyramids
and why do they build it in all kinds
of different locations in the world?
- Well, you know, my root answer is pretty boring really.
A lot of people ask me,
why are there pyramids all over the planet?
How is that, is that a coincidence, I mean, who?
I think that when people wanted
to build a big building without rebar or cement,
you end up building something with a fat base
that goes up to a skinny top and that turns into a pyramid.
You know, any kid who's playing
with blocks on the floor builds a couple towers
and his brother knocks them down.
And if he wants one that's gonna stay and be tall,
he ends up making something with a fat base
and a tiny top.
And I think that, you know, building something big
and tall together is one of those human things.
Like we built that, that will be here after we're gone.
People remember who we were.
We are all, if there's any human commonality,
it's fear of our own deaths and that we were nothing
and no one will ever remember us.
I think that the first big monuments like that were probably
a group of people saying we're gonna do something
that people will remember forever.
Now that being said, you remember we were just talking
about Huaca Prieta and this one
that's almost 6,000 BC now is the first one.
That one's a funny case.
We just talked about all these lofty goals,
but actually I'm pretty sure
that Huaca Prieta's first pyramid was about capping
a smelly pile of trash.
I think everybody piled up their trash
in the middle of town.
And it stunk, it's on the coast, it stunk like fish.
And somebody said, if we just bury this thing with dirt,
it won't smell anymore.
And then it was a big mound where people could get up
and talk to everybody and then said, well, it's squishy,
you know, if we cap it with clay,
then it will really not smell.
I really think that the very first pyramids
in Peru were about trash management.
Talk about deflating, huh?
- Yeah, but then they probably saw it
and they were impressed and humbled by the sort
of the enormity of the construction.
And then they're like, oh, we should,
maybe the next guy thought maybe we should
keep building these kinds of things.
- Yeah, yeah, not to jump ahead,
but in North America, you know,
where they also made pyramids.
There's this interesting evolution
where there were these piles of shells along rivers
and along the coastlines, people ate a lot of shells.
That was an easy thing to collect and eat.
So these piles of shells would be near communities
and they probably became landmarks,
but eventually they started burying their dead
inside those too, probably again, you know, about stink
and about, you know, well we don't want the dogs to eat 'em.
Maybe we put 'em in the middle of the shell pile.
But then that all of a sudden became this like,
that's where my grandfather's body is.
That's where great grandfather's body is.
And all of a sudden people started being attached to place,
not just for the resources,
but for the shared memories of their ancestors.
So when the very first pyramid was built
in Ohio area by the Adena people, it was built outta dirt,
but it's full of bodies.
And I think it's an echo of a old thing where they used
to be putting bodies in shell mounds.
- So where and who were the first civilizations
in South America, Mesoamerica?
- Well, you know, I think we're still piecing that together.
Coming back to the first things we talked about,
I think we're still missing a lot of stuff,
especially in South America.
It just keeps getting older and older.
Part of the reason it's hard to answer that question is,
you know, at what point do we consider people
a civilization or a culture?
We have in the Americas this long period of time
that we call the Paleo Indian time
where they were hunting megafauna.
And then when those went away,
we get into this even longer period
of time called the archaic,
where they're just hunters and gatherers.
Sometimes somebody's coming up
with a cool different kind of arrowhead.
They go back and forth with different hunting tools,
but really nothing changes for thousands of years.
And then finally they start developing
into these larger groups, which for the most part has
to do with agriculture, it used to be archeology.
That was just the end all, be all, civilization starts
with the invention of agriculture.
And we can't have sedentary communities
until people learn how to farm.
But that's been discounted.
Peru was a big part of that, that area of Caral.
It's connected to another city on the coast called Aspero.
And Aspero starts about the same time,
but they're all about fishing.
They have no farming.
And Caral who's up river from them is farming.
But funny enough, they're not really farming food.
They're farming cotton and they're making nets
and they're trading the nets
with the people on the coast for the fish.
So it's not as simple as it's just agriculture anymore.
But it is, I think, still rooted in
how can we feed more people than just our family?
How can we together create a food abundance
so we're no longer scared about running out of food?
- So is it possible, which is something you've argued
that civilization started in the Amazon,
in the jungle versus the coast?
- I think so, I think religion
in South America began in the Amazon.
I think there were people there, very old.
There's actually the earliest pottery in all
of the Americas of all these places
that we have civilizations that grew up, you know,
where the oldest pottery is?
The middle Of the Amazon.
- So there's interesting cultures developing in the Amazon.
So religion, you would say preceded civilization?
- In South America, Caral and Aspero,
that I was just talking about.
It's weird what a dearth of art
and any evidence of religion we have, we have those pyramids
and things that we call temples,
but we don't really know what went on in there.
And there's no hints of religious iconography,
ceremonies, nothing like that.
The first stuff that we get is right
when that culture ends about 1800 BCE,
this culture called Chavin starts up and they,
their main temple is up in the Andes.
And this place of path
of least resistance between the Amazon and the coast.
It's about three days walk either way from this place
where this temple is, that's
where we start seeing the very first religious iconography.
And it's all over the temples.
There are things that are definitely from the coast,
but the iconography are all jaguars and snakes
and crocodiles, and those don't come from the coast.
All of those things are coming out of the Amazon.
- Religion is a really powerful idea.
Religions are one of the most powerful ideas.
They're the strongest myths that tie people together.
And to you, it's possible that this powerful idea
in South America started in the Amazon.
- I do, I do think it did.
And you're right, you know,
ideas are more powerful than weapons,
but archeology can't see them at all.
We can see, sometimes we can see ideas manifesting
in the things they create and lead to,
but there's an interpretation problem.
Are we right about what idea created this?
That those are things that archeology just can't get at.
- That's one of the challenges of archeology
and looking into ancient histories.
You're trying to not just understand
what they were doing in terms of architecture,
but understand what was going on inside their mind.
- That's really what I'm in it for,
trying to understand these people
and it's real detective work
and we know we're dealing with a totally flawed record.
We only have what could preserve the test of time.
You know, if we look around this room here,
if 2000 years of weathering happened in this room,
what would be left and what would we think happened here?
- Right, right, right.
But there's not in this room,
but if you look at thousands of rooms like it,
maybe you can start to piece things together
about the different ideologies that ruled the world,
the religions, the different ideas.
Tell me about this fanged deity.
One of your more controversial ideas is
that you believe that the religions,
there's a thread that connects the different civilizations
to societies of the Indian region
and the religion that practice is more monotheistic
than is currently believed in the mainstream.
- That is exactly what I think.
And I think it's all about this fanged deity
who somewhere thousands of years ago crawled his way out
of the Amazon up into the Andes and a religion took hold.
That could have been kind of a combination
of ideas from the coast and the Amazon.
But he is the one creator deity,
in my opinion, through all of these cultures.
And the people in the Amazon still talk about him.
There his name is Vijomase in some groups.
But they say that his emissaries on Earth are the jaguars
and that he is the creator deity.
- Why is the current mainstream belief is that a lot
of the religions are not monotheistic?
- Well, there are bonafide pantheons.
You know, Greece had one,
Egypt had one, Mesopotamia had one.
Lots of the early religions
of the old world were pantheons.
And I think that was part of the problem.
The earliest archeologists walked in there
with a preconceived notion
that ancient cultures have pantheons.
And so they went to the art looking for them
and they came up with things like the shark god
and the moon goddess and the sun God and all these things.
But when I look at the art,
and I was trained by a person right here in Austin, Texas
as an art historian,
you follow certain diagnostic traits through art
to see the development over time.
And when I look at it
and use that methodology, there's a single face
with goggle eyes and fangs and claws on his hands and feet
and snakes coming off of his head and off of his belt.
He's got really identifiable traits.
He also likes to sever people's heads off
and carry them around.
But he's the fanged deity
and he's there, he shows up in Chavin de Huantar,
the capital of that Chavin culture.
And he keeps showing up through every culture,
even thousands of miles away
throughout the next two millennium,
right up to the Inca.
The Inca have a creator deity, they call Viracocha.
But Viracocha is the fanged deity.
When we do see him, by the time you get to Inca,
they do this kind of like almost Islamic thing
where they say you can't understand the face of Viracocha.
So when they do put him in a cosmogram,
they'll make him just a blob.
Like he's just unknowable, but he's at the very top.
I think we're misunderstanding a lot of things that we used
to say were deities as just supernatural beings.
If we flip the mirror on Christianity
and take a look at it,
which of course Christianity's monotheistic, right,
it would be heresy to say otherwise.
But who are all these other characters?
Who are all these angels and demons
and you know, Jesus Christ
and I mean, I don't even know who the Holy Spirit is,
but he's some sort of supernatural being.
But it's that monotheistic system has lots of things
that have supernatural powers that are not God.
That's where I think the crux
of us misunderstanding ancient Andean art is.
- So what is the process of analyzing art through time
to try to figure out
what the important entities are for that culture?
Do you just see what shows up over
and over and over and over?
- Well, certainly without the advent of writing,
depictions in art have all sorts
of meanings encoded in them.
And there are certain, you know,
what we call diagnostic elements.
Like we can pull apart the same sort
of thing in like in the Greek pantheon, you know,
you know by their dress and what they're holding,
what the different gods are.
You can tell Hades from Zeus
by the different things they're holding, you know,
lightning bolts or tridents or whatever it is.
So they all have these diagnostic elements to them.
So that's how art history goes
about analyzing art over time.
Once we can put it in a chronological sequence,
then we can say, okay,
here's a deity here in Chavin culture.
Now we move forward 500 years, now we're in Moche
and Nazca culture, you know,
where are the deities here?
And what I see is that same guy with not just one
or two traits, but a whole package of them
that shows up again and again
and again for thousands of years in each one
of these cultures, he's got circular eyes,
he's got a fanged mouth,
he's got claws on his hands and feet.
He's a humanoid,
but he also has snakes coming off of his head, like hair
and snakes coming off of his belt.
And then not so much in Chavin,
but as it goes forward, he starts carting around
severed heads, human severed heads.
So they're like, in the old literature,
the Moche will call him the decapitator deity.
But then they have these other like,
oh, here's the crab deity and here's the fox deity.
But if you look at them, like the crab deity is just
that guy's face coming off of a crab.
And the fox deity is that guy's face coming off of a fox.
So I think on that particular instance,
I explained it similar to what Zeus did.
You know how Zeus was able to like, you know,
turn into whatever animal he wanted
to get with the woman he wanted.
And he showed up in all sorts of forms.
But he was always Zeus.
I think that the fanged deity manifests himself
through people and animals throughout the art.
And that there are missing stories of mythology
that we don't have anymore.
- And across hundreds of years, thousands
of years from Chavin to Moche to Inca as you're saying.
- Right, Wari has them too.
Tiwanaku, that famous place Pumapunku,
he's all over there.
- I wonder how those ideas spread and morph
of this fanged deity.
- I think people walked and proselytized
and places like Chavin,
there's a later one in Inca times called Pachacamac
that are pilgrimage places where people come in
to be healed if they're sick,
but also just to pay homage to the powers that be.
So Chavin was a place where people from the Amazon
and people from the coast were all coming together.
In fact, we saw it in the archeology there.
There's these interesting labyrinths under the pyramids
with the fanged deity all over them that have like,
one labyrinth will have all pottery.
The next labyrinth will have a bunch of animal bones.
The next one will have a bunch of things made outta stone.
So people are showing up and giving this tribute
and they're learning
and then they're going back to their community.
So I think it dispersed from certain pilgrimage spots
and became just like pilgrimage spots do.
Somebody goes back and they build a temple
to the fanged deity.
- Do we know much about the relationship they had
with the fanged deity and like their conception
of the powers of the fanged deity?
Were they afraid of the fanged deities
and all knowing God?
Is it something that brings joy and harvest
or is it something that you're supposed to be afraid of
and sacrifice animals and humans to keep at bay?
- I think he had two sides of the coin.
Like a lot of the Hindu gods are, you know,
one aspect is terrible, the other aspect is lovely.
I think he had that same sorts of qualities
'cause we do see him
as a fierce warrior taking people's heads off.
And he is a jaguar, which in
and of itself implies a certain power and ferocity.
But then there are other funny things about him.
Like he is definitely involved
in a lot of healing ceremonies
and a lot of those healing ceremonies are involved
with sex acts, when it comes to the Moche,
there's this whole group
of sexual pottery where priests are having sex
with women or men.
And some of them show their faces transforming
into that fanged deity.
Like he is acting through them.
But the thing that most cracks me up
that shows his softer side
is the fanged deity has a little puppy.
He has a puppy that's like just dancing around his feet
and like jumping up on him in various scenes.
They see him again and again.
Sometimes he's in these healing sex scenes.
In fact, I tracked that puppy from other contexts
to these sex scenes where a priest was having sex
with somebody in a house and there's a fanged deity
and there's a puppy just scratching at the door like,
hey, you forgot me.
And then finally one day I found one
with the puppy having sex with the woman
instead of the fanged deity.
I was like, oh, he really is very involved in this.
What is this weird puppy?
So yeah, he likes to take heads off,
but he also has a puppy he adores.
- Actually this awesomely makes sense now
because I saw the opening
of a paper you wrote 30 years ago on shamanism
and Moche civilization.
It reads "the Moche are the major focus of this paper,
sex, puppies and headhunting will be shown to be related
to ancient Moche shamanism."
So now I understand, I was like, well, the puppies?
- [Ed] Yeah, it's true.
- And the headhunting, that's the decapitate aspect.
- And I've added rock and roll to that list since actually,
rock and roll are, you know,
music is also a big part of it.
- Oh, interesting. - They call spirits down.
There's this whole spirit world.
There's the ancestors
and the people that drink San Pedro cactus juice
kind of, they don't talk about the fanged deity anymore.
I think Christianity in 500 years
has somewhat put him in the back.
You know, it was unpopular to have a pagan deity.
So they don't talk about him much anymore,
though he's still around.
They're in like around Trujillo, they call him Aiapec.
But music play in the Amazon, they play flutes.
Sometimes a chorus of women sing
and that's supposed to bring the spirits down
into the ceremony.
There's a spirit that's hurting the person that's sick.
And then the priest or the shaman or the curandero,
whatever you wanna call him, has his own posse of spirits
that are gonna help him figure out what's going on.
So when the music starts, that's bringing
those spirits in and people don't see them
unless they've imbibed the San Pedro Cactus Juice,
which is the hallucinogen,
which is in the Amazon side, it was ayahuasca.
On the coast, it was San Pedro Cactus.
But that's what allows you to actually see that other world.
- Yeah, I went to the Amazon recently
and did Ayahuasca, a very high dose of it.
- Bold move.
- When in Rome.
How far back does that go?
- Oh, I think longer than anybody can remember.
But I mean, it's a natural plant that's been there forever.
I think that it's thousands and thousands of years.
That's another thing Chavin de Huantar, I was talking about,
where I think the things came,
the religion came from the Amazon.
There's this wall on the backside
that faces the Amazon side.
So if you're entering the city from the Amazon path,
you see this wall first.
And it's a bunch of faces that some of them are human,
some of them are total jaguar
and some of them are transforming in between.
But there's a group of them
that are midway through transformation
and they show their nostrils leaking out this snot
that's coming like down their face.
San Pedro doesn't do that to you, but ayahuasca does.
Ayahuasca traditionally, they'd take a blow gun
and just shoot it up your nose or up your ass.
But a lot of times up your nose.
And when it shoots up your nose, the first thing
that happens is just this gush of snot comes out of you.
And there are stone depictions
of people uncontrollably snotting
on the backside of this temple from,
you know, 3000 years ago.
- So that you think could have been a big component
of the development of religion and shamanism?
- I think that hallucinogens opened the mind then,
like they opened the mind now.
- Do you think that, you know, the stoned ape theory,
do you think that actually could have been
an actual catalyst for the formation of civilization?
- In the Americas, yes, I do, though,
you know, hallucinogens are not part
of every ancient tradition in the world.
In fact, strangely, the majority of plants
that are actually psychotropic, not just mood altering,
are from here in the Americas.
There are very few drugs
that will make you hallucinate outside of the Americas.
Of course now they're global
and you know, they can be grown all over the place.
But originally speaking,
very, very few were outside of the Americas.
So they were part of the experience here in a way
that they just couldn't be in other places.
- I wondered to a degree, they were just part of a ritual
and the creative force behind sort of art
versus like literally the method
by which you come up with ideas that define a civilization.
So like the degree
to which they had a role in the formation of civilizations.
It's kind of fun to think about psychedelics being
like a critical role in formation of civilizations.
- I think in terms of South America,
they really were.
In North America where we're in a more northern climb here
and there are less of them, not so much, at least in terms
of psychedelics, things like, you know,
tobacco was always a big part of it.
But a lot of the, you know,
there's more than one way
to reach a hallucinatory state.
The hard way is starvation, sleep deprivation.
And for the Maya, for example,
would go sleep deprivation, starvation,
and then they'd cut themselves very badly.
And that loss of blood, we believe triggered hallucinations
and visions, nothing to do with drugs.
I would much prefer the drugs route.
- It's the result,
the tools aren't the thing that creates insight.
It's the result.
- It's that getting to, you know,
the hallucinogens are poisoning us, they're killing us.
That's, you know, it's a near death state.
And people of the Americas believed
sleeping was entering that other world.
Death, you entered this other world
and that when you took this mighty dose of poison,
it was helping you enter
that other world for a period of time.
- Yeah, as Tom Waits said in that one song,
"I like my town with a little drop of poison."
So maybe that poison is a good catalyst for invention.
So who were the early first sort of mother cultures,
mother civilizations in South America?
And like what is, if we look chronologically,
is there a label we can put
on the first peoples that emerged?
- That picture is evolving.
I mean, forever it was just the Chavin people
that we've been talking about.
The ones with all the first depictions
of religious art were the mother culture.
And they certainly did transmit a lot of stuff,
but then all of a sudden we find Caral.
The next one that we've barely even begun looking at,
but it's probably older than Caral is Sachin culture.
I was just poking around there last year
and just from the bus on the highway,
I could see like, that's a pyramid out there.
What, oh, there's another one.
And I know how old the stuff we have studied there is,
it's again, 3000 BC,
we're just barely beginning to understand them.
Caral frustrates me to no end.
The lack of art there that's, we've got, you know,
stones and bones and not even ceramics to go on.
And they didn't have the courtesy to leave me a bunch
of art I can interpret.
So I don't know what those people believed.
- Right, so one of the ways to understand
what people believe is looking at the art,
the stories told through the art, and then hopefully
deciphering if they were doing any kind of writing.
- That's our most fruitful place to try
to get at these elusive ideas.
- Yeah, and it sucks when they don't have art.
If we just go back to the Amazon, you've mentioned
that it's possible that there's a lost civilization
that existed in the Amazon.
So it's carried a lot of names, Lost City of Z or El Dorado.
Do you think it's possible it existed?
- Well, City of Z
and El Dorado are in pretty different places.
El Dorado, the ideas of where it is kind
of center around towards Columbia.
And the City of Z is named
after a region of Brazil called the Xingu.
And so those, those are an America worth
of distance apart, you know,
people don't really think about it on the map,
but the entire United States would fit inside the Amazon.
That's how big that place is.
And these two are on either end,
but both of them have evidence of civilizations.
These big, you know, it's lowland
and it floods all the time.
So what they did is they'd make these big mounds
and then they'd make huge causeways between mounds
so they could walk through their cities
while they were seasonally inundated.
And a bunch of that stuff has been found in the Xingu area,
like huge areas that would support
tens of thousands of people.
Again, you know, it's not stone built
and it's been under the forest forever,
so it's very torn up.
But it's there now.
You know, Brazil is big
on cattle farming more than ever now.
And a thing that I think is completed now is Brazil
and Bolivia partnered together
and built a highway all the way across
and opened up a whole bunch more land, which has found more
of these, what we call like geometric earthworks.
So there's more and more evidence of these civilizations.
It's not, it could be there, it's there for sure.
- By the way, the people who are trying
to protect the rainforest really hate the highway.
One of the things I learned is
if you build a road, loggers will come.
And they'll start cutting stuff down.
Now from an archeology perspective, if you cut down trees,
you get to discover things.
But from a sort of protecting
very precious rainforest perspective,
it's obviously the opposite way.
But it is interesting I've seen where loggers cut
through the forest
and when they leave the forest heals itself very quickly.
- [Ed] So quick, so quickly.
- And you know, you just think that across decades,
you expand that to centuries and it's like you could see
how a civilization could be completely swallowed up
by the rainforest.
- And it happened for sure in the Amazon.
You know, one of the ways that we're trying
to push the frontier of where people were in the Amazon
'cause yes, the trees
and just the biomass have eaten so much evidence,
but they're finding more
and more of these places that they call terra preta,
which is black earth and there's huge swaths of it.
So I guess the anthropology term
is anthropogenic landscapes.
And what they're saying is that
that really dark earth couldn't have just got that way
through natural forest processes
that sometime in the distant past that forest wasn't there
and there was major farming
and human activity to the point
where they totally turned the soil black
and it's much more enriched.
And when I took a trip into the Amazon,
I went from Manaus up the river, the black river a couple
of days and went and met some different communities
and I asked them about this black earth
and they were like, yeah, that's why we're here.
Sometimes we move our village,
but when we move we look for the terra preta
and that's where we're gonna put our village
because that's a place that all of our gardens work.
The other places they don't.
- One of the things you talked about literally,
you have to ask the right question
and the stories, all the secrets that carried
by the people and they'll tell you.
- Yeah, there's so many of them.
You know, a thing
that excites the world about archeology right now
is Gobekli Tepe and this,
you know, 10,000, now Karahan Tepe is 11,000.
The whole area is called the Tas Tepeler,
we only found it a couple of decades ago,
but it was just a, you know,
a archeologist rowing through the area
and ask a sheep herder, hey, you know,
you guys know where anything ancient is?
Oh yeah, lemme show you this.
And then all of a sudden we've got a lost civilization.
And the shepherds always knew where it was,
just nobody asked him.
- So speaking of Gobekli Tepe,
what do you think about the work
of Gram Hancock who also believes
that there's a lost civilization in the Amazon?
- Well, I've met Graham and personally I like him.
He's a nice guy, got a nice sense of humor,
and I think he's smart.
And I also think he is a very good researcher.
He and I are working on the same set of facts.
The differences are interpretations.
I do not believe Graham's idea
that a single now lost ancient civilization seeded
the rest of them.
I just don't see that on a number of levels, artifact wise,
technology wise, art, historical analysis.
So I think his research is great.
I think that he's very well read,
in fact better read than a lot of my colleagues.
But his conclusions I disagree with.
And he and I have talked about this and had a very civil
and normal conversation about it,
and agree to disagree without spitting any venom
at any point in the conversation.
- That would be a fun argument to be a fly on the wall for.
So he believes, he's proposed,
it's possible that the Amazon jungle is
sort of a manmade garden.
So it was planted there by advanced ancient civilization.
Is there any degree to which that could be possible?
- Frankly, I agree with him.
I mean, it's just like what I was just talking about,
it's the conclusion part that we differ from.
But the facts that he's basing that on are
that terra preta are the huge geometric earthworks,
are the ever increasing evidence of them.
They are now from, you know,
the bottom of Bolivia to Guyana.
They're everywhere.
Every time we open up the jungle, we find these big works.
So yes, there was a vast civilization that was there.
How advanced they were is a question.
And also, you know, a perspective thing.
Graham really focuses in on what we don't know.
And what could be.
- What's the, just to educate me,
what's the key idea that he's proposing
that you disagree with?
It was the level of advancement the civilization was,
or how large and centralized it was?
- My main point of disagreement is that his,
and his ideas evolve, like everybody's,
you know, no scientist
or researcher in anything, has an idea at the beginning
of their career and holds it till the day they die.
His ideas are evolving, but his ideas remain,
a core of them are that there was a very advanced single,
ancient civilization that was utterly destroyed
by climactic conditions.
And the Younger Dryas hypothesis is part of that,
most recently, he used to not say that,
now he's into this meteor thing,
but he believes that that civilization was destroyed,
but that members of it escaped this cataclysm
and then spread out all over the world to seed all
of the world's civilizations for the next revival.
There's where I disagree with him,
I think these were independent civilizations that grew up
in their own ways, that they were not seeded
by some more advanced civilization from the past.
And that they all hold things in common
because they have this common ancestry of a, you know,
in his early books he suggested it's Atlantis.
I don't think he suggests that anymore,
but he still hangs on to the single advanced,
now completely lost civilization and, you know, archeology.
So we don't have, you know,
all of our ideas are theories.
Very few of them are facts,
and we're not, you know, we could have the story wrong,
but one thing we're real good at is finding stuff.
I mean, we find fish scales, so I find it just
too big a pill to swallow that there was a civilization
that was that technologically advanced
and that large that we can't even find a potsherd from.
- Yeah, and of course, it is a compelling story
that there's a single civilization from which all
of this came from, because the alternative is, you know,
the idea that we came across the Bering Strait
from Asia, went all the way down to South America
and got isolated
and created all these marvelous, sophisticated civilizations
and ideas, including religious ideas that look similar
to other, you know, everybody has a flood myth.
So like, there's a lot of similarities.
Everybody building pyramids.
But there could be a lot of other explanations
and even if it's a simple, compelling explanation
that has to be evidence for it, right.
And what would that evidence look like?
- Well, that's the bottom line.
I mean, everything's theories,
and as responsible scientists we're trying
to disprove our theories.
We are not supposed to be trying to prove our theories.
That's one more foot out of the science box
that archeology often steps.
We're supposed to be disproving
what we think is happening, not proving it.
- Yeah, you don't wanna lean into the mystery too much.
I mean, it's such a weird discipline
'cause you're operating in a,
it's like really in a dark room,
you're feeling around a dark room.
So it's mostly mystery, I would say,
a lot of sciences operate in a mostly well lit room.
It's like a dark corner
and you're kind of figuring out a way to light it.
But in, yeah, in archeology, it's,
most of it is a mystery, right?
- Yes, it's job security, I like that part, you know.
But I do also try to always remind myself
that every paradigm shifting idea
that humans have ever had began as heresy and lunacy.
You know, that guy was crazy up
to the second he was brilliant.
And so we gotta keep our minds open
to the things that sound outlandish,
because one of them eventually is gonna lead us
to the big paradigm shift.
And if we, you know, if we're busy burning books of ideas
that we don't like, that's where we close our minds
to the possibility of advancing things.
- I really love that,
and I really appreciate that you're saying that.
One of the fascinating things about just the Amazon to me is
that there's still a large number of uncontacted tribes.
To rewind back into ancient history, you can imagine all
of these tribes that existed in the Amazon
that were isolated, very sort of distinct from each other.
Can you speak to this, your understanding of these tribes
and their history that are still here today?
- Well, a lot of them are these, you know,
by uncontacted we mean
we don't know anything about these guys.
We know roughly where they are,
but places like Ecuador have very responsible policies
where no one's allowed to go contact them.
So we have a dearth of information.
If they walk out of the jungle
and talk to us, that's one thing.
But we don't go out and there looking for 'em.
But they do seem, you know, frozen in time.
And I don't think any of us have a good estimation
of how long they've been like that.
But, you know, we were saying earlier that, you know,
humans change based on pressures of their environment.
You know, it's a mother necessity is oftentimes
how we invent things or why we change it's pressure.
And one thing the Amazon is, once you, you know,
figure out how not to die in it, it's a paradise of food,
food's falling from the sky all the time there.
And if once you learn to adapt to that environment,
you've got very little need.
There's no pressure to make anything else.
Things are working.
- So for the modern humans
that come across these uncontacted tribes,
one of the things they document
and notice is the propensity of these tribes for violence.
So they get very aggressive
in attacking whoever they come across.
- And not just foreigners, they attack each other.
The Yanomami are famous for just having
never ending feuds with each other.
- What do you think of the philosophy behind that?
- I don't, you know, I'm a relatively peaceful person,
but I've got, you know,
I've got the monster in me like everybody does.
And I think that these, you know, it's cultural norms
that become institutionalized.
For the Yanomami, they really,
part of the rite of passage to be a man
is to go kill or maim somebody from an outer village.
And they go in there, they oftentimes,
the way they don't let inbreeding set in
and ruin everybody, not that they think
of it scientifically, but they typically go
and steal women from far off communities.
And that starts a big fight.
Another thing that starts fights
when nobody even fought is illness.
Illness in the Amazon
and all of the ancient Americas wasn't seen
as a biological thing, it was a spiritual thing.
So if somebody in your village gets sick,
the question is asked, well, what spirit is menacing him?
And who called it out on him?
And then the rumor starts,
well, I bet you it was Joe over there
in that other community, he's still pissed off
for that time when we stole his daughter.
And we ought to go over there and kill Joe.
And then he'll get better.
And so this round of never ending violence,
like Hatfield and McCoys had that thing.
And the people of New Guinea also do that.
So it's not, you know, there are certain areas,
mostly wooded areas now that I think about it,
where people just hide out
and they attack each other as a cultural institution.
- It's such a tricky thing to do,
to study an uncontacted tribe
without obviously contacting them
to figure out their language, their philosophy of mind,
how they communicate, the hierarchy they operate under.
- And yeah, you know, there was a fascinating story in Peru,
I guess it was probably like eight years ago or something,
but there was a ranger from one of the biology stations
who just in the by and by of protecting his area,
met one of these uncontacted tribes
and befriended someone, not the whole tribe,
but he made some friends
who would meet him in the woods, not in their community.
And he started to learn their language over a couple years.
And so he was this kind of important guy
who actually could be the first translator
to talk to these people.
And one day a couple of them just came out of the woods
and just plugged him with arrows and just killed him.
And then they went back in the woods.
Like, that's the one guy who understands what we're saying,
we should kill him and move our village.
- So those folks really lean into the,
as you said, the monster versus the puppy.
- You know, everybody's got it, I think,
I think, you know,
we need to listen to our better angels
because if we don't, we as a human species
can easily devolve into just using violence
and against others to get what we want.
It's a daily choice we make not to be savages.
- Which is fascinating thing to remember.
We kind of think in civilized society,
we've moved past all that.
But it can be summoned like in 1984, the two minutes of hate
with the right words, that primal thing can be summoned
and directed and lead to a lot of destruction.
- And, you know,
our sports are really based on taking those kinds of urges
and channeling them positive,
where somebody's not dead at the end of it.
- Yep.
So at which point
did what we now call the Maya civilization arise?
- That's another complicated one.
Another group living mostly in a jungle
that we have barely begun to explore.
You know, the truth is, a lot of the questions in the Amazon
and what we're talking about now is the Peten
and the mountains there.
Those aren't places archeologists wanna live.
They're horrible, I mean, I've been there.
I don't wanna live in a tent and eat rations.
I wanna live in a nice town.
So a lot of the places where the answers are,
we still really haven't gotten there
'cause it takes a special person to be educated enough
to know what they're looking at
and tough enough to want to be there.
I've done my tour of duty,
I'm now in a nice little podcast studio.
But seriously, the Maya, the first hint
that we see people who are culturally Maya very close
to where the time period
for that Chavin culture is about 1800 BCE.
There's a culture that's some called the Mokaya, not Maya,
but they're on the Pacific coast
where Guatemala and Mexico connect.
It's called the Soconusco.
And those are the first people
that are really gonna be culturally Maya.
And they're interacting with the culture
that has traditionally been seen as Mexico's mother culture,
which is the Olmec.
They're kind of the same thing
as we were talking about in South America,
where the Maya, the original Maya are not,
there's not a whole lot
to indicate that they have a religion,
but the Olmec have this religion they develop
and they start exporting it.
And you see the Maya become more
and more involved in the religion that's being created
by the Olmec who are to the north of them
in the swamps of what we call the Isthmus of Tehuantepec.
- I have a lot of questions
to ask here about just the natural stupid confusion I have.
So first, did the Maya or the Olmec come first
and are they distinct groups?
Like how do you maintain a distinct civilization
when you're so close together?
- I just finished filming a whole thing on the Olmecs
and their interaction with the Maya for the great courses.
I'm thrilled for it to come out next spring.
I think they co-evolved.
Archeology in this regard is the worst enemy of this.
So we put these names on cultures.
We talk about how they evolve from one to another.
We draw these lines where there aren't any,
we make these time periods that a culture
magically transforms into somebody with another name,
where I'm pretty sure they didn't care
about any of those names.
But the Maya and the Olmec are two parts
of a larger interaction sphere
that's happening in Mesoamerica, very dynamic time.
The Olmec are really bringing the religion part,
but the other areas are bringing technology,
ceramic technology, making hematite mirrors,
making tools out of obsidian
and other stone types.
So you've got the Olmec in the middle
where Mexico gets skinny and it gets swampy down there.
That's called the Isthmus of Tehuantepec.
That's where the Olmec are.
Then you've got the Maya to the east of them.
Then you have the Valley of Oaxaca
where the people call the Zapotecs, they're rising up.
And then you have the Valley of Mexico,
which will eventually become the Aztecs,
but not for millennia.
All those areas are interacting with each other.
- Can we just also draw some more lines?
- Yeah, sure.
- So what is Mesoamerica and what is South America
and what you just said, the Olmecs and the Maya,
like, can we just linger on the geography
that we're talking about here in the,
what is this, like a thousand BC?
- Yeah, the time period we're talking about
where the Olmec are there,
a thousand BC is a great midpoint of it.
I'd say it starts about 1800 BCE.
And by 500 BCE the Olmec are gone.
And a whole new wave of civilization
and population increase happen.
In terms of Mesoamerica,
looking at your map here, I'd say about halfway
through the Chihuahua desert up there in the top left.
That's about the boundary of Mesoamerica.
There's this big desert where almost nobody lives.
And once you get north enough,
you get into the ancestral pueblo people
of what's now America, the Four Corners area.
They're not Mesoamerican, they have different lives.
- Where does modern Mexico end?
- Modern Mexico ends, right,
you know, you see the name Maya
there with the white line around it.
That's Guatemala, so Guatemala cuts off most
of Mexico from Central America.
- Got it.
- But Mesoamerica only goes about halfway
through Honduras.
And then it's really kind of a no man's land.
Nicaragua, Costa Rica, Panama.
They really, they're neither,
they're not Mesoamerica, they're not South America.
They're more South America
'cause they've got some gold there.
But then basically you get on the other side of Panama
and you're fully in South America
with two distinct groups too.
You've got the guys that are on the Andes on the West Coast,
and then you have the Amazon.
- So the West of the Andes
and the Amazon are very distinct.
So when you refer to the Andean region,
is that referring to the Andes and the Amazon
or just the Andes?
- Just the Andes and the coast to the Pacific there.
That's Andean civilization.
- So did the Maya make it to the Andes, the Andean region?
- Not that archeology can prove,
but it's almost certain
that they interacted with each other.
Number one, it's just, you know, it's biased to think
that these people couldn't travel as widely
as people on the other side of the planet did.
But there's all sorts of hints.
Like that first ceramics I was talking about
that the Maya made, they show up strangely,
sophisticated technologically already
and down in Ecuador,
they had them for a thousand years before.
So a lot of people, myself included, think that the idea
of ceramics actually came from South America to the Maya.
- Did the Maya get seeded by the second wave
across the Bering Strait
or did that initial wave of people that came
and populated South America,
were they the ancestors of the Maya?
Like how did the migration happen here?
Do we understand that?
- We're still piecing it together.
I don't think, you know, I'd be lying if I told you I had
the answers, but we do have evidence of Maya stature people,
they are small people, generally speaking,
people that grow up in the forest are smaller
and people that grow up in the open plains are taller.
Probably about, you know, just generations of people
that hit their head on a branch or not. (laughs)
- Joking, but, you know, there could be something to that.
- I think there's some truth to it,
I mean, the Pygmies are small
and the people on the plains in Africa are big.
The North American Indians are tall and the Maya are small.
There's definitely a pattern of smaller people
in the forests.
But anyway, there's a cave
in the Yucatan called Loltun Cave
that has hand prints in the cave.
It's somebody who put their hand on the cave
and spit charcoal around their hand,
like a negative print.
We can date that charcoal.
And it comes from 10,000 years ago.
And the hands are all small.
It's, you know, typical Old Mexico.
I walked right up to these things and could put my hand.
I didn't, you know, mess with them,
but I put my hand next to these hands
and they're all smaller than my, you know,
Northern European hand.
And so either it was a bunch of kids
who were in this cave 10,000 years ago,
or it was people of Maya stature who did it.
- It's so cool that you can date the charcoal.
And it's so cool that 10,000 years ago
there were people living.
- And actually we have one that's,
I think 2000 years older now,
just a couple years ago, again in Yucatan, in a cave.
They found a woman they named Naia now,
and she's like 12,000 years old.
- So the best guess maybe that you have
is it goes across the Bering Strait to South America,
possibly the Amazon, develop a lot
of cool ideas in the Amazon
and start drifting back up into Mesoamerica.
- Was kind of a co-evolution.
The technology of ceramics,
I think got there through an interaction with it.
- See, the interesting thing is
that the Maya didn't really have religion,
didn't have as a vibrant religious set of ideas,
and they borrowed it from the Olmec.
- I've been doing a deep dive on this
for this Olmec course that I just did.
And it really does seem like these other cultures
that have jade and hematite and obsidian,
the Olmec had none of that stuff.
They were living in a swamp and building things out of dirt,
but they were importing those materials from those areas,
carving them into all sorts of religious iconography
and then exporting them back to them.
- And still the fanged deity show up there?
- No, the fanged deity's nowhere in Central America
and Mesoamerica.
There's jaguars, there's jaguar iconography,
but it's not the same thing.
This whole Jaguar transformer deity does not exist there.
They do have a pantheon.
- So the Maya, the Olmec
and the interesting peoples of the regions.
What was their, I'd love
to ask questions about who were they?
So one question I'm curious about,
what was their sense when they looked up at the stars?
What was their conception of the cosmos?
- That's a question I've spent
my entire career trying to answer.
I think that they saw it as proof
of the cyclical nature of life.
And certainly they saw,
like every ancient group did, like, are those the gods?
Why are those things so far away?
But I think that the Maya especially looked at it
with a much more mathematical mind than most did.
And so they watched these things move every night.
And if you do that, even today,
you notice that all the stars move in tandem.
They're just this blanket, they're like,
they're like this curtain behind me.
They're the stage upon which
some very important players are dancing,
and that's the moon, the sun, and the planets.
There's five planets we can see visibly.
So they started watching like, why are just those seven
moving differently than the rest?
And those are the things that they keyed on mathematically.
The sun, of course was also involved
in the agricultural cycle.
So that was important in and of itself.
But the planets, we can see them coming up with ideas,
definitely doing the math
and seeing that there is a repeated cycle.
And then coming up with mythology around them,
like Venus for them was associated with war.
And they had very ritualized times to go to war.
That had something to do with Venus.
Sometimes in the classic period Maya,
it was the first appearance of Venus as the morning star.
That was a good time to go
to battle with your neighbors.
And when it became the post-classic
with like Chichen Itza being the capital of the Yucatan,
then it looks like if you watch Venus day after day,
it goes slowly up every day.
And then when it hits its highest point
as morningstar in the morning,
it goes down to the Earth like three times as fast.
All of a sudden it just shoots down and hits the Earth.
And so the people of post-classic Maya civilization
saw that as the gods shooting a spear into the Earth.
And that was a good time to attack your neighbors.
That was like wartime when the spear is gonna hit the Earth.
- Right, so this is fascinating.
They just had at the foundation a sense
that life existence at the various timescales is cyclical.
That's the starting point.
And then you just look out there
and if you are extremely precise, which is fascinating,
how precise they were, you can just measure the cycles.
- Yeah, and they did it really well.
Now of course, they are the only ones
to develop a fully elaborated writing system
in all of the Americas.
The South America had the Quipu,
but it's so different than our writing.
We're still trying to figure out what the heck it is.
We know there's math there too,
but they had the ability to take a lifetime worth
of measurements and hand it to the next generation
who would then do it more and do it more.
That's how they figured out
kind of the holy grail of ancient astronomy.
How good were they
was whether they could see the procession of the equinoxes,
the fact that we're just barely wobbling.
And there's a 26,000 year period where the stars
as that backdrop will spin all the way around and come back.
It's 26,000 years.
But the Maya were able to figure out, wait,
it's moving one degree every 72 years,
and did a calculation based on
where it should be in the ancient past.
And they're using constellations.
They're showing us they know by saying like,
this planet's in this constellation right now
and 33,000 years ago it would be
in this constellation.
- It's just fascinating
that they were able to figure this out.
I would love to sort of understand the details
of the scientific community, if you can call it that.
- I think we absolutely could.
And that's actually one of the things that I'm hoping
to move the needle on in my generation with my career,
is to give these cultures the respect they deserve
as standing toe to toe with the rest
of our ancient civilizations we respect,
there are things that should be called science
that are not being called science at the moment.
You know, their math is incredible.
Their hydraulic engineering is incredible.
Their chemistry is incredible.
And so I hope to talk about these things differently
as a way to get people
to recognize the achievements in a different way.
- Yeah, I mean, unquestionably incredible scientific work
in the astronomy sense, especially here.
Can you speak to all the sophisticated aspects
of the Mayan calendar that they've developed?
- I don't know, you got another five hours.
- [Lex] Let's go.
- No, I'm kidding.
- I should say that you also gave me
the 2024 Mayan calendar.
- Yeah, I do this just to, you know, show the world
that that calendar system is evergreen.
It can go into the future
or the past for billions of years in the system they made,
just like our system is.
- So can you speak to the three components here
as I'm reading that Tzolk'in, the Haab and the Long Count.
What are these fascinating components of the calendar?
- It's neat how obsessed,
they were really math nerds.
It wasn't good enough for them
to just make one cycle to describe time.
They had all these cycles
that interlocked into each other.
Like cogs in a machine,
though they never thought of it like that.
But the Tzolk'in's their oldest one
and the one that still endures today, there are millions
of Maya people that are living their lives
based on a 260 day count.
No weeks, no months.
It's just 13 numbers combined with 20 day names
for a total of 260 days.
And then it goes again.
Everybody in the highlands knows
what their birthday is in that calendar,
knows what it means about their personality
and the kind of jobs that they're supposed to do.
Each one of those days has their own spirit.
And what's supposed to happen in those days,
the Maya collectively call them the mom,
the grandmother, grandfather spirits.
And they talk to each one
of those days and they pray to them.
There's now an association of some 8,000 people
that are called Aki that are day keepers
who are keeping the days.
And they're also like community psychologists almost.
People come to them and say, you know, my life is mixed up.
What's wrong here?
Well, let's ask the mom, like, okay,
well it looks like you're not doing this or that.
Or you know what, you're an accountant.
You're not supposed to be an accountant.
You're supposed to be a, you know, a midwife.
What are you doing?
You're living your life wrong.
You're a kib.
You need to start being a kib person.
- So they take extremely seriously
the day on which you're born.
What that means, like the spirit that embodies that day.
- Right, like I'm kib, I'm 13 kib
and it says my, it's funny how accurate a lot of them are.
Mine is basically is,
I'm an irresponsible husband and parent,
but people like me, so my family still prospers.
Like, well God, that's horribly accurate.
- I mean some of it is also the chicken or the egg
if you truly believe,
so, if you structure society
where this calendar is truly sacred,
then it kind of like you manifest a lot,
the spirit does manifest itself in the life of the people
that is born on that spirit's day.
- Absolutely. - It's interesting.
- And the Maya really feel this in this system.
So that's the core system.
This 260 day calendar was the very first calendar
they made thousands of years ago.
And it's the one that's most important today.
- Why 260 days, by the way?
Is there a reasoning behind it?
- Most Maya agree with this today
and you know, who knows
what the original architects thousands
of years ago were thinking.
But it's nine months.
It's the human gestation period.
So if you conceived on the day 13 monkey,
chances are your kids coming out on or near 13 monkey.
And I think it's beautiful.
I mean, if that's right, that means the Maya
and the people of Mesoamerica will all share it together.
When they thought about we need a count
of time, that's for us.
They didn't look up into the heavens,
they looked like into their bodies.
What's the first cycle that we actually go through as humans
and they pick this nine month thing.
It really is our cycle.
And no other culture on the planet looked inside themselves
to create their calendar like that.
- So that's the oldest one
and the sacred one that still carries through to today.
What's the second one, the Haab?
- The Haab is the solar calendar, the one that everybody
on the planet eventually comes up with.
We know it's second though
because when they start talking about it,
they use all the symbols and the numbers from the 260 one.
They say, well we need a solar one too.
Let's just keep counting this another 105 days
and we'll get to 365.
- Oh, interesting, they kind of carry the same.
Got it, got it, got it, got it.
And that's useful because for all the sort of agricultural,
all this kind of reasons.
- Right, though interestingly,
they never put a leap year in,
the Haab is also called the vague year
'cause it's just 365, which means
every year they're off a quarter of a day
and eventually it starts really adding up.
In fact, it's even caused modern problems.
In this calendar here,
I just do the straight math from a thousand years ago.
And so I place the beginning of the solar year differently
than some Maya groups do, especially the guys
in the highlands of Eastern Guatemala.
They write me nasty emails saying,
I don't know what time the year is,
but their relatives changed it in the 1950s
because their agricultural cycle was so far off.
They moved it 60 days back to make it in the spring again.
But it drifts, which is strange
'cause it's not a very good thing
for the agricultural cycle.
It's one of these mysteries
we still don't have an explanation for.
- So that's the Haab, and then what's the Long Count?
- The Long Count's the really mysterious cool one
because it's a linear count of days,
which are not like them.
It's a bunch of cycles like ours, you know,
our weeks are a cycle, our months are a cycle.
But it's weird in that its estimation of the year
in the long count system is only 360 days.
So it's miserably off a solar year.
They count in base 20.
So they count, like we count in tens we're decimal,
they count in base 20, vigesimal.
And so it should be, you know, there's ones,
there's twenties, there's four hundreds,
there's eight thousands, there's 160 thousands.
It's up, it goes just like our tens,
hundreds, thousands, 10 thousands.
But it's times 20.
So that third, so they have days, months of 20 days.
And then they have these years that are,
should be by their math 400, but it's only 360.
And that throws the whole thing
outta whack going further up.
Then they have a 20 year period
and a 400 year period, 400 years to their calendar.
But it's only by that time it's only 396 years
in our period, in our reckoning.
So it's mysterious that it's, why did they tweak it
at the year to be only 360 days?
That's, you know, that doesn't follow any astronomy.
That's not the human cycle.
- Yeah, but they're, I mean, it's interesting
that they build up towards thinking
about very long periods of time.
Like baktun is 144,000 days.
- Right, or a baktun is 400 of the long counts years.
So it's kind of like our millennium, you know,
we think it's a big deal when we hit a millennium
or a century.
They have a 20 year period that they do a lot
of celebrations on called a katun.
And then they have the 400 baktun, which is the big one
that's like their millennium.
And 13 of those baktuns occurred in the creation before us.
They also think that we are in,
that the world has had multiple creations.
They're not alone in that.
There's lots of ancient civilizations who say that,
but we're technically in the fourth creation.
And they have a creation story called the Popol Vuh.
And the Popol Vuh is clear as day
that the third creation ends with the help
of these heroes called the hero twins.
And the fourth creation begins.
And so on the Maya monuments,
we see them doing the math through the long count
and we can calculate it back very exactly.
It happened.
The fourth creation started on August 11th, 3114 BC
and it says, it doesn't say it's day one,
it says it's the last day of the 13th baktun
of the third creation, which leads us
to believe that a creation is only 13 baktuns long.
- Right, so, and this would be
the fourth creation, the calendar.
- The fourth creation.
But if you do the math going from 3,114 BC
and count 13 baktuns forward, you get to 2012.
- And hence the very popular notion that 2012,
whenever that was December, something like that.
- December 21st, 2012.
- Will be the end of the world.
So can you explain this about?
- Those were very fruitful years for me.
I had so many lectures around the country that was,
it's like Garrett Morrison Saturday Night Live.
The apocalypse was very, very good to me.
- I mean, but that is pretty interesting.
So technically it would be in the what, in the fifth now?
- Yeah, technically we'd be in the fifth.
Though, my argument was that actually, if you look
through all the corpus of Maya mathematics
and calendars, they never say anything like that.
In fact, there's a handful of dates that tell us
that the fourth creation does continue farther on.
That that baktun place should have 20 baktuns in it.
Like their counting system would dictate, not 13.
And there's a place in Palenque,
there's a place in the Dresden Codex
and one other place I'm forgetting
that all talk about time after 2012.
So how does that happen, it's a conflict.
- Is there supposed to be an overlap of the 13?
So it's like 13 is the core of it, and it's 20 long.
- They love the number 13, it's all over the place.
It's a magic number to them.
My explanation, which I admit is not very solid.
But I think that the magical deeds
of the hero twins in their creation story at the end
of the third creation hit the magical reset button.
And that it just restarted time right there
because of their magic.
But that was not to say
that the natural baktun cycle should be 13.
And there are certain texts
that go way forward in time or way backward in time.
And whenever they wanna do that,
there are higher increments than just the baktun.
Above that, there's the piktun,
then there's the kalabatun, then there's alawatun
and it goes on and on.
And these are like, you know, 160,000 years,
huge increments of time, whenever they wanna do that,
and they talk about a long period of time,
they start putting thirteens in all of those increments,
those higher increments.
And I think what they're saying is
they're making an esoteric statement
about the never ending nature of time.
That's what I think they're telling us
in those texts that time goes on forever, magically.
- But they still had a conception
that it didn't go on forever before.
That there was other civilizations that came
before and this is the fourth creation.
- This is the fourth creation.
And the gods made everybody,
the first ones were made of mud and they melted.
The second ones were made of sticks,
but they were jerks to the animals.
The third ones were like us,
but flawed in some other way.
And then we are finally made of the blood
of the gods and corn, we're made out of corn.
So we're perfect.
And as it explains to us, the Popol Vuh does,
we got it right this time.
There's no reason to believe
that this creation has a set duration.
One of the weird things is that the Aztecs,
who we talked to a lot at contact,
they also had the concept of multiple creations before us.
But they were real clear to the Spanish
that they weren't all the same time element.
Some of them were in the three hundreds of years.
Some of them were in the seven hundreds of years,
but they were not the same time period.
So our mathematical logic
that if the third creation was 13,
this one must be third creation or also be 13.
It's in direct opposition
to what the Aztecs told us about the nature of creations.
They're different time periods.
- Why do you think there was the myth
of the previous creations?
Did they have some kind
of long multi-generational memory of prior civilizations?
- It may have had some echo in the flood myths.
- It's the same kind
of major myths carried through long periods of time.
- There's a lot of different opinions about it.
And you know, like if they were all 13,
if we have five creations, like the Aztec said,
and they were all 13, they would come up
to roughly 25,000 something years,
which is very close to that processional cycle.
So some people are like, they designed it all
to be one completion of the procession of the equinoxes.
- And I mean that.
- I don't believe that one,
but that one sure sounds good, doesn't it?
That's gonna get a lot of internet hits.
- And one of the things I do obviously wonder
about is why the flood myth is part of
like most societies and most religions?
- I think that one's pretty easy.
It's the end of the ice age when the bathtub filled back up.
- So it's just the ice age bathtub refill.
- It's the seas filling back up.
- And without really understanding what happened,
they just carried that story?
- Everybody knows
that everybody's nice coastal village went underwater.
And they had to seek higher ground.
- And then just like people like talking about the weather,
everybody was talking about the weather for many generations
as the sea level was going up.
And then that myth carried?
- Why do we live here, grandpa?
Well, we used to live over there, but then the water came.
- And then many grandpas later is
just kind of permeates every idea.
- It becomes mythology, but global mythology.
So that one, you know, there's a lot
of things I don't have a reasonable explanation for,
but the flood myth is almost certainly
the rise in sea level.
- So this idea that every day represents,
that carries a spirit.
You know, there's modern day astrology, you know,
most people kind of consider astrology this
maybe a bit unscientific woowoo type
of set of beliefs.
But do you think there's some wisdom that astrology carries
from your scholarship of the Maya calendar?
Do you think if we carry that
to the astrological perspective on the world,
do you think there's some wisdom there?
- I don't know, you know,
I have a woowoo part of me.
I would like to believe that stuff,
but I don't think as a scientist it makes,
I cannot come up with a biological
scientific reason why that would be true.
And you know, when you look at it objectively,
I mean really is everybody born with the sign Scorpio,
a moody person?
That's just objectively not true.
But it is funny how oftentimes these Maya horoscopes,
for lack of a better word, do hit the mark.
There was some student who surveyed like 300 people
with the app I made and asked them about their Greek sign
and their Maya sign
and his conclusion for his term paper was
that the Maya one was working way better.
Which that's fascinating.
At least that's fun.
But no, I think I'm too much of a scientist
to believe that, I just don't have
any foundation in science that would allow us to believe
that the month in which we were born
in a cycle sets our personality and destiny.
- I agree, and yet there's so much mystery
all around us that what I do like is
the inbuilt humility to that worldview.
That there's this whole, you can call it a spiritual world,
but a world that we don't quite understand.
And then you can wander about what is the wisdom
that that world carries.
And then you can construct all kinds of systems
to try to interpret that.
And then there is where the human hubris can come in
and, you know, but it's good
to be humbled by how little we know, I suppose.
- I do love the mysteries of the world
and I would love to find an ancient civilization,
but I don't want to solve the mysteries of the world.
I think they're one of the things
that make life worth living.
- That's true, that's true.
You mentioned the Maya writing system.
What are some interesting aspects of their language
that they've used and the written language that they used?
- Well, you know, one of the things that confound me
as a guy who spent, you know, better portion
of my life studying it, I had the honor of being the student
of Linda Schele right here
at the University of Texas at Austin.
She got the group together who broke the Maya code
of hieroglyphics in the 1970s.
So I learned from the best.
And loved every minute of it, I miss Linda.
- Can you speak to that code actually,
the hieroglyphic code and what it takes to break it?
- Oh boy, I mean, what a thing.
We had kind of a Rosetta Stone.
We had a page out of Diego de Landa's book,
a priest who was converting the Maya in Yucatan asked
his informants about their writing system
and what every sound meant.
And he was convinced they had a alphabet like we do.
So he got this Maya guy sat down in Spanish
and he said, okay,
you're gonna write all the symbols right here in my book.
Write an A here, write a B here, write a C here.
And that guy just wrote all of the sounds
that the priest told him to write.
They were actually syllables,
they were vowel consonant combinations.
They weren't an alphabet.
But that turned into our Rosetta stone of sorts.
The big key is that the Maya still speak that same language.
There are millions of Maya people
who are speaking a version of Maya.
Now, there's where I get confused
that we've got a single writing system that is intelligible.
We've broken the code.
So we know that it's basically the same writing system
from the top of the Yucatan into Guatemala and El Salvador.
But we have 33 Mayan languages today
that are mutually unintelligible.
And we backwards project the language
of what they spoke back then.
That the glyphs are in to something called Cholti
which is a combination of Chorti and Chol,
two of those languages.
But it doesn't work for me at all.
How did, if there was one language, maybe two back then,
how did it flower into 33 mutually unintelligible languages
in just 500 years during acculturation
and horrible infectious diseases
that killed 90% of the population?
How did that happen?
So we're missing something huge here.
I think it's more like Chinese, where Chinese letters,
writing can be read in multiple languages
and still understood.
I don't know exactly the mechanics of how that would happen,
but it just seems impossible that there are more languages,
not less languages in the Maya area
after the last 500 years that they've been through.
- So you think that there's some kind of process
of either rapidly generating dialects
or there always has been these dialects,
or I should say they're distinct languages,
even though there was a common writing system?
- There must have been a way that multiple languages
understood the same writing system.
Or maybe there was something like Latin, you know,
how there was a period in Europe
where like most people were illiterate
and there was this priesthood who all understood Latin
and they wrote in Latin.
Maybe the hieroglyphs represent a kind
of Latin in the ancient Maya world.
- But we don't really know.
And there's not clear evidence to fill in the gaps
of how it's possible to have that.
- Right, but we did realize it was actually
a Russian scholar named Yuri Knorozov who broke the code.
The Americans and the Europeans were absolutely sure
that the language was,
that the written language was a dead language.
But Yuri not knowing any of that, not being filled
with all of those thoughts from America, and Europe
went about it in the way that he was taught
in his grad school in Moscow.
And just went to the dictionaries
and he looked at Yucatec language
that they're speaking today
and he applied it to the symbol system
and he knew that there were certain sounds.
He used Lambda's alphabet.
And he found there was, his two key examples were
a picture of a dog with a symbol over it
and a picture of a turkey with a symbol over it.
And the dog,
a dog in Yucatec is "zool."
So he saw two symbols and he said,
this one's probably "zool" and this one's "ul".
And then the Turkey was "kuuts,"
so it would be "kuu" ending in "tsu".
And he showed how, look, you know, this is "tsu,"
this is "zool,"
those two things that should be "ts" are the same symbol.
And that began this process of unraveling the syllables
that we're still working on today.
- That's fascinating.
Just that decoding process is fascinating.
Like how do you even figure that out?
And there's probably still, is there still, are you aware
of any written languages that haven't been decoded yet?
- Yeah, yeah, there's a number of them.
There's Easter Island Script, I was just talking to.
We've apparently made a few advances there.
Now it's called Rongorongo.
And we only have about maybe 25 examples of texts,
but we're beginning to break that.
There's also the big one is Harappan.
Harappan for a long time we used to say
there were five independent scripts on the planet
and those were Chinese, Cuneiform,
which is Mesopotamian, Egyptian, Maya,
and then Harappan, which is from Northern India.
That's the only one that we've never cracked.
And now all the epigraphers, the people, that's the term
for epigraphy is translating these languages.
They're all ganging up on Harappan
and want to kick it off the list 'cause we can't break it.
It had a big enough symbol set,
but no one's been able to crack it.
And now they're saying it's just an elaborate symbol set
and doesn't reflect the spoken word.
- That's a hypothesis,
which is what would explain why it's so difficult.
- Right, but you know, we could just be faced
with the quitter generation.
Maybe somebody will pick up the baton next generation.
- Kids these days with their.
- The other one that fascinates me is from the Americas.
It's the Quipu, the Inca had the Quipu.
This nodded string records,
but it was definitely encoding more than just math.
We know the math.
I know lots, I can do the math Quipus
and figure out what they're totaling and things.
Yeah, there's a Quipu right there.
- Quipu are recording devices fashioned from strings,
historically used by a number of cultures in the region
of Indian and South America, a Quipu who usually consists
of cotton or camelid fiber strings.
So there's a set of strings
and they're supposed to what, to be saying something?
- There's one long string
that the little ones dangle off of.
And each one of the dangling strings have sets
of knots on them.
And the knots, some of them are mathematical Quipus
and those, we can just do the math,
we can prove that it's math.
They also encoded language in there.
They had entire libraries in Cusco
where Spanish conquistadors were brought through.
And the caretakers of the libraries would just put,
they'd say, pull that one down, read that one to me.
And he'd pull it out and just read a history of something
that happened 200 years earlier.
So it was definitely writing.
But in the 1570s,
one head of the church there had all of the people
that could read them called quipucamayocs,
gathered up, had them read all of their Quipus
and transcribe them into Spanish books,
and then had the Quipus burned and those people murdered.
- Okay, well there you go.
- And so we can't break the code still today,
but we know it was absolutely a written language
though it wasn't written, it was weaved or knotted.
- And there's still some Quipus available that could be.
- There's, I think now we've just crossed the 1000 mark.
So we have a thousand Quipus,
there's enough to break the code.
And I think this generation
might be the one that does it.
- It's sad that so few have survived.
I mean a thousand is good, but it's.
- But see, there's, Peru has barely scratched
the surface with archeology.
There's so much out there.
There was a priest I read about named Diego De Porres,
who was one of the early people
in Peru converting communities.
And his chronicle is real clear that he wanted
to teach this community of 3000 people,
all the Spanish prayers, the important ones
for them to be converted into Christianity.
And he had the communities' quipucamayocs knot Quipus
for each person that told them
that they could read them out and memorize the prayers.
And if they were caught without their Quipu
in town, they were flogged.
So he had 3000 of the same Quipu made
and handed out to this community.
If we find that community
and find its cemetery, there is a Rosetta Stone.
- You know, it is probably the case there is somebody
in Peru and maybe a large community
that knows this language that understands, and like,
you just have to show up and ask them.
And it's like,
they're like, oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
- There are some communities that are using them.
There's a couple of them that we had high hopes for.
And then it was apparent
that they were just making shit up.
They didn't actually know how to read it.
They just knew it used to be read.
So they like made a bunch of stuff about what it says.
And they bring it out and they act like they can read it,
but then when you ask 'em the details, they don't know.
But then on a much simpler level,
there's llama herders who keep a string in their pocket
and they've got the knots equaling
how many llamas they have.
And then they have subcategories of information like,
this one's sick, we've lost these ones, this one's pregnant.
So they have these more simple and more mathematical Quipus
but they're using them to affect as a record.
- Is it possible through archeology to know what, you know,
the social organization of the Maya was?
Like, what maybe if there was a hierarchy,
maybe what the political structure was,
if there was a leader, different roles, you know, priests
or like who had the power, who was powerless,
who had certain kinds of roles, is it possible to know that?
- Actually because of hieroglyphs,
yeah, we know a whole lot.
There's, you know, basic things that archeology,
which is a very blunt tool, can figure out like,
this guy lives in a rich house,
this guy lives in a poor house.
But the hieroglyphs tell us specific stuff
about who can rule, that it was hereditary.
That that hereditary rule was based
on royal blood that could be burned
and connect to the ancestors
that lived up in the sky versus the one
that's lived in the underworld.
It also told us things about hierarchy like
that there were councils of lords underneath the king
who each represented clans, who had their own neighborhoods,
and that there were revolving positions of authority.
There was the site that I mapped for my dissertation
and spent years in the jungle there, Palenque,
had lord's title named Fire Lord, that was one of the,
like, generals of their army.
And we could tell that position changed over time.
So there was one guy named Chak Suutz, who was the Fire Lord
for the early part of a reign
of a king called the Ahkal Mo' Naab.
And then by the time he carves this other panel,
there's another guy in the position of yajawk' ahk',
which was the fire Lord.
And so he had. - Got promoted?
- Well he could have been killed.
I mean, in the case of that,
but then we have the interesting case of,
in the post-classic, they shed the idea of kings.
They don't like kings anymore.
That's probably a big part of why the classic disappearance
and the abandonment of all those cities happened.
People just got sick of kings.
And so they turned into this more council system
at Chichen Itza.
But then when Chichen Itza falls, there's a new city,
that's architecture looks a lot like Chichen Itza.
It's called Mayapan,
but it has what it's called the League of Mayapan.
And it has a council
of representatives from the communities
from all around the Yucatan.
And it is basically a democracy.
It is a Maya democracy that happens.
The individuals from all around the Yucatan are there.
Each family has their own council house at Mayapan
though they live back at their place.
It's kind of like a Maya Congress.
- They have representative democracy.
- it really was, I mean,
and this happens in I guess 1250 AD
that this Maya democracy happens
and we know the names of them, we know the families,
and of course they were humans.
So eventually they screwed it all up.
One family murdered another family
and the whole city burned.
- Yeah, and of course it's probably
some fascinating corruption,
which is hard to discover through.
- Part of it was the Aztec screwing things up.
The Aztecs came down with all sorts of like,
we'll buy everything you're making.
And then eventually they were like,
could we maybe buy some humans?
And then one family was like, no.
And the other family was like, I don't know,
they're making us a lot of money.
So then, you know, they murdered each other
and the water supply got polluted and then the city burned.
- It seems like slavery, murder
and disease is a large component of the story of humans.
As you mentioned, different periods in the Maya,
the classic, the post-classic, the pre-classic, the archaic,
can you just speak to that?
So archaic is before there was
really a civilization that was.
- Archaic is pretty much when everybody's hunter-gatherers.
- So the classic period was the golden age.
And then the pre-classic is the interesting time
that we were talking about
and the post-classic is when the democracy came about.
- Well, midway through it.
Reverted back to council systems.
The Maya loved to be part of councils.
So yeah, we have,
pre-classic is like the origins of civilization.
They're starting to build cities.
They're starting to create their calendar.
They're starting to create these wonderful works of art.
And the classic period, if you look
at 10 different textbooks for the Maya,
you'll get 10 different dates that wiggle around in there.
But basically that's the age of kings, to me,
that's when these cities decide
that they're gonna organize themselves
around elite royal families that have this magical blood
that can contact their ancestors
that are directly in contact with the gods.
The Maya never contact their gods directly.
They contact their ancestors who are up there,
who act like liaisons to the gods.
And so the Maya age of kings has
these dynasties sprouting up
where these people have, you know,
basically snowed the rest of the people,
that they've got a special quality of their blood
and only their offspring can do the same trick
and talk to the gods where everybody,
every Joe Maya can let their blood
and burn it and contact their ancestor
but Joe Maya's dad is just a corn farmer
who lives down below,
and he's got no influence over the gods.
But the rulers, their spirits go down briefly,
but then they go up into the heavens
and reside where the gods are and can act as liaisons.
So that's the validation for this kingship
that happens for about 400 years.
I know we say 250 to 900,
which is kind of the encompassing edges of it.
But it's interesting that it's actually specifically
the ninth baktun of their history.
The ninth baktun begins in like 426,
and it ends in like 829.
So it's a 400 year period of time.
And before that, there were no kings.
And after that, there really aren't kings.
They're heads of councils.
So I call it the age of kings,
where everybody's following the directives
of basically a despot and for a while that's great.
I mean, cities build up, populations happening.
I see it as kind of a cult of personality moment too,
strong, charismatic leaders inspire people
to do great things together,
but eventually, like happens all the time with power,
too much power corrupts,
all of a sudden there's this unwieldy huge elite class
that has to be treated special by everybody else.
And they start saying, well, I think we should fight
with those guys, and you guys should go cut,
take these things.
And people eventually get sick of it,
and they walk away from these cities.
And that's how we get the mysterious Maya collapse
where all these cities are just gone.
- That's one of the great mysteries
of the Maya civilization is that over a very short period
of time, like a hundred years,
it seems to have declined very rapidly.
It collapsed, what do you think explains that?
What happened?
- I think it's a failing of archeology
to properly see what was happening.
I think that most of those cities, populations, moved,
you know, no more than 20 to 40 kilometers out
and started their own farm,
and they lived in perishable houses.
And all archeology signature sees is
that nobody lives in the city center anymore.
We don't see a bunch of mass bodies.
There's no evidence of people getting sick.
There are certain cities that fought
with each other at the end,
and we see that signature plain as day.
We know when a city was attacked and burned,
mostly that didn't happen.
People moved and migrated.
And it seems like right there around like
between 800 and 900, a lot of the elites that were on top
in the most of it was in the rainforests
of northern Guatemala.
They move, they move in two directions.
Some of them move into the highlands of Guatemala,
and some of them move up into the Yucatan.
The city of Chichen Itza becomes
the next big capital in Yucatan.
But the word Itza is actually a word describing
the people who lived around Lake Peten Itza
in northern Guatemala.
And all of the Maya are super clear about that,
that the Itza came in as immigrants with these new ideas
and created Chichen Itza.
So the elites
who were no longer welcome in their cities just moved
and set up shops somewhere else.
- So why was there a decline?
What was maybe the catalyst?
Was there a specific kind of events that started this?
Was this an idea that kind of transformed the society?
- We are still debating that.
I don't think there is a single reason.
I think humans are complicated.
I think a lot of things led to this.
One thing we can see archeologically is that every one
of the cities became overpopulated.
They were too popular,
and we think that they pushed the limits
of their capacity to feed and house people.
We see it in lots of the cities at the end
of the classic period that people are seasonally starving.
I remember really stark evidence in Copan, Honduras.
Copan was this beautiful city, lineage of 17 kings.
But the last kings
and the last elite burials that we dig from the city center,
the teeth are the telling part.
They get this thing, when you're growing up
and you're not getting enough food seasonally,
it shows up in the enamel of your teeth.
It's called dental hypoplasia.
And if somebody's seasonally starving,
it gets these lines in their teeth.
And that last generation of Maya before they left Copan,
even the rich people are seasonally starving.
So there's a problem there for sure.
But I also think, it's a weird thing.
It was not an empire.
It was a group of independent city states like Greece.
Some of them were allied, some of them were enemies.
There was a huge civil war that settled out
about the end of the classic period.
So if it was Europe, you know,
the victors would've taken over.
The losers would've beat it and gone wherever they went.
But when they abandoned these cities
that were independent still, they all left,
both the guys that won and the guys that lost the war.
So it couldn't be just as simple as spoils go to the victor.
It's such a wide area.
Not everybody was starving like the people
in the Copan Valley.
So I personally think it was cylindrically timed.
It is interesting to note that that ninth period,
that ninth 400 year period ends right then,
and I think a lot of people, you know,
I can't prove it archeologically,
but I think a lot of people said, we're coming to the end
of a great cycle and we need to renew.
We need to change what we're doing.
When you talk to the Maya today, like at the end
of this 2012 thing, if you actually talk to Maya,
say, you know what happens at the end of a big cycle here,
they say cycles are a time of renewal
and transformation.
That it is all of our obligation
to change our lives at the end of cycles,
that change is coming.
We can either be part of it or we can get steamrolled by it.
The Aztecs did this neat thing
called the New Fire Ceremony every 52 years,
which was the biggest their calendar would go,
they'd burn down perfectly good temples
and they'd burn down their houses sometimes.
And they would just, everybody in society
would perform this, what they call the new fire ceremony,
and they would renew the world.
So I think my personal theory is
that the Maya decided at the end of the ninth baktun
that it was time to renew the world.
- I think this theory makes sense
because they really internalized the calendar.
I mean, that was a really big part of their culture,
the sense of the cyclical nature of civilization.
- That's what I think.
I think that they created
that calendar to perceive the cycle
and to harmonize with it.
- You mentioned Aztec, what was the origin of the Aztec?
Where did these people come from, at what time and how?
- You know, almost every one
of the cultures we're talking about now,
we have two different versions
of the answer to that question.
We have the archeology version,
and we have the Aztecs themselves.
The Aztecs have this wonderful migration story
where they say that they came from a place,
well to the north called Aztlan,
and that they had this migration that went through
kind of a hero's journey where they go
to this snake mountain place
and they encounter the birth of the war god,
that they'll worship after this.
And how they stepped into the valley of Mexico as the last,
the lost brothers of everyone in the Valley of Mexico,
they said that they all came from the north.
Near Aztlan is a place, a cave
with seven different passages called Chicomoztoc.
And that all the people
who spoke the language nahuatl came from the cave.
And most of them went early to the Valley of Mexico.
And in the Aztecs story,
they were just the lost tribe.
They were the last brothers to come in.
But then they show up late game,
and they become mercenaries.
They just start working
for communities in the valley of Mexico.
And this takes place in the 1300s.
So about 200 years before Cortez shows up,
the Aztecs show up to the Valley of Mexico,
and they make themselves this
indispensable group of mercenaries.
They do the dirty work, all the civilized communities
around Lake Texcoco, which is now Mexico City.
It's all dried up, but those guys were too civilized
to fight with each other, but they could hire
the Aztecs to do their dirty stuff.
So the Aztecs did that
and really changed the politics in the game
of the Valley of Mexico.
- The dirty stuff, they're the muscle.
- Yeah, they'd go in
and they'd kill whoever you wanted killed.
Now you're the king of this area.
So one of these kings that they were working for
really liked them and decided,
I'm gonna make the Aztecs part of our ancestry.
I'm gonna give them my daughter
to marry the head of the Aztecs.
And the Aztecs sacrificed her,
and that really pissed that guy off.
So he took like his whole army
and ran the Aztecs out.
For a while, they say they live
in this horrible desert section eating lizards,
but then one of their priests say, we're gonna walk
around the lake, and my visions say that where we see
an eagle sitting on a cactus with a snake in its mouth is
where we will build our capital.
And they see that, but it's out on an island in the lake.
And he said, well, I don't know.
That's the place.
So they build up an island, they go to that island,
and then they just start piling up lake muck until they make
a whole city there in the middle of the island.
They make, or the lake, they make an island city.
And all of this occurs in about a hundred years.
So they show up about 1300.
The capital of Tenochtitlan, as they called it,
is really established.
And from there, they quickly take over the entire valley.
They make what they call the triple alliance,
which is the two other big communities
of the lake are now their allies,
but they're not really allies.
The Aztecs were brutal.
They were just, those guys agreed to shut up
and let the Aztecs run the show.
And then the Aztecs spread like a wildfire all the way down
into the Maya area.
Everywhere they go, they rename everybody's towns
and make them pay tribute.
- Pretty short last thing, civilization,
spread extremely quickly.
Famous, what are some defining qualities that explain that?
- I think they were very much like,
they had an attitude, like Attila the Hun.
They just had no problem ripping your skin off.
Everybody else had become too comfortable and too civilized.
And the Aztecs were just mercenary.
They told everybody, you know,
we can either rip your heart out or you can work for us,
and if you work for us, you'll be just fine.
They'd go to every town they'd go to.
The first thing they do is they'd show up
with a bunch of merchants.
There was a merchant class who were also military.
They were really the people who assessed
where they were gonna attack next.
They'd go in with a bunch of Aztec products and say,
we'd like to trade with you.
But all the time they were assessing their military prowess,
what products they had that they could take.
And then soon after the Pochteca were there,
would come the military with the reconnaissance.
- So the Aztec had a huge warrior class,
as you're saying.
So can you linger on their whole relationship
with war and violence?
- They worshiped a war deity.
Their main temple was the Templo Mayor.
It had two temples up on top.
One was to Tlaloc the rain God,
who liked a lot of sacrifice himself.
But then the other one was Huitzilopochtli.
He was, that translates the hummingbird on the left.
But he's the war God, I love that he's a hummingbird.
Maybe, you know, he's fast
and he comes from the magical side or something.
But then right next
to the temple on either side were
the two temples of the warriors.
One was the eagle warrior clan,
the other one was the jaguar warrior clan.
And they were symbolically
in competition with each other.
Though a unified force, I guess, you know,
probably an analogy between like the Navy and the Air Force.
You know, they had a good natured competition
of who was better, but they were the same force.
So those were their symbolic warriors,
dressed up in all of their finery.
And they would come at people with these two forces.
And it was very unlike anything
that had happened before in Mesoamerica.
Again, I think I could draw a parallel
to what happened in Europe.
You know, the famous Henry the V moment in Agincourt where,
you know, his kind of ragtag army
wipes out half of France's aristocracy with the longbow.
Like up until that moment, Europe had
a very wars for the elite classes kind of attitude.
And then after France lost half their aristocracy,
then it was like,
maybe we should be hiring from the villages.
The same sort of thing happened with the Aztec,
that there was a,
Mesoamerica really didn't have huge standing armies,
but the Aztec put this army together
and they intimidated people.
They didn't actually have to use it a lot.
It was used to great effect
in the valley of Mexico.
And for the rest of Mesoamerica.
It was mostly the fear factor.
- But there also seemed to be, you know,
a celebration of violence.
I think you said that beauty
and blood went hand in hand for the Aztec,
maybe like the Roman Empire.
Was it they just had a maybe a different relationship
with what violence, where that stood
in the purpose of life,
purpose of existence, is that fair to say?
- I would hypothesize so, I mean, you know,
I think it's one of the wonderful things
about studying these ancient cultures, you know,
knowing what our human capacity is.
And the Aztecs, when I said that statement,
what I meant by that is they were absolutely comfortable
with human sacrifice and,
you know, ripping people's hearts out.
They had this just, you know,
grotesque, violent bent.
But in the same way they also
absolutely loved flower gardens and poetry
and music and dance.
The same Aztec king who would order the hearts
of a thousand people extracted also would stand up
at dinner parties to recite his own poetry
or the poetry of famous statesmen that had come before him.
And they spent money on things like flower gardens.
All of the causeways leading
to the Aztec capital had beautiful flower gardens.
And they had a museum, and they had an aquarium
and a zoo, and they had an opera and they had a ballet.
And these things existed together.
There was not in the Aztec mind any conflict
between witnessing someone's heart getting ripped out,
one moment, in the evening we'd go to the ballet.
- How does that contrast the relationship with war
and violence, with the other civilizations
of Mesoamerica and South America, maybe the Maya?
What was their relationship like with war?
- The Maya were certainly influenced
by the Aztec at the end.
So we get a skewed perspective
from the contact period accounts,
because the Maya were much more violent
and sacrifice oriented in their post-classic rendition.
But in the classic period, it was mostly the priests
and the king who were doing the sacrificing of themselves,
that we know that the Maya kings would cut their penises
and then bleed that blood onto paper
and the paper would burn
and become the smoke through which they'd commune
with their ancestors, but they'd actually tie this paper
onto their penis, cut it, and then dance.
So the blood splattered, but it was them cutting themselves.
It was different than killing a bunch
of other people for it.
It was a auto sacrifice, we call it.
Still very macabre,
but very different than deciding a whole bunch
of other people should die.
It was a self sacrifice thing.
- Can you speak to the sacrifice a bit more?
Animal sacrifice, human sacrifice.
What role did that play in for the Maya,
for the Aztec, for the different cultures here?
Was that religious in nature?
- It was absolutely religious in nature.
And the Aztecs were of the opinion
that the war God demanded people were captured
and sacrificed, and it had to be valuable people.
There was a lot of, before they made that big standing army,
they had just ritual battles that they would have,
and they'd take captives.
In fact, all around Mesoamerica, they wanted captives
so that they could bring them back
and sacrifice them for the gods
and the Aztecs deciding to specifically follow
the war god did this more than anybody.
They did it so much and so successfully
that they didn't have any enemies nearby.
So they decided this one poor sucker group,
not that far away, called the Tlaxcallans,
that they were never going to make peace with them
so that they could go close by every year
and just have a little symbolic war with the Tlaxcallans
and haul 'em back for a sacrifice.
Cortez met those guys
and he was like, here are people who hate their guts.
I'll just use these guys.
So, you know, we say, oh, Cortez took over the Aztec world.
It was Cortez and 20,000 super pissed off Tlaxcallans.
- And they actual sacrifice what,
so there would be kind of these ritual battles,
or is it chopping off people's heads,
like is there some interesting rituals around the sacrifice?
- It's mostly heart extractions, sometimes heads,
but they bring them up on top of the temple
so everybody can see it.
And they had a specific stone
where they would bend them over,
so their ribcage would come out
and they'd use like a thick obsidian knife.
And they had a really just like tried and true way to do it.
They'd stab it in a certain place close,
and then they'd push down on the sternum
as they ripped up on the rib cage.
And they just, so they just make a place
where they could just rip it right out
- With their hand? - Yeah, with their hand.
But they were really just surgical about it.
They'd use a thick obsidian knife where they could
just break the ribs right along the sternum
and then push the sternum down.
Pull up and just.
- While the person was alive?
- Yep, while the person was alive.
And the Aztecs had this idea,
like there was a horrible drought that went on
that almost ruined the entire valley.
And they came to this conclusion that it's
because we haven't been killing enough people.
We've got to bump this up.
And then when they did and they decided,
they really took it out on the Tlaxcallans, it rained again.
So it was proof positive
that they should just keep doing that.
And they ate people as well, they really did.
- As part of the sacrifice, or is this?
- After the sacrifice, then they would eat them.
And this was part of the drought
and the famine thing that started,
but then it was just kind of the thing to do.
When Cortez got there, they were still having
certain special feasts that involved humans.
And it really upset the Spanish
that they would be like tricked into eating human.
Like, hey, you liking dinner?
That was a human.
- So the idea, was it actually,
having a taste for human flesh
or is it just, you know, these kinds of ideas of like,
if you eat a person's heart
that you can get their spirit and their strength.
- In the case of the Aztecs,
it seemed like they just liked it.
This guy, Sahagun, who was a very responsible chronicler
that was pretty specific.
That like, there was a distribution thing.
Like the elites got butts.
The butts were the best part.
So the butt cheeks, those are the best parts to eat.
And then like, it went down the chain
until some people just got like fingers and toes.
- Literally about taste for the Aztec.
Boy, all right, well.
- They really did, they really did.
In fact, that's what caused the,
have you heard of the Noche Triste, the sad night,
The night that the Aztecs really go nuts
on the Spanish and kicked them out.
It's all triggered by this one guy,
Pedro de Alvarado, who's left in charge by Cortez.
As Cortez, goes to the coast
and tries to talk to the New Force,
talk him into being for him, which he does.
But Pedro Alvarado's left back in town in charge,
and they're doing another one of these huge Aztec buffets
and parties to honor them, and it happens.
The guy says, you know, hey, do you like dinner?
Like, oh yeah, it's a nice dinner.
Well, it's humans, you're eating humans.
See, I told you they were good.
And Alvarado just freaks out.
And he has the guards close the doors
and he murders everyone in the party.
Women, children, nobody has weapons.
He just murders everyone,
and that's what spazzes the Aztecs out
to eventually murder Montezuma who was their captive,
and then try to murder all of them.
And it was all Pedro Alvarado's fault
for freaking out about eating humans.
- Just a little practical joke.
- It was just, they thought it was funny, he did not.
- That's fascinating, I didn't realize.
So I kind of assume that some level
of cannibalism would have to do with, you know,
eating the heart to gain the spirit
of the person or something like this.
- In certain, like, you know,
deer hunting rituals, things for sure.
But the Aztecs, no, they just liked eating humans.
It was part of the fear factor too.
I mean, they could walk into a new town
and be like, you guys could either send us, you know,
a number of Quetzal feathers every month,
or we could eat you.
- So that psychological warfare
and actual warfare, it worked.
And that's how they spread quickly.
- And they were just about
to take over the Maya when the Spanish came
and messed everything up.
They had the Maya surrounded
and they were about to take over the whole Yucatan.
- So you think without the Spanish
there would be this Aztec empire
that would last for a very long time?
- Mm, I think there would've been an Aztec empire.
I think they would've finished dominating everybody,
but they did it through hate.
And everybody hated the Aztecs.
So it wouldn't have lasted forever.
They were not ruling justly.
They were ruling by force.
And that can only go on so long before revolution happens.
The Inca Empire, I think that would've gone on forever
'cause they were really community oriented.
Once the Inca took over,
like no one in the Inca empire starved,
they built architecture, everyone was safe.
It was the society
that could have lasted a long time.
- What was the origin of the Inca Empire?
- Well, it was bloody at first, like most of them are.
But once they started taking over that,
what they did is they empire built.
Everybody else had just raided their neighbors
to get the resources, but everybody they raided,
they turned them into the Inca Empire.
And they created this incredible Mita system
where you took turns working
and they created the road system so they could get groups
of workers back and forth.
So a town of let's say 5,000 people,
the Inca would roll up with an army
of a hundred, 200,000 people
and say, you know, would you guys like
to be part of the empire?
Or would you like us to escort you
to the edge of the empire?
And if your mayor here agrees, then he can have a town,
he can have a house in Cusco.
But then the very next month, a big work crew would show up
and they'd start building agricultural terraces
and storage units.
And every month with the agricultural excess,
they would have big parties and everybody would eat.
So people lived well in the Inca Empire.
It was a rough beginning,
but everybody who agreed to be part of it
immediately had access to a whole bunch of resources
and security they never had.
- So they started in South America and Peru and Cusco,
Cusco was like the center of it?
- Cusco in their language, Quechua
it means navel or belly button.
And it's up in the mountains.
But there's four quarters.
They called their empire Tawantinsuyu,
the Land of Four Quarters.
And the center of those four quarters was Cusco.
- It sprung to life, what, in like 1200 DC?
- Yeah, we backwards project what it was.
But it was probably mid 1200s
when the first Sapa Inca, the first ruler came in,
but it was the, I think it's the ninth one is Pachacuti
who really started being an empire builder.
- And part of that, I mean, what really defined the empire,
as you said, roads, they build a massive road network.
- Roads, and in the same way that the Roman strategy
of building roads and infrastructure.
And then every place they took over,
they'd create certain key pieces of Roman architecture
that kind of made that city Roman.
And they'd rename it something, the Inca did the same thing.
They had certain signature Inca architecture
that they would build in as the administrative part.
They'd send the quipucamayoc, the guys
who would weave the, or knot the Quipus as accountants.
And though they would go through
and say what everybody did, okay, you know,
you're a good farmer, you're gonna farm.
You are a good weaver, you're gonna weave.
All the men here are gonna take a turn
at being part of the army.
And they sent independent quipucamayocs too,
that every community had like five or six
that were not allowed to work with each other.
And they all had to independently send their Quipus
back to Cusco.
And if there were accounting discrepancies,
they were called to Cusco to figure out
who was lying about what.
- So there's like a super sophisticated
record keeping system.
- Yeah, and that was the Quipu
and the Spanish recorded
what they could and then burned them all.
- But that's an interesting development for an empire
'cause that allows you to really expand
and have some kind of management,
some level of control.
- Yeah, they couldn't, at the end they were
at least 10 million people
and there was just no way to do that.
Without some sort of sophisticated record keeping system.
- If the Inca had to face Aztec, who wins?
- Inca.
I mean, the Aztecs were psychotic,
but the Inca had just reserves for miles.
And they had that essential hearts and minds.
And there was only one thing
that everybody got pissed off about
when they joined the Inca Empire.
For some reason everything was owned communally,
except the llamas.
The llamas were the king's.
And so that was one thing that like
some of them would stay in town just to be work llamas.
But you know, you don't own your llama anymore.
And people are really attached to their llamas.
To this day, they are like family members.
So it'd be like everybody walked in
and said everybody's family dog is now mine.
Like really upset people on an emotional level.
- Well, the, I mean, so llamas
got domesticated at some point, probably early.
I mean, I don't even know when, but early on.
- We have rock art that progresses to make it seem,
like a progression from people depicted hunting them
to people depicted standing next to pregnant ones.
So it was still in that archaic period
at least that they became friends.
- Yeah, but if you roll in and you own them, that's.
- Yeah, that pissed everybody off.
For some reason the Inca owned everybody's llama instantly.
And he would take anything he wanted.
A lot of them would just get carted away that day,
just sent to Cusco.
They'd also take their mummies, that was a weird thing.
Everybody mourns their dead.
But the Inca just like ceased to accept it.
They would just, the mummies were still there.
Okay, he's dead, but look,
he still got clothes, he's at the party.
Let's put a beer in front of him.
They just like, they just kept people as mummies.
And so the ancestral mummies of every town,
part of the being absorbed into the empire was, okay,
your most important mummies are now gonna have
their own beautiful house in Cusco.
But they would physically bring those mummies to Cusco
to make now Cusco the spiritual heart
of their belief system.
- I mean, I could see how that would piss people off,
but it's also a pretty powerful way to say, like,
the ancestors that you idolize,
that you respect are now in the capitol.
- They've been elevated, we didn't steal them.
We have given them a new place of honor,
and you are welcome to come visit them all the time.
And they did, they have these festivals
where everyone from all corners
of the Inca world would come to Cusco.
- And which of the civilizations mummified people?
- The Incas for sure mummified people.
And even did some of that kind of
like Egyptian esque taking out of organs
and preparing the body.
They'd put like straw inside the cavity and mummify them.
But the Maya didn't do it at all.
The Maya, in fact,
on purpose would flood tombs with water
so that the skin would float off the skeletons faster.
And then they'd get back in there, it was jungley.
So I think the bugs probably had part of it too.
But then they would get back in there to get the bones.
They'd open it back up and take the bones out
and paint them with red cinnabar.
The one that I was in in Copan, we had evidence
that they had gone in there four different times,
and the last couple times they only took the skull out
and repainted it
and then put it back in articulated on the skeleton.
But they didn't mummify,
they on purpose would like grossly float the bodies.
So they could get the skin off faster
and get to the bones.
- But would they keep the bones?
- Yeah, they'd keep the bones and they'd pull the bones out
occasionally and do rituals to them
or commune with them and then put them back in.
- So there's a still a deep connection
to the ancestors through the physical manifestation
of the ancestors then.
Whether mummified or bone.
- And to this day, like,
if you do an excavation here in the United States,
Native American people don't like it.
They don't like their graves, which is fine enough.
I wouldn't want somebody digging up my grandma either.
But the Maya, they love it.
And every Maya person, if we find a grave,
they're like, yeah, look at that, bones, cool.
Can I touch?
They're not spooked about it at all.
They think it's exciting.
I one time helped out
a physical anthropologist in town in Copan
to get a osteology collection together of various animals.
So if we got bones from an excavation, we could see
what kind of animal it was based on the collection.
And this family said, well,
our family dog died last year
and buried him in the backyard, you could go dig him up.
And so we were like, okay, yeah, I mean, we do need a dog.
We'll go dig up your dog.
And they were like, but the kids really want to help you.
So their kids came out, and this was like their puppy.
And it died, you know, less than a year ago when we got
to it, that like, one of them just like grabbed up a bone
and he was like, "huesitos," like little bitty bones, yay.
Like what a weird attitude, that's your dead dog there.
But they just,
they have a different relationship with the dead.
- In some sense that's a beautiful attitude, right?
- Yeah.
- Why pretend like we're not mortal
and there's not this is just the process of it,
and it's kind of,
as you say it now, it kind of would be cool.
- That's what Day of the Dead is all about.
And I love Day of the Dead, you know,
Halloween's this creepy thing where they're all monsters,
but Day of the Dead is this beautiful time
where we remember our ancestors.
I convinced my kids after the movie Coco came out.
Now we have an altar with all
of our great grandparents on the altar.
And we talk about who they were and how they lived.
And we put things on the altar that mattered in their life.
And we remember them on that day.
And it turned something that was a weird eat too much candy
and wear a monster mask thing into something beautiful
where we discuss where we came from.
- I have to ask about the giant stones
that Inca has been able to somehow move
and fit together perfectly.
Do you understand?
Is it understood how they were able to do that so well?
- No. (laughs)
You know, the moving of it,
I think that we have reasonable theories.
You know, there are ways to pivot large weights.
There's a great guy named Wally Wallington,
a retired contractor here in the US
who built Stonehenge in his backyard in Minnesota,
single handedly showing how you can move big stones.
So you know, I think Wally's
already figured out how to move 'em.
It's the perfectly fit so carefully fit together
that you couldn't even put a dime in between the stones.
That's the one that I think still has people baffled.
The common archeological wisdom that you'd find out
of a textbook is that they just kept pecking away
at it with hammer stones and setting them
and resetting them until they were perfect.
Which has to be bullshit.
There is no way that they just were that meticulous.
I mean, everybody's got a hammer stone.
I personally think it's acids.
I think they melted them together.
And there are weird places when you really look at closely
to these stones, which I've done a number of times.
I'm going back next month to Machu Picchu
and especially Cusco, I walk around in the alleys
where these 500, you know,
to a thousand year old walls are still there.
And you see, I see things like the crystals
in the andesite are almost stitched together
along the seams.
Like the andesite around it is melted
and the crystals haven't.
And there are other places
where there are weird wipes on the wall.
Like it's just melted, like somebody like took a rag
and wiped it while it was soft.
Lots of talk about soft stones turning hard too,
I haven't been able to prove it.
This is one of these, you know,
end of my archeological career chapters.
I'm either gonna prove myself wrong or prove it.
But I think they used acids.
My dad's a chemist
and he told me a long time ago that there's no way,
there's no naturally occurring acids.
But my current theory, actually,
I got the idea initially from the show Breaking Bad,
I don't know if you ever saw that show,
but there's a point in which they're trying
to dissolve a body.
And they're using hydrofluoric acid
and it goes right through the ceiling.
That hydrofluoric acid is so fascinating.
You know, it won't go through plastic.
And you can also bring it in inert parts
and then combine it.
The Inca made tons of jewelry out of fluoride.
Fluoride is big in the Andes.
And they also mined a lot of things for gold and silver.
And the byproduct of that mining is sulfuric acid.
You put sulfuric acid and fluoride together
and it's hydrofluoric acid
and that will burn through andesite or anything.
And if you learned how to do it, you know, judiciously,
and then you didn't care whether, you know, servants lost
an arm or two, then you could actually use them
to fuse these together.
And I think they're fused together.
I asked the city of Cusco
if I could take some core samples and they said,
go away, gringo, don't touch our walls.
So this actually,
this next time I'm gonna go try to talk
to the more Quechuan authorities
in a place called Ollantaytambo.
And maybe I can convince them,
but right now they just think I'm a weirdass gringo
who wants to put holes in their walls.
- That's a fascinating theory.
And so how could you get to the bottom of that?
So getting core samples
to see if there's some kind of trace?
- Chemists I'm working with say
that if there was hydrofluoric acid in between these,
that a core sample right along a seam,
they they can separate out the elements in there
and detect whether there was actually elements
of hydrofluoric acid.
I wanted to go straight to burning rocks,
but they were like, no, I mean, we already know that's true.
I mean, yeah, we can burn some rocks, but it would happen.
That's just chemistry.
We gotta prove that it would happen in the walls.
So go get us samples.
And that was before COVID
and all sorts of, you know how it is,
you probably are the same guy
where you've got a thousand ideas and you know,
the ones that are fruitful you run with
and the other ones you'll get back to.
- That would be fascinating if true.
And I hope you do show that it's true
or false, either one.
- I'll try to disprove it.
- Disprove it, yeah, I wonder if we discount
how much amazing stuff of collection of humans can do
'cause it just feels like if a large number of humans
are just working a little bit chipping away
at stuff at scale, they can do miraculous things.
So the question is, how can a large number
of humans be motivated to do a thing?
Because I just, when we think about like Stonehenge
or some very challenging architectural construction,
we don't think about a large number
of humans working together.
- Well, you know, that large number of humans are motivated
to work together by a small number of administrators
who are dynamic and convincing in some way or another.
One of my favorite quotes is,
and I'm probably gonna misquote it here,
but I think it's Margaret Mead who said,
"never underestimate the power
of small groups working together.
And the truth is that those are the only people
that have ever changed the world."
That small dedicated groups
of people are what change the world.
And they inspire big groups of people
to embrace their vision.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think we sometimes underestimate how much humans can do
across time, across scale.
- And we are way less capable than we used to be.
I mean, the average human had all sorts of skills
that at least I personally do not, you know,
I'm wearing a shirt,
but I can't make a shirt, that's for somebody else to do.
- You've also lectured about,
which I really enjoyed about North America
and also helped teach me that
there was a lot more complex societies going on here
for a long period of time.
So maybe can we start at the beginning?
Who were the early humans in North America?
- Well, we go through that paleoindian
and archaic period for thousands of years.
You know, as we started this conversation, probably,
you know, 30,000 years as a conservative now
humans first enter the Americas.
But the first cultures we get here are mound builders
around the Mississippi and to the east.
And then also a totally separate group in the,
what we call the American southwest now,
the four corners who will develop
into mostly the people we call the Pueblo people
who are still there today, like Zuni and Hopi people.
So we've got these two clusters.
The very first major community in North America is
in the most unlikely place.
It's in northern Louisiana.
People think I'm crazy when I say this,
but there is a pyramid in northern Louisiana,
a big one at a site called Poverty Point
that is 3,500 years old.
So it's the same age as the pyramids in Egypt.
And it is a giant thing
just poking out of the bayous of Louisiana.
And people don't believe me when I say it, but it's there.
- The mound builders.
What was that society like in comparison
to everything else we've been talking about in Mesoamerica?
- They evolved over thousands of years.
We call 'em mound builders.
This is something I, you know, object to.
I think we should have a better,
the last version of them we call the Mississippians now,
but generally speaking,
we call all these guys mound builders.
But what they built were pyramids.
They look like mounds now.
And they didn't build them out of stone.
That's, you know, that's kind
of our just inherent western bias.
Something that's built outta stone is sophisticated
and something that's built outta dirt is rudimentary.
But in their full living form,
they did have cores of dirt.
But then they also had kind of clay caps.
So they had terraces, they had whole complexes
of buildings up on top.
There were kings that lived up there.
The biggest of the Mississippian cities,
it's called Cahokia, and it's right outside of St. Louis.
And it was huge.
It had a population of 20,000 people
and pyramids all over the place.
A huge palisade wall around it.
It was absolutely gigantic, a thriving metropolis.
And we in America have kind of a collective amnesia.
Like we never hear about these massive civilizations.
Cahokia was the big first city,
but then it spread from the Mississippi
all the way to the Atlantic.
There were hundreds
and hundreds of these big cities that had, you know,
five to 10,000 people each.
- Were they their own thing
or was there some kind of thread connecting all of them?
- They had a unified religion and culture.
They were, again, not an empire.
So there were warring city states.
There were kind of territories that were owned
by big kings.
And then the cities around them were kind
of the subsidiary lords and kings.
And then one kingdom could either ally
with a neighbor or have a fight.
So they were kind of countries I think for, yeah,
we could safely say there were different countries
within this patchwork that was Eastern United States.
And you know, it's so weird that we don't know this
because it was clearly documented by the Spanish.
I'm not talking about just archeology,
we find them in archeology now.
But Hernando de Soto landed in Florida
and went for three years from, he went up into the Carolinas
and over down into Alabama and Louisiana.
And he's the first one to see the Mississippi up there.
But for three years he went through city after city,
after city, unfortunately decimating them,
eating all their corn, giving them diseases.
But I mean, the documentation's clearly there.
He met collectively, millions
of people in a very sophisticated
and uniform civilization.
- So it was disease and stealing of resources.
But was there like explicit murdering going on?
- Unfortunately, yeah.
He was a murderer and a psycho and a liar.
He snowed them that he was some kind of deity,
actually learned a trick from the Inca
he was with Pizarro in his first run
and went back to Spain, was rich, had a wife, a castle.
Then he got bored and he decided to have a reign
of terror on Northern America for three years.
But he had people burned at the stake.
He had his dogs rip them apart.
He was very, very brutal.
He ruled that area through fear
and had absolutely no respect for anybody.
He made promises and broke them all the time.
He was really, he was a brutal man.
- So this whole period when Christopher Columbus came,
how did that change everything?
- Well, you know,
there's a great anthropological body of literature.
It's called the Colombian Exchange, based on Columbus.
But it's, you know, all this trade back
and forth between the new world and the old world.
And the old world got just wonderful stuff.
All of a sudden their diet didn't suck.
All these vegetables came in.
The new world got herd animals.
It got pigs and cows and goats that it didn't have,
but it also got 13 infectious diseases.
Europe had had wave after wave
and kind of had herd immunity on a lot of things.
But it didn't actually go away.
It just couldn't spread
like a wildfire through the community.
So when they arrived to the Americas,
all of a sudden these just a pile
of horrible diseases hit people.
I think in the first 20, 30 years there were people
who like had contracted multiple deadly diseases
at once and died of them.
But the numbers, you know,
it's a shameful part of history.
And it wasn't something that Europe perpetrated on them,
but the medical science
at that time was still the four humors theory
that people were made of yellow bile,
black bile, blood, and phlegm.
And we did things like, well, you've gotta bleed him.
He'll feel better then.
So we had no idea what an infectious disease was,
but the reality was that this hoard
of diseases hit everyone.
And the numbers are now saying in the first 50 years
that 90% of everybody was dead.
And that the number of people has increased as well.
As far as our estimates,
we're thinking it's somewhere around 150 million people
and 90% of them died.
And with them all their knowledge
and just, I mean, imagine the moment where, you know,
who dies when things get bad, it's the young and the old.
So all the knowledge keepers die suddenly,
the children die.
This next generation that's half taught
and now completely demoralized,
thinking that this is a spiritual attack,
that their gods hate them.
That the only way out of it is
to accept this new Christianity.
But they, you know, they don't wanna bring kids
into this world where everybody's dying.
And even if they do, they can't teach them
what the old people were gonna teach them
'cause the old people are gone
and didn't finish the transmission.
So in a single terrible moment in human history,
you know, the generation loses all their knowledge.
So a lot of the things
that these people knew just blipped out.
- But with that also just the wisdom
of the entire civilizations.
- So much of what they knew was just lost at that moment.
We have the Maya who had those hieroglyphs
and that we've learned a lot from that.
- Yeah, but not a significant integration
of that wisdom into, so it wasn't,
when the Europeans came,
it wasn't like the cultures were integrated.
It was a story of domination, of erasure, essentially.
- In North America,
there's a new term in the literature that I like,
we call it the Mississippian shatter zone.
That Mississippian civilization was millions of people,
but they got spread out all over the place
over the next centuries.
And now we have this shatter zone
where we have ruins and the people
that were actually from those ruins are somewhere else
on a reservation far away.
And, you know, I'm just about to talk to a Cherokee man
who listened to some of the things I had to say
and says all those Ho-Chunk things you were saying
from that whole Ho-Chunk culture.
My grandparents talk about this sort of thing too.
Can I talk to you by phone
and tell you about these things?
So we've got this shatter zone where, you know,
we're gonna try to put the puzzle back together.
Especially in terms of Mississippian religion.
I really think we're making headway in this generation.
And it's exciting to be part of piecing this old religion
and its mythology back together.
- Just since a lot of people kind of refer
to Christopher Columbus
as the person who discovered America.
I read that the Vikings reached North America
much earlier in 1000 BCE.
And why do you think they didn't expand and colonize?
- Because they got their ass kicked.
- Okay, simple. - It's the truth.
It is absolutely true that the Vikings were here.
There's a great site in Nova Scotia
called L'Anse aux Meadows,
which definitely has what's left of a Viking colony.
It was Leif Erik
and his father Erik the Red, who they got kind
of kicked outta Europe 'cause they apparently
couldn't stop murdering people.
And so they went to Greenland
and then kind of island hopped over to Canada.
But I think the culture
that was in that area was named the Dorset.
But they would have nothing to do with the Vikings.
They attacked the Viking settlement every day
and did not give them an inch
until they decided it was just worthless.
And they left it, you know, the Vikings attacked Ireland
and they just found a bunch of, you know,
monasteries full of gold with a bunch of guys going,
we're men of God, we don't fight.
And the Vikings were like, this is great, that's great.
This'll be easy then we'll just loot all these Easter eggs.
But the Native Americans in Canada were like not having it.
They kicked their ass, in fact,
Leif Erikson's brother Thor died there.
The natives killed him.
He was supposed to be in charge of expanding the settlement,
but they just killed him.
- So a lot of the Native American cultures were also,
I mean, they're sophisticated warring cultures also.
- Yes, they fought, especially the Mississippians,
boy, they were tough.
And so were, you know, the Five Nations, the Mohawk,
the Huron, the ones that kicked the Vikings' ass up there.
They were probably Algonquian speakers,
but they were connected like, you know,
just above the Great Lakes.
But they were all very tough people.
- When you think about the Spaniards and the Portuguese
and over a hundred million people that were killed,
do you see that as a tragedy of history
or is it just the way of history?
- I think that the epidemics, I consider it a tragedy
that did not have to happen.
And that was not, you know, that was not a fair fight.
Nobody knew what to do about it.
There was just a tragic, perfect storm of events.
It was not, you know, I think that the Spanish
and the Portuguese get unfairly maligned
in what's been called the black legend
that they just marched into America and murdered everyone.
That's not the fact.
It was the diseases that murdered everyone.
In fact, there was a really poignant story I read
of a Spanish priest in the Amazon
in the Brazilian northern part of the Amazon
where he made this utopian community
and he was bringing people in that were getting sick.
And he wrote, you know, I'm baptizing everyone,
you know, I have baptized 10,000 people a day,
and yet God's still killing them.
What, why is he doing this to them?
They're doing everything that I ask them to do.
They are submitting to the will of God.
But this guy doesn't realize that the same bowl
of holy water that he's baptizing them in,
he's just wiping the disease on everybody's faces.
He's accelerating it when he doesn't even realize.
He thinks he's saving them, but he's actually killing them.
- Yeah. - That's a tragedy.
You know, that's not just
like spoils go to the victor stuff.
That's just straight up tragedy.
- Yeah, yeah, but that one is hard to know
what to do with like black death.
It's, I mean, infections,
they don't operate on normal human terms, right.
They just go through entire populations.
Back to wild ideas.
- All right, just my style.
- I mean, we didn't really talk
about how life originated on Earth
or how humans have evolved.
And we did talk about that there could be just a lot
of stuff in ancient history we haven't even uncovered yet.
Do you think it's possible
that other intelligent civilizations
from outside of Earth, aliens ever visited?
- You had me right until the ever visited thing.
That one I'm not entirely sure about.
I'm not sure whether we have any,
we certainly have no archeological proof that I would cite
or contemplate as the evidence of such.
But, you know, the guys that discovered DNA,
Watson and Crick,
Watson, who actually habitually used hallucinogens
to invigorate his thinking, he said that he thought
that DNA on this planet was way too complex
to have developed over the time period
that it had at its disposal.
And that his guess was
that our DNA was somehow seeded from outside of our planet
and, you know, take that for what it is.
But the guy who we respect
on many other levels also said that.
So that's interesting, but in terms of, you know,
aliens visiting us, I don't know,
it does smack of a kind of human hubris
that we think we're important enough
for some advanced species to give a shit about us.
Statistically speaking, the universe is way too big.
We can't be the only sentient beings.
There's gotta be somebody else out there
whether they care about us, that's a question.
I've been on "Ancient Aliens" a number of times.
I show up and, you know, I'm an educator.
I mean, refusing to be part
of the conversation's an immediate fail in my book.
But there was one time where they asked me at the end,
you know, do you have anything else that you wanna say?
And I said, well, you know, yeah.
Y'all's premise is that aliens came down a long time ago
and they gave humanity these wonderful gifts of, you know,
science and medicine, engineering, all these things.
Today we also have a lot of stories
of the aliens coming down,
but now all they're doing is mutilating cows
and sodomizing rednecks.
Like whatever we did, we super pissed them off, apparently.
- The quality of the gifts has decreased rapidly.
What it's an interesting thought you've mentioned.
What archeologically would you have to see
to be like, this might be an alien?
- A technology that doesn't belong there,
first and foremost.
I mean, you know, we gotta,
if we just run with the premise that somebody was capable
of making a vehicle
that could get them from somewhere far away to here,
that was almost certainly mechanical.
Now, you know, I love the aliens thing where, you know,
biomechanical is something that certainly could be
and that would, you know, that would disintegrate.
We wouldn't see that at all.
But I would expect some kind of technology
that showed up out of the blue and changed things.
That would be something.
But I would think, you know, mechanical.
Or, you know, a substance that's not from here.
- But of course we would only see the results
of that mechanical,
you mean like literally a mechanical thing?
- Right, some sort of thing like that.
The typical thing people say is like, you know,
how did they move these giant stones, right?
But, you know, just look
at that on the face for a second.
Aliens come from across the universe to meet humans
and the thing they tell them is how to move rocks.
Are you fucking kidding me?
I mean, you know, like give them antibiotics
or a combustion engine or something.
They came across the universe
and they showed 'em how to move big rocks.
I mean, that doesn't make any sense.
Yeah, that just doesn't make any sense.
- What do you think Earth will look like
10,000 years from now?
- That's a interesting question.
I think it will be a lot more automated
or it'll be a smoldering pile.
I mean, there is a possibility we could end ourselves.
There's always that possibility
that we've really opened Pandora's box in some regards.
I did listen to one of your podcast guests
with the what would happen in the case of nuclear war.
That was chilling.
Her opinion was certainly we would burn everything
to a crisp within minutes apparently.
So we have that capacity, that's scary.
That's a possible future for us, but I'm an optimist.
You know, I'd like to think
that guys like you are gonna make friendly robots
who make my job better.
- But a thousand, 10,000 years is a long time
and technology is improving
and becoming more advanced rapidly,
and the rate of that improvement is increasing evermore.
- That's the part that frightens me actually.
I dunno, does that frighten you?
- Yeah, it's terrifying. - You know,
I heard somebody say, I forget who it was,
but, you know, systems of any kind,
human systems, biological systems can be put on a graph
that's change over time.
And any graph
that the change is way faster than the time.
And the line starts going straight up.
That is a system in crisis
in almost any biological system
that has that fast change over that little a time.
Any other thing, you'd describe it as a crisis.
When you apply that chart
to technologies change, it's a crisis.
- From that perspective, absolutely.
But I also have a faith in human ingenuity
that we humans like to create
a really difficult situation
and then come up with ways to get out
of that difficult situation.
And in so doing, innovate and create a lot of awesome stuff
and sometimes cause a lot of suffering,
but on the whole, on average, make a better world.
But yeah, you know, like with nuclear weapons,
the bad stuff might actually lead to the death of everybody.
- I guess there's always that chance.
But I am an optimist.
You know, I think you're an optimist too.
I think exactly as you just said,
I think that the greatest capacity
of humans is our ability to innovate.
And we are never more innovative
than when we're under distress.
I think that a lot of the developments
of humans over the last thousands of years have been about,
you know, we didn't change the world
when we were comfortable, it was when we were in crisis.
Mother necessity is the mother of invention.
And I think we'll be all right.
I think that this impending climate crisis
is real and happening.
I actually personally think
that I'm gonna answer a question
that you didn't even ask me.
I think we're wasting our time
thinking that we can reverse this.
We're delusional, I'm all for electric cars
and, you know, being good stewards of the environment,
but we are wasting our time
not technologically adapting to what's about to happen.
We're spending too much time pretending, you know,
the average American thinks
if we all just drive electric cars, we'll be okay.
That's bullshit, that's not gonna happen.
We need to start making technologies that desalinize water,
that, you know, a host of things that we need
to use our technological capacity to accept it
and adapt instead of Pollyanna thinking
we can make it go away.
- Yeah, yeah, kind of accept that the world will change
and a lot of big problems will arise
and just develop technology that addresses them.
- I think you have some guys
that have their finger on the pulse there.
We need to start thinking
about how we're gonna survive this.
Not that we're gonna make it go away.
- And not just survive, thrive.
Again, we're pretty innovative in that regard,
but if some catastrophic thing happens
or we just leave this planet,
what do you think would be found
by aforementioned alien civilizations
when they visit.
The anthropologist, the grad student anthropologist
that visit Earth and study,
how much of what we now have
and love and think of as human civilization
will be lost, do you think?
- Well, you know, time moves on
and things that are perishable perish.
So, you know, you didn't put a time element in there,
but I would say that, you know,
everything that can perish will,
and whoever shows up here will be stuck
with only the things that didn't perish.
So we'll have, you know, buildings, plaques,
but they won't have any books.
They won't have any, you know, billboards.
They'll have the incomplete record I have.
I one time did a talk in Sioux Falls
and I said, you know, I drove in here
and there was a big obelisk in front of the town
and everywhere I go, I see the names Lewis and Clark.
And a thousand years from now,
if I was an archeologist investigating this place,
I would think that it was founded by the Egyptians
and their kings were named Lewis and Clark.
But the truth is, you know,
Lewis and Clark stayed one night here,
but it's just a big deal.
So I would be so wrong about what I thought about your town
based on what preserved.
- That's so beautiful as a thought experiment.
Like what would archeologists be really wrong about
and what would they could possibly be right about.
- Washington DC was clearly made by a combination
of the Egyptians and the Greeks and the Romans,
because that's what all the architecture is.
- Yeah, and would they be able
to reconstruct the important empires,
the powerful empires and the warring empires.
- For that matter,
have me and my colleagues done that at all?
I'm almost certain that the Maya would just gut laugh
at what I think I know what they were.
- I wonder, do you ever think about like what
we just as a human civilization are wrong about the most,
like mainstream archeology, just like a suspicion,
what could we get completely wrong?
Well, one way to get something wrong is
totally like lost civilization.
Like an obviously gigantic civilization that was there
along with the Maya or something like this
in the 10,000 years ago.
- There's certainly that there could be things
that were either wiped away
or still hiding under the oceans
that would completely change the way we think about things.
- And everybody knew they existed
and everybody interact with 'em.
- I think that's our estimation
of their motivations that we're probably most wrong on.
My teacher Sheila, a long time ago said,
you know, I've come up with all sorts of theories.
I was always thinking about stuff and she looked at me
and she said, if you don't stop thinking
like a Western European
and start trying to put yourself in the mindset
of these people, you will never understand any of it.
Which I've always taken to heart, I mean, I really do.
When I approach these things, I try to step out
of my cultural assumptions, try to think
like they would think as the best I could.
And it's very different.
I mean this whole, you know, the Maya are cyclical,
you know, the whole sacrifice,
were so, you know, obsessed with that.
But, you know, that was a austere actual sacrifice
on their part.
They weren't just, you know, hey, let's all get together
and kill that guy that's pissing us off.
I mean, they were like, you know, giving the best of them.
It was a different mentality, this was not brutal.
This was a, you know,
bonafide sacrifice on their part, a loss.
- Plus the whole mystery of the puppy
that eventually starts having sex with this.
- I tell you, that one, I'm gonna unweave that one,
one of these days.
- Now that puppy appeared on pottery.
- All over pottery.
He's everywhere, I gotta write this book.
This next year is the year
I'm gonna write my fanged deity book.
And I will have a whole chapter
dedicated to the puppy.
- Mystery solved, I mean,
it could just be the birth of memes, of humor.
I don't know, I mean, again, humor, you don't know
what the nature of their humor, of what their jokes are.
- Oh, that's a neat one too, and that's so human.
You know, I'll tell you a little like side story here
that when I worked with the Maya people in Palenque,
I spent three years making this map of the city
and hiking through the jungle every day.
And they would talk to each other in their own language.
It was tseltal was the group I was working with.
But I noticed after a while, they were big jokers.
They loved to make jokes and they would laugh at jokes,
but then they would also, one of them would say something
and the other ones would go, hoo hoo.
And I eventually asked, you know, what is that?
Why do you guys always make that hoo hoo noise?
And he said, that's 'cause he made a really smart pun.
It was like he said three different things at once.
It was a turn of phrase that was smart.
And they didn't make laughs at that.
It was, they had a noise
for when somebody said something just super clever.
So there's also that like, you know,
just clever turn of speech.
- Yeah, wit.
- And I think about that when I'm a hieroglyphic translator.
Like, here's a beautiful thing that's gonna be like a poem
or a political statement.
Like, and I'm just plottingly looking
in a dictionary of what that word means.
There's probably double,
triple entendres all through this text.
And the real meaning is the subtext.
And I'm, you know, I'm thinking they're talking about corn
and they're talking about the nature of life.
- Yeah, it could be satire, it could be, you know,
as it was in the Soviet Union when there's a dictator,
maybe there's a overpowering king.
You're not allowed to actually speak.
You have to hide the thing
you're actually trying to say in the subtext.
So, and all of that.
- There was a funny Maya ceramic that had,
the ceramics are neat 'cause they don't,
the monuments can be kind of broken records.
I'm the king, I was born this time, I beat these people up.
I married this woman, I died.
But the ceramics will tell us like things out
of mythology stories.
And there was this one with a rabbit looking
at the merchant god, and nobody could translate the text.
And finally this eastern European,
actually a Ukrainian guy translated it
and the rabbit's saying to the merchant god,
bend over and smell my ass.
And like, oh man,
we were expecting this wonderful piece of mythology.
But no, it translates bend over and smell my ass.
That's great, that's human.
- As we mentioned previously, human nature does not change.
You mentioned Palenque, mapping it.
Just outta curiosity,
what is that process like, it seems fascinating.
- Oh, it was a great adventure, I loved it.
But it was difficult.
I woke up every morning thinking
I will be hurt today somehow.
I don't know how, I don't know how badly,
where on my body it will occur, but it's gonna happen
because it was the jungle.
- So in the jungle, what's the process like?
Like what do you have to do to map it?
- Well, it was tricky too
because it was also a national forest.
So the forestry department didn't want us
to cut down anything more than we had to.
So we basically just cut tunnels through the foliage
and I would, we'd map everything twice.
The first thing we'd do is I'd go in, find a building,
draw it on a piece of graph paper,
and I'd say like, you know, you guys go north,
you guys go east, west, find other buildings,
and when you find them pace back to this one.
And so I'd start making a map
and I'd make the whole, one piece of graph paper was enough
to then we'd bring the machine in,
we'd bring the laser theodolite
and get really accurate information.
But on that piece of paper, I would write like,
don't bring the machine this way.
There's a tree fall or stand on top of this building
and you'll see four different buildings
at once from this one.
- And all of this is in dense jungle.
- Right, and the deeper we got off the road,
the deeper it was, sometimes it would clear out,
but certain places, if it was low,
it would be such thick vegetation
and it would grow back so fast.
Sometimes we would cut just tunnels through tall grass
and we'd come back like five days later and they were gone.
We couldn't even find where our trails were.
They would grow back that fast.
- But you see the building so you could see.
- Right, and that was the fun part.
I mean, sometimes it would just be like
a little neighborhood with little low buildings,
no bigger than this table, but sometimes, you know,
just five more meters in.
And I'm standing under a pyramid
that nobody had ever mapped.
Like, wow, I've just found another one.
And some days, you know,
on good days we'd find three pyramids.
And I felt that's such a more exciting job
than the typical excavations.
Although my buddies were all just, you know, in a hole
for the whole week in the middle of the city
and where I'm dancing around through the jungle,
I could find, you know, 10 buildings today.
I might find a pyramid today, who knows.
- What's that feel like to find like a pyramid
or buildings that you are one of the only humans
that are not from that civilization to ever see this thing?
What's that feel like?
- It's great, I love that feeling.
I am, you know, I'm an explorer at heart,
so finding something like that, you know,
when I was 25 years old, I found a whole Maya city.
I got to name it, its name is Ma'ax Na,
it's off in the Belizean jungle.
And that was just, just outrageous.
I mean, it almost, that one almost depressed me.
My entire, like, I had this great life ambition
that I would find a lost city.
And then I did it at 25
and I was like, God, now what do I do?
I thought that was supposed to take me my whole life.
I actually, I wrote a bunch of letters to NASA trying
to get them to let me be the first archeologist on Mars.
I never got a single reply back.
I'm sure I'm on NASA's list as some weirdo.
- How'd you find a Mayan city?
- I used a topography map of the area
and I played the game.
If I was a Maya, where would my favorite place
to live in this big area be?
I looked for the biggest mountain
because they call all of their pyramids tunwits,
stone mountains, I knew they loved mountains.
And when I found that mountain,
there were two others right next to it that made a triangle.
And they loved those triads
and there were rivers in between them.
And I thought, that's it.
That's where I would build the city.
And I hiked out there over two seasons with students.
The other grad students were like,
he's just having his students just wander
in the jungle all day, but I came back with the city.
- So given that you've looked
into the deep pasts of humanity,
what gives you hope about our future,
maybe our deep future of this human civilization?
- That's a good one, and I do have hope.
I do have hope, I believe in the spirit of humankind.
I, as a person who have studied history,
I kind of feel like history does kind of a sine wave.
There's highs and there's lows,
but no matter how low we go,
we get up again and we climb.
And I think that humanity will continue that,
we will rise to the challenges.
Now, some of the challenges may be created by ourselves
as well, but we will adapt and overcome.
That's what we do.
- Yeah, humans find a way, right?
That's like, that's the thing you see with history,
even when the empires collapse.
The humans that come outta that,
they pick themselves up and find another way.
- And the people I study believe in the cyclical nature
of life that you really can't,
life can't continue without death being part of the cycle.
We get our lows, we get our highs,
but the cycle continues forever.
- I should mention that you have a lot of great lectures
on the great courses, but you have also an amazing podcast,
ArchaeoEd, if people wanna listen to it,
this is a tough question,
but what would you recommend,
what episodes should they listen to, what's the entry?
- Oh, that is a tough question.
- What is the sampling?
You know, it's like asking a chef,
like what's the best stuff on the menu?
- Well, different strokes for different folks.
You know, I do two different things on that podcast.
Sometimes I just teach about cultures
that you've never heard about.
I start off by saying it's my podcast
and I'll talk about whatever the heck I wanna talk about.
Sometimes I talk about really specific things
like a tool type or an animal type.
But my favorite ones have become,
when I just tell my stories of my adventures,
I've got a lot of weird adventure stories
and it's been fun and they've been very well received.
I've got, you know, I can put my humor in there
and I can talk about, you know, the things
that went right, the things that went wrong, the adventures
that I had are all part of this ArchaeoEd thing.
And ArchaeoEd's kind of a double entendre.
It's me, I'm just Ed, but it's also education.
You know what I'm really trying to do with this too,
it's specifically the Americas.
I want to be part of the reawakening
that there were these great civilizations here,
especially North America.
I think that we have a group amnesia
that there was no great civilizations here
before Europe showed up, that's simply not true.
I think it should be part of our history books.
In fact, I have a program called Before the Americas
that would introduce as part of American history,
the part before European contact.
And I think that kids
in the K through 12 level should grow up
not being told this fallacy
that no one was here before we showed up in 1492.
And one of these days I'm gonna find a funder
to help us put together Before the Americas
and we're gonna make it part of the curriculum
for every kid in the US
to know the full history of this country.
- That's a great project, Ed, thank you so much.
Thank you for talking today.
Thank you for all the fascinating ideas
that you put out into the world
and I can't wait to hear your new course.
- Thank you so much, Lex, it was a real pleasure.
- Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Ed Barnhart.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you some words from Joseph Campbell.
"Life is but a mask worn on the face of death
and is death then, but another mask,
how many can say asks the Aztec poet
that there is or is not a truth beyond?"
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.