I believe Optimus is gonna be the greatest product ever created by humanity.
Elon Musk and his xAI startup have built the largest and most powerful artificial intelligence training super computer in the world.
As far as I know, there's only one person in the world who could do that
you know?
Thi- this is a- an arms race of epic proportions.
He's a big thinker!
You guys went on Fox the other day with the Doge team- I saw Elon's face nodding while they were speaking with a grin ear to ear.
Right.
He was proud.
He is proud.
xAI has acquired X in an all-stock transaction.
Tesla's first robo-taxis are officially on the road.
The company's board proposed a new compensation package for the CEO that could pay him just about a trillion dollars in stock.
He gets nothing if he doesn't hit the numbers.
SpaceX will buy wireless spectrum licenses from Echo Star for its Starlink satellite network for about $17 billion.
Three, two, one.
There's a  Oh my god.
There's a splash down.
That's so awesome.
How do you have time?
This, I- I- I never understand you.
Yeah, well, I do work a lot.
I mean .
..
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome Elon Musk.
All right.
Yeah.
Hello.
Where are you?
Alto.
You're in Palo Alto.
Yeah.
And, um, not Washington, DC- I'm at- I'm at- I'm at- I'm at Tesla
uh, global engineering headquarters in Palo Alto.
Yeah.
So, no more Washington, DC?
You're back at work, you're focused, yeah?
Uh, yeah, I haven't been to DC since May.
Okay.
Uh- That was a s- that was a hell of a side quest.
Um- That was a good s- any lessons from your time in Washington
DC?
Uh, the government is basically unfixable.
Elon- O- o- only-  O- only- I applaud David's
uh, noble efforts, and let's uh, it- it's good to
it's good to have talented people in the administration
uh, but at the end of the day
um, if you look at our national debt
which is, uh, insanely high, uh
the interest payments exceed the, uh, Defense Department
I guess, sorry, War Department-  .
..
uh, budget.
Um, and, um, they keep rising.
So, if AI and robots don't solve our national debt
we're- we're toast.
Hm.
Which is a great segue.
Um, Optimus is, um, I think- That's right.
.
..
gonna be the greatest- That's right.
.
..
uh, product in the history of humanity.
What's the progress like in how much of your- how many of your cycles are going specifically to Optimus?
What's the timeline?
I think you're on version three, maybe four.
Uh, tell us everything.
Uh, well, yeah.
No, everything will take a long time.
We've got time.
Um, we're- we're finalizing the design of Optimus version three.
And, uh, that- that really is gonna be a very remarkable robot.
Um, it will have the, essentially the manual dexterity of a human
so meaning a very complex hand.
Um, a- the- a- an AI mind that can navigate and comprehend reality.
Um, and be made in very high volume.
Uh, those are the three things that are missing.
Like, if you see any other, um
robotics, uh, company, they're missing those three things.
Those are the three really hard things.
Um, and, uh, I- I- I spend actually at this point
um .
..
it- it might be more of my mental cycles than anyth- anything else
any other single thing on Optimus.
Uh, that's- that- that's solving for, uh
real world AI, uh, all of the electromechanical issues of Optimus
the- the supply chain and production challenges of it.
Because we have- there- there is no supply chain that exists for humanoid robots
so it has to be created.
We have to recreate it from scratch, um
and which requires doing a lot of vertical integration.
Um, n- none of the actuators in Optimus
um, are available from an existing supply chain.
Um, so, but I- I- I think it is accurate to say that if successful
Optimus will be the biggest product ever.
And the cost of it at scale?
20, 30, $40,000 a robot?
What- what do you think the first wave of them will cost and
uh, when will we be able to buy one to work on the ranch?
I think the- the- the marginal cost of production
once you hit a million units per year
uh, is probably around the $20,000 range.
Uh, it- it- it sort of depends on how much you spend on the AI chip in the- in the robot.
Um, and you need to achieve a lot of efficiencies in the actuators.
Uh, there are, um, 26 actuators per arm.
Like, 26 electric, like motors, gear boxes
and power electronics.
Um-.
..
so, so it.
But- but the- the- the- the AI chip will be pretty expensive
like that- that might be like five- $5
000 or $6,000 of the- of the bill of materials
maybe more.
Um, and, um, but- but so I- but I think at volume
at a million units a year, the- the production cost is probably in the order of $20
000, maybe 25, something like that.
And, um, the price will be as a function of demand.
Elon, um, can you maybe explain to everybody why the hand is so important to get right
and why, you know, the actuator design is so unique
and you know, why it's so difficult
why nobody makes it, and why you have to start there almost to build the rest of the- the robot properly?
Well, it turns out that human hands are incredibly.
..
that they've evolved to this- to be this incredibly sophisticated machine.
Like the- your hand is the- an inc- an- a- actually a remarkable thing.
It's just, look- look closely at your hands  and- and-  .
..
think of all the things you can do with your hands
which is a lot.
I can think of many things.
Yeah, I was just thinking about something.
You know, your- your hand's a very versatile instrument.
Um- Yeah.
You can give a high five.
Very versatile.
Um, you know, you- you- you can swing a baseball bat.
You can, uh, thread needles.
You can- you can- you can put thread in a needle.
Uh, you can play the piano, violin.
Um, you know, you could disassemble or assemble a car.
The- the hands are inc- incredibly versatile instruments.
Um, and, um, most of the muscles of- of- of the hand are- are actually in the forearm.
So your- your hand is kind of like a- like a- like it's like a puppet
like it's mostly a puppet.
The mus- the muscles are coming from the forearm and they're pulling the tendons
uh, which are l- you know, it- also human tendon design's in- or human- human tendon evolution is incredibly good.
Um, so you've- you've got this web of tendons.
You've- you've- you've got, um, I think- I think ha- the ha- human hand has something like
depending on how you count it, 27 or 28 degrees of freedom per ha- you know
i- i- in- in the hand.
It's, uh, it's amazing.
So, i- in order to create a robot that can
uh, be a generalized, uh, humanoid
you- you must solve the hand- the hands problem.
Yeah.
We had, uh- we had already a- It's- it's- it's got hands
these hands.
Yeah.
And so is it like, uh, when you were first building Tesla
where the supply chain doesn't exist and now you have to go out and find folks to work with
and you know, build all this vertical integration
get support?
Is it- is it literally like it's just nowhere to be found and you're gonna have to build- Yes.
.
all of this stuff up?
Yes.
We- we- we could not actually buy the actuators for any amount of money.
They simply didn't exist.
Even though there are, I don't know
10,000, 20,000 electric motors out there of various sizes and shapes.
Um, we've had to design, uh, every electric motor gearbox
um, out of- and the controlling electronics from scratch
basically from physics first principles.
Um, and then- The good news is you've got a lot of experience with factories over the last couple of decades.
So- Yeah.
.
..
how challenging is this versus Cybertruck, Model Y- Model X.
.
..
Gigafactory, you know, the- yeah.
The Faberge egg known as the Model X?
Yeah.
Right.
Um, it's harder than any- any of those things.
Okay.
Yeah.
Much harder?
Significantly, yeah?
Starship?
Yes.
Well, at least for- Harder than Starship?
.
..
no, not ha-  Starship's harder.
Okay.
Harder.
So somewhere between a Model X and a Starship?
.
Yeah.
Is it- Yeah.
.
is the.
..
What's harder, the hardware or the software?
Right now, we're struggling with the- the final design of the hardware.
D- like I said, it's really primarily the hand.
Uh, and not to dis- just dismiss the rest of the robot
re- rest of it's also, uh, important
but- but the hands are- the hands and inclusive of the forearm are a majority of the engineering difficulty of the entire robot.
And then le- let's assume you get past the hardware challenges.
How much do you sort of get for free
um, based on all the progress that's happening with LLMs?
Will, you know, will consumers just be able to interact with this
talk to the robot- Oh, yeah.
.
ask it to do things, it'll understand and sort of- Oh
yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, no problem.
You- you're spending a lot of time with Annie
I noticed online.
Not- not that long.
Um- Yeah.
.
maybe I went a little over the top promoting Rock Imagine but
uh-  Well, I- but in all seriousness
those characters and these robots that seems to be
you know, like maybe they- You could get the embodiments of Annie
I suppose.
Yeah.
Why- why the human form factor, Elon?
You could make something that's maybe better than a human or maybe simpler than a human to do specific tasks and maybe better than a human to do more things than a human can do.
How'd you decide to make it just like a human?
Well, if you wanted to do all the things that a human can do
it turns out you need a humanoid robot.
Um, so if you wanted to do a subset
it- that's much easier.
Um, but, uh, i- it turns out humans evolved to this- this shape and capabilities that we- we- we have
um, i- it- it- for- for good reasons.
Uh, it actually is- there- there is a- like there's value to having five- you know
four fingers and a thumb.
Um, and e- even the pinky actually is- is quite useful.
Um, uh, toes are a much more question mark
but- but- but the fingers-   Well
also humans- I- Humans have designed the world as well
so we designed it for us.
For us.
Right.
So- Exactly.
.
..
if you could make a humanoid robot, it'll be immediately backwards compatible with what we've built the world for.
Precisely.
M- m- Elon, there's another- Yeah.
There's another part of, um, the robot.
So there's the LLMs, there's the actuation in the hands
but also there's the, um, the silicon that runs it and there was.
..
You know, Dojo, I think you, you posted on X AI5 and AI6 and it just seemed like you were incredibly excited about the direction in which the silicon layer was also going.
Can you tell us about that and what that is and what
what, what, what are we ac- what are we building here?
What is being built?
Is it a compliment to everything that exists in the world?
Is it a potential long-term competitor?
What is it?
Um, yeah.
So, at T- at Tesla we basically had two different chip programs
one for Dojo and one, uh.
..
D- Dojo on the training side, and then what we call
you know, AI4, which is our inference chip.
Um, uh, the, the AI4 is what's currently shipping in all vehicles
um, and we're finalize- finalizing the design of AI5
which will be an immense jump from AI4.
Um, by some metrics, the improvement in AI5 will be 40 times better than AI4.
Wow.
So 40%, 40 times.
Um, and, and, uh, this is because we work so closely at a very fine grain level on the AI software and the AI hardware.
So we know exactly where the limiting factors are and
and, um, and so effectively the AI hardware and software teams are co-designing the chip.
Um.
..
So a 40x improvement in the silicon, I think then as it.
As everybody here in the audience experiences it
is that just an almost like an order of magnitude increase in the quality of FSD and the safety that you experience as a Tesla driver
and then the quality of the robot?
Like where does it all manifest when you
when you, you know, bring it up and actually get it into production?
Yeah, to be precise, the 40x is on.
..
If you said like compared to the worst limitation on AI4
which is running the Softmax operation- Yeah.
.
..
uh, we currently have to run Softmax in around 40 steps in emulation mode.
Whereas that'll be, just be done in a few steps
uh, natively in AI5.
Um, AI5 should also be, uh.
..
Easily handle mixed precision, um, models.
So you don't hav- i- i- it'll dynamically handle mixed preci- There's a bunch of sort of technical stuff that AI5 will do a lot better.
Um, in terms of, uh, of nominal sort of r- uh
raw compute, it's, it's eight times more compute.
Um, about nine times more memory, uh
roughly five times more memory bandwidth.
Um, so, uh, but because we're addressing some core limitations in AI4
you multiply that by.
..
That, that, that 8x compute improvement by another 5x improvement because of
of, uh, optimization at a, at a
at a very fine grain silicon level of things that are currently suboptimal in AI4
that's where you get the 40x improvement.
You had, um- Um- Oh, keep going.
Keep going.
Uh, so now, now that said, I th- I'm
I, I am confident that the current chi- uh
chips, uh, AI, AI4 chips that are in the cars will
uh, achieve self-driving safety that is at least two to three times that of the c- of human and
and maybe even 10x.
Wow.
Um, and the software that, uh, will be released for that is
is coming out over the next, uh
few months.
Mm-hmm.
So version 14 will be the biggest, uh
upgrade in Tesla software since version 12.
Um, we are increasing the, uh, parameter count by an order of magnitude.
Um, the, th- th- th- th- there's
there's, there's a lot of, uh, reinforcement learning that's been used.
There's, um.
..
We, we, we.
There, there were, there was a.
..
Like you can think of AI sort of
eh, as a way of compressing reality and
and l- and some of those compression steps
uh, we, uh, were, were too lossy and
and we addressed the lossiness in the compression steps.
Um, so the- these are all software updates that'll
that'll go out.
So just over-the-air updates.
Um, your car is going to feel like it is sentient by the end of the year.
Yeah.
It feels that way already, to be honest.
Um, I saw in the trades that you spent about $17 billion on some spectrum and that- Oh
yeah.
Yeah.
Um, so some cash change, um, to enable your satellites and the Starlink network to connect directly with phones.
What will that look like in a year or two?
Are we going to drop our Verizon account and just expand our Starlink account?
Uh.
..
We're kind of hoping 'cause-  .
Verizon kind of sucks.
Um, how many, how many of you want a Starlink phone?
Who wants a Starlink phone?
Oh.
Is it, is it technically possible?
Uh, Elon, I know you can't.
..
I know you can't see it, but it's everyone.
Yeah, exactly.
All right, cool.
Um, so this is a kind of a long term thing.
Uh, it, it, it will allow SpaceX to ha- uh
deliver high bandwidth connectivity directly from the satellites to the phones.
Um, but, uh, there are hardware changes that need to happen in the phone so the.
..
And since these frequencies are not supported in current phones
uh, they, the chipset has to be modified to in- in- add these frequencies.
..
. um, and that probably is a two-year timeframe
so the phones that, um, are able to use the spectrum that was acquired probably start shipping in around two years.
Um, and, um, a- and then we also need to build the satellites that are gonna communicate on those frequencies.
So in parallel, we're building the satellites and working with the handset makers to add these frequencies to the phones.
Um, and then the, the satellites and the phones will then handshake very well to achieve high bandwidth connectivity.
But the, the net effect is that you should be able to watch
uh, videos, uh, anywhere on your phone.
Wow.
And it's gonna- Phone is good.
.
be crazy.
And what .
..
A- and do these, do these frequencies
would they work indoors, inside buildings?
You know, like, like- Yes.
.
your phone currently does?
Okay.
Oh.
And so will you be able to have basically like- No
no, if you, if you, if you're in a building with a
with a, like, a, a thick metal roof
then no, but-  Um- No, the sa- the same types of
of, um- Yeah, yeah.
Normal- Yeah.
.
..
normal homes, yes, yeah.
Yeah.
Elon, is your vision- Um- .
..
for this that instead of, you know
having an AT&T account or .
..
and then roaming when you're in the UK or you're in India
it's just, we could have one direct deal with Starlink
it works all over the world eventually, not today
but at some point?
Is that the end goal, that basically we don't need a- Yeah.
.
..
regional carrier, we have a global carrier
and that would be you?
Uh, that, that would be one of the options.
To be clear, we're not, we're not gonna put the other carriers out of business.
They're still gonna be around 'cause they, they own a lot of spectrum.
So, uh, there's, uh .
..
but, but yes, you'll, you should be able to have a Starlink
uh, like you have, like you have an AT&T or T-Mobile
Verizon or whatever.
You should be a- you, you could have a
a, a, you know, account with Starlink that
uh, works with your, you know, Starlink
uh, antenna at home wi- uh, with your wifi as well as on your phone.
And, um, yeah, it would be a comprehensive solution for high bandwidth at home and for high bandwidth direct to cell.
Could you buy some carriers- Um- .
..
to have more spectrum?
Maybe even- Um- .
..
buy Verizon?
Not out of the question.
I suppose it, it, it .
..
that may happen.
Let's talk about, um .
..
Let's talk about Starship.
You just had a really what appeared to be a phenomenal
um, launch.
Ho- how close is it to, you know
being predictable and ready to go in a commercial setting?
I, I th- I think we will recover the ship next year.
Um, we've got one more launch of the
um, Starlink version two, uh, s- uh
stack, but there's only one, one, uh
booster and ship left that's in the version two
uh, design.
Uh, and then thereafter it's, it's version three
which is a gigantic upgrade 'cause that's got Raptor 3
um, and pretty much everything changes on the rocket with version three.
Um, so version three, you know, might have some initial teething pains
uh, 'cause it's such a radical redesign.
Uh, but, uh, it's, it's capable of over 100 tons to orbit
fully reusable.
Um, and I think it's, I think
I think, um, unless we have s- unless we have some very s- major setbacks
uh, SpaceX will demonstrate a full reusability next year
uh, catching both the booster and the ship
um, and being able to deliver over 100 tons to a useful orbit.
Um- How- What is the best rocket in the world do now in terms of tonnage to space?
Uh, well, in terms of, uh
sort of commercial rockets, there's, there's Falcon Heavy- Yeah.
.
uh, which will do, uh, in
um .
..
wi- with, with side booster reuse, uh
will do about 40 tons.
Hmm.
So this is five times- Um- .
..
bigger, yeah.
Well, two and a half times bigger in- Interesting.
But, but Starship will be full reuse
full reusability.
Got it.
Okay.
Hey, uh- So everything comes back.
Yeah.
Elon, after, after the explosion that happened
um, with the, the, the, the failed launch
um, there was a lot of- Which one?
Sorry?
Which, which failed launch?
Oh, oh, the more recent one.
The more recent- Okay.
.
one with the Starship he- with the he- The big boom.
Yeah.
And so with- The big boom on the base.
.
..
with the Starship, and, and, and- Oh
yeah, yeah.
.
there was a lot of, there was a lot of proclamations that there's gonna be environmental and FAA and all these other sorts.
Oh, yeah.
The recovery back to the launch pad again was incredibly fast.
How did you get back so fast, not just technically and work-wise
but just, like, regulatory clearance wise?
Because they said there were gonna be all these questions and reviews and so on.
How did, how did you guys manage that?
Uh, well, there were a lot of questions and reviews.
We got through them all.
Um, and credit to the SpaceX team.
They worked incredibly hard, and they, uh
got the next ship and booster tested and on the pad and
and flown.
And, um, yeah, hu- huge credit to the SpaceX team.
Wow.
Very proud of them for doing, doing such a job
a, a great job recovering.
Um, I, I mean, it's just creating a fully reusable orbital rocket is one of the hardest engineering problems ever.
Certainly, uh, you know, a candidate for most difficult engineering  project ever.
Uh, uh, you know, it's on the podium at least.
Um, so it's a .
..
tha- that, that's been the goal of SpaceX from the beginning
from 2002.
Um, and here we are 23 years later.
So it's, it's a long journey.
A- and, um, with, with a
a super tal- like, by far the
I think the most talented group of rocket engineers that's ever been assembled.
Um, and, uh, you know, finally next year
I think we'll be able to achieve full reusability.
Elon, what are the big, um, technical blockers that you're focused on there between now and that full reusability?
Are there some showstoppers where you're just kind of literally just obsessing over trying to figure out still?
Or is it more about getting through a sort of a laundry list of your learnings and just integrating it into the next launch?
Well, the- the.
..
For- for- for reusability of the ship, there's still a lot of work that remains on the heat shield.
So no one's ever made a fully reusable orbital heat shield.
Like, the shuttle heat shield, uh, had to go through nine months of repair after every flight.
Right.
Um, so n- no one has ever made a fully reusable orbital heat shield.
Um- And is that a material science problem
or is that an engineering problem, or both?
Uh, yeah, I mean, it's a ma- material science eng- engineering problem.
So it's.
..
But we really are, uh, looking at the fundamental physics here.
Um, again, physics-first principles and trying to figure out how do we make something that
um, is, uh, it, you know.
..
it can withstand the heat, it's very light
doesn't transmit the heat to the- the primary sh- Yeah.
.
..
primary structure.
Um, and, uh, a- a- where- But then whose integrity is intact?
.
..
all the tiles stay on and they don't crack.
Yeah.
Um, uh, and then as you ascend
if you hit some rain, you know
the tiles don't dissolve in rain.
There's- there's a lot of different issues.
And- and then you really need to know that these tiles are working.
You- you can't, uh, you know, go through this laborious in- inspection.
So it really needs to be where, you know
these- these tens of thousands of tiles all work and don't need to be refurbished or checked one by one.
That was the case with the shuttle.
Can we maybe, um, switch now?
It's in- I mean, who- who else were you talk- about Tesla then you go to SpaceX.
Yeah.
Now, I'd- I'd like to ask you some questions about Grok and
um, xAI.
Um, you want to just give us an update?
I think you- you kind of talked about where the next gen model is
and you said something incredible, I still don't think people really understand it which is
you know, there's gonna be a next training run where you expect
you know, not to start from the
you know, common web and common crawl
where you expected an enormous amount of synthetic data.
Just tell us about how, uh, the evolution of Grok is going and this innovation and why it's so important.
Yeah.
So we're- we're running a lot of.
..
using a lot of an- of inference compute and
um, and reasoning to look at all of the source data which is really like the corpus of human knowledge.
And then, uh, thinking about each piece of information and then adding mod- a- a- adding what's missing
um, and correcting- correcting mistakes and removing falsehoods from this- from that training data.
So it's- it's- it's.
..
Like if you take, say, Wikipedia as an example
but this really applies to- to books, PDFs
uh, the websites, uh, every form of information.
Um, the.
..
Grok is using, um, heavy amounts of inference compute to
say, to look at, as an example
a Wikipedia page and say, uh, "What is true
partially true or false, or missing, uh
in this page?
Now rewrite the page to inc- to correct the.
..
remove the falsehoods, uh- uh, correct the half-truths and add the missing context.
" Well, Elon, by the way, could you just publish that?
Could we create like a Grokopedia?
I mean that would be- Yeah, especially for our bio pages which are a disaster.
.
..
very valuable.
Because Wikipedia.
..
Yeah.
Wikipedia is so biased and it's- it's a constant war.
You know, if something gets corrected, five minutes later there'll be an army of people trying to.
..
I mean it's become hyper partisan and there's activists all over it.
Hyper political.
True.
So if you do fix, for example
Wikipedia as a source of truth, it'd be great to publish that just so the world has it.
All right.
I'll talk- talk with you about that.
So talk to the team about that like a Grokipedia or whatever.
This- here's the Grokipedia version.
Um-  It'd be interesting, yeah.
And then just have it out there for.
..
Where.
In- in terms of, um.
..
People here like it.
Um, in terms of training Grok-5, um
you're- you're scaling up your supercluster in Colossus in- in Memphis.
Can- Whoo!
Colossus 2 now, yeah.
But they're- they have a second one.
Yeah.
Could you- could you give us an update on that?
And then also, as part of that
um, whe- where are we in the scaling laws?
Um, if you scale a bigger cluster
do you get a more powerful AI model?
Is there a point of diminishing returns or.
..
Like how much more compu- if you throw twice as much compute at it
do you get a 10% better model?
Do you get a 100% better model?
Like is it log linear?
What- what.
..
I guess how much more juice is there left in scaling hardware do you think?
I think- I think there's a natural logarithmic function associated with the amount of compute.
So, uh, then like say for argument's sake like 10X more compute will double the intelligence.
Maybe that's- that might be a rough rule of thumb.
Uh, but, you know, that still means that
you know, you go from 100 IQ to 200 IQ.
Still a pretty- pretty big deal.
Um, so I.
..
And- and I think- I think we'll see intelligence continue to scale all the way up to where-.
you know, most of the power of the sun is harnessed for compute
and then ultimately, most of the power of the galaxy.
You know, sort of, Kadachev-IIP, Kadachev-III scale
uh, compute.
Um, so I guess, once you think about artificial intelligence not as sort of this
you know, a destination that you reach
but really, uh, as part of the overall escalation of intelligence
um, that, that, that we are aware of.
Um, you know, human intelligence has also scaled as you've ha- have
uh, as the population has increased, um
and we've been able to store more and more information
uh, human intelligence has scaled.
Now, human.
..
Because of population declines and low birthrate, human intelligence is
is somewhat plateauing, um, and will actually decline.
And, uh, m- my guess is that
eh, eh, I, I, I think that we might have AI smarter than any single human at anything as soon as next year.
Wow.
Okay.
Yeah.
Um, and, and, and then, and then probably within five
like say 2030, probably AI is smarter than the sum of all humans.
Do you think, do you think humans are on the decline because the AI is evolving?
Do you think there's this evolution of the ecosystem on Earth that's underway  that we don't really understand the structure of what's going on
but.
..
May- yeah, maybe we implicitly know that it's coming.
Um.
..
Yeah.
I, I, I mean, I hope the birthrates turn around.
I'm a, I'm a big proponent of
uh, increased birthrate, uh, obviously.
Well, are you doing anything about it or no?
Yeah, I'm trying to set a good example.
You know, we had a big conversation at this conference we didn't expect
which is suicidal empathy, the West, this
um, declining birthrate.
Yeah.
Uh, I noticed you've been pretty active about it.
And, and open borders.
And open borders.
Which is like Let the Invaders In.
Yeah, Tucker talked about it.
Could, could all three of those be the same thing?
It seems like there's a number of symptoms of the West being suicidal.
The most obvious one being the birthrate is not at replacement level
so obviously, if that continues indefinitely, then the West will literally not reproduce enough to replace itself.
Yeah.
But there's other things too.
There's the fact that the borders were totally opened to the point where Western culture
w- the social fabric started to come apart.
And, uh, you see this especially in Europe where their
um, you know, the indigenous cultures of the UK or France or Germany are starting to
um, potentially be taken over by, by cultures of people who were brought in and aren't assimilating.
You have crime where, you know, we have this case on social media right now
this young woman, Irina, who was just- Yeah
yeah.
.
..
killed in a senseless way on a subway
uh, which is horrific enough in and of itself
but then in addition to that, the elite media just
for whatever reason, just refused to cover it
like it didn't exist.
Yeah.
Um, so you have this issue of crime that's not being addressed or even- And no truth.
.
acknowledged.
And no acknowledgement of this.
Like, it's- Right.
.
almost like we're trying to deny the reality of the spiral and this
yeah.
The death spiral.
So you have, so you have the
you have all these data points, um
that seem to suggest that, um, the West
uh, is suicidal or doesn't, you know
doesn't seem to want to defend itself or propagate itself.
Um, look, I think everyone in this room thinks that
um, life is awesome, right?
I mean- It's pretty great.
And I think we're- It's worth living.
Yeah.
And when Al- when Alex Karp was here earlier today defending the West
that got some of the loudest applause of the conference.
So, uh, I guess we probably don't really understand what's going on.
We don't really, you know- Yeah, what's your take
Elon?
'Cause y- you know- What's your take on the suicide of the West?
Yeah.
What's, what's going on?
I'm very worried about it.
Yeah.
Um, you know, I think there's a
there's.
..
Let's just say that the actions of the West are indistinguishable from suicide.
So,  what, it's.
..
At, at, look, at least i- in America
there's y- there's, there's generally a sense of optimism
but when's the last time you m- you talked to someone from Europe
who lives in Europe, who's optimistic?
Not for a while.
Yeah.
Decades.
Like, even one?
It's rare.
And, uh, so I, I think uh
unless people have a sense of optimism and purpose about the future
they.
..
S- Suicide might be just what happens.
Um, like, like, like having a child is an act of optimism about the future.
So, uh, if you're not optimistic, there's hope-  Yeah.
S- so, so, I think we need to maybe give people a sense of optimism and excitement about the future
and a, and a belief that the future will be better than the past.
Um, and they'll be more interested in having kids.
Um- Did reli- did religion play a role in the past
Elon, to- Yeah.
.
..
kind of placate and make folks feel that way when they won?
Yeah, I think so.
Uh, uh, uh, d- nature abhors a vacuum.
And if you take away religion, then I think you're actually.
..
You, you, you get something in its place which is actually worse than what was there before.
I mean, it's, uh, like destructive basically.
You get, you get like the white wok mind virus
filling th- filling the hole that religion used to ha- like
like pla- taking the place of, of
of religion.
You, you get these this dystopian de facto religions
um, that, uh, that are, that are very s- very self destructive.
Um, so-.
..
I, I think perhaps some- some sort of re- revival of religion
or at least w- what we need is- is
um, some coherent philosophy that people can get excited about.
Um, you know, I mean, for me it's a philosophy of curiosity.
I'm curious about the nature of the universe and I wanna go out there and I- I want humanity to be out there exploring the stars
um, maybe meeting alien civilizations.
Uh, maybe in some cases we- we see the ruins of a long-dead alien civilization
but they were- they were very strong for 10 million years.
Um, you know, the kind of stuff that you see in Star Trek
in a- in a non-dystopian, sci-fi book or- or movie or show.
Um, and so I- I'm just, I have a- I have a philosophy of curiosity of- of like
I just want to know what's going on.
And- and- and in order to know what's going on
we- we must have, uh, an- an increase in the s- in the scope and scale of consciousness.
We must- we must expand as a- a consciousness.
We must grow, we must grow humanity
and we must extend humanity in order to comprehend the- and un- to- to understand the universe or even what- what questions should we should ask about the answer that is the universe.
Um, you know, Dou- Douglas Adams' book
The Hi- Hitchhiker's Guide To The Galaxy is actually a bo- a- a deep book on philosophy disguised as humor.
Um, and what.
..
The point he was trying to make in that book was that
um, the questions are the really- the- the hard part.
The- the answer is the universe, like
the answer is everything you see around you.
But- but- but one of the questions that we don't know to ask.
Yeah.
Um, now- now some of the questions
I guess, I- we- we- I do know
I'd like to know is the standard model of physics correct about the origins of the universe?
Are we actually 13.
8 billion years old?
Um, how does the universe end?
Does it end in heat, death or in some other way?
Um, you know- Or in a black hole.
We might be.
All right.
Um .
..
Elon, can you talk about, uh- Because the wh- the whole sort of simulation question
are we a simulation?
Maybe.
I don't know.
Where does the, uh .
..
Where do you think we find the answer first?
In AI or in the stars?
'Cause you're pursuing both, obviously.
Yeah.
I- I don't- I don't know if- if .
..
I- I ho- I hope more people can get behind a philosophy of curiosity.
Yeah.
Because I think it's very exciting.
Um, and- and- and- and inherently optimistic.
Um, you- the.
..
L- like you.
Because there's- there's this amaz- amazing sense of wonder about the nature of the universe.
Yeah.
And when you just, when you uncover some secret to the universe
that's amazing, y- and you're like, a whole world of understanding has opened up.
I mean, w- w- we used to not even know where all the continents were
um, you know, it used to be like
just the map would be, "There be dragons.
"  And like, all we know is that when they sailed in that direction
they didn't come back.
I mean, the moon base.
..
That's- that's all- that's all they knew.
Um.
..
I kind of feel like the moon base or just going to the moon for real this time would be a big step in the right direction.
Y- you still have the moon, uh
planned?
What's the status of that?
Is- is that still on the agenda?
Yeah, I- I think it- I think having.
..
I- I think we want to try to reach new heights as a civilization.
Yeah.
So, I- I think that it's fine to go to the moon but- but we should go to the moon in order to establish a lunar base like a re- a lunar research base.
Um, I mean, there are parts of the moon that are p- perhaps older than parts of- of Earth
um, and we- we- we might understand more about the nature of the universe if we had a science base on the moon.
Yeah.
Um, that would be very cool.
And then we- we obviously want to go beyond
uh, the moon, uh, to Mars and
uh, build a self-sustaining city on Mars.
The.
..
I- I- I do think that, uh
that- that there is a fork in the road of human destiny where
um, if we can establish a self-sustaining city on Mars
uh, the.
..
With the- the key test being if the resupply ships from Earth stop coming for any reason
does Mars continue to- to prosper or does it die out?
Mm.
At the point at which Mars is able to
uh, prosper and grow on its own
the probable lifespan of consciousness is dramatically greater
because we are no longer dependent on everything going right on Earth.
You know, there's- there's always some possibility of self-annihilation on Earth with World War III
some.
..
Or- or a super virus or, um
or- or a meteor, like, extinct- you know
that destroyed the dinosaurs.
We know from the fossil record that there have been many mass ex- mass extinction events.
So, uh, the question, uh, that I sort of am- was wondering about is
will civilization can.
..
Will- will the civilizational arc continue to ascend such that we can make Mars self-sustaining before the civil- civilizational arc descends?
Mm.
Um, because the- the- the window of opportunity to make life multi-planetary exists now for the first time in the four and a half billion year history of Earth.
Yeah.
Elon, let's assume that we get there
and you're there.
Um, you know, you'd be the elder statesman
you'd have the moral authority of Mars.
How do you run Mars?
But I just.
..
Uh, there's- there's a point that I- I think I- I wanna just emphasize again that- that's more important than what the form of governance on Mars or who's there in the early days.
What really matters is that Mars, um
is- is self-sustaining.
That we are truly a multi-planet species and such- such that we would achieve planetary redundancy.
..
. so that, that if, if something ch- .
And I, and I obviously we sh- we should do everything possible to make sure life on Earth is great
but there's always some risk that, of an annihilation event on Earth.
Yeah.
Um, like I said, self-annihilation or some natural disaster.
Um, and, uh, and so the
the probable lifespan of consciousness increases dramatically as soon as
uh, as soon as we are a multi-planet species
with the key test being can Mars survive if the resupply ships stop coming?
So it's not, it's, so getting, like
the first missions to Mars are not that important.
The, what matters is can you get sufficient tonnage
tonnage to Mars such that Mars can, uh
prosper on its own?
Um, and that means it has to have all of the ingredients of civilization.
It, it, it's not just that you need to build
for example, a chip factory on Mars or a ship fab on Mars
but you, you need the ability- Ability to- .
..
to build ship fabs.
Do you, do you have a sense of the time scale?
Like, let's assume Starship is at a state starting in
you know, 2026, then there's going to be a bunch of testing obviously
there's going to be a bunch of early testing.
We only have certain launch windows, so there's a bunch of time constraints.
Is that a, is this a 50-year thing in your mind?
Is it a 150-year thing?
Is it something that is for our generation or is it our children's generation?
Where do you see that point if it's optimally possible
you know, if things go and break our way?
Um, I think it can be done in
in 30 years.
Wow.
Um, so if- if, provided there's an exponential increase in the
in the tonnage to Mars with each successive Mars transfer window
which is every two years.
So every two years the, the planets align and you can tr- you can transfer to Mars.
Um, so, uh, I think in roughly 15
but maybe as few as 10, but as so- 10 to 15-ish
uh, Mars transfer windows if you're, um
seeing exponential increases in the tonnage to Mars with each Mars transfer window
then it should be possible to make Mars self-sustaining
um, in, in about roughly 25 years.
Amazing.
That's incredible.
All right, ladies and gentlemen,  Elon Musk.
We'll see you when we're back in town.
We miss you.
All right.
We'll see you in person next time.
Later, guys.
Thank you, brother.
Thank you, Elon.
All right.
Thanks, guys.