i'm i'm sick of multi-millionaires
telling
kids who can't afford to turn the heating on you just need to be more entrepreneurial
it's sick
dan it's sick
well your video
where you talk about
if you don't have a rich dad you're screwed
well to me if i had have come across your content
at 19
20 years old i would have been screwed
my friends
can't feed their kids
okay if it was that easy
why is everybody
not doing it i'll tell you why people aren't doing it
it's
because
you like to say one thing back on
that
today's debate
is fiery to say the least but important nonetheless
as i sat down with two leading experts in wealth and entrepreneurship
and the economy
to discuss the state of the us the state of the uk and the western world
do you think the reason
the average brit american are getting poorer
is because they don't know how to create wealth no the reason people are getting poorer
is because of big governments
record levels of taxes
an outdated schooling system
technology
and remote working
you sure about that
how do you disagree with those opinions
living standards are falling
because of growing wealth in equality
if you allow the rich to get richer
they squeeze
the middle class and the poor class out of things like housing
let's cut tax on people who are working
hard
and let's raise tax on the richest
and most powerful
people in the world that's an overly
simplified
view of things we now have a th000
millionaires
a month leaving
which means every ordinary
person
who pays
10 grand
a year in tax
will now have to pay
grand
a year in tax
you end up cutting off your nose to spite your face
if we are a country
that don't try and do things which are necessary
because they are hard
then our kids
will live in poverty
what do you want people to do there's a lot of different ways
backle
up
this has always blown my mind a little bit 53%
of you that listen to the show regularly
haven't yet subscribed
to the show
so could i ask you for a favor
before we start
if you like the show
and you like what we do here and you want to support
us
the free
simple way that you can do just that is by hitting the subscribe
button
and my commitment
to you is if you do that
then i'll do everything in my power
me and my team to make sure that this show is better for you every
single week we'll listen to your feedback
we'll find the guest that you want me to speak to
and we'll continue to do what we do thank you so much
gary
daniel
daniel you've been on the show a few times before so i want to start with
gary and understand a little bit about your backstory and who you are and
having
been through the trading
game and read
and watched many many of your videos over time i have a
a sort of deep
understanding of that but for anyone that doesn't know you
can you give me a picture of the context
that
um has brought you to where you are today
writing
about the things you're writing about today and running the youtube channel
and speaking to the subject matter that you're speaking about today
take me right back and give me as much as you possibly
can
okay so
my name is gary stevenson
i was born in a place called ilford which is in outer east london
quite a poor family little terrace house by the railway
you know playing football in the streets kind of stuff
um
always very good at maths since i was a kid very talented master student
eventually able to get into the london school of economics
which is an extremely elite university economics university
in the center of london which is
basically a kind of investment banking boot camp got a job as a trader
started working full-time as a short-term interest rates trader at city bank in london
in june
when i was 21 obviously
yeah exactly that's just before the big credit crash the big leman crisis
and i watched the leman crisis happen in front of my eyes i was um
short-term interest rate trading is basically like short-term loans
and during the credit crisis what credit crisis is is nobody can borrow any money
so like short-term loans become really really important important
my desk which was like historically an unfashionable
area of trading
became like the center of the crisis or one of the centers of the crisis
people started making tons of money
um i was working with all these crazy
people
and you can imagine
me like i turn up
21 years old and then like within three months
like everyone around me is making a ton of money during the credit crisis
but what really interested
me
was what happened after the crisis itself
which was
so we're betting on interest rates
long story short interest rates
come down when the economy is weak
and they go up when the economy is strong
or when the economy is overheating
from an inflation
perspective
in 2018
all the interest rates go to zero
so suddenly
our job is basically predicting and betting on
when will
those interest rates go back up which is when will the economy recover
and this is super interesting right in
because all the interest rates went to zero so quickly
like before
it's important to remember
rates would move
from like five and a half to five and a quarter
and then here in 2008
everywhere in the world slashing to zero bo half a percent exactly and everybody
all the economists were like wow this is going to cause a massive recovery
because they thought
that interest rates were powerful
and everybody predicted
that rates would come back up in 2009
which of course we knowed they didn't
then everybody predicted that rates would go up in 2010
which we now know they didn't and then at the beginning of 2011
everybody was predicting rates would definitely go up this year and this to me
was so interesting
so interesting because you know i studied master and economics at one of the
best economics universities
in the world and now i'm working with these
traders
who are getting paid millions of pounds a year million pounds a year to predict
the economy to predict the interest rates
and everybody
is wrong
year after year after year and this
was
i was
so amazing
to me for a couple of reasons
first of all it's like wow
like
this is a big
thing that we as a society should understand and like we're getting it wrong
but secondly
if all of the best guys in the world are getting this wrong
then if i can figure this out
i can make a ton of money here
g how much money did you make for city bank at the age of 24 years
old
that year so that year 2011
i put this big bet on that it would get worse forever
and i was city bank's
most profitable trader in the world that year
and i made them just over $ 35
million
you made them $35 million you eventually decide to leave city bank yeah why
i mean i think that's an interesting question right you know
in the sense that i've just explained to you what happened which is
i made a ton of money by betting on the collapse of
western
society
i did it in 2011 i did it again in 2012
um
i would prefer
for it not to collapse step
and i'm trying to stop it from
collapsing
when you say it collapsing what exactly you're referring to that you you don't want to
collapse
so you you born in botswana right yeah do you still have family there
um i've got family in nigeria
which is where my my family are from i was born in botswana
because we were visiting there but
got family in africa do you go to nigeria much no
i i've got home in cape town in south africa so i see the
it's a great place if you want to see
inequality
i think there
is
a naivity
in in in this country in places like the us that the kind of inequality
the kind of broad poverty
that you see in places like south africa in places like nigeria
in places like india
can't happen
here
it will happen here
that is the future
of this country
that is the future of the us and i'm not just saying
that
i'm betting on it and i've been betting on it for 15
years
and i've been right for 15
that is what i'm trying to avoid
daniel where did you come from yeah so i grew up in australia
um and i was born to low-income
family i grew up in a place that had 24%
unemployment
pretty much the only jobs or opportunities around me were things like
the trades building construction
pest control
um hospitality and tourism
um so
at 14 i got a job at mcdonald's
and then i'm
got a job in a bar and pizza hut delivery driving and i discover entrepreneurship
so i discover books about entrepreneurship
and i discovered that some people make millions similar to yourself
you saw canary wf i read a book about business ownership
and as we sit here today can you give me
the overview of your business success since then
yeah so i now have a group of companies that i've either started or bought
um there's i've just sold a company so there's seven companies in the group
um
i've started a couple of software
companies
one of our companies
is now the fastest
growing
one of the fastest growing companies in the uk
um we you know we're a software business
i've got a couple of agencies i've got a education and training business
and where when you think about the uk and broadly the western world today
what is your assessment of where we're at as a country and what's concerning you because
gary expressed quite articulately
that his big concern is that because of wealth ine equality
we're going to end up in a similar position to the likes of india
what are you concerned about i agree that it wasn't that long ago that we had
real serious wealth inequality in this country there are amazing photos from
like a 100 years ago of kids working in mines
and kids
doing oyster shocking
and all this horrible
work and
um you know
there's a there's a book charles dickens wrot wrote called the tale of two cities
and the opening
line of the book
is it was the best of times it was the worst of times
and i think we've actually gotten to that point here where some people in the uk
it's the best of times
if you
like in your situation you're you know you're booming you're a globally successful business
um i've got a globally successful business and then there are a lot of people who
completely
cannot relate to this their you know
energy
prices are now the most expensive in the western world
house prices are completely unaffordable
it used to be
used to take 3 years to
for a deposit it's now 20 years if you you know theoretically
20 years if you can save for a deposit
food prices are through the roof
so we're we're in a really diff like for anyone who
is not tapped into digital economy fast growth and all of that sort of stuff
life is getting harder and worse
um and things are collapsing
um if you if you would
um go with that
the
there is a predictable
path countries
go on
and there's this thing called the economic freedom index
and the economic freedom index basically
says how economically
free are you how how much access do you have to free markets
um do can you start a business can you scale a business
um does anything inhibit your ability to run your own life
countries that have high degrees of economic freedom have very low poverty they have widespread affluence
and countries that have low economic freedoms
have high poverty and it can be the difference between less than 10%
right up to 70%
poverty rates
um and when countries go on a path towards economic freedom
poverty
just drops
so india for examp example has been on that path and they announced
today that they've almost
eradicated
abject poverty or extreme poverty
um the uk went on that path of
low economic freedom to high economic freedom and we saw
poverty rates come right down
but in 2008 when the global financial crisis happened
one of the things that happened is the government said we need to step in
and we need to take charge and everyone said please do
um so
they
came in and they said all right we're going to ramp
up debt
ramp
up taxes
to pay for the debt and we're also going to put it all regul
in and unfortunately
that starts to reduce economic freedom
then the pandemic happens
and they say oh we're going to spend
more money again through debt we're going to have more
taxes more regulations
less economic freedom so the uk
we went from an 82
when i arrived in 2006
went from 82 out of 100
down to 68 out of 100 so we're less economically
free
and predictably
what we will always see happen if you lower people's economic freedom
more poverty
less affluence the millionaires and the wealth creators leave the people who are stuck in
um dead end jobs
or no jobs get incredibly frustrated
everyone starts looking for someone to blame people are angry
and they're like who do we blame
and who do they blame
it's very different because in the us we blame us blam someone different to the uk
so
we have a historical
cultural memory
in the uk we have a cultural memory
that the people to blame are the rich
so so
we have landlords
and aristocracy
and the landed gentry
those guys are to blame
right so blame the rich is what we say in the uk
in the us
they have a very different view their cultural memory is that they're anti-government
they want limited government
in 2023
there was this song that came out called rich men north of richmond
and it was the number one song in america
and the lyrics of the song basically says
people in washington do not care about working people
um they att taxing everything we touch you can't earn money they depreciate the dollar
um they tax tax tax tax tax
and they want to control
our lives those are the lyrics of the songs
controlling
our lives and taxing us
so the american
reaction to this is who's to blame government
so we want smaller government we want a department of government efficiency
to come in we want
someone as a wrecking ball who will come in and smash government
the british instinct
is
hate the rich
it must be the rich's fault so when we look for
like all all of the western countries that implemented lower economic
freedoms
created more poverty less affluence and more disruption to their economies
so both us and uk for example and australia as well but both
sides of the pond
want someone to blame it's just that the americans blame government and we blame the rich
gary i'm sure you you have a lot to
to say there i know you both use the word collapsing
so you agree
that there's a problem
here
but i think
you from studying
both of your sort of
perspectives
you think that
this the solution and the cause of the problem is different
i mean i put bets on i put bets on
i put bet that's what i do i put bets on
um
at the beginning of covid
we knew the government was going to give enormous amount of money out
um
total amount of money now uk government deficit since the beginning of co is is1 trillion
pounds
us number is $4
trillion that's you know £20,000 per uk adult
my background is i understand that when
the distribution gets worse when inequality gets worse living standards full
so when
when the uk government
was going to give a trillion
pounds out
all i wanted to know was
who's going to end up with that money
that's all i wanted to know
and um i mean the us number 13 trillion 14
trillion
is just outlandish but i think the most amazing thing i've ever seen in my whole
life
was that at the beginning of co the very beginning of co we knew
governments across the world we're going to be giving out tens of trillions of pounds dollars
euros
nobody even thought to ask
who's going to get tens of trillions richer nobody in the conservatives
nobody in labor nobody in the republicans
nobody in democrats nobody in the media nobody in academia
nobody the central banks nobody asked this it's
it's
it's it's almost beautiful it's it's unbelievable
it's unbeliev
so i i sat down and i did i did the analysis at the
beginning
because lockdown is essentially banning the spending of the rich
and replacing that spending of the rich with printed money from government
what happens is the government
gives workers money
they use that money to pay their bills to pay their rent pay their mortgage
it goes to the rich the rich can't spend it because they're locked indoors
and what you get is essentially
an enormous amount of money from the government
to the poor to the rich
and this
massive
massive transfer
of wealth
um
that was obviously going that was so obviously going to happen at the beginning of co
nobody discussed it which i think is itself
amazing
let me ask you a question right if we were now
to pause the economy for 2 years
and during that pause
massively increase wealth inequality
what do you think would happen to broad living conditions when we
unpaused
see one of the things that i think happened during the pandemic
is everything went digital
and
um entrepreneurs and investors did actually think about what would happen the investors immediately
boomed stocks like zoom and microsoft
and we ended up with the magnificent 7
um i don't know if you you know there's seven big tech companies in the usa
market
and those big seven companies have gone from five trillion valuation to 17 tr trillion valuation
in the time of the pandemic and if you think about what did the pandemic do
everyone had to work from home so we all had to have microsoft subscriptions
everyone went onto website so we all went to aws
amazon we all started buying
and learning how to buy from amazon rather than buying from from our local high streets
every business in the world figured out how to run their business remotely
we had this massive transformation
it wasn't it was like it's actually a wholesale transformation of society
that we all learned how to live and work differently
um i saw a boom in entrepreneurship so what i saw as an entrepreneur accelerator
um someone who runs an entrepreneur accelerator
is just there was this sudden boom in people launching businesses
setting up shopify accounts setting up youtube
businesses
so the money really has moved from the traditional economy the 2019
high street economy
over to the digital economy
and what we see
is that the investors know what's going on and they just invest in this magnificent
seven company i think
50%
of the gains of the s&p 500
is tech companies
um so all the money just goes flooding into the the technology companies
my my belief is that technolog is really dividing people
that essentially if you take anyone from any background
if they work in technology
if they're in media tech finance any of that stuff that operates online
they tend to actually do pretty
pretty well after the pandemic i ask you a question yeah go for
do you think the average
brit american australian
whoever
the person out there is watching if they quit their job
and go work in tech
do you think they'll be able to get financial security relatively
easily
depends when you defi define financial security the issue with house prices
the ability
to raise a family have a home yeah so having a home is a big issue
right so
here's here's what i here's what i see with houses
cuz houses annoy me as well my dad bought a house for
$188,000
which is about £10,000 or less than £10,000 and it's probably worth over a million dollars
um today so something went wrong and and this by the way is not uk specific
the socialist
countries
had house prices go through the roof
if you go to norway or sweden their house prices grew by
600%
in then it's happening everywhere
it's not specific to anywhere it's happening everywhere but but what happened
what what has definitely
in the uk
is we actually have
um a housing traffic jam
so
in this country in the uk
we have 9.5
million homes that have two or more spare bedrooms
big family homes
have two or more spare bedrooms and when you look into who owns those houses
78%
of housing wealth is baby boomers
um and now anecdotally
i take my kids trick-or-treating at halloween
and we go down a street that is big family homes
and you go knock on the doors and it's all people over 65
right and
living in a big family home with empty spare bedrooms
we you think the average american over 65 is living
luxuriously
the average american over 65
so more than half of the us economy is in the hands of baby boomers
right so they own all the houses
the the houses got bought up cheap
baby boomers
still own those houses to this day the big family homes with multiple spare bedrooms
are empty
um and now that creates this traffic jam
people my age my grandparents
yeah they all owned property
all four of them died with nothing
um because
that wealth which they had in in property was
was used in equity release schemes
they they it was used in paying through their retirement
it was used in end of life care
um do you think when those old people die young people today will be rich
there is half the economy held by baby burus
it's either going to be
passed down or passed into the age care industry or passed into
the but the issue of why we can't get homes two things
government
massively
inflated the value of homes through debt so they just in injected
like low interest rates that you involved in who who is the debt to
well the debt is to anyone who can take out al loan because if a 0%
interest rates or 2%
interest r you think it's the debt is the ordinary
families
do you think ordinary families are the creditors
when you say ordinary families you mean
bottom third so if your average
british or american
family
now has half a million pounds of debt
crit it's anyone who could get their at that particular
time
anyone who could get their hands on a loan
to buy a house
but who has the credit
who has who is on the other side of the debt
so if the average british family
million p banking license does the average british family have half million pound of credit
well a lot of people have got a lot of equity
in their home now you think the average
british
family
is sitting on half a million
pound
cash
i'd love to look at the what the actual
number
is but it's a couple
hundred thousand
worth of equity
what about the credit on the line credit on the line
owns the credit on the line in mind it's disproportionately
older people so
think the average
british
old person is sitting on million
millions
of pounds of cash
not millions
of cash
no
equity
well someone is on the other side of
just one say the difference
the difference is if you inflate
the value of a house
you don't have cash you have a
house that's worth a lot of money
so 78%
of home ownership
wealth is in the hands of people over 65
now it's baby boomer generation
and they got a great gift from the government
which is the government said we're going to just give free loans away
if someone previously could have only afforded to take out a 200 grand loan
with low interest rates they can afford a 300 grand l do you think it's okay
that the average
british
or american
young person
will never
own
any wealth
the issue is not whether it's okay or not
the issue is what do you do about it i do you own wealth
i've got wealth yeah you own wealth
but depends what you call wealth i do so do we three multimillionaires
do
we think it's okay
that the average
brit or american
young person will never own any wealth
that to me that's because i don't think that's okay to me that's not the debate
is it okay it's not well it it's not okay no we want widespread
would you rather that the people who currently are multi-millionaires
would you rather that all of the world was owned by their kids
i think that the way you see the world as a trader
is that the world is a zero sum game
and that there's
basically
the pi is a fixed pi and it gets sliced
up
how fast is the growing now there's something like this
what's uk gdp growth at the moment yeah it's not it's not high right 1%
how much did your wealth grow in the last year
exponentially
okay so if our weals
my wealth probably grew about 20%
in the last year maybe 30 okay okay
if our worlds are growing 30%
and the economy is growing at 1%
where is it coming from if it's not coming from our viewers
so i'll tell you where my wealth comes from
my wealth comes from building technology companies
and the way it works is pretty weird
which is that
i invent something out of my head
and i go to investors
and i say to the investors
here's what we're going to create and i give them a spreadsheet
and then they say we'll give you a couple hundred grand to get started
which is called seed
capital
but on paper makes me worth a couple of million
right but there there's nothing has been taken from anyone at this point
the investors have said okay we'll invest some money then as the business succeeds
some more investors
come along and they say we'll give you a little bit more money to keep growing
it
um and i'm innovating something new
and let's say investors come in and give me a million pounds
and for 10% of the company
and the rest of the company's worth 9 million
or $9 million
right
so i'm not stealing
something from the existing economy i'm bringing something from outside of the economy
into the economy
um and my quote unquote net worth is growing exponentially
because investors
say
we'll give you a little bit of money that values the rest of the pie
at a lot of money
but there's everyone's getting richer
in the in the wealth create
there's where there's wealth extraction
which is what traders do they extract from the existing economy
um and they bet on
the economy and then there's wealth creation which what entrepreneurs
do they come up with new ideas
better ways of doing things
and they build wealth so do you think the reason
our viewers
the average brit american are getting poorer is because they
don't know how to create wealth
no the reason people are getting poorer is because economic freedoms are being eroded
when we have high economic that with taxes
well anything that imp it could be anything that impacts economic freedom so
taxes and regulations are big was economic freedom higher in the 50s
50s was okay so 50s was a
interesting time
we we were in food russians in this country till
1956 so we had 10 years of food rations after the war
um we had a labor shortage
because only really men worked women hadn't entered the workforce in mass
um there had been three or 400,000
men
killed in war
so we actually had this big labor shortage the whole country needed to rebuild
because of the blitz had bombed it so we had this huge need for economic
activity
and not enough people to do it we only had 2%
unemployment
people who had had their blown off were put to work at that particular time
so we had this boom this postwar
boom and we also had the postwar baby boom which drove
consumption
and then when we got to the 60s we had the roaring 60s or the
um the swinging 60s right pretty amazing time in britain and along comes high taxes
and they put up the taxes massively at the end of the 60s
um and it pretty much crashed the economy
one of the things that happened so what were the tax rates in the 50s
well they went up as high as 80 to 90%
for the top for the top ear i think it was in the 60s
you sure about that i think the 50s are unique what is the answer
feel like you they went up off the wall
they went up after the war well in the us actually
tax rates
started
got before the war
but also the size of government as a percentage of gdp was like 30%
it was a tiny like we're we're now 45%
of the uk economy is government spending
we have got a mass who funds that spending
debt they the bank of england allows them to print endless amounts of debt which deflates
gary i want to get your opinion
here
cuz you're asking a lot of questions
but i actually don't know your opinion
i just want to know what daniel thinks
and i want our viewers to be able to research daniel's
opinions
but how how do you disagree with those opinions
listen
daniel's a businessman he's obviously a very successful businessman
you know i i've not been any
i'm not a businessman i'm not going to pretend to be a businessman i'm an economist
i make money by being right on the economy
daniel's a good businessman
and i'm right on the economy
you know it's a simple as that basically
you know i'm not a good businessman
but i've got 15 years of being right on this on the economy
and look and i know
you're probably a wealthy
man
you probably don't want
to pay high taxes
you probably don't want your kids to pay high taxes
but we exist in an economy
where wealth
is being extracted
out of the middle class out of the working class very very rapidly
it's benefiting people like the three of us at this table
it will benefit our kids
you know our kids will be rich their kids will be poor
and i just think we should be honest with them capitalism's finished we won
well done stephen
well done daniel well done gary
it's over now our kids will be rich their kids will be poor
they'll pay the tax taxes we won't pay the taxes
we'll avoid it i'll make money betting on it year after year
why are we lying to them why are we lying to them
yeah i i think that's an overly simplified
view of things i don't
an overly simplified
view of things that has made me a multimillionaire
yeah well look entrepreneurs take bets on the economy as well we take bets differently
um when we start a company we're betting on how the econ the average
british and american worker at the 50th percentile
do you think their kids will be richer than they are
it depends if we have economic freedom
or not
right we're going to have a split test on this
right we're going to have a split test we're going to have
the uk seems like we're going to have more taxes more regulations
and it seems like the us is going to have less taxes and less regulations
here's what i've noticed i've noticed that places like singapore that have small governments
um have got widespread affluence there's not a lot of poverty in singapore
yeah except for the cleaners living in the closets yeah you know
look but we don't count them in the statistics just like we don't count our viewers
that that's not widespread in well there's a lot of people w
i've seen them in the closets
i've seen them in the closets there are there are some but they're not singaporeans
well also you only count the rich ones
look the the also the issue is is that they've come from
even worse conditions in many cases people mve to singapore for an increase in lifestyle
right the
um
you could take ireland or switzerland
right economically free places ireland was economically in a disaster
in think the average irish person lives well
well the their
economy
their economy almost collapsed in 2011
and they went down the road of lower taxes lower regulations and they attracted
all sorts of businesses
into the economy
and do you think that works well for the average irishman
who doesn't own a home in dublin
the the if you measure everything by home ownership
i'm measuring people by the average
i want to know what the average man or woman
today lives that by the way i i'm also furious
about the home ownership
thing everyone is
um i think it's utterly ridiculous
the way like the idea that homes are now worth 10 times the average wage
all of that difference is i blame government for that
i blame high taxes
where they've
because of high taxes they can take out more debt
they can then inflate the economy do you think if we shrink the government
if we start to slash government spending
do you think that would improve living conditions well the uk government is 45%
of the economy
like that's a huge government it's
think using
additions will increase
in the next few years
because we have us government now that's planning to slash
the us government
well that's what the us voters have asked for do you think it would improve
living
conditions
do i think it'll improve
the average american if they're smaller government
yeah i trust market so you think
the average us american
will be rich in years than the here what i trust
i trust
economic
freedom
if people have freedom
they create
better decisions for their own life there's two ways to make decisions
right there's two ways you have freedom
i got less freedom
than i did when i ared
just
because my sister can't pay the rent
is that freedom
the
if you're living in a country
she can't
to live in the city that she was
born
in
i i agree
you and i agree on the problem you keep bringing
back to the problem
i keep bringing it back to people because the people who watch we're millionaires
okay the people who watch us are mostly not
millionaires
is life going to get better for them they life will get better
if you are connected to the most productive parts of the economy
um if you pretend that it's 1955
and you recreate the postwar era conditions if you try to go back to 1955
i don't think
that's going to work
so so let me ask on that then
the point
about
if you're connected
to the most productive
parts of the economy
i was quite
um
quite surprised
when i was doing some research on this to find that there's quite big differences
between the uk and the us in terms of gdp
growth
in q4 2024 the us economy grew by 6% while the uk growth was 0.1%
so they're doing significantly better in that regard us gdp per head stands at $82,000
per head whereas the uk stands at $49,000
per head and stock market performance
which is an
indication of i guess what ever
rose by 300%
in the us whereas the footsy
100 declined by 20% which is the uk stock market productivity growth since 2018
productivity increased by 30%
in the united states which has outpaced
the the uk and lastly income growth since 2007
american income per head has increased by 72%
while it has decreased
in by 2%
in the uk in dollar terms
so they seem to be doing better from if you just look at the economy
um
why is that is that because they lean more into technology and innovation and entrepreneurship
and is it because of the things you were saying earlier about their attitude towards
the govern like reduced government spending versus tax the rich why
i'm keen to hear gary's
view on this because i
understand yours because you've just said it
yeah i think these are great statistics
um and of course the us has a strong reput
reputation
for being very free markets and being very small states
in the last 5 years 10 years 15 years
we've had a uk government that has been aggressively slashing the state
and the us state's bigger than ever it's 45%
of the economy and the us we had
a government in the last four years which has been running a massive massive deficit
so in that period of time
it appears the government which has been aggressively increasing its deficit has massively overperformed
the government which has been aggressively slashing the
state
that's what it looks to be from the last
i mean b joe biden in enormously increased the deficit enormously
and the conservatives were austerity government for 14 years
which one seems to have given the better numbers
well i mean there were austerity in name only they went from 30%
the state was 30% of gdp to 45% of government services haveed
now they're the government is terrible at doing most things that's the problem
you you you don't want you don't think that spending on
government service has been slashed
let me let me zoom out a little you think the police spending has been slashed
oh police spending
is definitely
do you know where it ends up it ends up with like big corporates
big consulting
who get paid $50 million to produce a report to tell government some thing
right all of these big i won't name names but all the big consulting firms
they're all blood suckers to government they
they know that the money is in the government
and they set up business models to extract that money from government
and it also is in the financial trading side of things
the one of the issues that we've got
right and this is a big big issue as well cuz you care about wealth
inequality
one of the biggest issues i see
is that during the pandemic we all learned to work remotely
and remotor
became
the norm and what i see at the moment is
huge amounts of what would have been normal british jobs
are going to the philippines
going to india going to
vietnam
people who work remotely now
we now have a thousand millionaires a month leaving to go to dubai we have 120,000
british people living in dubai
in in that economy the world's become incredibly mobile
and one of the things that's happening
is that what would have previously been good british jobs
are getting moved overseas to lower cost countries
and that's technology
that drives that wedge
the us is very smart in that they've built a technology
powerhouse
and the uk has completely lost our technology industry
our tech industry is in decline same same across europe
china
and the us
know that the game is tech
and they've basically pulling all the tech company
into the into their
borders
and what's happening a lot is the erosion
of good jobs and the erosion of of just normal
well-paying
jobs because they they're going
and it's a bit of a self-fulfilling loop that the more we lose millionaires
the tax burden falls on everyone else so they put the taxes up
and then the millionaires
say oh the taxes are too high so they leave
um i've watched some of the most incredible entrepreneurs
that you would want here that would employ your sister at a high rate
um and they've
picked up and left cuz the taxes are too high so you saying we should tax
working people less
well the the the overall government has to be smaller
you can't whoever what do you want to cut in the government if you
yeah i mean you'd have to child services we'd have to no police no education
nhs
all i know is this pensions
you go to switzerland they sp single mothers 25%
disabled benefits
what do you want to cut hold up all i know is in switzerland
i tell you what i want
the government is
ta
on those entrepreneurs
and raise the taxes on the billionaires
because i worked my tits off how many billionaires are in the uk
there's a lot of billionaires in the uk 150
yeah so tax them more what do they pay listen i went my tits off
and i paid it was 50%
top rate tax 50%
top rate tax plus national insurance 60%
million to bring my family out of poverty
at the same time the duke of westminster inherited 10 billion
and paid nothing do you think that's fair that's not true
okay why is it not true because the duke of westminster
is one of the highest tax payers in the country what does he pay
well on the trust the groer estate
they don't pay inheritance tax because trusts can't die they pay something called periodic taxes
which how much 6% every 10 years 6% so they pay 0.6%
so i paid 16% and this guy pays 0.6%
apples with apples inheritance tax is 40% across the course of your life
if a trust is
if a person lives who owns a trust for 70 years
then 6% time 7 would be 42 so they actually pay more so he pays 0.6%
a year
pro 0.6%
that would be the same as
what percent did i pay per
no no no but that's 60%
so you're saying i pay what 60 of a 0.6
what 100 times the tax not comparing apples with apples
wait why is it not apples with apples this guy pays 0.6%
a year i paid 60% a year that's inheritance tax i paid that 60%
every year daniel every year i paid you're pay income tax so why have i du
p more than the duke of westminster pays income tax he probably
he probably makes your bill blush
yeah think can pay his income tax
yeah well if he's going to live he has to withdraw money to have his income
he also
let me give you a list of all the taxes
he would pay
he'd pay income
tax
corporate
tax he'd pay stamp duty when he buys a building
he pays
any of the other taxes vat when he spends money
all the same taxes
apply to a duuk
as they apply to anybody
else
so you think he pays income tax on on the income on that
any income he draws
okay well our viewers can research whether he pays income tax on his income
because i don't think he does
it's in a trust but the only difference with the trust
versus income
is that the trust pays periodic tax versus inheritance tax 0.6%
but we're only talking inherit that that's just one type of tax
you think he's paying 60%
on his income
he's one of the highest taxpayers
in the uk i'm not like his big fan
club but
the truth is he's one of the highest taxpayers
in the uk
um he's one of the biggest employers
he's one of the
like
one of the biggest land owners
in the uk land owners
in the uk
right
so
the the issue is is does he pay tax
all the same taxes that apply to you apply to him
and if you want to set up a trust you can also pay periodic
taxes as well
um which would be on top of all the other taxes so what would you say
but it's just not true that he doesn't pay tax
no what would you say this guy has inherit 1010 million
p
so he's worth 10 billion ps
what would you say will be the total
amount
of tax
he will pay in his lifetime
well i know that just the smallest
if i make 10 million i pay 60% just one sec
you're not you're talking about income versus the transfer of
an estate so why why is it that the
be 10 million p just you're comparing your income
yeah versus the amount he inherited
which is not a fair thing that's not income that's his income
he inheritance is not income
so wait wait wait wait wait wa so if i get given1 billion
i don't pay any tax but if i work for10 billion i pay 60%
well if you inherit
this is the tax system that you want
you'll end up in a system
where the kids of the richual own everything
that's what i'm saying that's what i'm saying
and that's fun because that's our kids you're not telling the truth about his
let's support it let's have a tax system where your kids and my kids and steven's
kids are multimillionaires
and
these
guys out there
can't
afford
to feed
their kids
and put the heat in
that's not what i'm saying
but that's what you will get
that is what you will get that's listen
that's what i'm betting on that's fine because i'll make money in the markets
it's fine and you'll make money and you'll make money
it's our viewers who will be poor and that's fine
that's fine that's fine for us let's let's explore the other alternative
right so let's say tax the rich
right so let's play the game of tax the rich
tax the owners
not the workers
the owners
so the issue that we have with the rich
is that is the number one most valuable assets in the economy now in tangible assets
so there's this chart called the s&p 500 of the 500
richest countries in the country in the world in the us sorry
um in 1970s 75% of the value of the s&p 500 was physical assets like property
um and today it's less than 10%
it's closer to 5%
you think that housing is not particularly important
just just let's stick stick with what i'm saying
okay
the the the powerhouse the engine room of the economy is digital assets
and that's reflected in
the s&p 500 for example which is 95%
intangible assets
one of the issues that we have is that the richest people are completely
mobile
now
so they can be absolutely
anywhere in the world
so if you come up with this idea of let's tax richest people 1%
if a tiny proportion of them leave
we're all in trouble
so this really rich guys m
what do they own
companies
and why are those companies worth money
because investors say they are and where do the revenues come from globally
okay the issue is is that these companies operate globally now so
take my company for example
my company has 8,000 customers in 150
countries
okay we could be anywhere if you p what country is your biggest single revenue source
probably the us now
let's say you move to cayman
island
and the us says we're going to tax your revenue at point of sale
m what can you do
well that's different right because that's not taxing billionaires that's taxing
companies
see when you say tax the rich on their wealth
yeah that's different to saying tax companies a consumption tax
oh but you just said the're rich owned companies
you said that's what they own yeah but you're saying
how do you tax them right so do they do you tax their wealth
which is what they own
or do you tax the companies where they trade
um typically consumption taxes get passed on to consumers
it's not consumption tax it's the tax on the ownership
yeah but if you simply say when you're doing revenues
then that's a consumption we start to tax
if we start to taxit
by the way i'm not exactly against you on on companies i think it's disgusting
that a british company
can can take out a facebook ad to sell to a british
consumer
a british product and facebook pretends to be in ireland on that transaction
um and amazon you can buy something on amazon in britain from a british supplier
from a british warehouse
and amazon pretends to be in luxembourg
in that situation
and that sucks right like that that does not seem
fair and it strikes me as very strange that the government
is okay with that right now the government is chasing
down
moms and dads who sell a few things on ebay
and chasing them for taxes but they don't talk to ebay
they they they're paranoid
about someone
doing a little bit of a side hustle on facebook
but facebook's
fine to pretend to be an ireland
so i don't agree with all of all of that right like i think where
missing some serious tricks here
but the idea
with
taxing
billionaires at wealth
billionaires will just leave they just get up and leave and and not just billionaires
but what the billionaires
own what the billionaires own companies
and where do companies get their money from revenues
and where do the revenues come from
purchasing
people purchasing where do those people live
all over the world
we can tax them at that point
that's consumption tax this is the thing that's a consumption
tax
no it's not it's
v
is a tax on revenue
tax these guys on
profits based on where the revenues
come from
so
it's very easy to move profits
internationally
see steven had a
starbucks cup when he buys that starbucks
yeah it's bought from a british company
who licenses the starbucks logo
from luxembourg or somewhere like that so 15%
so here we are saying oh we're going to tax their profits
they say ah i wish we were profitable
sorry
unfortunately we had to do that licensing deal with that international
i know how profit shifting works okay so are you you think are you telling
me
compan selling to
the uk the us enormous amount of of profit in the us
and they turn around and say actually our profit is not in the us
the difference you think the us
is in is is incapable
of going and looking if that's seeing
where they really where the profit is i'm not saying
that you can't
do
this
i'm saying
that the benefits
of doing it it's so hard to tax
wealth for example or it's so hard to tax
millionaires and billionaires
that that you end up cutting off your nose despite your face
um for every
like if we britain for example
and we build a brand
which is that we're anti- wealth
we don't want you to ever have more than 10 million
if you've got more than 10 million we punish you
every young entrepreneur
who comes to me and says dan do you think i should start a company
here in this country
i'm going to say well if you do
they'll take it
as soon as you start to make it they'll take it
as soon as if you're successful
if you get investment
they're going to tax you at your wealth
if you sell the company they're going to take it off you
i'm going to basically say to that young entrepreneur
don't build your business in brit go start it somewhere that they're more proactive
and positive towards entrepreneurs
are we seeing that now with this they call it the millionaire exodus
which is
for people that don't know the uk has set to lose the greatest proportion of millionaires
in the world
um this parliament i'll put a graph on the screen which is this one here
this one here
and that little red line here is
us losing all of our millionaires at the moment and in 2024 it's an estimated
that 10,800
high net worth individuals left the uk which is
57%
increase from the previous year which means that 1 millionaire is departing every 45 minutes
the uk millionaire
exodus
is equal to losing 530,000 average
taxpayers
and another stat
the top 10% of earners in the us account for nearly half of all consumer spending
the top 1% of income taxpayers in the uk are projected to contribute
about 30% of total income tax from 2024 to
why are all these millionaires running away
well it's not because they're taxing their world because we don't have any wealth taxes
why why do you think they're leaving
i think the reason they're leaving is because the uk economy is is really really weak
because the uk consumer is really really weak because you've absolutely crushed the spending power
of your average british family
your average british family
can barely afford to feed the kids and turn the heating on
so why are you going to start a business
here
when the customers are absolutely impoverished
look it corresponds with a new tax that we brought in which was
um we ended the non-dom scheme
so the non-dom scheme basically said if you're living in the uk
but you've got businesses all over the world
then we only tax you on what you've got in the uk
um and if you die in the uk
we'll only tax you on your uk assets for inheritance tax if you're a non-dom
but if you die in the uk and you've got wealth in india
once that nonon
scheme ended
they basically said we will tax you on everything globally
if you're an economic
if you're a tax resident in the uk
everything you've got globally we want 40% of it so unfortunately every wealth manager
contacted their clients and said you can't stay here you're going to have to get out
um it's it's gotten really bad a th000 people a month are leaving
and
in the uk 1% of people pay 30%
of the taxes 10% of people pay 60%
of the taxes
and you imagine
if we're sitting out at dinner
and there's 10 of us out to dinner
and one person says hey i've got this i get i'll get 60%
of the bill tonight we say to them no it should be 70% should be 80%
and they say you know what i'll get up and leave so they leave
everyone else's bill just doubled
so what's going to happen is if we drive the millionaires out of this country
everyone
every ordinary
normal
person
who pays
10 grand
a year in tax
will now have to pay
grand
a year in tax
so the reason they left because we used to allow them to not pay tax
and we ta on their global incomes
on their global
isn't it a bit more like if we were 10 of us at dinner
and there was one guy
who
came on to dinner on the condition he wouldn't pay their leaves
because these guys weren't paying tax anyway
the reason they left is because they weren't paying tax
it's like saying
um
hey i'll pay 60%
of this table and they say at the table
hey wait a second
we also want you to pay for
everything that's happening at other restaurants as well isn't it a bit more like
these guys we're stretching
on a condition you you yourself said
the reason why they left
is because we let them live here
on the condition that they didn't have to pay taxes
on their global
yeah taxes matter right so why why is everyone going to dubai
dubai they're going there because there's no tax
these guys
they live in dubai
their money comes from the west
they are making money
from the west while your average western
ordinary person watching this show now
cannot afford to buy a house cannot afford to have a family
we can tax those revenues at the point of sale why do we allow these
it's a called a consumption tax no it's not it's a tax on
tax on profit
not tax on consumption
you just said at point of sale which means it's a consumption
tax based on the profits
you look at how much profit
they
where the profits exactly it's not consumption tax what i'm saying so
no so if you tax profits
yeah right then those profits
have to accumulate in that country and because of the digital
ecosystem that we now have the world we now live in
i can lease the database off of my company in luxembourg i can
license the i can license my logo from understand how profit shifting
listen these guys are not gandal you just say we don't accept profit shifting
we don't need to accept profit shifting china does not accept profit shifting
we did not accept profit shifting
50 years ago we do not have to accept profit shifting
but you have
a government class who are extremely wealthy and a media class are extremely wealthy saying
it's impossible to tax rich people and i would like to say
i will agree 100%
it is difficult to tax rich people it is very
very very difficult to tax rich people
i don't i don't come here saying i want to tax rich people because it's easy
i know it's hard
i know probably i'm going to lose
i know our viewers
kids will live in desperate poverty i know that
i do this because it is hard
if we are a country
which says to ourselves we don't try and do things which are necessary
to keep our kids out of poverty
because they are hard
then our kids will live in poverty i don't need to be here i'm a multimillionaire
just like you i could be in the philippines drinking panac laders
i come in here because i come from a poor background
and it's ordinary families like my family
like the kids i grew up with whose kids are going to be in poverty
it's
difficult but it is
necessary
sometimes we have to do things not because they're easy but because
they are hard that is what makes a rich country rich and that is what protects
ordinary people listen our grandparents lived in poverty
did they say let's not change it because it's hard no they didn't
they fought
and they demanded
they demanded health care education
housing food and they got it they got it that's why my parents
could live a good quality life
they got those things they got those things and they were aware
that in order to do that you could not allow
the super
rich
who have been living lives of luxury
for hundreds and hundreds of years
to eat
everything
while ordinary
families couldn't afford to feed their kids
i know it's
difficult i know it's
difficult and i know i'm probably going to lose
i know that i know i'm probably going to lose
and that means our viewers will be poor but i do it anyway
because i do not want this country that i grew up in to fall into desperate
poverty
i agree with you on the passion and i agree with you on the problem
i don't agree with you on the solution because in 2019
we be kids in 2020 and that's not what i'm saying in 2020
we made a decision globally to shut down the economy
and we taught
everyone that they can live and work from anywhere
the biggest threat to everything you're saying is remote working
the fact that we can live and work work from anywhere our grandparents
their boss if their boss owned a company
that company
had to physically
be in the country and the boss had to physically be in the country
if we look at today
there are plenty of fitness trainers who work for a gym
and the owner of that gym is somewhere overseas
plenty of people work in live
work in a restaurant
and the owner of the restaurant
lives overseas
you can live in you can run a business from anywhere in the world right now
so the problem that we face
is that you're describing
on one
hand you say
we need to tax it at the point of sale which is a consumption
tax
and not tax on profit okay and then you say a tax on profit
and then you say
oh
but then we'll stop
profit shifting
by the way i'm also
actually all for this idea of
stopping
profit
i i've already said i think it's utterly
ridiculous
the way that many of these global companies are treated
and if we don't
stop
that
then all the money just flows
out to the tech companies
um so i'm i'm with you on that but when you say tax the rich
the actual people who own the companies
those people can
be anywhere right now so but but their revenues
can't their customers
their customers are where their customers are
listen amazon doesn't pay any uk tax doesn't pay any us tax where are the customers
in the uk and us in uk
us
do you really think it's impossible for us to tax that well you're talking about taxing
people at 10 million
plus right
so this is a lot of startup entrepreneurs
jeff bez is a lot more than 10 million jez
jeff worth a lot more than you talk about
anyone above 10 million is on your radar you don't want people worth
11 million pounds we pay more i'm not just talk
it's not that
dan if you you you're worth more than 10 million pounds so if we tax people
on
as gary says that have more than 10 million what are your options
to avoid say if your objective was to avoid that
what options do you have look if if my objective was to
avoid it i pass a board resolution that we're moving the head office somewhere else yeah
um we move the intellectual property somewhere else
i pick up and move my family somewhere else
and within
about a week or two we've got a we
work office
somewhere else
i've got a new house
on airbnb
somewhere else
and i cut ties with the uk
and i'm non- tax resident
here and i can
i have a digital business
i can literally make my head office anywhere in the world
if there was a particular country that turned hostile towards
our operations they not have to withdraw service from that thing
you know so that that's possible but it's unlikely that that would actually happen
but ultimately if i choose to get up and leave then i get up and leave
now
the the the bigger issue is would i have even come here in the first place
and then there's another issue and here's the other issue gary for you
you've just had 750,000
subscribers to your youtube channel 820 it's 8:20 right so it's going up fast
i could have
one of my analysts at a consulting company do valuation of your brand
and do valuation of your youtube channel
we could say this is a fast growth media company
and it's worth
11 million
right so we could come up with a forecast
and a projection and we say gary's
economics
is actually a new fast growth media brand it's worth 11 million
now your channel
now you have to pay 100 grand a year in extra taxes
because you're a millionaire
sorry 1%
on wealth above
10 million on 11 million is going to be 10 grand taxes
oh you're saying only on the part above that's how
taxes work so it's not on everything
it's
okay so it's a it's a marginal tax that's how taxes work
so okay so but is it fair
that like who gets to decide what wealth is wealth and what it's worth because wealth
let's just hit me out wealth is a a technical term for unrealized
gains
right it's not real
you know someone buys a house for 20 grand and it's worth 200 grand
they've still got the same house but now they've got wealth
um if someone starts a business
and a tiny little seed investor
puts in a little angel
investment
now they've got wealth on paper but who gets to say what is wealth
um like for example
if you introduce wealth taxes theoretically
that will actually
reduce the value of wealth of things anyway
because
things in inside that economy
are now subject to a disadvantage
so therefore investors will be unlikely to invest in them to a certain point
and also
people start
cutting and dodging and weaving and ducking and weaving so they say oh our uk operations
worth 10 million so we're now going to start
a second company over in some other country and make sure that
that's where the wealth accumulates
so it's incredibly
difficult because it is just unrealized
gains
i know i know it's difficult
yeah i know i know these guys have the best accountants
i i know it's difficult i know so what if there was an easier
solution
if there was an easier
i would support
that you know what i mean it's called it's called economic
freedom
the economic
index
okay well
just tell the viewers
that give them more economic
freedom and then they'll be rich
yeah so this
this diagram
here basically says
the most free
countries
have less than 10% poverty in fact less than 7% poverty
as soon as you reduce economic freedom it jumps to 30%
poverty you reduce economic freedom again and it jumps up to huge huge amounts of poverty
so
the these countries here are the least economically
free and these countries are the most economically
free
the countries that get in the way of your economic
freedom
have more poverty and the countries that let people make decisions for their own life
what you're saying is
if the governments of our countries cut taxes on us the three multimillionaire
sitting at this table
that will improve the lives of
the ordinary british and american
give a real life example to feed their kids i'll give you a real life example
i know of a company
that was going to give pay rises to its employees
and then national insurance went up and instead of national insurance is a tax on employment
yeah
i'm saying to reduce that i'm saying to reduce tax on i want your viewers
the viewers
here to be paying less tax
while multimillionaires pay more tax good in theory
but
of if you could tax rich people 1% of their wealth above 10 million
i did a back of a napkin cap
calculation you might be able to get 20 billion
yeah
right that's if they don't leave that's if they don't respond
to it if they just happily pay it you get 20 billion
that's less than a week worth of current government spending
so the government's out of control 1.2
trillion a year of government spending is now what they spend
okay so let's cut that get that 20 billion
and cut the taxes
for
the viewers
cut their income tax so that works out about 250 a year
okay so let's do more let's make it 60 billion
so then you tax 3%
above wealth yeah do that right and then you also bring it down
this is what governments do make five or six
yeah and then and that's what they did
that's what they did in the second
world
war and that's why my dad could afford
a house
actually that's not why you could afford a house
okay well
who's buy if ordinary people are losing their houses and the wealth which they are yeah
and we're getting richer
yeah who is it who is now owning the houses if it is not us
the government used to own the houses and then they sold the government wealth is collapsing
government wealth is collapsing but what they did
is they sold the houses to the people
okay but but
ordinary middle
is also you can only do that once
and they did it for the baby
so you think it's our viewers who have got my houses now
who
where is the wealth
going
daniel
where is the wealth going who has the wealth now who is getting rich
who is getting the wealth that is lost by our viewers
i'll tell you where the biggest amounts of money are going the biggest amounts of money
since the pandemic
11 trillion went just to the value of seven companies that own te technology
so the biggest seven companies in the usa
11 trillion
has and you don't want their billionaire owners to pay more tax
well would that help the uk
well if you use that money to reduce tax on working
people then it it would help yeah they
own shares in the usa they're us citizens
so that doesn't help us here
but it will help the american
consumer
and then we can export the american consumer
and it will mean the american consumer
has money
and then it will show
british
people
how much you can achieve
by taxing super rich we can raise tax on our super rich here
and then
what i want is these guys to be taxed so much that they start to sell
assets
and then ordinary
british people can buy assets again because what i want is our viewers
to be able to own things
to be able to own their own homes
i when i hear this
um i
admissibly
don't know as much about these issues as you guys do but
when i hear that there's these seven
tech companies in the us my brain goes can't we have one here yeah yeah
can't we start
and then so my brain goes how what conditions do we have to create
ones that we had
yeah what conditions do we have to create
to have one of those seven
tech companies here especially
in this sort of ai world we're heading towards
where when i was reading through the stats
most of the investment in ai
which is going to be hugely destabilizing
across every industry from driving to to
any form of knowledge work even podcasting
i can play your podcast now yeah which sounds exactly like me which has a 4.6
star rating on apple which was written by ai in my voice published by ai
wild
and the and who's acing
the value there well it's a company in america
called 11
labs
and it's bloody
open ai
and i
why
why can't we have those companies here we need them here because china
and the us are dominating
this next
revolution
um and i i worry as a bystander that if we don't create entrepreneurship
friendly
environments
here
we're going to we are going to become indian yeah m so you
if you want businesses that to thrive
you don't need just a good environment for entrepreneurs
you also need people to have money that they can spend
mh
and we are in a country where increasingly
most of the people out there have almost
nothing left over at the end of the month
they can barely pay the bills
those companies are selling globally
right so they don't need any particular
company to do well they just they sell to anywhere
so like open ai chat gpt
we're all using that bloody product and pay our 20 $30
a month
yeah where do they actually get their money
from
right they get their money from selling
data
to to to the rich
right
my point was making the environment more friendly for entrepreneurs because when i start a company
i am at a i can't explain the disadvantage
i'm at at the moment if i start
that kind of company here in the uk there's no investors
and then all the talent seems to flock over to san francisco
so the the guys that built
the british guys that built
an ai company called fixer
which i was going to invest in all british lads from london
they went over to san francisco they're like 25y
olds they've just raised at a 60 million valuation
they're in this room
this building in san francisco full of entrepreneurs
and they're pumping knowledge and capital into this room
with all due respect stephen
you're not a great example for the fact that it's impossible
to start
a successful online brand in the uk
facts
um
but i also realized that the problem of of but he started when things were different
but i i also realized
i don't like using personal examples
because there's a huge amount of privilege and
okay is there a chat gbt in germany
no is there a chat gbt in in france
no is there a chat gpt in australia
no no is there a chat gpt in ja
it's china and one sec sec yeah exactly
what you have here is an extremely
low labor
extremely
high capital model which employs
few people across the entire world
that is focused in
basically two cities
yeah
good luck competing with that h how do we create an environment where the uk
can start to build some of these companies
which are going to capitalize
on this next technological
revolution
how if you were prime minister what would you do
i think you need to look realistically
about what companies do we have a chance of growing
you know i'm not an expert in ai
but i think trying to compete with san francisco
in london would
will probably
not work
why try try and do it you know try and do it and listen
i know
that you can get a lot of likes saying
let's just invest
in ai
only one city in the world outside of china has managed
it
china has managed it by basically state
capitalism
you know this is very similar in a sense to what we had with micro electronics
in japan in the 8s
right when you have a new industry
especially these industries which are very capital intense and don't employ many people
you get a first move advantage they tend to win eventually
often they get undercut
by cheaper rivals
and that does happen you know that does happen and you might stand in ai
i don't think ai is going to become
a massive massive
employer
of course you know a lot of countries are going to be like because basically
it sounds good we're going to invest in i we're going to invest in ai
personally i think we should be looking at what does the british person need
you know we live in a country where the housing stock is falling apart
if if we say ai
when we talk about ai i think we're actually talking about technology
because even a podcast
like a podcast like this you don't think this
of this as an ai company
but actually now the editing process the scripting process the transcription
process even youtube itself is an ai company
so
it's it's really technology
we're speaking about here and i'm wondering why we can't create a better environment
in the uk
to start launching
and building some of these technology
companies we've even seen i think we should and i think we should be looking
we should be look at reducing
taxes
on people who
who work and make money this is what i've been saying for the whole time
what about people what about people who start companies
yeah we should reduce
their taxes on the income that they make
but then if they start owning a50
million pound company
are you telling me
if you come to me and i say all right you want to start a company
we we tax you very very little on a company that you start
if that company becomes
worth 20 30 40 million quid
then we're going to start taxing
you you're going to come and say to me oh no sorry
50 million is not enough for me so can i ask a question on that so
um my company was was valued at x 50 whatever 100 millions
um congratulations i still had
because i hadn't had an exit event yeah i still had
101,000
20,000
in my bank account
are you saying
at the point when i sell the company
or are you saying just because i have shares from the company
i think
you can structure
it a number of ways you can structure
a number of ways
my preferred
way is to stop people
from
hoarding
enormous a of wealth for enormous amounts of time that's my
that's basically my preferred method
there's also the wealth tax method
there's also
capital gains
as a method there's a lot of different ways it there's a lot of different ways
but you have to deal with the problem
of
if you do not do not tax very wealthy individuals
and very wealthy families
their share of the pie will obviously goow over time
and they will and they are as we are watching
squeezing our ordinary families
you have to deal with that my friend sold his company in the uk
it's a company everybody
knows
um and he
i remember
him saying to me at the time it was in the middle of the pandemic
he got this big exit event i think he'd made 300 million
and he goes i'm off
i go where you going he goes i'm going to go to
dubai
in monaco
and live between the two
and i i said
explain
to me why he goes well the amount of tax
i'd have to pay in the uk
is equivalent
to me paying 20 million rent in the uk
for the next six or seven years
which he'd have to stay here for
so he
he went and he pops back in
every now and then but it meant that he could keep that
million whatever tax he would pay
never had to pay it to the uk is living this
highflying life now in dubai drops into monaco every now and then
um
and i remember him saying to me well steve
i'd have to pay 20 million
rent
a year to live here and he
went on to say the uk
product
is just isn't worth it
he goes crime
i'm going to get my rolex
robbed off me
he goes
um the healthare
system isn't the best the education
system isn't necessarily
the best
and the particular one was crime
which is i'll get i'll get i'll get mugged walking through
yeah london streets
stephen
if you allow british people who own 300 million pound of british assets
to
technically live in monaco and not pay tax
then you will get crime
and you will have
dirty streets
and you will have a bad health care system and you will have education
because if you give all of the wealth to a group of people
who do not tax
there will be nothing left to provide
things like healthcare and education
for ordinary people
it's not unconnected
these people are not technically
living there they're moving
out my friends have
moved
out of the country they don't come back to the uk
they've left and they leave with their they built a company here
they
glob
p tax they typically build globally business it's not that they p it was a global
they don't pay no tax they pay extortionate
amounts of tax
right anyone who's here is paying extraordinary
taxes more than they've ever paid before 1% pays 30%
10% pays 60% of
1 trillion a year gu 300 million how much tax rec he's paid in his life
i have no idea
his business was global that his biggest customer was the us it's i pay 60%
and our viewers will pay 30 40 50%
do you think it's fair that your 300
million guy pays his two or three
i have no idea what he
pays
well it sounds like he didn't pay 50%
well he dashed when before he got the tax bill
but why did we allow it
why did we allow
i i'm not allowed to not pay my tax
what could you have done
to you are allowed
to
when you were in japan
you wouldn't have paid uk
taxes
yeah because i was working in japan
and i pay japanese taxes because you're living in japan
this is the thing people can live wherever they want now so but
we're talking about this is
i think we should stop obfuscating
tax on people's work from tax on the ass they
so i'm talking about entrepreneurs work generates wealth
so when if i if i ear a billion pound of british houses
yeah and then i say i live in dubai yeah and i'm getting
the rent on a billion pounds of houses which would probably be something like like
that's going to be something like 50 million
a year so i'm getting 60 50 60 million a year of rent from british people
yeah and that gets paid to me from british people
yeah
and i pay and i don't pay tax i live in dubai
do you think that's fair
no
all right so let's change that let's let's make people pay tax on
on their world regardless where they live yeah the question would be though
how would you tax people right and how would you actually structure it because
regardless
of what you feel like is fair
this is the thing
it's not about fairness
it's about what you can pragmatic
and practically do in the modern economy
you might say oh i actually like for example if we said what's fair
a lot of people would say a flat tax is fair
you make one pound you pay 20%
you make a million pounds you pay 20%
make 100 million pounds you pay 20%
so a lot of people would say the fairest
tax system would just be a flat tax on everything
right that would be a fair thing it's pragmatically
can you do it is it actually good for society
should people be excluded from that so it's not about fairness it's about pragmatically
what can you get away with
all right well pragmatically
what we can get away with is desperate poverty for our viewers kids
if you want to have
can we zoom out just a minute
right i want to zoom out let's zoom away from our viewers
kids
forget about them they're not
i got i'm a dad right i got three kids you're you are a multimillionaire
dad you probably don't have the same problems as our viewers do you know that
do you know that kids born into the top have a 60%
chance of dropping out of the top
right 60%
that's the number it's called persistence you can google it
um the persistence rates is actually only 40%
for the richest
so which means 60%
drop out in the second
you think kids have a 60%
chance of living in poverty pos not poverty
do you know what's interesting
we're all trying to aim at the same goal
i think here
i'm not sure we are but well
that's fair
that's fair maybe we're not i suspect
some of us are maybe trying to protect
our
kids
i want widespread affluence through the technological
revolution that's happening
and i don't want the people who create that
to want to go somewhere else so you agree with me
that we should cut tax on wealth creators and raise tax on wealth
orders
well broadly
okay so let's do it let's cut on people who are making
let cut tax on people who are working hard creating a good product
making a good income
and let's raise tax on people who are sitting there on 20 30 40
200 500 million pounds of assets
that they're going to give to their kids and they're going to use to dominate
society
and squeeze out the middle class so who's an example
of someone who's hoarding
wealth
she so his family owns a tech company
his
wife's dad owns a tech compan
which he will inherit and his kids will inherit
his net worth
that is quoted
is based upon his wife's
but that company already exists
yeah it's created now yeah
it's worth billions but they they have to reinvent that business every two years
like it's a so you think that the reason you think that if r's father-in-law
stopped managing the company it would be valueless
no i think it it
it
hires
hundreds
of thousands of people
and
it's you know it's a big company i don't know a lot about that particular
company but i know it's a tech company
steve jobs died
okay
is apple valueless
no let's not pretend
that these creators are the sole
reason these companies are are valuable
sure you know and what we're talking about in many cases
you know i was a trader okay
and
i'm worth a millions
of quid
and
you know now
that is just
assets
i just own the assets
i own the assets
and that will grow and it will grow and it will grow and it will grow
and that will squeeze out and squeeze out and squeeze out and squeeze out our viewers
and i'll give that to my kids
they don't even need to work
they wouldn't even
have even have to work they could just live on
i could live on off the
wealth
is that what you want do
do you think there are any opportunities
for people today like if you're born into a poor family
do you think it's possible
that housing being
and we can both agree agree on that but do you think there are new opportunities
that didn't exist for our parents or grandparents but they do exist for people today
i think the reality is for kids from poor
backgrounds
it is almost
impossible
to realistically
get even financial security
never mind wealth but why do you think
you could do it i could do it he could do it
but you don't think other people could do
it
well the first thing is i'm 38 now so i'm not not a kid nowadays
um listen
i want every mass competition
i've ever been in
you know what i mean
since
i was a
little
kid
i didn't
even
have a
desk
in my
house
you know
i was one of the top students at
lc
and i still had to win my job by cheating in a card game
you know that's the world that we live in i don't think that's a very replicable
strategy
and it's very easy for people like us who've made money
to say oh ar we did it aren't we great go out and you know
you've said that you think if young people go and work in tech business
they can get financial security
if it was that easy
they'd all be doing it you know they're not idiots
our viewers
are not idiots
they're trying trying
they're trying
they want to find the good opportunities
and they work listen i speak
i'm the one saying they're idiots you're the one who says
that they can't do it anymore
i i see people do it all the time like i'm working in entrepreneurs
people from poor backgrounds
and so so then so but then why are i vi you think all of our
if it was that easy why is everybody
not doing it i'll tell you why people aren't doing it we went through a schooling
system
that taught us how to get an office job
okay right we went through a schooling system to prepare us for a
a world that doesn't really exist anymore which is the industrial revolution world
and you have to go through a process of figuring out how it really works
so
what what i see is
the most often the people who do really well financially
who are young
they dropped out of school they dropped out of university they started learning
how to do things
by doing their own research they start their own business or co-found a business
they take a very alternative
path
none of that was taught to us at school
none of it's taught to us in normal society
we have a school system that manufactures
people for a set of skills that are not particularly valuable anymore
and we also get them in debt for those skills
um when people sid step that
and say okay i'm not going to get into university
debt i'm just going to go off and actually figure out how the world works
there's actually loads of
opportunities
okay so
i guess we've sorted it then all our viewers need to do
is go and buy dan's book
become an entrepreneur
and become a millionaire
it's that easy
why w you guys doing it to begin with they're idiots
the viewers are idiots
they should be just being more entrepreneurial
it's as simple as that more entrepreneurial
start a business listen i come from east london okay my friends
can't feed their kids
okay
and if it was as simple as going out and be an entrepreneur
i can bet you they would do it
i can bet you they would do it let us
i'm sick of multi-millionaires
telling
kids
who can't afford to turn the heating on you just need to be more entrepreneurial
it's sick dan it's sick
i this gives people mental illness
it gives people mental illness tell them the truth okay we your older generation
we took the opportunities
and now is almost impossible to out of poverty
and don't just don't just stand up and wave
you know your millions
of pounds in front of them and say if you entrepreneurial
like me you could do it you could have it because it's sick because they can't
they can't feed their kids down
they can't turn the heating on don't tell them to be more entrepreneurial
fix the system that drives more and more and more of them into poverty every generation
i find it very strange
that you think it would be easier to fix the entire global economic
system
than to start a business
and fix your own personal
economics
the the thing that
the thing that i know that gives people mental health issues
is feeling that they have no agency in their life that they can't do anything
your video where you talk about if you don't have a rich dad you're screwed
there's no such thing as meritocracy
you're never going to be successful
to me
if i had have come across your content
at 19
20 years old i would have been screwed
i was so i'm so glad
that i came across people who said
daniel you weren't born into a
a rich family you don't have any bank of mom and dad
but it's cheap and easier than ever to start a business
start by working for someone who's got a business then figure out what's your opportunity
and there's a way there is a way
i've actually worked with a lot of teenagers from poor backgrounds
and one of the things we do is we
tell them if it's possible for someone else it is possible for you
um i also worked in rural uganda
um with a charity that did work with the poorest of the poor
um one of the most incredible things i ever saw was a woman who started
out
literally picking food out of a trash
pile
um and she was
basically
sh
they they shared
with her how to start a chicken
business
which then ended up as a pig business
which then ended up as a cattle business
and she ended up
making
hiring 15 16 people in her local community
the power of entrepreneurship is that starting with nothing you can
actually
make improvements
i'm not saying everyone ends up as a millionaire and i'm not saying everyone ends up
equal
but i'm saying you can make improvements
in your life and the thing that causes mental health issues
is the feeling of having no agency or no control over your circumstances
until the world changes the whole economic
system
i never told people don't work hard i never once said that never once said that
never said that you said if your dad wasn't rich you'll never be rich
which is true in 99.9%
of cases i've never told people don't work hard true 99%
i've never told people don't work hard okay and listen if you think that ugandans
should be more entrepreneurial
i've never been to uganda
maybe that's the problem out there maybe that's the problem in nigeria
maybe that's the problem in india listen
i've never said don't work hard
okay
when i brought my book out last year
the hardback
i was at some event and i come out i was drinking london bridge
and i come out late it was like it was like 1:00 a.m.
and
um
some guy come up to me when i was unlocking my bike
some guy from newcastle
which is the northeast
of england it's this quite a poor town there's a lot of workingclass
people there
and
um he said i've been watching you on youtube and um i love your stuff and
um
this guy started crying this guy start crying on the street right in front of me
he's like i work so hard gary i work two jobs
um
my mom's sick
and i'm trying to help i'm trying to support and and i don't understand why
and and i'm sorry that i'm
crying
but nobody ever told me that it wasn't my fault before
that's what he said to me okay and listen listen
i believe 100%
aspiration
ambition entrepreneurial
spirit
i would never say
see a kid that has that and say turn it off
okay
but the flip side of your if you just work hard enough you can make it
is if you didn't make it
it's because you didn't work hard enough and it's your fault
and i would like you to sit and think very hard
before you send that message to young men and young women in our
society meritocracy doesn't mean that everyone
ends up with the same result
what
what i'm trying to
what here's what i'm trying to achieve
i'm trying to achieve
the people who have ambition
who can go for it are incentivized
to do it and incentivized
to build jobs and build companies
about the ones
that just want to work hard and
have a good family
and take care of them
and have a home
and be able to turn the heating on and be able to
financial security they need to work for business don't they they need to work for you
yeah
p they need to work they need to work for a business
some business
right if someone doesn't create that business then where do they work for
we now have by the way we now have 11%
of 11% of working age people are now declared too sick to work
right we have a huge problem in the uk
we also have 25%
of people who are working age don't work
it's one in seven men don't work work at all do you think they're lazy dan
i think the system is collapsing do you think think the system is average british american
working is lazy what i think is happening
is that the technology
companies
are totally transforming and disrupting everything
um and what happened is around the post-war era we had good jobs we had
um you could work in a local thing what's happening
now is that jobs are going to the philippines
they're going to
techn technology does three things it makes jobs more simple which makes them replaceable
it makes jobs global
where you can move them to anywhere else
and then ultimately
it automates
the job al together and gets rid of it
through code and software
and what's really going on in the last especially 5 years since the pandemic
is technology
has decimated the existing systems
that we all relied upon when we grew up and when i say the
education system isn't really working
it's still pretending
that there are office jobs available
for people when they graduate and it's still pretending that there's like 1950
scenarios available
when actually
my kids are going to be disrupted by ai
everyone's kids are going to be disrupted by ai
um
you know
these sorts of things are the are the things that really
we
we also need to be talking
about
to all the founders and small business owners listening
i think you need to hear this it's an update from my sponsor fiverr
they've just launched something called fiverr
go and in short it's a huge
game changer for you and your team it's a tool that's been created to help freelancers
train and control a personalized ai tool
specific to them and in their style
which means that fiver freelancers
and their clients can now generate unique work almost instantly
purely by combining their own unique style of freelance talent with personalized ai technology
the big unlock for me here is time
and getting more of it back
what might have taken me a few days or a week
can now be done
in seconds
with five
ago
you get what you want and you get it straight away and if you need tweaks
the original
talent is on hand for fine
fivo is already available across 60 categories
and that number is growing
rapidly if it's something you'd like to tap into head to fiver.com
diary
now and explore fiveo use code diary
for 10% off your first order
this is the moment where ai superpower
meets human
talent
i i want to take this back to a point you were talking about earlier
which is about personal
agency
because i would like you daniel to give the counter to your own argument
because i want to make sure when we're talking about solutions to this problem
start a business
be
entrepreneurial
you can also understand how that might
that works for people with our brains
and our mindset and whatever we had that made us do that our risk appetite
our trauma whatever it might be
but not everybody
is wide in such a way
so that's not necessarily the best solution for
and also we sit here with a bit of hindsight bias where we we were lucky
and it worked out for us but when you look at the stats around businesses succeeding
what you know the stat it's like 90% of businesses fail
so most of them are failing
the ones that emerge from that people like me
then
we have a bias where we go well it work for us you do it too
i don't come from money so i have the same bias like i watched
well i've i've built
i've built from scratch several times because i got disrupted
several times so i've had to start with nothing several times and build
but you started
type of person right and when we say start from nothing
you actually started with a wealth of information
and the whole game in building building
capital
intellectual
capital having been through it before being around that mentor that gave you the information
also having access to a great market
like having
access
to a free
market
is is a big thing
i was born in australia
and i moved to london at the peak of london's
economic freedom so this can't be broadly applicable
advice
can it
well i think personal agency is broadly applicable
the idea
i got this friend of mine
who
woke up one day he went out clubbing
went out to a nightclub
felt sick collapsed
woke up and they had chopped off all four limbs right so
he
had quadruple ampute
um he was 19 years old so he wakes up in bed and he basically
says
i'm a quadruple
ampute
i was i was fine
48 hours ago and now i'm a qu quadruple amputee
and he decides to make this decision in the in the hospital room
um that this is going to be the best thing that ever happened to him
and he makes that decision right even that is a consequence
of
his him and his wiring
what i'm trying to
understand
but he ended up he ended up starting
a clinic
and it's a multi-million
dollar clinic
i mean it's incredible what
can do
the rule
it's incredible what people
but you only need a few people to succeed
and the whole economy starts to
improve
we we actually in this uk
we only at the peak of our entrepreneurial
like blitzing it where we're doing so well there was only 40,000 scale ups 40,000
companies were creating jobs growth higher wages
um investment into the company into the country
you know it's only
1%
of people who pay 30%
of the taxes
and 10% of people who pay 60%
of the taxes so you only need
one in a 100
to actually create something that's valuable and you get an extra 30% of taxes
but so
so that again is
we need this one that
advice for the what the people that end up getting into that 1%
but who does everyone else work for
like all jobs growth comes from entrepreneurs so what are you saying to those the 199%
there are you saying go get a job
well you you need wealth creators in the economy
who are building something like you take
um
gym shark
people who work at gym shark they're super glad that this guy started the company
they're really happy that there's a company
otherwise where would they go what would they work where would they work
so if ben decides that he doesn't want to start that company in the uk
um or if he gets to 10 million and stops
then all of those additional jobs are are toast they're all gone so you encouraging
the entrepreneurial
you're not encouraging everyone to become an entrepreneur
you're saying those that have those
that bias or that i'm saying we need a system
that encourages
the people who can to do
um and what about everybody else
well every the flow on effect
is that that creates
jobs
that creates wealth in the economy
um and free markets lift everybody up
um free markets just means that everyone's trading with everyone
um
you know it starts
to like the whole thing i mean it's
it's just a tail as oldest
time as soon as economies
are free
and there are entrepreneurs
starting things and growing things everyone's life improves everyone life get better
um and what's your what part of that do you disagree with gary
i think it's it doesn't work
it doesn't work the only period listen the last 70 years are not normal stephen
the last 70 years are not normal
the last 70 years in europe and the us
where ordinary
people like my dad
could work for the post office
on less than average wage
and buy a house and support family it's not normal
it's not normal
in the world and it's not normal in history
most countries in the world do not like that
most countries have a a small super rich elite
and a very large group of extremely poor people that's most of the country
and it's most of
history in this country and it's most of history in the us
you know
yeah we talk about charles dickens i read hard times
i read hard times and this is written in the 19th
century
when britain was like the industrial
super
of the whole world
and at the time
the government was talking about should we tax these industrialists
and the industrialists were saying if you tax us we'll throw our factories into the sea
and it just reminds me you know
the only time we've ever really been able to provide
decent living
conditions for ordinary working people
was the period after the war where we massively redistributed
wealth and and now we're losing
that
that holding of wealth
in of the middle class can you acknowledge
though that that was a completely different time
as it relates to being able to it was a different time but you
i could you know of techy nigeria today brazil today
the uk 300 years ago france 200 years ago there is only one specific
time
that we have ever successfully
provided
broad living standards for ordinary people and it was a period of time we protected
a broadly
equal wealth distribution
and tax the rich at very high rates and you can acknowledge that that's
extremely hard to do because the nature of the economy 100%
that's the reason why all of our grandparents and our great-grandparents
and our great great grandparents lived in poverty and that's why i know
i'm probably going to lose
and that's why i bet
on the economy
getting worse
and that's why i know poverty is going to increase
because it was extremely
difficult to get the unusually
fair share for ordinary working people and i know we're losing the argument
and i know that farage
will win and i know that trump
will win
and i know
that
and i know that things will get
worse
i don't think i'm going to win
so if you if you know you're
promoting
a a strategy
that is not going to work and it sounds like you think is incredibly
almost impossible then why would you not be more practical in your solution stephen
if it was impossible i wouldn't be here
think it's possible
of course it's possible of course it's possible but you believe you're not going to win
i'm a betting man steve
i'm a betting man i put my bets on you know i am
if i get okay look okay so my youtube channel is growing really really quickly
and you know i'm obviously
like starting a bit of a movement
and there's a lot of political
support and if it keeps growing we'll get more political
support
at the end of the day
i'm trying to tax the richest and most powerful people in the world
and most of these people
will come out and attack
me and they'll try and stop
me
and
i do not have
billions of pounds hundreds of millions of pounds to use to support my youtube channel
i'm counting
on ordinary people like your viewers to support and share my message
now listen
for most of history
that has not worked and for most of history
ordinary families live in poverty
i don't think it's impossible
that we ordinary people can win and get a fair share
but i think it's worth fighting for steve so i fight for it anyway
he's he's right that for most of history you've had the super elite
and then everyone else is down here and it's massive wealth inequality is almost the normal
for the last five thousand years and almost everywhere
you've got kings queens dukes
and peasants and surfs down there
there have been economic
situations that have been different
dubai is a really strange situation
it's a desert it's in inhospitable
to live in
it's the last
place in the world most people would think or choose that they would want to be
and yet it's one of the most economically
rich places in the world right now
they actually didn't start with oil wealth they were able to borrow money to build dubai
but the low tax environment
has now attracted raed some of the world's most talented
people to go and build technology
companies
there
and if you i don't know have you been there recently
i've been to dubai
few years ag now but i've been so at the moment
it is the most
thriving
entrepreneurial
community on earth outside of the us but probably even rivaling the us
that there are investors there's entrepreneurs
and the wealth is going through the roof
um i've got two friends who are personal trainers fitness trainers
one fitness trainer has decided to stop working
more hours because he's hit 50 grand a year and he now gets taxed at 40%
so he's basically decided he's going to earn right up to 50,000 and then stop working
and then the other fitness trainer went to dubai
launched an online fitness
community and has just bought a $350,000 ferrari
and one entrepreneur
is super pumped and super excited about building a business because he's not over taxed
the other entrepreneur
has literally said
i'm not
willing
to do this
because of how much i have to pay
just want to be clear
i've always
campaigned
for lower taxes on rich
on working people
always always so but here's
but here's the thing right if i was ask you
you've just become
one of the best selling authors
in the country
if your publisher came to you
and said because you're in the top 1% of our authors
we're going to harve your royalties
if you sign a second book with us
you wouldn't sign a second book with them you go to another publisher
who says we'll pay you more royalties
because you're so successful i would have written this book for free then
i would have written
this book for free in fact the first time i got off of a
deal
i said i said don't pay me an advance then give you royalties away
why
well because if
what i'm saying all right fine i'll give my royalties away
i'll shut my youtube channel
down
i'm saying we respond to incentives
that if your publisher
if penguin
came to you
and said book number two you get half royalties
because you're in the top 1%
would you sign with penguin or would you go someone el from a 2 million
job a year
to run a youtube channel
do you think i do the work that i do for money
i'm not talking about that you do it for money
i'm just saying
if you had the option to
sign
between
two
publishing
contracts
right and all things being equal
one's going to penalize you for being in the to 1%
and the other one's going to reward you for being in the top 1%
would you you of course you would go with the normal
like if all things being equal you want to write a second book anyway
it's the same for entrepreneurs
when entrepreneurs start companies
we can either start them in high tax economies
or with a stroke of a pen start them in low tax
i think the rich world is going to have to start rethinking
the fact that it allows
people to very very wealthy people to own
enormous amounts of their physical wealth
go live overseas and not pay tax i think that has to be revisited
for sure
because
what you're saying is
i want the benefit
of being able to sell to the us market
and the uk market
but i don't want the obligation
of having to pay us and uk taxes
and you are correct
that at the moment
the us and uk governments allow that and i think that's
us taxes you on worldwide income
well only a small amount right so i think that realistically
i think that the us and uk governments have to stop that but
the way i see it the us and uk governments and increasing a lot of global
governments
are kind of being bought up by the elites
and
you know we have elo musk is basically
the president
right and we had richy sunak who father
was one of the richest men in the world like if you're richy sunak
who for our american viewers was our prime minister until very recently
his father is one of the richest men in the world
he's got 700 million
personal wealth he's going to be making 3040 million pound passive income
and you're getting paid 130
grand de to be prime minister
when you're making policy do you think maybe i'll ask my father-in-law at once
you know the fact is what you're seeing here is if you allow the rich
i'm i'm never ever against entrepreneurship
i'm not against people getting rich
if you allow the rich to get richer and richer and richer
they squeeze
the middle class and they squeeze the poor class out of things like housing
of things like space in cities
of things like energy
and of things like owning
a sharing government and media do you acknowledge that countries that adopt a anti-ri
big government approach tend to collapse
what like like this country in the
60s
we needed a us bailout we needed an imf bailout in 1976
but the us did the same thing the us had even higher taxes than us
we
basically
like you take
you take all the countries
that where the government becomes big they meddle with your life they're involved in every decision
right half the economy
i mean here's one other the things
this period
is known
as the golden
age of capitalism
it's the period of time when
which period thisi 50 years off the second world war
oh it's the golden age of middle class to be middle class
you don't care about the middle class no no of course i do
the the but the 70
years after the world war ii
yeah
where the government
sold
off all of its houses to middle class
people
so we got housing
wealth
but you can only
do that trick once
right
so you can only sell
off all the houses
to everyone
once
which is why all the baby boomers
own them well
the
living s is collapsed
after the houses were sold there was a long period where the houses weren't sold
between the second world war and the 80s
pinpo living standards collapsing
well i think there's a few obviously
big moments
i think
is a big moment i think co is a big moment
i think it's the 80s
where you start to see the wealth distribution
go
what matters is actually the distribution itself
so once you change the tax system
it takes a bit of time for the wealth distribution to change
but once you start
for me the big thing is is the loss of wealth holding
i want ordinary
families to be able to hold wealth
and once you lose that
you lose a middle class and you will not find me a single
country
in in the world now or the history of the world
that has provided
good broad living standards
without allowing ordinary families to own assets
yeah i agree and take singapore for example
where everyone's encouraged to own properties they've got an amazing system in singapore
they've taken this a massive government by the way enormous government 25% of gdp
they they
own they own the houses they have a weal f they own all the houses
they don't own all the houses they have a
a sovereign wealth fund that circulates
houses through they've they own the hous they' solved they've solved
singapore owns the house they own the singapore government owns an enormous share of the houses
so do you think we should own pension pension funds people
they force not force their citizens but they
direct their citizens into home ownership
you don't think singapore and government owns a large sh i just know that the singaporean
government's only 25%
of the economy
but big sh of the housing stock 75
the economy is i would like to say by the way just to be really clear
i've never ever once advocated for big government
never a single time
big government i want higher taxes on the wealth orders
so we can tax wealth creators
and working people less
i don't want to big a government i want our viewers to have more money
i want our viewers to have more money and also
i want to tax those super rich so that they stop squeezing
ordinary
families out of asset ownership
it just
yeah it see it it seems like an obvious solution
it seems like
yeah
it's good solution
it seems like
like hey who's got the money rich people
not the money the assets
the asset who's got the assets
rich people
then let's just take them off them
and
no no no i don't want i don't want to redistribute
i'm i'm i am the only person in this table anti- redistribution
because the redistribution
is happening in front of our eyes
the middle class is losing its assets
government is losing its assets
those assets are being accumulated by the rich i want to stop the redistribution
please
please i'm i am the most anti- rist
redistribution person in this game we need to stop the redistribu
of wealth away from ordinary british and american families so
the difference is for me it's very simple
which is i really truly believe that free markets
and low governments
and less taxes
creates more wealth in the middle and freedom for the heron is death for the fishes
if we have complete freedom multi-millionaires
like you and me will get richer and richer and richer every year
and we will squeeze out and we will eat the middle class
ask you though if wealth inequality could be solved but everyone does worse
is that a good solu
obviously
not
the whole reason i do this because i don't want ordinary
people toap
into public
this is about people being able to feed their kids
so wealth inequality
is not the problem
it's collapsing living stand that's quite contorted
i mean quite contorted logic the problem isaps
living standards i am somebody who has made millions of pounds
by understanding the simple fact that living standards are falling because of growing wealth ine equality
so living standards if they were to increase
but they were super rich yeah is that a problem
i think you do need to be worried about
us
extremely wealthy elites
yeah i think what's interesting you look at the the founding of the united states
these guys the founding of the united states conceptually
is really based on these ideas of distribution of power
that's why you have the president
and the house and the senate
and you have this independent
judiciary
they're like we cannot allow power to become concentrated
because they came from a europe which had extremely
concentrated
power and extremely wealthy elites and extremely broad poverty
so i think that allowing a small group of society to increasingly
monopolize
power and wealth over time is obviously something we should be worried about but primarily
the reason i worry about wealth inequality
is because i see
and i bet on and i make money on
the fact that it causes
living standards
to fall
by the way i i actually really agree with you and the founding
fathers
of the us
they did
um especially around the 1900s
they did want to break up monopolies
and break up monopolies
was one of the big things that
um they did trust busting
where they broke up standard
oil and all of those sorts of things one thing i do really really
see happening at the moment
is that we have a stupid outdated definition of monopolies
where we use monopolies the same way they used it when they had the oil
companies that owned all the oil
in the technology world a monopoly is formed through an ecosystem
so amazon for example owning aws
and audible and this and this and this and whole foods
it creates
a a fortress that's almost impossible to
um to compete with and google owning youtube
and gmail and all of this they create these fortresses through ecosystems
one of the things that i do think we need to look at
is
compulsory
breakup of big tech once you hit a certain time
because
it's very
difficult
because
do you know
billionaires
have two big fears
right keep them up at night having nightmares
number two is high taxes
number one is that startup entrepreneur who disrupts their business
and they want to kill that early
you know steve jobs at 24 years old disrupted
ibm
um and jeff bezos disrupted walmart so they are terrified of entrepreneurs in the middle
um and they want to create government regulations
to say hey you know what let's cap entrepreneurs
at 10 million
you can get to 10 million
it's okay for us we're way past that point
but gary's our guy because he's going to cap everyone
i never said cap anyone at 10 million by the way
what do you think will happen people stop
as soon as you have wealth taxes
people just give up they just don't want
telling me our viewers
if if they said
if they knew they could build
a 20 30 million
ss ridiculous they knew they would have to pay 20
if you if you're if you're worth 30 million 1%
above
is
200 grand a year so if i said
if you you can have a 30
million pound company
tr
just bear in mind
right you make 5%
a year on your wealth
right so if you got 300
million pound company
you're going to be making 15 million pound a year
and i'm turning
to you and i'm going to say you know you've got to pay
200 grand
a year on your 50
million
pound revenue
and they're going to say you know what
i'm not going to start a business
i don't want to be worth 30 million quid
this is
you know this is ridiculous
you know nobody
is going to say
oh my god i don't want to be multi multimillionaire
because in 20 years time i'll have to pay 1% taxes but most traders
most traders are earning what most people earn in lifetime traders can earn in a year
most traders don't stop
talk about that a lot in my book right so most traders just keep going entrepreneurs
are the same
that they're motivated to keep going but when you have wealth advisors and investors
saying do not build a company in the uk because they're anti- wealth
l
i'm not trying to make the uk
anti-
wealth i'm not trying to make the uk
and anti wealth
i think
the uk and the us need to be looking at a situation where you cannot allow
people who own enormous businesses that sell to your country
to live in dubai
to live in the cayman islands and not pay tax
and i i don't think that's a controversial
position
i've got a question for both of you which is if you are a young person
and you're 18 years old now
and that you're listening to this but your objective really is an individualistic
one you want to get rich
and you have a great future
for you and your family
like all all of us have been able to do
what would your advice be to them gary at this moment in time
this is such a hard
question
i know dan's angry at me for
what i put in my video how to get rich
um
somebody
came around to my house and asked me this other day obviously
i get asked
it a lot
because
stupidly i'm very public about the fact that i'm rich
um
what i did is not replicable
it's not
i'm sorry
i'm sorry but it's not people always say why don't you teach me to trade
like it's hard
it's hard trading and it's dangerous
and i think a lot of young men are getting sort of sold into trading
and becoming gambling addicts
um
you know work hard and i would i wouldn't even say don't become an entrepr
i've never ever said these things work hard
you know if you think that you have an opportunity in tech entrepreneurship
go for it understand it's risky
i think that sometimes this message just become an entrepreneur
and you make it is a bit dangerous
because i think
most people who try to become entrepreneurs
fail
and i think it's super super dangerous
the reality is and you know maybe d like this maybe you won't like this
i think it is very very difficult for a young man or a young woman
from a poor family
to become
rich
and i think it's increasingly hard even to just get those basics of financial security
so
listen obviously reduce your spending if you can don't buy into this like balenciaga
stay away from that
but
work hard study hard try to get a good job but also understand
we are shrinking the seats on the lifeboat that's what we're doing
we used to allow
50%
to be secure then it's 40%
then it's 30%
then it's 20% you know you got family in nigeria
if a young person from
like shanty town in nigeria
i came to you and said stephen what could i do to get
rich
you would have to say to him realistically listen
you are in a difficult situation here
you need to work really really hard but if you are able to make enough money
to to support a family
be proud of yourself
what i would actually say to them so yeah i have got family in nigeria
um for people that don't know i'm by blood half nigerian
i would say to them that knowledge is really your life raft
so
obviously there's a
big tech boom happening in nigeria
which is liberating
a lot of people from that situation
so i would try and tell them to
get on the life raft that is like knowledge of this new revolution
so from nigeria you can learn to code and then
the the great thing now is that we're we literally
have actually this is quite interesting
we're building a tech company in san francisco
called flight cast it's live everyone can go look at at flight.com
and
the lead developer oh and guest radar
the lead developer of guest radar is a nigerian guy but how many of those
jobs in the nigerian tech sector
are going to kids that grew up in the shanty towns i have no idea
cuz i worked in
people
ask me tell me how to do what you did all right i worked in canary
warf it's in east london
i could see the building from my house going up
there was not a single
other kid from east london
the whole time i was there
do you know to dan's point about this remote work revolution where like work now has
you can work from anywhere and in our company third web san francisco
me some of the
stuff that we now have are in the philippines
because they just have like great creatives
there it's obviously more cost
effective
isn't this a huge part of what's going on in our economy this this digitalization
and this
remotify b your workers in the philippines very very well
um
most of these people
they used to have
a half decent wage on office
and now they're locked in their bedrooms barely paying the bills yeah um in the philippines
not in the philippines the philippine guys are balling out control
no i'm saying the philippines is booming at the moment
so you think the average person in the philippines is living a luxurious
life have you if you
what's happening at the moment
do you think the average
person in the philippines is living a luxurious
life there is there is this thing called remote foreign workers
and
this is a huge boom
the economic
the kidchen move to the philippines
then it's great you get great quality of life in the philippines
you know when i looked at the thums of manila
they should just get j they i don't know why they're not getting the laptops out
the the poverty in the philippines is horrific
i'm listen philippines a beautiful country an amazing country i love the philippines
number
in there at
at a rate that's never
what is the life
like for your average
filipino
well would you agree though that their economy is just
getting flooded with money at the moment like money is flowing in there
money is flowing
in but it is not giving a good quality of life your average filipino
that's not true remote foreign workers
well we can remote foreign workers filipino viewers to tell us what's
can actually support the often support their en
a look i don't know what the average
wages in the phili
just to bring it back to this point though so i wanted
to know from gary
he said work hard if you're a young guy listening to this now
um i was reading this really interesting article yesterday
from the i think it was from
major
newspaper
talking about the lost boys
and it goes to show that i think it's one in seven
young men that is at a working age now are out of work
so there's lots of talk around young men in particular
and how they're struggling
you'd say work hard gary
you' say work hard no blena but the big thing
the big thing is
recognize the situation that you're in and i would encourage them
to support my work and follow my channel because
the lifeboats are shrinking and trust me
we're going to get out kids in the lifeboats
and we all know that all right and if those life boates are shrinking
if you don't if you don't stop the from going down
it is not you and you and me
who are going to go down we will be fine
if you don't fight the political fight i guarantee
you
people like daniel will so
you're saying that they should also get involved in the political fight
you have to you have to that's what our grandparents
did
grand if they want to become millionaires like you and me and dan
well it sounds like dan's got better advice for that than i do
okay well i'm going to ask dan as well but i just wondering
i'm wondering how your your advice ties into sort of
like
the young the young person who's trying to liberate
themselves from where you came from or where i came from
you know what i don't think i'm the guy to say that man because you know
i had this unusual
gift from a young age i was very very very good at maths
and i just followed
that
um and you know
you know my sister she's a poet and she wrote a really successful
grime of musical about diy r's first album
all right
she comes from obviously the same family as me poor family
she works so hard she works so
so hard
two degrees
she can barely pay the rent all right so
i don't want to turn around to our young kids and say
well i've got this talent follow your talent
because it doesn't work stephen true it doesn't work yeah
wait
my sister does great work but financially
for young people following your passion following your talent unless you come from rich family
realistically
very very
really works and i know it worked for the three of us at this table
but let's not pretend
that everyone
experiences the same things that we experienced
what would you say to that d and what's your answer
i think there's two economies going on at the moment there's a dying economy
which is the industrial revolution
economy
um and that is all the office
jobs and the factory
jobs and all of that sort of stuff which is very much being automated
away and moved
globally
um and at the same time there's this new bubbling up digital economy
um which i'd call the entrepreneur economy or the digital economy
um both of these economies are kind of co coexisting one's going like that one's going
like that
um
and if you want to be economically
successful you need to stand next to the biggest piles of money that you can
um you know unfortunately being a poet
doesn't pay a lot of money and we all know that that's not a surprise
if you came from a very
rich
family
and you were a poet
you'd
probably
be one of the 60%
who fell out of a rich family
as well
um
if you want to be economically
successful you need to say what is the thing that's economically booming right now
gary
saw
the finance
industry
at that particular
time but if we actually look at the finance
industry
now it's in decline
um and trading is being rep replaced by ai robots
um people who worked in your career are going to be replaced by
it systems
that basically
do
similar
jobs it's going to be
you know these things happen
we're going through a massive
technological change
but at the same time it's never been easier
to learn skills for free
on youtube it's never been easier to join communities
where you can get mentoring
and get support
there are communities of angel investors who do invest in in startups
it's never been cheaper or easier to start a company
there's never been more software and technology to scale and grow
you know in just a in a short
space of time i would say do what gary's
done
gary publishes
online he's built a personal brand he's attached it to a recurring
revenue model
he's got yeah i also worked for three for free for four years
i'm not sure how replicable
that is
you know
so
build a personal brand
attach it to a business model that is that is where money is flowing
um these are these are positive things you can do
we all have to play the cards we're dealt
you can always find someone who's done better
with better cards
or someone who's been dealt
better cards and you can always find someone who's been dealt worse a cards
no matter who you are on the planet there's someone better there's someone worse
you have to play the cards that you dealt
you cannot sit around waiting for the economic system of the world to be changed
you have to say
you know what
these are the cards i was born at this particular time in this these circumstances
these are my strengths these are my weaknesses
i'm going to play the cards that i' i've dealt
um personal agency is what gets people
to feel good about their life to make progress
and as soon as you play the victim mindset
soon as you say
oh you know what
the answer to all my prayers is gary's going to change the system
you're in serious trouble can i just say one thing back on that
um if we become a society of of individuals
who think only individually and and never consider broader societal problems
we will become a society that becomes unable to fix societal
problems
i'm somebody who has made millions of pounds
betting on the collapse of society the collapse of the middle class
um i don't want to be giving stock tips on the titanic
okay
i i understand i understand that we live in individualized
societies and and it's not popular to say hey you need to protect your society
um
if you don't protect your society your society is going to collapse
and and the british public the american public have a choice to make here
here to protect these what do you want people to do
i want them to get involved
with watch my channel
subscribe to my channel
content on youtube instagram tik tok share it with your friends share it with your mom
understand
and then push for change push for change like our grandparents did
push the politicians
to tax working people less and tax extremely
wealthy wealth orders more so vote for the greens
vote for whoever
gives you that whoever gives you your share of the pip
basic listen this is not football
okay i'm not here
m of the gre
i'm here to protect the working class
so that's their sort of that would be their social and sort of
um political
energy
would be to stand up and fight
but in their in their personal lives are you telling them to
start businesses take big risks work really hard go for it because they can also
i would defer to you guys on that you know i'm not a businessman
i'm an economist
that's what i am you know i made my money by being an economist
i'm a very very good economist
my predictions will be right people can go and watch my predictions
at the beginning of covid
i predicted the entire co crisis
exactly correctly
in may 2020
you know this is you know i'm good at this i'm and listen
i'm never going to come here and say i'm a better businessman
than you and i don't
i'm pretty sure that i'm not
i'm a very very very good economist
this will happen
is there something
that i can do if i'm sat here listening
at home
i
understand everything you said i believe
everything
you said
i i i believe that it's going to get worse for me
do you think
i should still take responsibility of my situation
and fight to make my life
richer better moreful
100%
cuz you you know and i'm sure you know if you're average
british or american if you don't do that
you're not going to be able to turn the heating on
you have to do it you have to do it and i've never once you
i think my opinions
are often mischaracterized
to being anti- ambition
you've read my book do you think i'm anti- ambition
no
i work my tits
off to make money and i want every single
young person
in this country
to be able
to make money
if they
want to
if that's what they want to work towards
but we've created a society
where it's almost impossible
for young listen i've been there i've been at lc
i've been at oxford
i've been in the city i've been in the media i've been in politics
all all of the guys at the top are a bunch of rich idiots
we are not allowing
these smart kids from ordinary backgrounds
to get into those spaces
why why do we pretend we're not doing that
do that i disagree with that you're talking about two types of elite spaces
elite space of elite universities
yeah and you're talking about the elite space of derivatives trading
there's the real economy
yeah where entrepreneurs
do their work
then there's the first derivative which is the banking system
and then there's the second derivative which is rates traders like yourself
right these are these these are places that
normal people don't want to end up most normal people who grow up in normal households
don't
wake up one day and say i want to be a rates trader
on a double derivative of the economy making bets
most people want to start a business that employs
people and they want to grow that business and be successful
do you think that
starting a business
is a realistic
high success probability chance
of ordinary poor people becoming rich i i know that economies thrive when entrepreneurs are active
and it's not just the entrepreneurs
they create
is
our viewers can do and most of them will end up rich you only need 1%
to improve the whole economy there's a really interesting stat that says globally around 65%
of ultra high net worth individuals are
self-made
approximately 19%
primarily
primarily inherited their wealth and about 16%
inherited wealth but significantly grew it through their own ventures
so 65%
of the ultra high worth individuals globally
are self-made
does that not mean that if i want to become
an ultra high networth person it's going to come down to
listen
we are just come off the back of the golden age of capitalism
when ordinary
people
like my dad you know i grew up in ilford
it's in east london it's a very immigrant
area
most of my friends i grew up with come from
pakistani
indian immigrant backgrounds
they come over with nothing
they worked really hard they made money they had their own assets we had a period
where ordinary
people
could
make money and could make wealth
so obviously
we are now in a period
where
there are rich people who made money during that period
but it's over now i'm seeing ordinary people making money all the time
okay so you're telling our viewers they're idiots why are they not making money
i'm not telling anyone they're an idiot i'm saying that if it's that easy
okay all right fine go and buy dan's book read it and become a millionaire
because dan thinks it's easy
to become a millionaire
being an entrepreneur
but i suspect having not been an entrepreneur
that most of the people who've read your book are not millionaires
everything you've touched has turned to gold
you turned yourself to academia
you got
an amazing
qualification
you turned yourself to banking
you became 2 million a year
you turned yourself to being a writer
you become sunday
times bestseller
you turn yourself to content creating you get 800,000
followers
and you and now you sit there after all of that evidence
and say oh no it's all over guys it's all
i'm smart
enough to do it but you guys are not smart enough to do
if if you think you can teach
you've got your book
if you think you canach you say
you're smart enough but they're not smart enough
i i wonder if um we do have a bit of an education problem
at the at the heart of this because i was thinking about your sister
and i was like right if i was the ceo
of gary's
sister
what would i do
there's two things i do right now the first is okay where's where what what marketplace
is really valuing
an ability
to write
and write an impactful
way i go write you need to start an instagram
page
because
i've seen what happened
with j sh
this guy's
pulling
in tens of millions
a year
because he took like you
know
nice words that were motivational
poetic put them on there and i also youtube
needs to get to youtube
because
if she can talk like you
then she's going to do exceptionally well on youtube as well
um but the old
there's not going to be a great economy necessarily
for someone who's doing poetry
in many other places other than one i'm saying is the internet
but in school we don't teach this there's no youtube class for youtube
and and it's such a huge part of the economy i mean
i mean me and you have seen that it's there's been this decentralization
of media where the megaphone was growing at 20% a year the me
the megaphone was people watching start a youtube become ent
it's the internet isn't
e i'm not say
works for most people stepen for most people no it doesn't work
it doesn't work
why are we pretending
it does
but i what what i what i would say
is if in school
we taught young kids a couple
new things and we stopped teaching them about pythagoras's
theorem
which by the way chat gbt
is going to do for you with your eyes closed
and we taught them
about the new economy of the internet
about the ability to start a shop
and i
it's crazy that
i
the school system was designed in such a way where they put me in exclusion
unit because i was so preoccupied
with doing
business deals at school
and my headmaster
came on t
national tv on what i lied to and said
yeah we unexp
beled him eventually
because he made the school so much money but the system
was punishing
me
for entre for entrepreneurship
and it wasn't teaching me anything about the the new economy which is which is technology
st do you think it matters if the percentage
of young people who are able to
achieve financial freedom
and have a family is shrinking
so do i think it matters if the percentage of young people that are able
to
are you saying
attain wealth and have a family yeah achieve financial freedom and have a family
i think that's a really big problem listen
i think that's a really big problem
i agree i know listen and i know you've got this podcast
and i know you inspire
young people and i think that's a good thing
i think it's a good thing that you inspire
young people
to go out
and work hard and try and achieve
something
but i'm an economist
and what i see is the percentage of young people who make it shrinking
and i think if you combine those two things you reach a really dangerous place
because we go and tell the young people
it's there for you to start a business
and at the same time
the number of people who make it is 10%
5% 2%
1%
and
there will always
be that one person who makes
it
there will always be that steven
bartley
in every country in the world who's making it through
you know what i'm saying but
the systematic
issue matters stephen
c can we can we not change the education
system so that when i was
and they threw me in the exclusion
unit
which made me which would could so easily
have made me think
that i was a failure
because my brothers who went jason went to lsc
okay and became very much like you and now works in my company
um managing my investments
he in that education system was rewarded so i sat there as a kid thinking
rich and successful
my older brother jason
because he can do maths
and i thought i'm going to be a failure
because i like this thing called entrepreneurship
and i have adhd
so i can't pay attention in lessons
what i'm saying is if the education
system was designed in such a way where people like me who were entrepreneurial
who were interested in the internet and couldn't stop playing video games
were clapped for and said oh my god double down on that
yeah um i think
the net benefit
when you think about what the backbone of the economy is which is entrepreneurs
starting businesses
would be profound
for this country here
yeah but that
but but i i think that i believe
there
needs to be such a radical
overhaul
of our education
system if we want to stand a chance of capitalizing
on what the economy is today
yeah i i think
i think you could probably
change
the education
system in a lot of ways that could improve
it but you're kind of changing
the education
system
on the titanic
what my my perspective
is i can tell you with a very very high rate of certainty
if you don't fix this problem of the wealth being sucked out of the middle class
98%
of people will be in poverty in this country in 70 years i agree with you
this is the thing
i agree
that you can't
have a group of people at the very top that own all the assets
and all the money or else i mean it's going to come from somewhere
and i remember the day that i printed off the jobseekers
allowance
form
when i was stealing chicago
town
piz
10 years ago in my room in mosside
in manchester
i remember what it feels
like
to not have my parents speaking to me
to be
have all these ccj
letters and baith letters on my desk
and really
have no answer
how how to get out of the situation to the point that i was like shoplifting
i'd call the justy
driver and then trying to persuade him just to give me the food
that was that was that was 10 years ago for me so i i it's not
i've not forgotten
the the those years of my life
so i understand what it is
to be in that
situation
and on an individual level i need need some answers
because i'm not going to wait for these people in
the parliament to fix my life for me so i need some individual answers
and then i do also care about the bigger picture so i'm not like here
as someone that just wants to
acrew loads of wealth myself of course listen let's be honest
no one like
there's not many human beings that wouldn't like more money
so i try and acknowledge that bias
but what i'm the the the the big issue i have is
is is how
and from my personal experience
as someone that now employs
hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of people here in london
up in manchester in our offices
i there are a set of things that would make me leave this country
if it became increasingly
less
friendly to entrepreneurs i reckon if we come back here in 5 years time
i reckon i'll employ
500 more
people in the uk
and actually
as you look around
this room you can see the age of them these are young
people
yeah
um
there are things you could do to make me not do that
i mean it's probably worth pointing out that we're not taxing
wealth and you're leaving the country anyway stephen no i haven't left the country
okay you're going
i'm i'm a tax resident
here i pay my taxes
here and i have zero
intent in changing
that
i'm also on dragon
you know so we're investing
a lot of money in uk
businesses
but listen
i want to raise i want to tax only
high levels of wealth only high levels of wealth
and listen don't get me wrong i understand very rich people will complain
and very rich people will say just like they did in dickens
i'm going to throw my businesses
i'm going to throw my taxes
my
my businesses and my factories into the sea
stephen your viewers are here
you listen steven your viewers are here you are a very wealthy person
they are are paying 20 30 40 50%
you should be paying your fair share stephen you should
i think that i should
pay more tax especially when
um
i don't think my kids should get
should should benefit
from my wealth
and maybe this is a controversial
opinion but i actually don't
i don't think i should be able to pass down my assets to my children
you can't it's 40% tax i think it should be more 4 yeah
let's not pretend rich people don't successfully
pass their ass their children i'm just telling you now
i do
think i'd be robbing
my children of something
from the background
that i came from if my ch my child
gets
if my child
has gets tens of millions
let's say even
when i die i don't think that should happen
well i agree
people say
when i talk about
my sister
people like why don't you just give your sister
a load of money
listen
my sister works hard
she's a smart person she works hard
she produces
good work
i want to live in a society
where people like my sister
are able to support
themselves with the work that they do but we we're destroying that society
who would pay her
the the customers you know this the situ so you want her to start a business
she is a business
yeah
yeah and i want people like her to be to be taxed
less
so that
what i want is
ordinary
working
people
to be tax
less so they have more money in their pocket listen
the reason we had the thriving
art scene in the 60s
is because we had a thriving middle class
that could go and buy the new fashions
and buy the new records and then that created
this thriving art scene
now we have a middle class which is struggling to pay the bills so they can't
they can't buy stuff they you know
my syst makes theater shows
the only people who go to the theater
are rich people now but back back in the day you know theater
was something that was more accessible
you want you want the arts
i've got to mate use a fashion designer right
nowadays
there's all of the business is
super fast super cheap super disposable fashion
or unbelievably
expensive high-end
because that's the economy we've created
i want you go to japan which is a less unequal society
the restaurants are good quality restaurants for ordinary people because
a good capitalist society will produce things for the people with money
in the case of theater
where have the theater consumers moved to where are they getting their entertainment now
well
what you have is a very rich
group of people who will still go to the theater
and they will pay a lot but then you have
a large group of people who are relatively
cash scarce
and they will try to get their entertainment
in cheaper ways of course you know what i mean
they're spending their time watching your youtube channel well exactly my you
which is free by the way yeah but you get paid from it
you get the youtube
honest it's only in the last couple of months
that i started
to make any money
because i don't do my own
um editing
so
and you i mean you'll know
but in the first few
years you're paying
yourself
to
do it you know what i mean
like i think people
some
times
massively overestimate
the amount of money this is entrepreneurs
entrepreneurs
go through 2 three four
5 years worth of struggle
to get to the point where they're
successful
and it feels pretty horrific
that you say oh finally when i make it you take it
um and then the advisers to entrepreneurs just 10 million is quite a lot of money
so you know you can be worth 9 million
and not be paying anything more but what if i just raise 1 million for investment
into my company
but that then
like i do if i'm if if i'm raising money all the way along
and my investors are saying i'm sorry i don't invest in the uk economy
because it's wealth taxes and all that sort of stuff it's anti- wealth
and then i just have to move my company overseas
well i want to create a situation where the uk consumer is so strong
that you have to invest
in the uk
you don't have to be here to sell to
them
if you're looking to take the next step in your tech career
you'll want to hear about our sponsor inuit
i've always believed
that if you want to do your best work
you have to put yourself in the right environment
you want to work with the best you want to work with the best tech technologists
who are leading
innovation
with data and ai
and this is what you can expect into it they're growing
their tech careers building an ai driven expert platform
that connects people to all the money they deserve
the cutting edge tech they are developing in products like turbo tax credit karma
quick books and mailchimp
are helping around a 100 million customers and businesses put more money in their pockets
having a mission-driven culture
is something i really align with because it's all about solving
complex customer
problems with rapid experimentation
to move faster
quite similar to the culture i want to foster at my companies
if this sounds like you and you want to grow your tech career
working alongside the best
check out intuit.com
careers
they also offer hybrid work and a very inclusive culture with offices in atlanta
new york san diego the bay area toronto
and around the world head over to in
nitc
careers to explore their opportunities
quick one i want to talk to you about our sponsor whoop
a business i'm also an investor in
and if you follow me on instagram you probably noticed that recently i've picked up running
which i'm very much enjoying and it started out as a challenge
but it's now evolved into something i do almost
daily it is one of those things that's pushing me to be better every single day
but here's the thing to me progress isn't just about pushing harder it's also about training
in a smarter
way
which is where my whoop
comes in
whoop doesn't just track my workouts
it tells me how ready my body is to take them on
before i've even started the workout
a few years ago we ran a study called project
p are and it found that runners who adjusted their training based on their recovery
scores
improved their 5k times by an average of 2 minutes
and 40 seconds while reducing injury risk by over 30%
and they did it while training less
so if you're looking for this type of guidance when it comes to your training
head over to join.
woop.com ceo and get a 30-day trial with zero commitment that's join.
woop.com
ceo
let me know how you get on
so so do we all agree on this premise
though that gary's
saying which is the very
the ultra
rich
which we can classify
as being
worth more than you're saying
we say 10 10 million is the line that we campaign
for
okay
we
we think that they should pay a greater share of the tax
and then the qu if you agree with that premise the question then becomes
yes but how yeah
well they already do 1% pay 30%
i want to be clear
that's the top 1% of taxpayers
which is not the top 1% of richest people mind you i'm also not necessarily saying
um what's fair i'm saying what's practically
possible right so like you could you could come up with the world's most fair
on a back of a napkin this is what's fair
but whether you can implement it is a very difficult thing
the problem is wealth is completely
mobile
now it's really you can live work from
anywhere
the houses
dan yeah it's land
is that mobile you going rip you can't rip the country out of the
out of the sea there's very few i've never met any
seriously wealthy people who own a lot of houses
you honestly think that the entire housing stock of the uk is not valuable
yeah no it is but
78% is owned by baby boomers they just own they've they've bought a house in 1992
they own the house personally i think that that house ownership especially when you consider mortgages
is relatively unequally distributed
that is by the way the most equally distribut
young people have now had the commercial
property
the land the natural
by pension funds
so
you're the viewers own it do they
no they're owned by if they own a pension
fun
most of those commercial
what the distribution of pion
what is the distribution of pensions what percentage of pensions is owned by top 1%
the
i wouldn't know off the top of my head but with pensions
but i know i know that ob
obviously
wealth concentrates
at the top but here's the one thing keep in mind wealthy group are not necessarily
a static group
there was a study
of
the richest people
in
and most of those families are poor today
or they they've gone down in value today
if the richest people in 1900
had have just simply kept their wealth there'd be 16,000
more billionaires
but but they they don't
um you know in wealth management in banks yeah they have this thing called the
um succession planning
so succession
planning
is where they try and figure
out how to not to screw
it up across
generations
and they're they're notoriously
bad at it it's very hard to keep wealth in generations down in the 20th
century
we had two world wars and a
holocaust that redistributed
wealth
i would prefer not to have that again yeah yeah yeah
i'm with you i want a affluent
middle class
i i really
do
so where's
the we
going to come from
you want
to
just
you're going
to create
your
entrepreneurs
entrepreneur
economies that are friendly towards wealth creation and entrepreneurship
was the last time you had a government that wasn't let's grow let's grow let's
grow
it's not working
for the people
daniel
no the problem is is that they need to step
back they need to let shrink
let shrink
let
shrink
our viewers should keep
close
ey on donald trump and elon musk
because they're doing what you're asking
it'll be interesting to see what happens
right
it's too soon to tell if you were trying to grow the uk economy
would you not take america
approach because they seem to be much more successful at growing growing their economy
i think
i mean of course
when we talk about slashing
of the state they're going to use these examples
like oh there's this wasteful
government building
everybody
wants to slash
government
waste
of course i'm not going to fight against slashing
government
waste
um
i'm from the uk
you know i saw the austerity years
i've seen what's happened to local services
i've seen what's happened to things like the police like like education
you know especially things like youth services
um you slash the state you fire a load of people you know
what does the state okay yeah if you can get rid of state corruption yes 100%
if you can get rid of state waste 100% you know
this is how single moms feed their kids
stephen
you want to stop that
no i'm saying that
slashing the state
i don't think it's going to work
um to be honest i think tariffs is is not an uninteresting
discussion i think yeah of course tax avoidance is something you need to get rid of
really
i would like to take a step back look at the country and say
what is the state of the country
what what the people need
you know we have a country
here where the housing stock is falling
apart
and we're letting it fall apart
because
those houses
are owned by ordinary people who don't have any money
if you want the country to work for ordinary people
you need ordinary people to have money i'm always reminded of mr beast
he goes to places in africa
and he spends
quid
and he gives a kid eyesight
who would have been blind for the rest of their life
for 500 quid
why are kids in africa blind who could be given sight for 500 quid
because they don't
have
any money
this is what happens when you drain your middle class
you
this will end up like that you know you know
i've got a friend who
went to india
last week
he said there were people lying on the street outside with rotting limbs
you know that is what happens when you when you disempower
when you take the money away from your middle class
you've got to protect the middle class
if the middle class had
money
then there would be unbelievable
business opportunities for selling
goods and services like your business to the middle class so would you tax daniel more
i don't know if daniel's worth more than 10 million pounds it sounds like he is
um is
i mean i think
i want to make it clear right
you people you make
5%
on your wealth
so if daniel's
worth 100 million
he's making £5 million
we're only trying to tax you 1%
i think if you are worth 100 million
you're making 5 million pound passive income
you can afford to pay
a million pound tax a year you're going to still keep getting rich
the truth
is
even if we were to tax these billionaires
1% a year they would still squeeze the rest out this is not
this is not about morality
this is just cold
hard economic analysis that i have made a lot of money betting on so closing arguments
then chaps
um i'll start with you gary based on everything we've discussed today
um what is
i'm going to ask you to to give me two perspectives which is
if i'm a young individual in this country right now
what should i do to protect myself and my family and to feed my family
what kind of behaviors
what strategy should i drop
there
but also then from a
government level i know we have some politicians that listen because they message me
what should
politicians
be doing to to fix
the issue that we're all clearly identify
which is the collaps of the middle class the collaps of sort of working-class
people and the the
the increased wealth of the rich
i think
what i would like young people to understand is that
this gets worse this getss much much worse it will get much worse
um relatively quickly poverty will increase relatively quickly it will become increasingly
difficult almost impossible to make any serious money
prepare yourself for that prepare yourself when you consider your finances
when you consider your plans for having a family
um
this
gets
worse
and it's going to be really
really hard
it's going to be
a big mental
health
problem
for a lot of young
people
um so speak to people and understand that
um my youtube videos are there g's economics people don't understand what's happening
um
after that
you've got to do all the right things
yeah i mean i don't disagree
with you
you've got to work hard you've got to study the right things
um i i think it's a great shame we have made subjects like the arts
um a thing which
you you're not allowed
if you come from po poor backgrounds
you cannot work in arts
i'm sorry
you can't pay the bills you can't
so you have to go and study
ai and computing
and you know maybe social media although we have to be honest social media doesn't
pay for most
people
um
you have to realize the reality of your situation it's very very very
very bad
that doesn't mean you don't work that doesn't mean you don't aspire
you work damn hard because you have to
but if you manage
to make enough
money to even
support
a family
you should be proud of yourself
that that's the number one thing
um but
recognize
this can be changed this can be changed our grandparents our great-grandparents
fought
for our biggest share of the pie and they got it
they got healthcare
they got education
they got housing they got food
our young people can have that as well
but they won't get it unless they fight for it so i would encourage people
to
educate themselves support my work get involved politically but also work hard
support your friends and family try and make money because you'll have to
if you don't play politics
i guarantee you the other side will play politics and that means
your kids and your grandkids live in poverty so you have to do both
with regards to politicians
um i got mixed feelings about a lot of politicians
the truth is i think a lot of politicians are very rich and and ultimately
they don't care they're protected
a crisis of inequality
looks fantastic
from the top
and i think that's why the three of us can sit here and say
things will be fine
because for us they will be fine
and for our kids they will be fine
but for our viewers
kids they won't be fine
um the politicians are not going to try and save you
i'm going to try and make sure they do it but i don't think they will
listen
my plan
is not to get concessions from politicians
my plan is to get 5 million followers on the internet and bully the politicians
so that they have to give us what we need so i would support people
to get behind me get behind my campaign but also
understand what's happening educate your friends and your family and just crucially to understand
this is going to be a long fight so be strong
keep your people around you
but be ready for what's to come
i am i see hint and some of the things you've said recently of you
going into politics yourself at some point
stephen i'm in politics
but i me politics actively
listen i i do not want to be an mp
i do not want to be chancellor
i do not want to be prime
minister
if we get to a point where i feel that that is something that is achieved
when is the best way to
fix this problem
i will be open to it this is not plan a this is not
you know
would you like to be prime minister i suspect probably not right like this is
i'll be honest i i
am quite uncomfortable with even the level of um public profile
that i have at the moment
which is you know it's much less than what you have but it stresses
me out and
it's weird we spoke about it before we were shooting
um
i don't want to can you imagine
i i don't want to be prime minister i don't want to be an mp
um
but i'm serious about this work that i do
and if we reach a point that i think
that is the best way to do it
i will consider it but i would much rather
be able to influence the mps
from the sideline to influence the politicians from the sidelines
and for that person you just gave advice to who should they be voting for
well we don't have an election for listen
politics is not football
okay this is not about i'm labor i'm conservative
i'm republican
i'm democrat
you're losing your houses
here
you you're losing your houses
your kids will be in poverty
and you're going to see
both trump and the republicans
and karma
and labor
who are supposed to be on the opposite side of the political spectrum
they will both fail
because they will not take action on growing wealth inequality
and
i'll
be
right
on
that
you
know
bring
me
back
in a few
years
i'll
be
right
on
that
and
um that shows you it's not about i think this factionalism
is unbelievable
damaging to our societies
especially in the us where there's so much hatred behind it where suddenly
i'm on this side you're on that side
we're going to shake hands after this
nothing
we will you know it's there's no hatred
here
but if you allow yourself to be divided
from half of your country
and you allow we're seeing it growing
tensions
racial tensions gender tensions
if you allow yourself to be divided
they will win they will win so you need to vote for
whoever is going to protect your houses
and if you want to know who that is
come and check gary's
economics
before the election
and i will tell you who it's going to be
daniel nice closing arguments personal and social a a few things
um i read gary's bookin it's brilliant and regardless of
um
regardless of whether you actually
like economics
it's a brilliant story it's a really i read it in about two or three days
um and it'll it'll eventually be a good movie as well
um i agree with a lot of what gary's saying
um there is a collapse of the middle class and it probably will get worse
and
the traditional
middle class jobs
that came out of the back of the industrial
age
mature
industrial
revolution
system
th those are collapsing and it's globalizing we're seeing technology move opportunities all over the world
um and wealth inequality it has a cause
wealth inequality itself is a scoreboard
and there's a cause for what led up to wealth inequality
and the cause in my mind is technology
technology is moving the those opportunities around and it's changing things
we already have big governments
we have huge amounts of taxes we're at record levels of tax taes
um
wealth has never been more mobile
it's not about what's fair it's about what you can practically
get away with it's about what you can
actually
implement
um and
it's going to be very very
as gary said it's going to be very very very hard
to tax people who have digital
businesses
who can live and work from anywhere i know that firsthand
um that it's incredibly
mobile
with that said at a micro level oh sorry at a macro level big picture
we do know that there is a correlation
between economic freedom
where the government gets out of your way
and low poverty rates
and we know that as soon as governments become big
high taxes high regulations
it actually drops down
a category and we see poverty goes up from 10% to 30% so triples
um so
constricting economic freedom is never a good idea if you look at the data
at a micro level there's never been a greater opportunity
for anyone who's ambitious and entrepreneurial
to go and start a company
it's cheaper than ever to start a company
you can do what gary's done which is publish content
build a following
figure out how to monetize it
you can create products and services and sell them to anywhere in the world
um you're an example of someone who started with nothing and became a millionaire
in your 20s
and then again in your 30s with a completely
different thing
he became a millionaire
in his 20s
and then again in his 30s is's a bestselling
author and a content creator
i did it in my 20s my 30s and now my 40s
um starting from scratch
so
it's it's not normal that three guys
our agage could have done that over and over again
it's because we are living in a time where there is incredible
opportunities
but you have to be tapped into those opportunities
you never heard about it at school you never heard about it at university
you're going to have to learn the skills
to get tapped into those opp opportunities
but there are definitely
ways that you can succeed
in the world that we're living in
and on that macro point who should we be voting for because some of your
thinking in policy
suggestions
through this conversation align more with trump elon
the american mission now where they're welcoming millionaires
they're trying to create a really entrepreneurship
friendly environment
they're doing the doge dismantling
of sort of government waste
i i agree with gary it's not football you don't have a team you swing
you should be a swing voter
you should vote
every single election
you should make them work hard for your vote
and you should is trump going to succeed
though you should see it's too soon to tell
but he made a prediction
so i'm inviting you to make a prediction
he said five years time we come back here we're going to see that trump
i think
i think a lot of
very
wealthy
people are going to move
move to the usa
um you're going to get a lot of people from all over the world he's playing
to win
and he wants
rich people and entrepreneurs
and investors
to come into the us and be based there he's creating golden visas and open visas
and the success metric here is the middle class get richer and more affluent
what i actually
think will happen as a result of all of that you will see rising living standards
in the usa
and you'll see a detriment
to the places where those people live
it's not a good thing
to have the people who pay the majority of the taxes which is 1%
of people paying 30% of taxes
if those people leave
the bills
get spread across everybody else
well we'll have to do a part two and we shall see
um
i want to thank you both
for the work that you do
because
i'm a big fan of both of you
i watch gary's
videos all the time helps me to
understand another perspective
on what i'm typically hearing out out on the internet
or that i hear on twitter about what's going on in the world
and i think i really
respect
and admire
people that can do what both of you have done today
which is to exchange and listen to ideas in the pursuit of answers
and that's why i'd highly recommend anybody
regardless of whether you agree with everything or some things or
or or just a little bit
to go and follow gary's channel on youtube called gary's economics
because it's a great source of
information
from someone who has done it from understands the world from another perspective but also
someone who's providing a narrative
which i actually think there's we kind of talked about before you started
there's a big gap in the market for
there are a lot of people
like me and dan out on the internet that are talking about entrepreneurship
and finance and how to make money
but there aren't enough people talking about wealth inequality from the perspective as gary sees
um and that are providing more sort of
collectivist and sort of society
wide
solutions and answers and sort of explanations as to why that's ultimately happening
i do think
i do think because i know you dan i hope i know myself
i do think that we we all want
the uk to survive
and i think we all believe that the way that the uk survives
isn't necessarily a couple of ultra rich people getting more money
it is
sort of social mobility and it's allowing people that are at the very bottom
to create opportunities and to succeed we all agree upon that even if we agree
disagree sorry on the causes and the solutions to that
um
i'd also highly recommend
everybody to go check out the trading
game because everybody's
talking about this this book and
i think it's what four weeks at the moment on the sunday
times
besteller
list
four weeks number one number one
four weeks number one
which is
an incredible
achievement
but it speaks to what's in this book the way that the story is told
but also
the timeliness
of this message
so i'd highly recommend
everybody to go check it out i'm going to put a link below
so that everybody
can go and do it and if you just look at some of the
um
the the testimonials
for this book it's
profound i hear people describe it as like
unforgettable
on one end and then sad
on the other end because that's the
nature of the reality
it speaks to and i highly recommend everybody to go check out
dan priestley's
entreprene
revolution
but also
your website has all of your resources
and tools on it so i'll link that on the screen what's the
danel priest.com danel priest.com thank you both for your generosity
really really appreciate it thanks for bringing us together
no matter where in the world it seems like everyone
is drinking matcha
and there's a good chance that that matcha you're drinking
is made by a company
that i've invested
more than seven figures
in
who are a sponsor
of this podcast
called perfect
ted
because they're the brand used globally by cafes like blank street coffee
and joe and the juice
and many many more
not only can you get perfect ted match in cafes
but you can now also make it at home
much cheaper
in seconds
using our flavored matcha powders that i have here in front of me
perfect ted matcher is ceremonial
grade and source from japan it is smooth
it is naturally sweet not like those bitter grassy
matches
that i tried
before perfect
ted
and if you are one of those people that have told yourself
you don't like matcha
it's probably because you haven't tried our perfect ted matcha
and you can find perfect ted matcha in the uk and tesco
sainsbury
holland and barett and in waitrose or albert hine if you're in the netherlands
and on amazon in the usa or'll get the full range online at perfect ted.com
where you can get 40%
off your first order with code steve even
this has always blown my mind a little bit 53%
of you that listen to this show regularly
haven't yet subscribed
to the show
so could i ask you for a favor
if you
like
the show
and you
like
what we
do
here
and you want
to
support
us
the free
simple way that you can do just that is by hitting the subscribe
button
and my commitment
to you is if you do that
then i'll do everything in my power
me and my team
to make sure that this show is better for you every
single
week
we'll listen to your feedback
we'll find the guest that you want me to speak to
and we'll continue to do what we do thank you so much much
[music]