..
. the big question for me in that timeline is why didn't we do it sooner?
Why did it take so long?
Why did we wait until after 12,000 years ago
really after 10,000 years ago, to start seeing the beginnings of civilization?
The following is a conversation with Graham Hancock
a journalist and author who, for over 30 years
has explored the controversial possibility that there existed a lost civilization during the last Ice Age and that it was destroyed in a global cataclysm some 12
000 years ago.
He is the presenter of the Netflix documentary series Ancient Apocalypse
the second season of which has just been released and it's focused on the distant past of the Americas
a topic I recently discussed with the archeologist Ed Barnhart.
Let me say that Ed represents the kind of archeologist
scholar, I love talking to on the podcast.
Extremely knowledgeable, humble, open-minded, and respectful in disagreement.
I'll do many more podcasts on history, including ancient history.
Our distant past is full of mysteries and I find it truly exciting to explore those mysteries with people both on the inside and the outside of the mainstream
in the various disciplines involved.
This is a Lex Fridman podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description and now
dear friends, here's Graham Hancock.
Let's start with a big foundational idea that you have about human history
that there was a, an advanced Ice Age civilization that came before and perhaps seeded what people now call the six cradles of civilization: Mesopotamia
Egypt, India, China, Andes, and Mesoamerica.
So let's talk about this idea that you have.
Mm-hmm.
Can you, at the highest possible level
describe it?
It would be better to describe it as a foundational sense of puzzlement and incompleteness
uh, in the story that we are taught about our past
which envisages more or less there have been a few ups and downs
but more or less a straightforward evolutionary progress.
Uh, we start out as hunter-foragers then we become agriculturalists.
The hunter-fother- forager phase could go back hundreds of thousands of years.
Uh, I mean this is where it's also
it's also important to mention that anatomically modern humans
um, were not the only humans.
We, we had Neanderthals from, I don't know
400,000 years ago to about 40,000 years ago.
They were certainly human because anatomically modern humans interbred with them and we carry
we carry Neanderthal genes.
There were the Denisovans maybe 300,000 to perhaps even as recently as 30
000 years ago and again interbreeding took place.
They're obviously a human species so, you know
we've got this background of humans who didn't look quite like us
and then we have anatomically modern humans and I think the earliest anatomically modern human skeletal remains are from Jebel Irhoud in Morocco and date to about 310
000 years ago.
So the question is what were our ancestors doing after that?
And I think we can include the Neanderthals and the Denisovans in that
in that general picture.
And why did it take so long?
This is one of the puzzles, one of the questions that bother me.
Why did it take so long when we have creatures who are physically identical to us?
We, we cannot actually weigh and measure their brains
but from the work that's been done on
on the crania it looks like they had the same brains that we do with the same
the same wiring.
So, so if we've been around, uh
for 300,000-plus years at least and if ultimately in our future
uh, was, uh, the, the, the process to create civilization or civilizations
why didn't it happen sooner?
Why did it take so long?
Why, why, why was it such a long time?
Even the story of, of anatomically modern humans has kept on changing.
Um, I, I remember a time when it was said that there hadn't been anatomically modern humans before 50
000 years ago and then it became 196
000 years ago with the findings in Ethiopia and then 310
000 years ago.
Um, there, there's a lot of, a lot of missing pieces in the
in the puzzle there.
Um, but the big question for me in that timeline is why didn't we do it sooner?
Why did it take so long?
Why, why, why did we wait until after 12
000 years ago, really after 10,000 years ago to start seeing the beginnings
what are selected as the beginnings of civilization
uh, in, in places like, like Turkey
for example?
And then there's a relatively slow process of adopting agriculture and
and by 6,000 years ago we see ancient Sumer
uh, emerging as a civilization.
And w- we're then in the Predynastic period in Ancient Egypt as well
6,000, 6,000 years ago beginning to see definite signs of what will become the
the Dynastic civilization of Egypt about, about 5
000 years ago.
And interestingly, round about the same time you have the Indus Valley civilization popping up out of nowhere
and, and by the way, the Indus Valley civilization was a lost civilization
uh, until the 1920s when, uh, railway workers accidentally stumbled across some
some ruins.
I've been to Harappa and Mohenjo-daro, uh
and these are extraordinarily beautifully, centrally planned
uh, cities.
These, th- clearly they're the work of a
an already sophisticated, uh, civilization.
One of the things that strikes me about the Indus Valley civilization is that we find a
a steatite seal, uh, of an individual seated in a
a recognizable yoga posture and that seal is 5
000 years old, uh, and the yoga posture is Mulabandhasana which involves.
..
. a real contortion of the ankles and twisting the f- feet back.
It's an advanced yoga posture.
So there it is 5,000 years ago and that then raises the question
well, how long did yoga take to get to that place when it was already so advanced 5- 5
000 years ago?
What's the, what's the background to this?
China, the Yellow, the Yellow River, uh
civilization.
Again, it's around about the same period.
Five to 6,000 years ago you get these first signs of something happening so it's very odd that
that all around the world, uh, we have this
this sudden upsurge of civilization about 6,000 years ago
preceded by what seems like a, a natural evolutionary process that would lead to a
to a civilization.
Um, and yet certain ideas being, being carried down and manifested and expressed in
in many of these, in many of these different civilizations.
I just find that, that whole idea very puzzling and
and very, and very disturbing, uh, especially when I look at this radical break that takes place in not just the human story but the story of all life on Earth
which was the last great cataclysm that the earth went through
uh, which was the Younger Dryas event.
Uh, it was an extinction level event.
Uh, that's when all the great megafauna of the Ice Age went extinct.
It's after that, it's, it's after that event that we start seeing this
what are, what are taken to be the beginnings of the first gradual steps towards civilization.
We come out of the Upper Paleolithic as it's defined
the old f- end of the old Stone Age
and into the Neolithic.
And that's when the wheels are supposedly set in motion to start civilization rolling.
But, but what happened before that and why did that
why did that suddenly happen then?
And I can't help feeling, and I've felt this for a very  long while
that there are major missing pieces in our story.
It's often said that I'm claiming to have proved that there was an advanced lost civilization in the Ice Age and I am not claiming to have proved that.
That is a hypothesis that I am putting forward
uh, to answer some of the questions that I have
uh, about, about pre-history.
Um, and, and, um, I think it's worthwhile to inquire into those possibilities because the Younger Dryas event was
uh, a massive, uh, global cataclysm
whatever caused it, uh, and, and
um, it's strange that just after it we start seeing these
these first signs.
So the current understanding in mainstream archeology is that after the Younger Dryas is when the civilizations popped up in different places of the globe with a lot of similarities
but they popped up independently from one another.
Yeah, independently and, and, um, by coincidence.
And by coincidence those, the, those big civilizations that we all remember as the first civilizations
Sumer, Egypt, the Indus Valley civilization, China
they all pop up at the, pretty much the same time.
Um, that is, that i- that is the mainstream view
yeah.
And they don't just pop up.
They kind of build up gradually.
First there's some settlements- Oh, definitely.
Yes.
.
..
and then there's different dynamics of how they build up and the role d- the role of agriculture in that is
uh, also non-obvious, but it's just, there's a first
a kind of settlement, a stabilization of where the people are living
then they start using agriculture, then they start getting urban centers and that kind of stuff.
It seems like an entirely reasonable argument.
Every- everything, everything about that makes sense.
There is no doubt that you're seeing, uh
evolutionary progress, uh, social evolution taking, taking place in those thousands of years before Sumer
uh, emerges.
But what's happening now, uh, r- really I spent much of the '90s and the late 1980s investigating this issue of a lost civilization.
I wrote a series of books about it.
But by 2002 when I published a book called Underworld
which was the re- most massive and most heavy book that I've ever written because I was writing very defensively at the time.
Um, by the time I finished that book my wife Santa and I spent seven years scuba diving all around the world looking for structures underwater often led by local fishermen or local divers to anomalies that they'd seen underwater.
By the time that book was finished I
I thought, "Actually I've done this story.
I've walked the walk.
I, I really don't have much more to say about it.
" And I, I, I turned e- in another direction and I
I wrote a book called Supernatural Meetings with the Ancient Teachers of Mankind
recently retitled, uh, Visionary.
And that was about the role of.
..
fundamentally about the role of psychedelics in, in the evolution of human
human culture.
And I didn't think that I would go back to the lost civilization issue.
But Gobekli Tepe in Turkey kept on forcing itself upon me
the more and more discoveries there, the 11
600-year date from Enclosure D which has the two largest megalithic pillars.
And I, I reached a point where I
I realized I have to get back in
I have to get back in the water and I have to investigate this again.
And, and Gobekli Tepe was a game changer but I think it's a game changer for everything because Gobekli Tepe
the, uh, extraordinary nature of it, we're looking at a major megalithic site which is at least 5
500 years older than, say, Ġgantija in Malta which is
was previously considered to be the oldest megalithic site in the world.
And, uh, this led of course to a huge amount of interest and attention both from
uh, the Turkish government who see the potential
tourism potential of, of having the world's oldest megalithic site
and, and from archeologists.
And this in turn has led to exploration and excavation throughout the region.
And what they're finding throughout that whole region around Gobekli Tepe
uh, and going down into Syria and further down into the Jordan Valley as far as Jericho
uh, and even across a bit of the Mediterranean into Cyprus
uh, is what Turkish archeologists are now calling the Taš Tepeler civilization
they're calling it a civilization, the Stone Hills civilization.
Uh, with, uh-.
..
very definite identifying characteristics: semi-subterranean, circular structures
the use of T-shaped, uh, megalithic pillars
sometimes not anywhere near as big as those at Gobekli Tepe.
It's clear that Gobekli Tepe now was not the beginning of this process.
It was actually, in a way, the end of this process.
It was, uh, the summation of everything that that Stone Hills civilization had
had achieved.
Uh, but what, what is becoming clear is that this is a period between- before the foundation of Gobekli Tepe
as far as we know, that date of 11
600 years ago is the oldest date for Gobekli Tepe.
But of course, there's a lot of Gobekli Tepe still underground
so we w- we can't say for sure that that's the oldest
but it's the oldest so far, uh
excavated.
What we're, what we're seeing, uh, is that in that whole region around there
there was- something was in motion, and it began to go into motion round about the beginning of the Younger Dryas.
And, and this is where these two dates are really important.
The Younger Dryas, I'll round the figures off
begins around 12,800 years ago and it ends around 11
600 years ago.
So Gobekli Tepe's construction date, if it is 11
600 years ago, if they don't find older materials
marks the end of the Younger Dryas.
Um, but the beginning of the Younger Dryas
we're already seeing the stirrings of the kind of culture that manifests in full form
uh, at Gobekli Tepe.
Uh, and, and after the construction of Gobekli Tepe
in fact even during the construction of Gobekli Tepe
uh, we see agriculture beginning to be adopted.
The, the people who created Gobekli Tepe were all hunter-foragers at the beginning.
But by the time Gobekli Tepe was finished
and it was definitely deliberately finished, closed off
closed down, deliberately buried, covered with earth
covered with rubble, uh, and then topped off with a hill
which is, which is why Gobekli Tepe is called
um, what it is.
Gobekli Tepe means potbellied hill or the hill of the navel.
For a long time, Gobekli Tepe was thought to be just a hill that looked a bit like a pot belly.
Can you say how i- it was discovered?
I think, I think this is one of the most fascinating- Well- .
..
things on earth, period.
So maybe can you say what it is?
Yeah.
And how it was discovered?
Well, Go- Gobekli Tepe is, uh
first of all the, the oldest fully elaborated megalithic site that we know of anywhere in the world.
It doesn't mean the older ones won't be found
but it is the oldest so far found.
Um, the part of the site that's been excavated
which is a tiny percentage of the whole site
we do know, my first visit to Gobekli Tepe was in 2013
and Dr.
Klaus Schmidt, the late Dr.
Klaus Schmidt, who was, wh- who, who died a year later
uh, was very generous to me and showed me around the site f- over a period of three days.
And he, he explained to me that they've already used ground penetrating radar on the site and they know that there's much more Gobekli Tepe still underground.
Um, so anything is, anything is possible in terms of the
in terms of the dating of Gobekli Tepe.
But what we have at the moment is a series of almost circular but not quite circular enclosures
which are, which are walled with relatively small stones
and then inside them you have pairs of megalithic pillars.
And the, the archetypal part of that site is Enclosure D
uh, which contains the two largest upright megaliths
about 18 feet tall and reckoned to weigh somewhere in the range of 20 tons
uh, if I have my, my memory correct.
They're, they're substantial, hefty pieces of stone.
It isn't, it isn't some kind of extraordinary feat to create a 20-foot tall or 20-ton megalith
uh, nor is it an extraordinary feat to move it.
Uh, there's nothing, there's nothing magical or
or really weird about that.
Human beings can do that, and always have.
Besides, the quarry for the megaliths is right there.
It's within 200 meters of the, of
of the main enclosure, so that's not a mystery.
But the mystery is, the mystery is why suddenly this
this new form of architecture, this massive
massive, um, megalithic pillars appear.
And the, the pillars, one, one of the things that interests me about the pillars i- is their alignment
and there is good work that's been done which suggests that Enclosure D
uh, aligns to the rising of the star Sirius.
And the rising points of the star Sirius appear to be mapped by the other enclosures
which are all oriented in slightly different directions.
It was the work entirely of hunter f- foragers
but by the time Gobekli Tepe was completed
uh, agriculture was being introduced, and, and was
was, was taking place there.
Now you asked how Gobekli Tepe was found.
The answer to that is that there was a survey of that potbellied hill in the 1960s by
um, some American archaeologists, and they were looking
absolutely looking for Stone Age material, for material from the Paleolithic.
Um, and they had found some Paleolithic flints
upper Paleolithic flints around there, so it looked like a good place to look.
But then they noticed, sticking out of the side of the hill
some very finely cut, uh, stone, bits of very large and
and very finely cut stone.
And looking at that, the workmanship was so good that those archaeologists were confident that it had nothing to do with the Stone Age
and they thought they were looking at perhaps some Byzantine
uh, r- remains, and they abandoned the site and
and never looked at it further.
And it wasn't until the German Archaeological Institute got involved and p- particularly Klaus Schmidt
who I think was a genius, had real insight into this
uh, and, and started to dig at Gobekli Tepe
that they realized what they'd found, that they'd
that they'd found potentially the oldest megalithic site in the world.
Uh, and they'd found it at a place where agriculture
according to the established historical tr-.
..
timeline.
That's where agriculture, at any rate in-in Europe and Western Asia begins.
It begins in Anatolia, in Turkey and then it gradually disseminates westward from there.
And yet the understanding is, it was created by hunter-gatherers.
It was created by hunter-gatherers, yeah.
They were- there- there was no agriculture 11
600 years ago in Gobekli Tepe.
But by the time Gobekli Tepe was decommissioned
and I use that word deliberately, was closed down
uh, and- and buried, uh, agriculture was all around it.
Uh, and- and- and this was agriculture of people who knew how to cultivate- cultivate plants.
Do we have an understanding when it was turned into a
if I could say, a time capsule?
So protected by forming a mound around it?
Yes.
It- it- Is it around that similar time?
It stood from roughly 11,600 years ago to about 10
400 years ago, to about 8400 BC.
So, around 1200 years it was there and it continued to be elaborated as a site.
And while it was being elaborated as a site
we see agriculture.
..
I'm gonna use the word being introduced.
Uh, it had n- there'd been no sign of it before and suddenly it's there
and to me that's another of the mysteries about Gobekli Tepe.
And then with the new work that- that's being done
we realized that it's part of a much wider phenomenon
uh, which spreads across an enormous distance.
Um, and- and, um, the puzzling thing is that after Gobekli Tepe
there almost seems to be a decline.
Things- things fall down again, and- and then we enter this long slow process of the Neolithic
thousands of years, uh, gradual developments until we come to ancient Sumer and- and- and Mesopotamia.
But agriculture has taken a firm- a firm root by then.
Actually one other thing, I'll just say this in passing.
Uh, when- when I talk about a lost civilization introducing ideas to people
I'm often accused of stealing credit from the indigenous people who had those ideas in the first place.
So I do find it slightly hypocritical that archeology is- fully accepts that the idea of agriculture was introduced to Western Europe from Turkey.
Uh, and that- that- that Western Europeans didn't invent agriculture
it was absolutely introduced by Anatolian farmers who- who- who traveled west.
So the no- the notion of dissemination of ideas perhaps shouldn't be so
um, annoying to archeologists as it is.
And perhaps we should also state, if we look at the entirety of history of hominids
humans or hominids have been explorers.
I- I didn't even know this.
When I was preparing for this- Yeah.
.
..
looking at Homo erectus- Yeah.
.
..
1.
9 million years ago- Absolutely.
.
..
almost right away they spread out through the whole world.
Yeah.
And we Homo sapiens evolved from them, and we should also mention since we're talking about a sort of controversial debates going on
as I understand there's still debates about the dynamics of all that was going on there
like we mentioned in Africa- Mm.
.
..
that it's th- you know, I think the current understanding we didn't come from one particular point of Africa
that there's multiple locations.
Mm-hmm.
This is the Out of Africa theory.
Yes.
I think it's more than a theory, it's- it's really strongly evidenced.
Why?
Because we're part of the great ape family and it's- and it's
uh, a- an African family.
Yeah.
Uh, there's no doubt that- that human beings
our deep origins are in Africa.
But then there, as you rightly say
there were these very early migrations out of Africa
uh, by species that are likely ancestral to anatomically modern humans
including definitely Homo erectus and- and- and the astonishingly distant travels that they undertook.
Yes, I think- I think there is an urge to explore in- in- in all of humanity.
I think there is an urge to find out what's around the next corner
what's over the brow of the- of the next hill.
Uh, and I think that goes very deep into human character
and I think it was being manifested in those- those early adventures of people who left Africa and traveled all around the world.
And then settling in different parts of the world
uh, I- I think a lot of- a lot of anatomically modern human evolution took place outside Africa as well
not- not only in Africa.
So I guess th- the general puzzlement that you're filled with is given that these creatures explore and spread and
uh, try out different environments, why did it take hundreds of thousands of years for them to develop complicated society settlements?
Yes.
That's the first big question.
Why did it take so long?
And that raises in my mind a hypothesis
a possibility.
Maybe it didn't take so long.
Maybe- maybe things were happening that we haven't yet got hold of in the archeological record which- which await to be discovered.
Um, and of course there are huge parts of the world that have not been studied at all by archeology.
But the fact that- the fact that huge parts of the world have not been studied at all by archeology is not in its- on its own enough to suggest that we're missing a chapter in the human story.
Uh, the reason that I come to that isn't only puzzlement about that 300
000 year gap.
It's also to do with the fact that there's common iconography
there's common myths and traditions, and there's common spiritual ideas that are found all around the world.
Um, and- and, uh, they're found amongst cultures that are geographically distant from one another
uh, and that are also distant from one another in time.
They don't necessarily occur at the same time.
And this is where I think that archeology is perhaps desperately needing a history of ideas as well as just a history of things.
Uh, because an idea, um, can- can manifest again and again
uh, throughout the human story.
So that- so there are particular- there are particular issues
uh, for example the notion of the afterlife destiny of the soul.
Uh, what happens to us when we die.
Um, and believe me when you reach my age
that's something you do- you do think  about
what- what- what happens.
I used to feel immortal when I was in my 40s
but now that I'm 74, I definitely know that I'm- th- th- that I'm not.
Well, it would be natural for human beings all around the world to have that same- that same feeling
that same idea.
But why would they all.
..
. decide that what happens to the soul after death is that it makes a leap to the heavens
to the Milky Way, that it makes a journey along the Milky Way
that there it is confronted by challenges, by monsters
by closed gates.
The course of the life that that person has lived will determine their destiny in that afterlife journey.
And this idea, the, the path of souls
the Milky Way is called the path of souls
it's very strongly found in the Americas, right?
From South America through Mexico, through into North America
but it's also found, uh, in ancient Egypt
uh, in ancient India, in ancient Mesopotamia
the same, the same idea.
Uh, and I don't feel that that can be a coincidence.
I feel, I feel that what we're looking at is an inheritance of an idea
a legacy that's been passed down from a remote common source to cultures all around the world.
And th- and then has taken on a life of its own within those cultures.
So the remote common source would explain both the similarities and the differences
uh, in the expression of these ideas.
The other thing, very puzzling thing, is
um, the sequence of numbers that are a result of the precession of the equinoxes
at least I think that's the best theory to explain them.
Um, here I think it's important to pay tribute to the work of Giorgio de Santillana and Hertha von Deschend.
Giorgio, Giorgio de Santillana was professor of history of science actually at MIT
where, wh- where you're based, back in the '60s.
Um, and Hertha von Deschend was professor of the history of science at Frankfurt University.
And they wrote, uh, an immense book in the 1960s called Hamlet's Mill.
Uh, and, and Hamlet's Mill, uh
differs very strongly from established opinion on the issue of the phenomenon of precession
and I'll explain what precession is in a moment.
Um, generally, it's held that it was the Greeks who discovered the precession
uh, and the dating on that is put back not very far
maybe 2,300 years ago or so.
Santillana and von Deschend are pointing out that knowledge of precession is much
much older than that, thousands of years older than that
and, and they do actually trace it
I think I'm quoting them pretty much correctly
to some almost unbelievable ancestor civilization.
Reading that book was one of the several reasons that I got into this
this mystery in the first place.
Okay, now, the precession of the equinoxes
to give it its full name, is
is, uh, results from the fact that our planet is the viewing platform from which we observe the stars.
Uh, and our planet, of course, is rotating on its own axis at roughly 1
000 miles an hour at the equator, uh
but what's less obvious is that it's also wobbling on its axis.
And that i- so if you imagine the extended north pole of the Earth pointing up at the sky
in our time, it's pointing at the star Polaris
and that is our pole star.
But Polaris has not always been the pole star
precisely because of this wobble on the axis of the Earth.
Uh, other stars have occupied the pole position
and sometimes the extended north pole of the Earth points at empty space.
There is no pole star.
That's one of the obvious results of the wobble on the Earth's axis.
The other one is that there are 12 well-known constellations in our time
the 12 constellations of the zodiac, that lie along what is referred to as the
the path of the sun.
The Earth is orbiting the sun, uh
and we are seeing what's behind it, what's
what's in direct line with the sun in our
in our view.
And the zodiacal constellations all lie along the path of the sun
so at different times of the year, the sun will rise against the background of a particular zodiacal constellation.
Uh, today we live in the age of Pisces
uh, and it's n- definitely not an accident that the early Christians used the fish
uh, as their symbol.
Uh, this is another area where I differ from archaeology.
I think, I think the constellations of the zodiac were reco- recognized as such much earlier than we suppose.
Anyway, to get to the point, uh
the key marker of the year, certainly in the Northern Hemisphere
was the spring equinox.
Uh, this was, the question was, what constellation is rising behind the sun?
What's c- what constellation is housing the sun at dawn on the spring equinox?
Uh, right now it's Pisces.
In another 150 years or so, it'll be Aquarius.
We, we do live in the dawning of the age of Aquarius.
Uh, back in the time of, um
the late ancient Egyptians, it was Aries
going back to the time of Ramesses or before.
Before that, it was Taurus.
And so on and so forth.
It's backwards through the zodiac, uh, until 12
500 years ago, you come to the age of Leo when the constellation of Leo houses the sun on the spring equinox.
Now this process unfolds very, very, very
very slowly.
It un- the whole cycle, and it is a cycle
it repeats itself roughly every 26,000 years.
Put a r- put a more exact figure on it
25,920 years.
Uh, that may be a convention.
Some scholars would s- would say it was a bit less than that
a bit more, but you're talking fractions.
It's, it's in that area, 25,920 years.
Um, and, and, uh, to observe it
you really need more than one human lifetime
because it unfolds very, very slowly, at a rate of one degree every 72 years.
And the parallel that I often give is hold your finger up to the horizon
the distant horizon.
The movement in one lifetime, in, in the period of 72 years
is about the width of your finger.
Uh, it's not impossible to notice in a lifetime
but it's, but it's difficult.
You gotta pass it on.
Um, and, and what seems to have happened is that some ancient culture
the culture that Santillana and von Deschend call some almost unbelievable ancestor culture
worked out the entire process of precession and.
..
. selected the key numbers of precession, of which
of which the most important number, the governing number
is the number 72.
Uh, but, but we also have, uh
numbers related to the number 72.
72 plus 36 is 108, 108 divided by two is 54.
Uh, these, these numbers are also found in mythology all around the world.
There were 72 conspirators, uh, who, um
were involved in killing the god Osiris in
in ancient Egypt and nailing him up in a wooden coffer and dumping him in the
in the Nile.
Um, there are 432,000 in the Rig Veda.
432,000 is a multiple of 72, uh
and, and, um, at Angkor in Cambodia
for example, you have, uh, the bridge to Angkor Thom
and on that bridge you have figures on both sides
f- sculpted figures, which are holding the body of a serpent.
Uh, that serpent is Vasuki, and what they're doing is they're churning the milky ocean.
It's the same metaphor of churning and turning that's defined in the story of Hamlet's mill
of Umlotti's Mill.
Uh, there are 54 on each side.
54 plus 54 is 108, 108 is 72 plus 36.
It's a precessional number according to the work that Santillana and von Deschen did.
And the fascination with these, this number system and its discovery all around the world
uh, is one of the puzzles that
that intrigue me and, and, uh, suggest to me that we are looking at ancestral knowledge that was passed down and probably was passed down from a specific single common source at one time but then was spread out very
very widely around the world.
So one of the defining ways that you approach the study of human history that I think contrasts with mainstream archeology is that you take this sort of astronomical symbolism and the relationship between humans and the stars very seriously.
I do.
Uh, as I believe the ancients did.
I think it's important to sort of, uh
consider what humans would have thought about back then.
Now we have a lot of distractions.
We have social media, we can watch videos on YouTube and whatever.
Mm-hmm.
But back then, especially before sort of electricity- Mm.
.
..
the stars is like - Yeah.
.
..
the sexiest thing to talk about.
There's no light pollution.
There's no light pollution so there's th- that's
and you're spending s- That's the majesty of the heavens.
Every single night you're spending looking up at the stars
and you can imagine there's a lot of sort of status value to be the guy who's very good at studying the stars- Yeah.
Yeah.
.
..
and sort of the scientists of the day- Yeah.
.
..
and I'm sure there's going to be these geniuses that emerge- Yeah.
.
..
that are able to, uh, do two things.
One, tell stories about the gods or whatever- Mm.
.
..
based on the stars, and then also as we'll probably talk about
use the stars practically for navigation, for example.
Oh yeah.
Definitely.
And s- and so like, it makes sense that the stars had a primal importance for the ideas of the times
for the status, the, for religious explorations.
..
It was an ever-present reality.
Yes.
And it was bright and it was brilliant- Yeah.
.
..
uh, and it was full of lights.
Uh, it, it, it, it's inconceivable that the ancients would not have paid attention to it.
It was, it was an overwhelming presence
and that's one of the reasons why I'm really confident that the
the constellations that we now recognize as the constellations of the zodiac were recognized much earlier
because it's hard to miss when you pay attention to the sky that the sun over the course of the solar year is month by month rising against the background of different constellations.
And then there's a much longer process, the process of precession
which takes that journey backwards and where we have a period of 2
160 years for each sign of the zodiac.
I think it would have been hard for the ancients to have missed that.
They might not have identified the constellations in exactly the same way we do today
that may well be a Babylonian or Greek
uh, convention, but that the constellations were there
uh, I think was very clear, and that they were special constellations unlike other ones higher up in the sky
uh, which were not on the path of the sun that
that people paid attention to.
Well, but detecting the precession of the equinox is hard because especially they don't have any writing systems
they don't have any mathematical systems, so everything is told through words.
Yeah.
They, well, they, and they have
uh, let's not underestimate oral traditions.
Uh, the, th- or- oral traditions, that's something we've lost in our culture today.
It's one of the things that happens with the written word
uh, is that you gradually lose your memory.
Um, actually there's a nice story from
from ancient Egypt about the god Thoth, the god of wisdom
who is very proud of himself because he has invented writing.
"Look at this gift," he says to a mythical pharaoh of that time
"Look at the gift that I am giving humanity.
Writing.
This is a wonderful thing.
It'll enable you to preserve so much that you would otherwise lose.
" And, and, um, the pharaoh in this story replies to him
"No.
You have not given us a wonderful gift.
You have destroyed the art of memory.
Uh, we will forget everything.
Words will roam free around the world not accompanied by any wise advice to set them into context.
" And actually that's a, that's, that's a
that's a very interesting point and, and we do know that cultures that still do have oral traditions are able to preserve information for very long periods of time.
One thing I, I think is clear in
in any time, in any period of history is human beings love stories.
Yeah.
We, we, we love great stories and
and one way to preserve information, uh
is to encode it, embed it in a great story.
Uh, and, and.
..
. so carefully done that, that actually it doesn't matter whether the storyteller knows that they're passing on that information or not.
Uh, the story itself is the vehicle
uh, and as long as it's repeated faithfully
the information contained within it will be, will be passed on.
And I, I do think this is
this is part of the, the story of the preve- preservation of knowledge.
So that's one of the reasons that you take myths seriously?
I take them very seriously, and, and the other
hmm, many reasons, but, but I can't help being deeply impressed and deeply puzzled by the worldwide tradition of a global cataclysm within human memory.
I mean, we know that, we know scientifically that there have been many
many cataclysms in the past going back millions of years.
I mean, the best-known one, of course
is the K-Pg event, as it's now called
that made the dinosaurs extinct 65 million or
or, or 66 million years ago.
But has there been such a cataclysm in the lifetime of the human species?
Um, yeah, the Mount Toba eruption about 70
000 years ago was pretty bad, uh, but a global cataclysm
the Younger Dryas really ticks all the boxes as a
as a, as a worldwide disaster, which definitely involved sea level rise
both at the beginning and at the end of the Younger Dryas.
It definitely involved the swallowing up of lands that previously had been above water
uh, and I think it's a, an excellent candidate
uh, for this worldwide tradition of a global cataclysm of which one of
but not the only distinguishing characteristics was a flood
an enormous flood, and the submergence of lands that had previously been above water
uh, under water.
The fact that this story is found all around the world
uh, suggests to me that the archeological explanation is
look, people suffer local floods all the time.
I'm, I mean, as we're talking, there's
there's, there's flooding in Florida, uh, but I
I, I don't think anybody in Florida is going to make the mistake of believing that that's a global flood.
They, they know it's, they know it's local
um, but that's the argument largely of archeology dealing with the flood myths or that some local population experienced a
a nasty local flooding event and they decided to say that it was
that it affected the whole world.
I, I'm not persuaded by that, particularly since we know there was a nasty epoch
the Younger Dryas, when flooding did occur and when the earth was subjected to events cataclysmic enough to extinguish entirely the megafauna of the Ice Age.
So there is the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis that provides an explanation of what happened during this period- Yeah.
.
..
that resulted in such rapid environmental change, so can you explain this hypothesis?
Yes, um, the y- the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis
YDIH for short, uh, is, uh
is not a lunatic fringe theory as its opponents often attempt to write it off.
Um, it's the work of more than 60 major scientists
uh, working across many different disciplines, including archeology
uh, and, and including oceanography as well.
Um, uh, and, and, uh, they are collectively puzzled by the sudden onset of the Younger Dryas
and by the fact that is, it is accompanied 12
800 years ago by a distinct layer in the earth.
Uh, you can see it most clearly at
uh, Murray Springs in Arizona, for example.
You can, you can see, it's about the width of a human hand
uh, and there's a, uh, a draw there that's been cut by flash flooding at some time
and that draw has revealed the sides of the draw.
And you can, you can see the cross-section
and in the cross-section is this distinct dark layer that runs through the earth
and it contains evidence of wildfires, fires.
There's a lot of soot in it.
Uh, there are also nanodiamonds in it.
There is shocked quartz in it.
There is quartz that's been melted at temperatures in excess of 2
200 degrees centigrade.
Um, there are carbon microspherules.
All of these are proxies for some kind of cosmic impact.
I talked a moment ago about the extinction of the dinosaurs
Louis and Walter Alvarez who, who made that incredible discovery
uh, initially their, their discovery was based entirely on impact proxies
just as the Younger Dryas is.
There was no crater, and for a long time they were disbelieved because they couldn't produce a crater.
Uh, but when they finally did produce that deeply buried Chicxulub crater
that's when people started to say, "Yeah
they have to be right.
" But they weren't relying on the crater.
They were relying on the impact proxies, and they're the same impact proxies that we find in what's called the Younger Dryas boundary layer all around the world.
Um, so, so it's the fact that at the moment when the earth tips into a radical climate shift
it, it, it's been warming up for at least 2
000 years before 12,800 years ago.
People at the time must have been feeling a great sense of relief
you know?
"We've been living through this really cold time
but it's getting better.
Things are getting better.
" And then suddenly around 12,800 years ago
some might say 12,860 years ago, there's a massive global plunge in global temperatures
and, and the world suddenly gets as cold as it was at the peak of the Ice Age
and, and it, it's almost literally overnight.
It's very, very, very rapid.
Normally in an epoch when the earth is going into a freeze
you would not expect sea levels to rise
but there is a sea level rise, a sudden one
right at the beginning of the Younger Dryas
and then you have this long frozen period from 12
800 to 11,600 years ago.
And then equally dramatically and equally suddenly, the Younger Dryas comes to an end and the world very rapidly warms up
and you have a, a recognized pulse of meltwater at that time as the last of the glaciers collapse into the sea
uh, called Meltwater Pulse 1B, round about 11
600 years ago.
So, so this is, um.
..
This is a period, uh, which is very tightly defined.
Uh, it's a period when we know that human populations were
were grievously disturbed.
That's when the, the so-called Clovis culture of North America vanished entirely from the record
uh, during the Younger Dryas and it's the time when the mammoths and the saber-toothed tigers vanished from the record as well.
Is there a good understanding of what happened geologically
whether there was an impact or not?
Like, what explains this huge dip in temperature and then rise in temperature?
The abrupt cessation of the global meridional overturning circulation of which the Gulf Stream is the best known part.
Uh, the main theory that's been put forward up to now
and I don't dispute that theory at all
is that the sudden freeze was becau- was caused by the cutting off of the Gulf Stream
basically, uh, which is part of the central heating system of our planet so no
no wonder it became c- c- cold.
But what's not really been addressed before is why that happened
why the Gulf Stream was cut, why a sudden pulse of melt water went into the world ocean and
and it was s- so much of it and it was so cold that it actually stopped the Gulf Stream in its tracks.
And that's where the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis offers a very elegant and very satisfactory solution
uh, to the problem.
Now, the hypothesis of course is broader than that.
Uh, amongst the scientists working on it are
for example, Bill Napier, an astrophysicist and astronomer.
Um, they have assembled a great deal of evidence which suggests that the culprit in the Younger Dryas impact event
or events, was what we now call the torrid meteor stream
uh, which the earth still passes through twice a year.
It's now about 30 million kilometers wide.
Takes the earth a couple of days to
to pass through it on its orbit.
It passed through it in June and it passes through it at the end of October.
The suggestion is that the torrid meteor stream is the end product of a very large comet that entered the solar system round about 20
000 years ago, came in from the Oort cloud
got trapped by the gravity of the sun
and went into orbit around the sun, an orbit that crossed the orbit of the earth.
Um, however, when it was one object
the likelihood of a collision with the earth was extremely small
but as it started to do what all comets do
which was to break up into multiple fragments
'cause these are chunks of rock held together by ice
uh, and as they warm up, they split and disintegrate and break into pieces.
As it passed through that, its debris stream became larger and larger and wider and wider
and the theory is that 12,800 years ago
the earth passed through a particularly dense part of the torrid meteor stream and was hit by multiple impacts
uh, all around the planet, certainly from the west of North America as far east as Syria.
Uh, and that we are, by and large
not talking about impacts that would have- that would have caused craters
although there certainly were some.
Uh, we're talking about air bursts.
When an object is 100 or 150 meters in diameter and it's coming in very fast
uh, into the earth's atmosphere, uh, it is very unlikely to reach the earth.
It's gonna blow up in the sky and the best known recent example of that is the Tunguska event in Siberia
which took place on the 30th of June
1908.
The Tunguska event was- nobody disputes, it was definitely an air burst of- of- of a cometary fragment.
And the date is interesting, uh, because the 30th of June is the height of the beta toroids.
It's one of the two times when the earth is going through the toroid meteor stream.
Well, luckily, that part of Siberia wasn't inhabited
uh, but 2,000 square miles of forest were destroyed.
If that had happened over a major city
we would all be thinking very hard about objects out of the toroid meteor stream and about the risk of
uh, cosmic impact.
So the suggestion is that it wasn't one impact
it wasn't two impacts, it wasn't three impacts
it was- it was hundreds of air bursts all around the planet coupled with- coupled with a number of bigger objects which the scientists working on this think hit the North American ice cap
largely.
Some of them may also have hit the northern European ice cap
resulting in that sudden, otherwise unexplained flood of melt water that went into the world ocean
um, and- and, uh, caused the cooling that then- that then took place.
But this was a disaster for life all over the planet and- and it's interesting that one of the sites where they find the Younger Dryas boundary and where they find overwhelming evidence of an air burst and where they find all the shocked quartz
the carbon microspherules, the nanodiamonds, the trinitite and so on and so forth.
All, um, o- of- of those impact proxies are found at Abu Hureyra.
That was, uh, a settlement within 150 miles of Gobekli Tepe and it was hit 12
800 years ago and it was obliterated.
Interestingly, it was reinhabited by human beings within probably five years
but it was- it was completely obliterated at that time.
Uh, and it- it- it's difficult to imagine that the people who lived in that area would not have been very impressed
uh, by what they saw happening, by the- the- these massive explosions in the sky and the
uh, the obliteration, uh, of- of Abu Hureyra.
Now, this is a theory, the Younger Dryas impact
it's a hypothesis actually, it's not even a theory.
A theory is, I think, considered a higher level than a hypothesis.
That's why it's the Younger Dryas impact hypothesis
and of course, it has many opponents and there are many who disagree with it
uh, and there- there- there have been a series of- of-.
..
peer-reviewed papers that have been published supposedly debunking the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis.
One, I think, was in 2011.
It was called a, a "Requiem for the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis.
" And there's one just been published a few months ago or a year ago c- you know
called a, A Complete, uh, Refutation of the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis
something, something like that, some lengthy title.
Um, the, so, so it's, it's a hypothesis that has its opponents and even within
within those of us who are looking at the alternative side of history
there are different points of view.
Uh, Robert Schoch from Boston University, the geologist who demonstrated that the erosion on the Sphinx may well have been caused by exposure to a long period of very heavy rainfall
uh, he doesn't go for the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis.
He think, he, he fully accepts that the Younger Dryas was a global cataclysm
uh, and that the extinctions took place
but he thinks it was caused by some kind of massive solar outburst.
So there, there, what everybody's agreed on is the Younger Dryas was bad
um, but there is dispute about what caused it.
I personally have found the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis to be the most persuasive
uh, which most effectively explains all the evidence.
How important is the impact hypothesis to your understanding of
um, the Ice Age advanced civilizations?
So is it possible to have another explanation for environmental factors that could have
um, erased most of an advanced civilization during this period?
In a sense, it's not the impact hypothesis that is central to what I'm saying
it's the Younger Dryas that's central to what I'm saying
and the Younger Dryas required a trigger.
Something, something caused it.
Uh, I think the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis
the notion that, that we're looking at a debris stream of a fragmenting comet and we can still see that debris stream because it's still up there and we still pass through it twice a year
uh, is, is the best explanation.
But I don't mind other explanations.
I, it's good that there are other explanations.
The Younger Dryas is a big mystery and it's not a mystery that's been solved yet.
And that word "advanced civilization," this is another word that
um, uh, that is easily misunderstood, and I've tried to make clear many
many times that when we, when we consider the possibility of something like a civilization in the past
we shouldn't imagine that it's us, that it's something like us.
We should expect it to be completely different from us
but that it would have achieved certain things.
So amongst the clues that intrigue me are those precessional numbers that are found all around the world and are a category of ancient maps called portolanos
which suddenly started to appear just after the crusade that
uh, entered Constantinople and sacked Constantinople.
The portolanos suddenly start to appear, and they're extremely accurate maps.
The most of the ones that have survived are extremely accurate maps of the Mediterranean alone
but some of them show much wider areas.
For example, on these portolano-style maps, you do find a depiction of Antarctica again and again.
And another thing that these maps have in common is that many of the map makers state that they based their maps on multiple older source maps which have not survived.
These maps are intriguing because they have very accurate relative longitudes.
Our civilization did not crack the longitude problem until the mid-18th century with Harrison's chronometer
which was able to keep accurate time at sea.
So you could have, uh, the time in London and you could have the local time at sea at the same time on
and then you could work out your longitude.
Um, there might be other ways of working out longitude as well
but there it is.
The fact is these portolanos have extremely accurate relative longitudes.
Secondly, some of them showed the world to my eye as it looked during the Ice Age.
They show a much, a much extended Indonesia
uh, and Malaysian peninsula, and the series of islands that make up Indonesia today are all grouped together into one land mass
and that was the case during the Ice Age.
That was the, that was the Sunda Shelf.
And the presence of Antarctica on some of these maps also puzzles and intrigues me and is not satisfactorily explained in my view by archeology
which says, "Oh, those map makers, they felt that the world needed something underneath it to balance it
so they put, uh, a, a fictional land mass there.
" Um, I- I- I don't think that makes sense.
I think somebody was mapping the world, uh
during the last ice age, but that doesn't mean that they had our kind of tech.
Uh, it means that they were following that exploration instinct
that they knew how to navigate.
They'd been watching the stars for thousands of years before.
They knew how to navigate and they knew how to build seagoing ships
uh, and they explored the world and they mapped the world.
Those maps very, very, were made a very
very long time ago.
Some of them I believe were likely preserved in the Library of Alexandria.
I think even then they were being copied and recopied.
We don't know exactly what happened to the Library of Alexandria except that it was destroyed.
Uh, I th- I suggest it's likely this was during the period of the Roman Empire.
I suggest it's likely that some of those maps were taken out of the library and taken to Constantinople
uh, and, uh, that's where they were liberated during the crusade and entered world culture again and started to be copied and recopied.
So from this perspective, when, uh, we talk about advanced Ice Age civilization
it could have been a relatively small group of people with the technology of they're scholars of the stars and they're expert seafaring navigators.
Yes.
That's about as far as I would take it.
And when I say that it, uh
as I have said on a number of occasions
that it had technology equivalent to ours in the 18th century
I'm referring specifically to the ability to calculate longitude.
Yeah.
I'm not saying that they were building steam engines.
Um, I don't see, I don't see any evidence for that.
And perhaps some.
..
. building tricks and skills of how to
uh, ar- Well, def- well, definitely.
And this, this again is where you come to a series of mysteries which are perhaps best expressed on the Giza Plateau in
in, in Egypt with the three great pyramids
and the extraordinary megalithic temples that many people don't pay much attention to
uh, on the Giza Plateau, and the Great Sphinx itself.
This is, uh, an area of particular importance in understanding this issue.
Well, can you actually describe the Sphinx and the Great Pyramids- Yeah.
.
and what you find most mysterious and interesting about them?
Well, first of all, the astronomy, uh
and here I must pay tribute to two individuals
actually three individuals in particular, one of them is John Anthony West
passed away in 2018.
He was the first person in our era to begin to wonder if the Sphinx was much older than it had been.
Actually he got that idea from a, from a philosopher called Schwaller de Lubicz
who'd noticed what he thought was water erosion on the body of the Sphinx.
John West picked that up, and he was a n- great amateur Egyptologist himself
he spent most of his life in Egypt and he
he was h- hugely versed in ancient Egypt.
And when he looked at the Sphinx and at the strange
scalloped erosion patterns and the vertical fissures particularly in the trench around the Sphinx
um, he began to think, "Maybe Schwaller was right
maybe this, there was some sign of some sort of flooding here.
" And that's when he brought Robert Schoch
second person I'd l- I'd like to recognize
geologist at Boston University.
He brought Schoch to Giza, and Schoch was the first geologist to stick his neck out
risk the rire, the ire of Egyptologists
and say, "Well it looks to me like the Sphinx was exposed to at least 1
000 years of heavy rainfall.
" And as Schoch's calculations have continued as he's continued to be immersed in this mystery
he's continuously pushed that back, and he's now again looking at the date of around 12
000, 12 and a half thousand years ago
during the Younger Dryas, for the creation of the Great Sphinx.
And then, of course this is the period of the w- uh
o- o- of the wet Sahara, the humid Sahara.
The Sahara was a completely different place during the Ice Age
there were rivers in it, there were lakes in it
it was fertile, it was possibly densely
densely populated.
And there was a lot of rain.
There's not no rain in Giza today, but there's relatively little rain.
The next person.
..
Not enough rain to cause that erosion damage on the Sphinx.
M- The next person who needs to be mentioned in this context is
is Robert Bauval.
Uh, Robert and I have co-authored a number of books together
and unfortunately Robert has been very ill for the last seven years.
He's, he's, um, uh, got a very bad chest infection
and I, I think also that, that Robert became very demoralized by the attacks of Egyptologists on his work.
Uh, but Robert is the genius, and it does take a genius sometime to make these connections 'cause nobody had noticed it before
that the three pyramids of Giza are laid out on the ground in the pattern of the three stars of Orion's Belt.
And skeptics will say, "Well you can find any buildings and line them up with any stars you want
" but Orion actually isn't any old constellation.
Orion was the god Osiris, uh, in the sky.
Uh, he was m-.
..
The ancient Egyptians called the Orion Constellation Sahu
and they recognized it as the celestial image of the god Osiris.
So what's been copied on the ground is the belt of a deity
of a celestial deity, it's not just a random constellation.
Um, and then when we take precession into account
you find something else very intriguing happening.
First of all, uh, you find that the exact orientation of the pyramids as it is today
and, and pretty much as it was when they're supposed to have been built 4
500 years ago, uh, it's, it's not precisely related to how Orion's Belt looked at that time.
There's a, there's a bit of a
a twist, is they're not, they're not quite right.
But as you precess the stars backwards, as you go back
and back, and back, and you come to around 10
500 BC, 12 and a half thousand years ago
in the Younger Dryas, you find that suddenly they line up perfectly
they match perfectly with the three pyramids on the ground.
And that's the same moment that the Great Sphinx
an equinoctial monument, aligned perfectly to the rising sun on the spring equinox.
Anybody can test this for themselves, just
just go to Giza on the 21st of March
be there before dawn, stand behind the Sphinx
and you will see the sun rising directly in line with the gaze of the Sphinx.
Um, but the question is, what constellation was behind the Sphinx?
And 12 and a half thousand years ago
it was the constellation of Leo.
And actually the constellation of Leo has a very sphinx-like look.
And I, I and my colleagues are pretty sure that the Sphinx was originally a lion entirely
uh, and that it, over the thousands of years it became damaged
it became eroded, particularly the part of it that
that sticks out, the head.
Uh, there were periods when the Sphinx was completely covered in sand but still the head stuck out.
Um, by the time you come to
to the fourth dynasty when the great pyramids are supposedly built
by the time you come to the fourth dynasty
the head of the s- the, the lion
original lion head would have been a complete mess.
And we suggest that it was then re-carved into a pharaonic head.
Egyptologists think it was the Pharaoh Khafre, uh
but there's no real strong resemblance, but it's definitely wearing the nemes headdress of
of a- an ancient Egyptian pharaoh.
Uh, and we think that that's the result of a re-carving of what was originally not only a lion-bodied
but also a lion-headed monument.
It wouldn't make sense if you create an equinoctial marker in the time of Khafre
4,500 years ago, and the Sphinx is an equinoctial marker
I mean it's 270 feet long and 70 feet high and it's looking directly at the rising sun on the equinox.
If you create it then, uh, you would be betterYou'd be more likely to create it in the shape of a bull because that was the age of Taurus
when the constellation of Taurus housed the sun on the spring equinox.
So why is it a lion?
Uh, and, and again, we think that's because of that observation of the skies and
and, and putting on the ground, as above
so below, putting on the ground an image of the sky at a particular time.
Now, the fact that the Giza Plateau
it's a fact, of course, that Egyptologists completely dispute
but the fact that the principal monuments of the Giza Plateau
the three great pyramids and the Great Sphinx all lock astronomically on the date of around 10
500 BC, uh, to me, is most unlikely to be an accident.
And actually if you look at computer software at the sky at that time
you'll see, you'll see that the Milky Way is very prominent and
and seems to be mirrored on the ground by the River Nile.
I, I suggest that may be one of the reasons
amongst many, why Giza was chosen, uh
as the site for this, for this very special place.
So the point I want to make is that
that an astronomical, um, design on the ground which memorializes a very ancient date does not have to have been done 12
500 years ago.
If, if, if from the ancient Egyptian point of view you're there 4
500 years ago, uh, and there's a time 8
000 years before that which is very, very
very important to you, you could mem- you could use astronomical language and megalithic architecture to memorialize that date on the Giza Plateau
which is what we think we're looking at except for one thing
and that's the erosion patterns on the Sphinx.
Uh, and we're pretty sure that the Sphinx at least does date back to 12 and a half thousand years ago
uh, and with it the megalithic temples
uh, the so-called Valley Temple, uh, which stands
uh, just, just to the east and just to the south of the Sphinx
and the Sphinx temple which stands directly ins- in front of the Sphinx.
The Sphinx temple has largely been destroyed, but the Valley Temple attributed to Khafre on no good grounds whatsoever
um, is a huge megalithic construction with blocks of limestone that weigh up to 100 tons each.
Um, and yet it has been remodeled
refaced with granite.
There are granite blocks that are placed on top of the
the core limestone blocks, and those core limestone blocks were already eroded when the glanite- granite blocks were put there.
Why?
Because the granite blocks have actually been purposefully and deliberately cut to fit into the erosion marks on the
we believe, much older megalithic blocks there.
So I think Giza is a very complicated site.
I would never seek to divorce the dynastic ancient Egyptians from the great pyramids.
They were closely involved in the construction of the great pyramids as we see them today.
But what I do suggest is that there were very low platforms on the Giza Plateau that are much older and that the
when we look at the three great pyramids
we're looking at a renovation and a restoration and a enhancement of much older structures that had existed on the Giza Plateau for a much longer period before that.
Actually, the Great Pyramid is built around a natural hill
uh, and that natural hill might have been seen as the original primeval mound
uh, to the, to the, to the ancient Egyptians.
So the idea is that the Sphinx was there long before the pyramids
and the pyramids were built by the Egyptian to celebrate further a- an already holy place.
Yeah.
And there were platforms in place where the pyramids stand.
Not the pyramids as we see them today
um, but the, the, the bases
the base of those pyramids, uh, was
was already in place at that time.
So, so what's the case, what's the evidence that the Egyptologists use to make the attributions that they do for the dating of the pyramids and the Sphinx?
Well, um, the three great pyramids of Giza are different from later pyramids.
This, this is another problem that I have with  the whole thing
um, is the, the, the story of pyramid building.
When did it, when did it really begin?
And the timeline that we get from Egyptology is the
the first pyramid is the pyramid of the Pharaoh Djoser
uh, the Step Pyramid at Saqqara, um
about a hundred years or so before the Giza pyramids are built.
Uh, and then we have this explosion in the Fourth Dynasty
uh, of, of true pyramids.
Uh, we have three of them attributed to a single pharaoh
Sneferu, who built supposedly the pyramid at Mai Dum and the two pyramids at Dashur
the Bent and the Red Pyramid.
Uh, and then within that same 100-year span
uh, we have the Giza pyramids being built.
This is according to the orthodox chronology.
And then suddenly once the Giza project is finished
pyramid building goes into a massive slump in ancient Egypt
uh, and the pyramids of the Fifth Dynasty are
frankly speaking, a mess outside.
They're, they're very inferior constructions.
You can hardly recognize them as pyramids at all
but what happens when you go inside them is you find that they're extensively covered in hieroglyphs
uh, and imagery repeating the name of the king who was supposedly buried in that place
whereas the Giza pyramids have no internal inscriptions whatsoever.
Uh, what they do, what we do have is one piece of graffiti w- about which there is some controversy.
Uh, basic statistics, it, it's a six million ton structure.
.
Um, i- each side is about 750 feet long.
Yeah.
Um, it's aligned almost perfectly to true north
south, east, and west, uh, within three-sixtieths of a single degree.
The sixtieths because degrees are divided into 60s.
Um, and, and, um.
..
. uh, it's the precision of the orientation and the absolute massive size of the thing.
Uh, plus it's very complicated internal passageways
uh, that- that- that- that are involved in it.
You.
..
you know, in the ninth century, the Great Pyramid still had its facing tone- stones in place
but there were, there was an Arab- a- an Arab caliph
Caliph Al-Ma'mun, who had already realized that other pyramids did have their entrances in the north face.
Nobody knew where the entrance to the Great Pyramid was.
Mm-hmm.
He figured if there's an entrance to this thing
it's gonna be in the north face somewhere.
So he put together a team of workers and they went in with sledgehammers and they started smashing where he thought would be the entrance
and they cut their way into the Great Pyramid
uh, for a distance of maybe 100 feet
and then the hammering that they did dislodged something.
They heard a little bit further away something big falling
and they realized there was a cavity there
and they sa- started heading in that direction
and then they joined the internal passageway of the sy- uh
of- of the Great Pyramid, the descending and the ascending corridors that go up.
When you go up the ascending corridor, every one of the internal passageways in the- in the Great Pyramid that people can walk in slopes at an angle of 26 degrees.
That's interesting because the angle of slope of the exterior of the Great Pyramid is 52 degrees.
So we know mathematicians were at work as well as geometers in the- in- in the creation of the Great Pyramid.
Um, if you go up the Grand Gallery
which is at the end of, uh
the, uh, so-called Ascending Corridor and it's above the so-called Queen's Chamber
you go up the Grand Gallery, you're eventually going to come to what is known as the King's Chamber
in which there is a sarcophagus, and that sarcophagus is a little bit too big to have been got in through the narrow entrance passageway.
It's almost as though the so-called King's Chamber was built around the sarcophagus
uh, already in place.
Above the King's Chamber are five other chambers.
These are known as relieving chambers.
Uh, the theory was that they were built to relieve the pressure on the King's Chamber of the weight of the monument
but I think what makes that theory dubious is the fact that even lower down where more weight was involved
you have the Queen's Chamber, and there are no such relieving chambers above that.
In the top of these five chambers, a British adventurer and vandal called Howard Vyse
who- who dynamited his way into those chambers in the first place
allegedly found.
..
well, he claims he found the graffiti
uh, uh, a piece of graffiti left by a work gang naming the Pharaoh Khufu
and it's true.
I've been in that chamber and there is the cartouche of Khufu there
uh, quite- quite recognizable, but the dispute around it is whether that is a genuine piece of graffiti dating from the Old Kingdom
uh, or whether Howard Vyse, uh, actually put it there himself
uh, because he was in desperate need of money at the time.
Um, I'm not sure what the answer to that question is.
Another reason why, but it's one of the reasons that- that
uh, Egyptologists feel confident in saying that the pyramid is the work of Khufu.
Um, another is what is called the Wadi el-Jarf papyri
uh, where, uh, on the Red Sea
uh, uh, a diary, the diary of an individual called Merer was found and he talks about bringing
um, highly polished limestone, uh, to the Great Pyramid and it's clear that what he's talking about is the facing stones of the Great Pyramid.
He's not talking about the body of the Great Pyramid.
He's talking about the facing stones of the Great Pyramid during the reign of Khufu.
So that's another reason why the- the- the Great Pyramid is attributed to Khufu.
Um, but I think, I think that we're- we're- Khufu was undoubtedly involved in the Great Pyramid and in a big way
but I think he was building upon and elaborating a much older structure and I think the heart of that structure is the subterranean chamber
which is, uh, 100 feet vertically beneath the base of the Great Pyramid.
Anybody who suffers from claustrophobia will not enjoy being down there.
You gotta go down a 26-degree sloping corridor
uh, until, uh, uh, a distance of about 300 feet.
It's 100 feet vertically, but the slope means you're gonna walk a- a distance of about.
..
not walk, you're gonna ape walk.
You're gonna.
..
you're almost gonna have to crawl.
I've learnt from long experience that the best way to go down these corridors is actually backwards.
Uh, if you go forward, you keep bumping your head on them 'cause they're only three feet five inches high.
Uh, you get down to the bottom
you have a short horizontal passage, and then you get into the subterranean chamber.
Um, the theory of Egyptology is that this was supposed to be the burial place of Khufu
but after cutting out that 300-foot-long, 26-degree-sloping
um, passage, a lot of which passes through bedrock
and having cut the subterranean chamber out of bedrock
gone to all that trouble, they decided they wouldn't bury him there and they built what's now known as the Queen's Chamber as his burial chamber
but then they decided that wouldn't do either
so they then built the King's Chamber and that's where the Pharaoh is supposed to have been buried.
Those Arab raiders under Caliph Mamun didn't find anything in the Great Pyramid at all.
So your idea is that, um, the Sphinx and maybe some aspects of the pyramid were much earlier.
Yes.
And why that's important is i- in that case it would be evidence of some transfer of technology- Yes.
.
..
from a much older civilization.
Yeah.
The idea is that during the Younger Dryas
most of that civilization was, uh, either destroyed or damaged- Mm-hmm.
.
and they desperately scattered across the w- the globe.
Seeking refuge.
Seeking refuge and telling stories of, um
maybe, one, the importance of the stars.
Mm-hmm.
Their knowledge about the stars- Yeah.
.
..
and their knowledge about building and knowledge about navigation.
Mm-hmm.
That's- that's- that's- that's roughly the idea.
Uh, so it's interesting that the ancient Egyptians
uh, have an a- a notion of.
..
. an epoch that they call Zep Tepi
which is the first time.
It means the first time.
This is when the gods walked the earth.
Uh, this is when, uh, seven sages brought wisdom to ancient Egypt
uh, and that is seen as the origin of ancient Egyptian civilization.
There are king lists in.
..
By the ancient Egyptians themselves, there are king lists that go wa- go back way beyond the first dynasty
go back 30,000 years into the past in ancient Egypt
considered to be entirely mythical by Egyptologists.
But nevertheless, it's interesting that there's that
that reference to, to remote time.
Now, what you also have in Egypt are what might almost be described as secret societies.
Uh, the Followers of Horus are one of those specifically tasked with bringing forward the knowledge from the first time
uh, into later periods.
Uh, the Souls of Pe and Nekhen are another one of these
um, mysterious secret society groups who are possessors of knowledge that they transmit to the future.
And, and what I'm broadly suggesting is that those survivors of the Younger Dryas cataclysm who settled in Giza may have been relatively small in number.
It's interesting that, that they are referred to in the
the Edfu Building Texts as Seven Sages because that repeats again and again.
It, it's, it's also in Mesopotamia, uh
it's Seven Sages, Seven Apkallu, who come out of the waters of the Persian Gulf and
and teach people all the skills of agriculture and of architecture and of astronomy.
It's found, it's found all around the world that there was a relatively small number of people who took refuge in Giza
who benefited from the survival skills of the hunter-foragers who lived at Giza at that time
and who also passed on their knowledge to those hunter-foragers.
But it was not knowledge that was ready to be put into shape at that time
and that knowledge was then preserved and kept and handled within very secretive groups that passed it down over thousands of years
and finally it bursts into full form, uh
in the fourth dynasty in, in ancient Egypt.
And, and, you know, the notion that knowledge might be transferred over thousands of years
uh, shouldn't be absurd.
Uh, we know, for example, in the case of ancient Israel
it goes back to the time of Abraham
which is pretty much, I think, around 2000
2000 BC, and, and knowledge has been preserved from that time right up to the present day.
So if you can.
..
if you can preserve knowledge for 4,000 years
you can probably preserve it for eight.
Now, of course, the error bars on this are quite large
but if, uh, an advanced ice age civilization existed
where do you think it was?
Where do you think we might find it one day if it existed?
And, uh, how big do you think it might have been?
Well, this is where, where I'm often accused of presenting a god of the gaps argument
that I think there was a lost civilization because there's lots of the earth that archeologists have never looked at.
Of course I'm not thinking that.
Um, these are very special gaps that I'm interested in
uh, and I'm interested in them because of all the curiosities and the puzzlement that I've expressed to you before.
It's, it's not just because there are gaps in the archeological record.
Um, it's, it's because those gaps involve places that were very interesting places to live during the ice age
and they specifically include the Sahara Desert, uh
which was not a desert during the ice age and
and, and went through this warm, wet period when it was very
very fertile.
Uh, certainly some archeology has been done in the Sahara
but it's fractional.
It's, it's, it's tiny, and I think if we want to get into the origins
true origins of ancient Egyptian civilization, of the peoples of ancient Egypt
we need to be looking in the Sahara
uh, for that.
Um, and, and, um, uh, the Amazon rainforest is another example of this.
I think the Sahara is about nine million square kilometers.
The Amazon that's left under dense cono- canopy rainforest is about five million square kilometers
maybe closer to six.
Um, and then, uh, you have the continental shelves
uh, that were submerged by sea level rise at the end of the ice age.
Now, it's, it's well-established that sea level rose by 400 feet
but it didn't rise by 400 feet overnight.
Uh, it, it came in dribs and drabs.
There were.
..
There were periods of very rapid, quite significant sea level rise
and there were periods when the sea level was rising much more
much more slowly.
So that 400-foot sea level rise is spread out over a period of about 10
000 years, but there are episodes within it
like meltwater pulse 1B, like mel- well
meltwater pulse 1A, when the flooding was
was really immense.
How big do you think it might have been?
And do you think it was across the.
..
spread across the globe?
So if there were expert navigators, uh
do you think they spread across the globe?
Well, well, the reason I'm talking about the gaps is I don't know where this civilization started or where it was based.
All I'm.
..
All I'm seeing are clues and mysteries and puzzles that
that, that intrigue me and which suggest to me that something is missing from our past.
Uh, and I'm not inclined to look for that missing something in
for example, Northern Europe because Northern Europe was not a very nice place to live during the ice age.
I mean, nobody smart would, would build a civilization in Northern Europe 12
000 years ago.
It was a hideous frozen wasteland.
The places to look are places that were hospitable and
and welcoming to human beings during the ice age
and that of course includes the coastlines that are now underwater.
Uh, of course it includes the Sahara Desert
and of course it includes the Amazon rainforest as well.
All of these places, I think, are candidates
uh, for, quote-unquote, my lost civilization.
Um, and because I think, largely from those ancient maps
that it was a navigating, seafaring civilization
uh, I suspect that it wasn't only in one place.
Uh, it was probably in a number of places.
And then I, I can only speculate.
Uh, maybe, maybe there was, um.
..
There was a cultural value where it was felt
it was felt that it was not appropriate to interfere with the lives of hunter foragers at that time.
Uh, maybe it was felt that, that they should keep their distance from them.
Just, just as even today, uh, there is a feeling that we shouldn't be interfering too much with the uncontacted tribes in the Amazon rainforest.
Uh, although in- interestingly, some of those
some of those tribes are now using cell phones.
Um-  yeah.
.
..
that possibility may have been there in, in the past and only when we come to a
to a global cataclysm does it become essential to have outreach and actually to take refuge amongst those hunter forager populations.
That is the hypothesis that I'm putting forward.
I'm not claiming that it's a fact, but for me it helps to explain the evidence.
So that speaks to one of the challenges that archeologists provide to this idea
is that there is a lot of evidence- Yeah.
.
..
of humans in the Ice Age and they appear to be all hunter-gatherers.
Mm-hmm.
But like you said, only a small percent of areas where humans have lived have been
um, studied by archeologists.
That's right, very tiny percent, and even a
a tiny percent of every archeological site has been studied by archeologists too.
Typically, 1 to 5% of any archeological site is excavated.
I mean, that's why, uh, Gobekli Tepe fills my mind with imagination
especially seeing as a time capsule.
You know, it's almost certain that there is places on earth we haven't discovered
that once we do, uh, even if it's after the Ice Age
will change our view of human history.
Yeah.
Uh, do you think there is going to be a place.
..
Like what, what, what would be your dream thing to discover
like Gobekli Tepe, that says a definitive
like, perturbation to our understanding of Ice Age history?
Some kind of archive, some kind of hall of records.
There's, uh, both mystical associations with the hall of records at Giza from people like the Edgar Cayce Organization.
There's also ancient Egyptian traditions which suggest that something was concealed
uh, beneath the Sphinx.
Um, this is not an idea that is alien to ancient Egypt.
It's, it's quite present in ancient Egypt.
Uh, so far, as far as I know
nobody has, um, dug down beneath the Sphinx.
And of course there's very good reasons for that.
You don't want to damage the, the
the place too much, but I, uh
let's call it the Hall of Records.
I, I'd, I'd love to find that.
Uh, but I think in a way that's what Gobekli Tepe is.
Gobekli Tepe is a hall of records.
You know, it's interesting that, that just as I've
I've tried to outline, I hope reasonably clearly
that the three great pyramids of Giza match Orion's Belt in 10
500 BC just as the Sphinx matches Leo in 10
500 BC, 12,500 years ago or so.
Pillar 43 in Enclosure D at Gobekli Tepe
uh, contains what a number of researchers
myself included, regard as an astronomical diagram.
Martin Sweatman of Edinburgh University has, is
is, has brought forward the best work in this field
but it was initially started by a gentleman called Paul Burley who noticed that one of the figures on Pillar 43 is a scorpion
uh, very much like we represent the constellation of Scorpio today
um, and that above it is a vulture with outstretched wings which is in a posture very similar to the constellation that we call Sagittarius
and on that outstretched wing, uh, is a
a circular object.
And the suggestion is that it's marking the time when the sun was at the center of the dark rift in the Milky Way
uh, at the summer solstice, uh, 12 and a half thousand years ago.
That's, that's what it's marking.
Uh, and, and, um, it's interesting that the same date can be deduced from Pillar 40.
..
Of course it's controversial.
Martin Sweatman's ideas are  by no means accepted by
by archeology, but he's done very, very thorough detailed statistical work on this and I'm personally convinced.
So we have a, a time capsule at Gobekli Tepe which is memorializing a date that is at least 1
200 years before Gobekli Tepe was built, uh
if that dating of 11,600 years ago pro- proves to be absolutely the oldest date
uh, as it is at, uh, as it is at present.
The date memorialized on P- Pillar 43 is 12
800 years ago, the beginning of the Younger Dryas
the beginning of the impact event.
And then Giza does the same thing, but in much larger scale.
It, it, it draws our.
..
It uses massive megalithic architecture which is very difficult to destroy and a profound knowledge of astronomy to encode a date in a language that any culture which is sufficiently literate in astronomy will be able to decode.
We don't have to have a script that we can't read like we do with the Indus Valley Civilization or with the Easter Island script.
We don't have to have a script that can't be interpreted.
If you use astronomical language then any astronomical literate civilization will be able to give you a date.
The Hoover Dam has a star map built into it
um, and that star map is, uh
is, is, is part of a, a
a, an exhibition that was put there at the founding of the
of the Hoover Dam, and what it does is it freezes the sky above the Hoover Dam at the moment of its completion and Oscar Hanson
the artist who created that, uh, piece
uh, said so specifically that this would be so that any future culture would be able to know the time of the dam's construction.
So you can use astronomy and architecture to memorialize
uh, a particular date.
Quick pause.
Bathroom break?
Sounds good.
So to me the story that w- we've been talking about
it is both exciting if the mainstream archeology narrative is correct- Mm-hmm.
.
..
and the one you're constructing is correct.
Mm-hmm.
Both are super interesting because the mainstream archeology perspective means that there is something about the human mind.
..
. from which the pyramids, the, these ideas spring natural.
You place- Mm-hmm.
.
humans anywhere, you place them on Mars- Yeah.
it's gonna come out that way.
Yeah.
So that's an interesting story of human psychology that then becomes even more interesting when you evolve out of Africa with homo sapiens
how they think about the world.
Yeah.
That's super interesting.
And then, uh, if there's an ancient civilization
uh, advanced civilization that explains why, uh
there's so many similar types of ideas that spread
that means that there's so much undiscovered- Yeah.
.
..
still- Yeah.
.
..
about the, the sort of the spring of these ideas of civilization that come from.
So, to me, they're both fascinating so I don't know why there's so much sort of infighting but- I think it's partly territorial.
I think that, I think that, um.
..
I don't, I can't s- can't speak of all archeologists but
but some archeologists feel very tor- very territorial about their profession
uh, and they do not feel happy about outsiders
uh, entering their realm, uh, especially if those outsiders have a large platform.
Um, and that's w- I've found that the attacks on me by archeologists have increased step by step with the increase of my exposure.
Uh, uh, I wasn't very interesting to them when I just had one minor bestseller in 1992 with a book called The Sign and the Seal.
Uh, but when Fingerprints of the Gods was published in 1995 and became a
a global bestseller, then I started to attract their attention and
and, uh, appear to have been regarded as a
as a threat to them and I, I.
..
and that is the case today.
That is why, uh, Ancient Apocalypse season one was defined as the most dangerous show on Netflix.
Uh, it's why the Society for American Archeology wrote an open letter to Netflix
uh, asking Netflix to reclassify the series as science fiction.
It's why they accused the s- th- they  accused the series of antisemitism
uh, misogyny, uh, white supremacism, uh
and a whole.
..
I don't know, a whole bunch of other
other things like that.
It's n- nothing to do with anything that's
that's, that's, that's in the series.
It was, it was, it, it was like
"We must shut this down.
This is so dangerous to us.
" It is certainly not a danger to.
..
There are many more dangerous things  in the world than a
than a television series, um, r- going
going on right now but, but maybe it was seen as a danger to archeology
that this non-archeologist was in archeological terrain and being
uh, viewed and seen by large.
..
and read by large numbers of people.
Maybe, maybe that was part of the problem.
And, and human nature being what it is
I noticed that, uh, two of my principal cl- uh
critics, uh, John Hoopes from the University of Kansas and Flint Dibble who's now teaching at the University of Cardiff in
in Wales in, in the UK, uh
are both people who like to have media exposure
um, and, uh, John Hoopes has just recently started his
uh, YouTube channel.
Flint Dibble has had one for, for quite a while
uh, v- pretty small number of followers.
I think that they, they, they feel that they should be the ones who are getting the global attention and that it's not right that I am and
and that the best way to stop that is to stop me
uh, to shut me down, to get me canceled
and basically requiring Netflix to re- relabel my series from a documentary to a science fiction
which is what they actually had the temerity to suggest to Netflix
uh, that would.
..
If that had gone through, if Netflix had listened to them
that would have effectively been the cancellation of my documentary series.
It would no longer have been ranked under
under documentary, so it was a deliberate attempt to shut me down and
and I see that going on again and again and it's so unfortunate and so unnecessary.
I've become very defensive towards archeology.
I, I, I hit back.
Well, after 30 years of these attacks on my work
uh, I'm tired of it and, and I'm
I, I do defend myself and sometimes I'm perhaps over vigorous in that defense.
Maybe I was a little bit too strong in my critique of archeology in the first season
uh, of Ancient Apocalypse.
Maybe I should have been a bit gentler and a bit kinder and I've tried to reflect that in the second season
uh, and, and, and to bring also many more indigenous
uh, voices into the second season as well as the voices of many more archeologists.
Yeah.
In general, I got a chance to get a glimpse of the archeology community and
um, in, in archeology, in science in general
I don't have much patience for this kind of arrogance or snark or- Mm.
.
..
dismissal of, uh, general human curiosity- Yeah.
.
..
that I think your work inspires in people
so that's why, uh, people like Ed Barnhart who I recently had a conversation with
you know, he radiates sort of kindness and curiosity- Me too.
.
as well.
And it's, like, that kind of approach to ideas
especially about human history, it inspires people.
Exactly.
It inspires millions of people- Exactly.
.
to ask questions.
Exactly.
I mean, that's why you had, uh
Keanu Reeves on the n- on the new season and he
he's basically coming to the show from that same perspective- Yes.
.
..
of curiosity.
Keanu is, is, is genuinely curious about the past and
and, uh, very, very interested in it and
and, and he's bringing to it questions that everybody brings to the past.
He's, he's speaking for every man, uh
in, in, in the series.
So given that, can you maybe steel man the case that
uh, archeologists make about this period that we've been talking about?
Can you make the case that that is indeed what happened is it was hunter-gatherers for a long time- Mm-hmm.
.
..
and then there was a cataclysm, a very difficult period in the human history with the Younger Dryas
and that changed the environment and then led to this
the springing up of civilizations at different places on Earth?
Mm.
Can you sort of, uh, make the case for that?
Uh, no, I completely understand why-.
..
that is the position of archeology because that's what they found.
Archeology is very much wishing to define itself as a science.
Uh, and, uh, it uses the techniques of weighing and measuring and counting
are very key to- to what archeology does.
And in what they found and what they've studied around the world
uh, they don't see any traces of- of a lost civilization.
And- and the idea that, um.
..
besides the- the.
W- we live in a very politically correct world today
and the idea that- that, uh, some kind of lost civilization brought knowledge to other cultures around the world is seen as almost
uh, racist or colonialist in some, in some way.
It triggers, it triggers that aspect as- as- as well.
But basically, arc- I think m- majority of archeologists are in complete good faith on this.
I- I- I- I don't think that anybody's r- really seeking to frame me.
I think that, I think that what- what we're hearing from most archeologists
some much more vicious than others, but what we're hearing from most archeologists is
"This is what we found and we don't see evidence for a lost civilization in it.
" Uh, and to that I- I must reply
please look at the myths.
Please consider the implications of the Younger Dryas.
Please look at the ancient astronomy.
Please look at those ancient maps and don't just dismiss them and sneer at them.
And for God's sake, please look more deeply at the parts of the world that were immensely habitable and attractive during the Ice Age and that have hardly been studied by archeology at all
uh, before you tell us that your theory is the only one that can possibly be correct.
In fact, it's a very, it's a very arrogant and silly position of archeology because archeologic- archeological theories are always being overthrown.
It can take years.
It can take decades.
It took decades in the curse, case of the Clovis first hypothesis for the settlement of the Americas.
Uh, but sooner or later, a bad idea
uh, will be kicked out by a preponderance of evidence that that idea does not explain.
If we can just look back at your
uh, debate with Flint Dibble- Mm-hmm.
.
..
on Joe Rogan Experience, what are some takeaways from that?
Uh, what have you learned maybe?
What are some things you like about Flint?
You said that he's one of th- your big critics.
Yeah.
But what do you like about his ideas and what
uh, what were you maybe bothered by?
First of all, just very recently, and it can be found on my YouTube channel
uh, channel, and it's signaled on- on my website
I- I have made a- a video, runs about an hour
uh, which looks at a series of statements that Flint made during the debate which I was not prepared to answer.
Um, and it turns out that some of those statements are not correct.
Uh, the- the notion, for example, that there were three million shipwrecks
uh, that have been mapped.
Flint actually uses the word mapped, three million shipwrecks that have been mapped
at one point in the debate, and I've- I've put that clip into the video that I brought out.
That is not a fact, that is an estimate
a UNESCO estimate.
Um, and- and actually in the small print on one of the slides that he has on the screen you can see the word estimate
but he never expresses that word outlie- out loud.
So those who are listening to the podcast rather than watching it wouldn't even have a chance to see that
and I sitting there in the studio didn't see that word estimate either.
And I didn't know that.
I thought, "My God, Flint has a point here.
If there'd been three million shipwrecks found and mapped
if that's the case, the absence of any shipwreck from a lost civilization of the Ice Age is a problem.
" But then I discover that it isn't three million shipwrecks that have been mapped.
It's much, much less than that.
Maybe it's 250,000.
Uh, still a large number, uh, but most of them from the last 1
000 years.
Uh, and- and, uh, unfortunately what Flint didn't go into
and perhaps he should have shared with the audience
and again I go into this in the
in the video, is that there is
uh, indisputable evidence that human beings were seafarers
uh, as much as 50 or 60
000 years ago.
The peopling of Australia involved a- a relatively short 90 kilometers
100 kilometer ocean voyage, but nevertheless it was an ocean voyage and it must have involved a large enough people
uh, a large enough number of people to create a permanent population that wouldn't go extinct.
The settlement of Cyprus is the same thing.
It was always an island even during the Ice Age
um, and, uh, no ships have survived that speak to the settlement of Australia
and no ships have survived that speak to the settlement of Cyprus either
but that doesn't mean that that thing didn't happen.
I- I should just, like, linger on this because for me it was
the shipwrecks thing was convincing, and then looking back
first of all watching your video but also just realizing the peopling of Australia part
that's mind boggling to me.
Yeah.
50,000 years ago.
Just imagine being the person standing on the shore looking out into the ocean
standing on the shore of a harsh environment looking out into the ocean of an even harsher environment and deciding that
you know what, I'm going to go towards near certain death- Mm-hmm.
.
..
and explore.
I don't know what's on the other side of that water.
You can't see 90 kilometers.
And humans did it.
Yeah, yeah.
Man, I love humans so much.
And again, it's that, it's that, it's that urge to explore.
Yeah.
And I suggest that it- it probably began with a few pioneers who made the journey there and back.
They ventured into the water, they definitely had boats
uh, and lo and behold after a two or three day voyage they ended up on a coastline.
You're an individual, you've got by relatively straightforward island hopping with w- where each island is within sight of each other as far as Timor
and when you get to Timor suddenly you can't island hop anymore.
There's an expansive ocean that you can't see across.
But that urge to explore, that curiosity that is central to the human condition would undoubtedly have led some adventurous individuals to want to find out more
and even be willing to risk their lives.
And that- that first reconnoitering of what lay beyond that strait would have undoubtedly been undertaken by very few individuals
uh, not enough to create a permanent population in Australia.
But when they came back with the good news that there's a whole land there-That's the
that's the land that was in it, that
that, uh, geographers call, uh, Sahul
which in, just as Sunda, uh, was the Ice Age Indonesian and Malaysian peninsula all joined together into one landmass.
So Sahul was New Guinea joined to Australia.
So they would have made landfall in New Guinea.
And then they think, "Well, here is this vast
open, incredible land.
Uh, we need to bring more people here.
" Uh, and, and th- that would have involved larger sh- larger craft.
Uh, you, you need to bring people
uh, with resources, and you bring, need to bring enough of them
both men and women, in order to produce a population that will not rapidly become extinct.
And, and it's the same in Cyprus.
There, the, the detailed work that's been done suggests very strongly that we're looking at planned migrations of groups of people in excess of 1
000 at a time, bringing animals with them
and this certainly would have involved multiple boats
and boats of a, of a significant size.
And there's no archaeological evidence of those boats?
None whatsoever.
The oldest boat that's ever been found in the world is the Dorcos shipwreck off Greece
which is around 5,000 years old, if I recall correctly.
So everything that's makes a boat is lost to time?
Yes.
Uh, b- boats can be preserved under certain circumstances.
There's a wreck at the bottom of the Black Sea
almost two miles deep.
I, I didn't know the Black Sea was that deep.
But there's a wreck, and there's no oxygen down there.
Um, that is, uh, that is more than 2
000 years old and i- is still in pretty much perfect condition.
Um- Sure.
.
but in other conditions, uh, th- the structure of the ship evaporates.
Sometimes what you're left with is the cargo of the ship
and you could say there was a ship that sank here
but the ship itself has, the ship itself has gone.
Uh, the fact is, we know that our ancestors were seafarers as much as 50
000 years ago, and no ship has survived to testify to that.
Yet we accept that they were.
Do you think, do you think one day we'll find a ship that's 10
20, 30, 40, 50,000 years old?
Uh, it's not impossible.
Um, I, I think it's, I think it's quite unlikely
given the, given the very thin survival of ships the further back you go in time
uh, with the oldest, as I say
being about 6,000 years old now.
And then the other, the other thing to take into account is the Younger Dryas event itself and the
the cataclysmic circumstances of that event.
And, and, and, um, the roiling of the seas that would have taken place then.
H- How much would have survived in a
in a, in a boat accident at that time would have survived for thousands of years afterwards?
I, I, I'm not sure.
But I, I don't give up hope.
It's possible.
So, okay, so that's back to the three million shipwrecks.
Yeah.
So what's your takeaway from that debate?
Uh.
..
Well, my takeaway from that debate is
um, that  I should have been better prepared.
Uh, and, and I should have been less angry.
Uh, uh, uh, I've.
..
I have to say that Flint had, had
had really, um, disturbed me with the
these, this constant snide, not quite exact references to racism and white supremacism in
in, in my work.
I, I, I detest such things.
Uh, and to have those labels stuck on me.
..
He's always avoided taking direct responsibility, pretty much always avoided.
There's one example that I include in the video I've made
uh, where he really hasn't successfully avoided it
but in most cases, he's trying to say that I rely on sources that were racist
but that.
..
h- he's not saying that I myself am a racist.
But the end result of those statements is that people all around the world
uh, came to the conclusion that Graham Hancock is a racist and a white supremacist.
And that really got under my skin, and it really upset me
and I felt, I felt angry about it
and I felt that I was there, uh
to defend Ancient Apocalypse season one, whereas
in fact, what I was there to do was to listen to a series of lectures where an archaeologist tells me what archaeologists have found
and that somehow I'm to deduce that from what they have found
they're not gonna find anything else.
At least not anything to do with the lost civilization.
Listen, I feel you.
I've seen the intensity of the attacks, and the whole racism label i- is
uh, is the one that can get under your skin.
And it's, it's a toolbox that's been prevalent over the past
let's say decade- Mm-hmm.
.
..
maybe a little bit more, as a method of cancellation- Yeah.
.
..
when, when a person has.
uh, is the opposite of racist, very often.
It's kind of hilarious to watch.
But it can get under your skin- Mm-hmm.
.
..
especially when you have certain, uh, dynamics that happen on the internet where it seeps into a Wikipedia page and then other people read that Wikipedia page and you get to hear it from
like, friends.
"Oh, I didn't know you're a" whatever
and then you- Mm-hmm.
.
you realize that Wikipedia description of who you are is actually has a lot of power.
Mm-hmm.
Not by people that know you well, but by people that just kind of are learning about you for the first time.
Oh, yeah, definitely.
And they can really start to annoy you and get under your skin when people are- Totally.
Totally.
.
..
kind of indirectly injecting.
They're writing articles about you that can then be cited by Wikipedia.
Yeah.
It can really bother a person who is actually trying to do good science and
or just trying to inspire people with different ideas.
I felt that my work was being deliberately misrepresented.
Yeah.
Uh, and I felt that I as a human being were being.
..
wo- was, was being insulted and wronged
uh, in, in ways that are deeply hurtful.
Um, my wife and I have, have six children between us
and we have nine grandchildren.
And of those nine grandchildren, seven are of mixed race.
Um, and, and this is my family.
And these are kids who are gonna grow up and read Wikipedia and learn from reading Wikipedia that Grandpa was some kind of racist
you know?
This is a personal issue for me, and I'm afraid I carried that personal anger into the debate and
and it made me less effective than I should have been.
But ultimately, I do want to pay tribute to Flint.
He is an excellent debater.
He's got a very sharp mind.
He's a very clever man, and he's very fast on his feet.
And I recognize that.
I, I was definitely up against a superior debater
uh, in that debate.
I'm not sure that I have those debating skills
and I certainly-  .
..
didn't have them on, on that particular day.
I also admire about Flint, uh, something else
which is that he was willing to be there.
Uh, most archaeologists don't want to talk to me at all.
They want to insult me from the sidelines.
Uh, they want to make sure that Wikipedia keeps on calling me a pseudoarchaeologist or a per- purveyor of pseudoarchaeological theories.
They want to make sure that the hints of-.
..
racism are there, but they actually don't want to sit down and confront me.
At least Flint was willing to do that
and I'm grateful to him for that, and I- I think in- in that sense it is an important encounter between people with
uh, let's say, an alternative view of history and those with a very much mainstream view of history that archeology gives us.
And he's also a- a very determined character.
He- he- he- he doesn't give up.
So all- all of those things about him
I- I admire and- and- and respect.
Um, but, um, uh, I think he fought dirty during the debate
and I've said exactly why, uh, in this video that I now have up on YouTube.
To say a positive thing that I enjoyed
I think towards the end in him speaking about agriculture was pretty interesting.
Yeah.
So the techniques of, uh, archeology are pretty interesting
like, where , where you can get some insights through the fog of time- Mm-hmm.
.
..
about, like, what people were doing- Yeah.
.
..
how they were living.
That's pretty interesting.
It's- it's very interesting.
It's a very important discipline, and I've said many times before publicly
I couldn't do any of my work without the work that archeologists do.
I emphasize very strongly in this video that I don't study what archeologists study.
Um, but nevertheless, the data that archeologists have generated over the last century or so has been incredibly valuable to me in the work that I do.
But when I- when I look at the Great Sphinx and the studies of archeology saying that this is the work of the Pharaoh Khafre
despite the absence of any single contemporary inscri- inscription that ascribes it to Khafre
and in fact the presence of other inscriptions that say that it was already there in the time of Khufu
uh, I- I am not looking at what Egyptologists study.
They just dismiss all of that and lock into the Khafre
uh, connection.
At Gobekli Tepe, I'm- I'm not really looking at what archeologists look at.
I'm looking at the alignments of the megaliths and how they seem to track precession of the star Sirius over a period of time.
Archeologists aren't interested in- in any of that.
So I- I value and respect archeology.
I think it's an incredible tool for investigating our past
but I wish archeologists would bring a slightly gentler frame of mind to it and a slightly opener perspective
and also that- that archeologists would be willing to trust the general public to make up their own minds.
It's as though certain archeologists are afraid of the public being presented with an alternative point of view
which they regard as, quote-unquote, "dangerous," uh
because they somehow underestimate the intelligence of the general public and think the general public are just going to accept that much.
Actually, by condemning those alternative point of view
archeologists make it much more likely that the general public will accept those alternative point of view
because there is a great distrust of experts in our society today
and behaving in a snobbish, arrogant way
"We archeologists are the only people who are really qualified to speak about the past
and anybody else who speaks about the past is dangerous
" that actually is not helpful to archeology in the long term.
Th- there could be a much more positive and a much more cooperative relationship
and I can see that relationship with, uh
with a gentleman like Ed Barnhart.
Mm-hmm.
Was very much the case with, uh
archeologist Martti Paasonen, uh, from the University of Helsinki
and with geographer Alceu Ranzi, a Brazilian geographer
very, very senior figure, um, who I worked with in- in the Amazon for season two of Ancient Apocalypse
looking at these astonishing earthworks that have emerged from the Amazon jungle
and which more and more are now being found with lidar.
Indeed, we found some of them ourselves with lidar while we were there.
Yeah, that was an incredible part of the show that I got a chance to preview.
That .
..
It's like, there's all this earthworks, yeah
the, uh, traces of things built on the ground that probably you can only really appreciate when you look from up above.
That's right.
So the idea that they built stuff that you can only appreciate when viewed from up above means they had a very kinda deep relationship with the- the sky.
With the sky.
Yeah.
And- and- and- and a very good knowledge of geometry as well
because these are geometrical structures.
And some of them even- even seem to incorporate geometrical games
almost of the kind, like squaring the circle.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, it's not quite that, but you have a lovely square earthwork with a lovely circle earthwork right in the middle of it.
Uh, whatever else they were, they were geometers.
They- they- they- they were not just builders of fantastically huge earthworks that nobody expected in the Amazon
uh, not just builders of cities that we now know existed in the Amazon
but that they were, uh, astronomers and mathematicians as well.
Everything we're talking about is so full of mystery
it's just fascinating, especially the farther back we go.
That's what I love about the past, is the mystery that's there
and that's another thing that I regret about some archeologists
is that their mission seems to be to drain all mystery out of the past
to suck it dry like some kind of vampire sucking the blood out of the past
and to reduce it to a series of numbers
uh, that, uh, that appear to be scientific.
I- I think that's- that's most unfortunate.
The past is deeply mysterious.
The whole- the whole story of life on Earth is deeply mysterious.
I- I mean, we were talking about the timeline of- of human beings
but you know, if you go
if you go back to the formation of the Earth itself
if I've got the figures right, it's about four and a half billion years ago that the Earth supposedly formed.
It was then incredibly hot and inhospitable to life
uh, for the next several hundred million years
but it was actually Francis Crick who pointed out something odd
that within 100 million years of the Earth being cool enough to support life
there's bacterial life all over the planet.
..
. and, and Crick wrote a book called Life Itself that was published in 1981
and he suggested that life had been brought here by a process of panspermia.
Now that's, uh, an idea that's around in circulation
that, that comets may carry bacteria which can seed life on
on planets.
But Crick actually in Life Itself was talking about directed panspermia.
He envisaged, uh.
..
This is Crick, not me.
He, he envisaged an alien civilization
uh, far away across a galaxy which faced
uh, extinction.
Perhaps a supernova was gonna go off in the neighborhood.
They were highly advanced.
Their first thought might have been, "Let's get ourselves off the planet and go and populate some other planet.
" But the distances of interstellar space were so great.
So their second thought was, "Let's preserve our DNA.
Uh, let's, uh, put bacteria, genetically engineered bacteria
into cryogenic chambers and fire them off into the universe in all directions.
" And bottom line of Crick's theory in Life Itself is one of those cryogenic containers containing bacterial life from another solar system crashed into the early Earth
and that's why life began so suddenly here on Earth.
If we as a human civilization continue, I think that is a one way to
uh, create backups of us- Mm-hmm.
.
elsewhere in the universe given the space, is to do a life gun and shoot it everywhere.
Yeah.
And there's just plants- Yes, yes.
.
..
and you kind of hope that whatever is the magic that
that makes up human consciousness, and if that magic was already there in the initial DNA
uh, of th- the bacteria.
Hm.
The potential for that magic is there.
The potential is there.
And, and evolutionary forces will, will, will work upon it and in
in different ways in different environments.
Uh, but that the potential is there.
Yes, it's something that we would do.
If we were facing a complete extinction of life on planet Earth
uh, a major global effort would be made
uh, to preserve it somehow.
Uh, and, and that might well include firing off cryogenic chambers
uh, into the universe and hoping that some of them would land somewhere hospitable.
And, uh, as you were mentioning, there's just so many interesting mysteries along the way here.
For example, I mean it's like, I think like three billion years it was single-cell organisms.
Yeah.
So it seems like life was pretty good- Yeah.
.
..
for single-cell organisms, that there was no need for multicellularity
that like- Mm-hmm.
.
..
for animals, for any of this kind of stuff.
So why is that?
It seems like you could adapt much better if you're a more complicated organism.
It took a really long time to take that leap.
Is it because it's really hard to do?
And what was the, uh, uh, what was the forcing function to do that kind of leap?
Mm-hmm.
And the same, I mean, for us to be selfish and self-obsessed
for us humans, like what was the magic leap to homo sapiens from the other hominids?
Hm.
And why did homo sapiens win out against Neanderthals and the other competitors?
Why are they not around, uh, anymore?
So those are all fascinating mysteries, and it feels like the more we propose sort of radical ideas about our past- Mm.
.
and take it seriously and explore, uh
the more we'll be able to sort of
uh, figure out that puzzle that g- leads all the way back to homo sapiens and maybe all the way back to the origin of life on Earth.
Yeah, yeah.
I think that homo sapiens is the tail end of a very long
deep series of mysteries that goes back right to the beginning of life on this planet and
and probably long before actually, because this planet is part of the universe
and God knows what else is out there in the
in, in the universe.
Wh- why do you think homo sapiens, uh
evolved?
What, like what, what was the magic thing?
There's a bunch of theories about fire leading to meat
to cooking, which can fuel the brain.
That's one.
The other is like social interaction.
We're able to use our imagination to construct ideas and share those ideas and tell great stories
and that is somehow an evolutionary advantage.
Do you have any, like favorite  conception of.
..
Well, um, it's interesting.
There's no doubt that anatomically modern humans and Neanderthals coexisted in Europe for at least 10
000 years, probably more than that.
And yet one of the, the popular views is that anatomically modern humans wiped out the Neanderthals
that we, we killed them off.
Um, but at the same time, we were interbreeding with the Neanderthals.
In a sense, the Neanderthals are not gone.
They're, they're still- Mm-hmm.
.
..
within us today.
We are part, part, part Neanderthal.
There's another theory that I've read about w- There
there is some evidence that Neanderthals were cannibals
that there was r- ritual cannibalism took place amongst Neanderthals
and particularly the eating of human brains.
Uh, and this, uh, can cause
uh, kuru, uh, which can kill off whole populations.
That's o- another suggestion of why the Neanderthals died out.
There's lots of possibilities that have been put forward.
Maybe we just out-competed them, you know?
Maybe, maybe anatomically modern humans had some brain connections that they didn't have.
Even though the Neanderthal brain was bigger than the brain of anatomically modern human beings
as the old saying goes, "Size isn't everything.
" Uh, maybe we just had a more compact
more efficient brain.
The fact of the matter is, uh
that, uh, Neanderthals and Denisovans did not survive the rise of homo sapiens.
For our discussion though, what is interesting is all the hominids seem to be explorers.
Yes.
They spread.
I mean, I didn't know this fact.
The, the fact that homo erectus was all over the planet more than a million years ago
uh, is testament to that.
Uh, and I, I do think that exploration urge is
is fundamental to humanity.
And I, I would like to say that's what I think I'm doing.
I'm, I'm exercising my urge to explore the past in
in my own way, making my own path and defining
defining my own route.
IThat's the leap from non-human to human.
Uh, one of the things you've discussed is your idea of what was the leap to human civilization!
What is the driver?
What is the inspiration for humans to form civilizations?
And for you, that's shamanism.
Definitely.
Can you explain what that means?
I think that, um, shamanism is the origin of- of- of everything of value
uh, in humanity.
Uh, I think it was the earliest form of science.
When I spend time with, uh, shamans in the Amazon
I observe people who are constantly experimenting with plants in a very scientific way.
Uh, they're always trying a pinch of this and a pinch of that in different forms
for example, of the ayahuasca brew, to see if it enhances it or makes it- makes it different in- in- in any way.
Uh, the invention of curare is a remarkable scientific feat which is entirely down to shamans in the- in the Amazon.
They are the- the scientists of the hunter-for- forager
uh, state of society.
Um, and they were the ancient, um
leaders of human civilization.
So I think all- all civilization arises out of shamanism.
Uh, and shamanism is a naturally scientific endeavor where experimentation is undertaken
an exploration, an investigation of the environment around us.
And what I'm suggesting is that- that one group
perhaps more than one group, uh, went a bit further than other groups did and- and used that study of the skies and developed navigational techniques and- and were able to sail and explore the Earth.
Uh, but that ultimately what lies behind it is the same curiosity and investigative skill that shamans are still using
uh, in the Amazon to this day.
Uh, and- and, uh, I do see them as- as scientists
in a very proper use of the word.
But do you think something like ayahuasca was a part of that process?
Yes.
Ayahuasca is the result of shamanistic investigation of what's available in the Amazon.
Uh, of course, ayahuasca is all the fad in Western industrialized societies today and- and some people see it as a miracle cure for all kind of ailments and problems.
And perhaps it is, perhaps it can be
uh, in- in certain ways.
Ayahuasca itself is not an Amazonian word.
It- it comes from the Quechua language and it means "the vine of souls" or "the vine of the dead".
Uh, but the ayahuasca vine is only one of two principal ingredients in the ayahuasca brew
and the other ingredient are leaves that contain dimethyltryptamine
and there are two sources of that.
One is a bush called Psychotria viridis, that's its botanical name
they call it chakruna in the Amazon, and its leaves are rich in dimethyltryptamine
DMT, which is arguably the most powerful psychedelic
uh, known to science.
Um, and- and, uh, the other source comes from another vine
Diplopterys cabrerana, uh, which the leaves of that vine also contain DMT.
So the ayahuasca vine on its own is not going to give you a visionary journey
and the leaves that contain DMT on their own
whether they come from Diplopterys or whether they come from chakruna are not gonna give you a visionary journey.
And the reason they're not gonna give you the visionary journey is because of the enzyme monoamine oxidase in the gut that shuts down DMT when absorbed orally.
Basically, DMT is not accessible orally unless you combine it with a monoamine oxidase inhibitor.
And that's what I mean when I'm talking about science in the Amazon
because there's so many tens of thousands, hundred th- thousands different species of plants and trees in the Amazon
and they've gone around and they found just two or three of them that put together can produce these extraordinary visionary experiences.
Just imagine the number of plants they had to have eaten.
Yeah.
And consumed and smoked, or used all kinds of combinations to arrive at that.
Exactly, exactly.
To realize that this is something- this is something very special
and then- and then to use the principles there to- to find another form of it.
So ayahuasca is the form that is made with the ayahuasca vine and the leaves of the chakruna plant.
Uh, but Yage, uh, is made from the ayahuasca vine and the leaves of another vine
D- Diplopterys cabrerana, uh, which contain not only N
N-DMT, which is the DMT that everybody's pretty much familiar with these days
but also 5-MeO-DMT.
Uh, and the Yage experience which I have- I have also had
uh, in my view is more intense
uh, and more powerful almost to the point of being overwhelming
uh, than the- than the ayahuasca experience.
But- but what the- the result of this
uh, sophisticated chemistry that we find taking place here
uh, is- is, uh, a brew which is hideous to drink.
It- it.
..
The taste, ugh, I find it quite repulsive.
Um, I almost retch just to, just smelling it in the- in the cup.
Mm-hmm.
Um, but then unleashes these extraordinary experiences.
And it isn't just pretty visuals, it's the sense of encounters with sentient others
that there are sentient beings, that somehow we're surrounded by a realm of sentience that is not normally accessible to us.
And that the, what the ayahuasca brew and certain other psychedelics like- like psy- some psilocybin mushrooms in a high enough dose can do it as well
LSD can do it, but ayahuasca is the master in this of- of lowering the veil to what appears to be a seamlessly convincing other realm
other world.
And of course, the hard-line rational scientists will say
"That's just all fantasies of your brain.
" Um, but-I don't think we fully understand or even close to understanding exactly what consciousness is.
And I remain open to two possibilities, that consciousness is generated by the brain
is made by the brain in the way that a factory makes cars
uh, but I also am open to the possibility that the brain is a receiver of consciousness just as a television set is the receiver of television signals.
Um, and- and, um, that if that i- if that is the case
then we locked into the physical realm, we need our everyday alert problem-solving state of consciousness and that's the state of consciousness that Western civilization values and- and- and- and- and highly encourages.
Uh, but these other states of consciousness that allow us to access alternative realities are possibly more important.
It may be apocryphal, uh, but it was reported
uh, after Francis Crick's role and his Nobel Prize for the discovery of the double helix that he finally got it under the influence of LSD.
There's the classic example of Kary Mullis and the polymerase chain reaction
he said he got that under the influence of LSD.
So the notion that the alert problem-solving state of consciousness is the only valuable state of consciousness is disproved by a- a- ex- valuable experiences that people have had in- in a visionary state.
Um, but the question that remains unresolved is those entities that we encounter in the.
..
and not everybody encounters them and you're certainly not gonna encounter them on every ayahuasca trip.
There are ayahuasca journeys where nothing seems to happen.
Um, I suspect something does happen, but it happens at a subconscious level.
I know that shamans in the Amazon regard those trips where actually you don't see visions as amongst the most valuable and they say you are learning stuff that you're not remembering
but you're learning it, you're learning it anyway.
Um, these sentient others that are encountered
what are they, you know?
Are they just figments of our brain on drugs or are we actually gaining access to a parallel reality where.
..
which is inhabited by consciousness which is in non- a non-physical form?
Uh, and- and I'm equally open to that idea.
I think that may be, may be what is going on here with- with ayahuasca.
But the other thing is that there is a presence within the ayahuasca brew and she is present bo- present both in ayahuasca and in yage.
And that's one of the reasons why the shamans say that- that actually the master of the process is the ayahuasca vine
not the leaves.
It's as though the vine has harnessed the leaves to gain access to human consciousness.
And there if you have sufficient exposure to ayahuasca or yage
you drink it enough times, I've had maybe 75 or 80 journeys with- with ayahuasca
uh, you s- you definitely start to feel an intelligent presence with a definite personality which I interpret as feminine and which most people in The West interpreted as feminine and they call her Mother Ayahuasca.
There are some tribes in the Amazon who interpret the spirit of ayahuasca as male
uh, but in all cases, that spirit is seen as a teacher.
Uh, that's fundamentally what ayahuasca is, it's a teacher and it teaches moral lessons.
And that's fascinating that a mixture of two plants should cause us to reflect on our own behavior and how it may have hurt and damaged and affected others and fill us with a- a powerful wish not to repeat that negative behavior again in the future.
Uh, y- the more baggage you carry in your life
the harder the beating the ayahuasca is going to give you until it forces you to confront and take responsibility for your own behavior.
Uh, and- and that is a, that is an extraordinary thing to come from a
from a pl- a plant brew in that way.
And I think in- in yes, the.
..
I- I think ayahuasca is the most powerful of all the plant medicines
uh, for accessing these mysterious realms, but there's no doubt you can access them.
..
they're- they're all tryptamines, they're all related to one another in- in one way.
You can access them through LSD and you certainly can access them through psilocybin mushrooms as well in large enough dose.
Both possibilities, as you describe, are interesting
and to me they're kind of akin to each other.
Uh, just I wonder what the- the limit of the brain's capacity is to create imaginary worlds and treat them seriously
make them real, and in those worlds explore and have real sort of moral deep brainstorming sessions- Mm.
.
..
uh, with those entities.
It's almost like the power of the human mind to imagine taken to its limit.
Mm.
It is.
Um, and the curious thing is that the same iconography.
..
people paint their visions after ayahuasca sessions.
People were painting in Europe in the Cave of Lascaux
for example, and of course, they had access to psilocybin mushrooms
uh, in prehistoric Europe.
Uh, there's a remarkable commonality in the imagery that is
that is painted.
I- I, uh, I like to give credit where credit is due and there are two names that need to be mentioned here.
One is the late great Terence McKenna and his book Food of the Gods where he proposed the idea very strongly that it was our ancestral encounters with psychedelics that made us fully human.
That's- that's what switched on the modern human mind.
And very much the same idea began to be explored a bit earlier by Professor David Lewis-Williams at the University of Witwatersrand in South Africa.
Fabulous book called The Mind in the Cave
uh, where- where he is again arguing that these astonishing similarities in- in cave art and rock art all around the world can only be properly explained by people in deeply altered states of consciousness attempting to remember-.
..
when they return to a normal everyday state of consciousness
intem- attempting to remember their visions and document them
uh, on permanent media like the, like the wall of a cave.
So typically, you get a lot of geometric patterns
but you also got entities, and those entities often are therianthropes
part animal, part human in form.
Might have the head of a wolf and the body of a human being
uh, might have the head of a bird and the body of a human being and so on and so forth.
And that they communicate with us in the visionary state.
Interestingly, although this sounds like woo-woo, and it is an area that most scientists would steer clear of at risk of their careers
there is very serious work now being done at Imperial College in London and at the University of California at San Diego where volunteers are being given extended DMT.
There's a new technology, uh, DMTX, uh
where the DMT is fed directly into the bloodstream by drip
and it's possible to keep the individual in the peak DMT state
uh, which normally when you smoke or vape DMT
you're looking, if you're lucky, at 10 minutes
or if you're unlucky, if it's a bad journey
because those 10 minutes can seem like forever.
Um, but, uh, with DMTX, with the drip feeding of DMT into the bloodstream
these volunteers actually could be kept in the peak state
uh, for hours.
And unlike LSD where you rapidly build up tolerance
nobody ever builds up tolerance to DMT.
It always hits you with the same power.
Even if you took it yesterday and the day before and you're taking it tomorrow as well
it's still gonna have that same power.
There's no tolerance there.
So that's how they can, they can use that lack of tolerance to
to keep volunteers in this state.
And then when they debrief those volunteers, they're also putting them in MRI scanners and looking at what's happening in the brain.
But when they debrief them, they're all talking about encounters with sentient others.
There's even a group now called Sentient Others where people are exchanging.
..
Volunteers are, are now exchanging their experiences.
They didn't do s- they weren't allowed to do so at the beginning of the experiment
but now that most of them have left it
they're exchanging their experiences and it's all about encounters with insentient others who wish to teach them moral lessons.
Now, uh, to me that's wild.
What, what is going on here?
Uh, what, w- what, what, what
what.
..
how do we account for this?
Yeah, I get the notion of hallucinations and brightly colored visuals
but the moral lessons that come with it
tho- those are very odd.
Yeah, and would you say that the reason that could give birth to a civilization
is it because th- such visions can help create myths and especially like religious myths that would be a cohesive thing for a large group of people to get around?
Yes, yeah, and can help us to be better members of our own community.
Right, with the moral lessons.
Yeah, more contributing members of our community
uh, more caring, more nurturing members of our community.
That's got to be good for, for
for any community.
I'm, I'm on, I've said this a dozen times but uh
uh, I'll say it again.
If, if I had the power to do so
I would make it a law, an absolute law
that anybody running for a powerful political position
particularly if that position is president or head of state in any kind of way
that that person has to undergo the ayahuasca ordeal first.
They have to have 10 or 12 sessions of ayahuasca
uh, as a condition for applying for the job.
Uh, I suspect that most who had had those experiences wouldn't want to apply for the job anymore.
They would want to live a different kind of life.
And those who did want to carry on being a leader of a nation would be very different people from the people who are leading the nations of the earth into chaos and destruction today.
Yeah, they would be doing it for the right reasons.
I mentioned to you, I recently interviewed Donald Trump and actually brought up this same
uh, same idea that, uh, it would be a much better world if most of Congress and most p- politicians would take some form of psychedelic- Yeah.
.
..
at the very least.
I have no doubt that it would be a better world .
I mean, this raises an interesting point
which is the role of government in controlling our consciousness.
Uh, and in my opinion, the, the
the so-called war on drugs is one of the fundamental abuses of human rights that have been undertaken in the past
in the past 60 years.
Uh, it should be a Republican issue.
If I understand the Republican Party correctly, the Republican Party believes in individual freedom for adults as much as possible
uh, and particularly the freedom to make choices over their own bodies.
Uh, but in the case of even cannabis
I know, th- it's one of the great things that's happening in America
it's, it's happening state by state where cannabis is being
is being legalized and that draconian hand of government is being taken off the back of people who are
who are consuming a medicine that is far less harmful than alcohol
which is glorified, uh, in, in our society.
Um, we cannot say that we are free if we allow a government to dictate to us what experiences we may or may not have in our inner consciousness while doing no harm to others.
And the point there is, we already have a whole raft of laws that deal with us when we do harm to others.
Do we really need laws that tell us what we may and may
or may not experience in the inner sanctum of our own consciousness?
I think it's a fundamental violation of adult sovereignty.
Uh, and we would have much less drug problems if these drugs were all legalized and made available to people without shaming them
without, without punishing them in any way
but just part of normal social life.
And then you could be sure that you were getting good product rather than really shitty product which has been cut with all sorts of other things.
Ultimately, the way forward is for adults to take responsibility for their own behavior and for society to allow that to happen and not to have big government taking responsibility for decisions that should be in the hands of individuals.
And for me also it's exciting, some of these
uh, substances like psilocybin are, are, uh
being integrated to s- scientific studies at larger scales.
That's really interesting.
We've seen a revolution in, in the way science looks at psychedelics in the last 20
25 years.
Um, they, they were in that highly demonized category.
But again, it's one of those paradigms which gets overwhelmed by new evidence
and it began  to be realized that
that, uh, psilocybin and, and other psychedelics are very helpful in a range of conditions from which people
people suffer.
Post-traumatic stress disorder.
Uh, the fear of death when you're
when you're suffering from terminal cancer can be overwhelming
and it's been found that, that, that
uh, psilocybin can, can remove that.
Uh, deep depressions can be evaporated with one single massive psilocybin journey.
They just go away.
There's really good science on this.
And, and they are being integrated into conventional medicine more and more.
We'll see it happening.
I'm not sure if it'll happen as much as
as fast as I would like to see it happen in my lifetime
but it is gonna happen.
Yeah, I actually, uh, just recently found out that you had a TED Talk
War on Consciousness-  Yes.
.
..
that, uh, was taken down.
Yeah.
And that was just part of just the
the general resistance.
'Cause it was, it was a pretty.
It wasn't a radical.
No.
I, I wa- It wasn't really a radical talk .
I was talking about ayahuasca.
Yeah.
And I was talking about the view that I hold very strongly that as long as we do no harm to others
sovereign adults should be allowed to make decisions about their own bodies and not face a jail sentence or
or shaming as a result.
But this.
..
So it was a TEDx Talk, not a TED Talk
organized by a local TED, TED group.
They call them TEDx Talks.
Um, and, uh, I, I gave this
I gave this talk about the war on consciousness.
And it was immediately pulled down from TED's main channel
uh, with all kinds of bizarre reasons being given.
But unfortunately it was too late, because a number of people had already downloaded the talk and then uploaded it onto other YouTube channels.
And actually, their banning of it made it go viral
uh, in a way that would not have
would not have happened otherwise.
But again, it's a sign that, that points of view that are not acceptable to those in positions of power
uh, are simply dismissed and shut down
uh, or at least attempts are made to
to do so.
In general, just along that line of thinking
I'm pretty sure that what we understand about consciousness today will seem silly
uh, to humans from a ho- 100 years from now.
You bet it will.
Uh, es- especially if we harness psychedelics to investigate consciousness and
and, uh, you know, that is
that is what is happening at, uh
at Imperial College right now, is, is the investigation of the experience.
They're not looking.
..
There are other trials that are looking for the therapeutic potential of DMT
but in this case, they're looking entirely at the experiences that people have and why they're so similar from people from different age groups and different genders and different parts of the world are all having the same experiences.
And for me, from an engineer perspective
it's interesting, if it's possible to engineer consciousness in artificial beings.
Yeah.
It's, it's, it's another way to approach the question of how special is cons- human consciousness.
How.
..
From where does it arise?
Uh, is it, is it something that permeates all of life?
And then in that case, what is the thing that makes life special?
Like, what is life?
What is these living organisms that we have here and
uh, that, that evolved to create humans
and what is truly special about humans?
And it's both s- scary and exciting to consider the possibility that we can create something like this.
Yeah.
But why not?
We're a vehicle for consciousness, in my view.
Uh, I think consciousness is present in all life on Earth.
Uh, I don't think it's limited t- to human beings.
We have the equipment to manifest and express that consciousness in the way that a dog
for example, doesn't have, or a snail doesn't have
or a pigeon doesn't have.
But when I look at two f- pigeons sitting on my garden fence and rubbing up close to each other and enjoying each other's company and taking off together and hanging out together
I think they're conscious beings.
Um, and, and I think, I c- I think consciousness is everywhere.
I think it's the basis of everything, and I suspect that fundamentally
consciousness is nonphysical, and that it can manifest in physical forms where it can then have experiences that would not be available in the nonphysical state.
That's a, that's a guess though.
That'd be a fascinating.
..
Because then you can construct all kinds of physical forms- Yeah.
.
to manifest the consciousness.
And see if consciousness enters, if they become consciousness.
Isn't, isn't there some suggestion that artificial intelligence is already becoming conscious?
That makes humans really uncomfortable.
Yeah.
Because we are at the top of the food chain.
We consider ourselves truly special, and to consider that there's other things that could be special- Mm-hmm.
.
..
is, uh, is scary.
Well, look how other people make us uncomfortable too.
I mean, look at the state of the world today.
Uh, all the conflicts that are, that
that, that are raging.
Uh, that's, that's because we're afraid.
When I say we, I'm speaking nation by nation
that, that, we, we are afraid of other people.
We fear that they're going to hurt us or damage us in some way
and so we seek to stop that.
It's the, it's the root of many
many conflicts, this, this fear.
And so fear of AI may not be such a good idea after all.
It might be very interesting to go down that route and see where it comes.
Certainly, in terms of exploring consciousness, it is very interesting.
Yeah.
Fear is a useful thing.
Mm-hmm.
But it can also be destructive.
Well, it can be destructive and it can shut you down completely.
If you look into the, into the future
maybe the next hundred years, what- what do you hope are the interesting discoveries in archeology that we'll
that we'll find?
Well, I'd really like to know how the Great Pyramid was built.
Uh, and- and we now have with new tech
with- with scanning technology, it's now become apparent that there are many major voids within the Great Pyramid.
Uh, uh, right above the Grand Gallery
there's, uh, what looks like a second grand gallery that has been i- identified with remote scanning.
Uh, and- and, um, new chambers
one of them has even been opened up
uh, already, are being found as a result of this.
So- so it may be that the se- that the Great Pyramid will ultimately give up its secrets.
I often think that the Great Pyramid is- is partly designed to do that.
It's designed to invite its own initiates.
Some people aren't interested in the Great Pyramid at all
uh, but some people are fascinated by it and they're drawn towards it.
And when they're drawn towards it, it immediately starts raising questions in their minds and they seek answers to their questions.
So it's like saying, "Here I stand.
Investigate me.
Find out about me.
Figure out what I am.
Why have I got these two shafts cut into the side of the so-called Queen's Chamber?
Why do they slope up through the body of the Great Pyramid?
Why do they not exit on the outside of the Great Pyramid?
Why when we send a robot up those shafts do we find them after about 160 feet blocked by a door with metal handles?
Why when we drill through that door to see what's beyond it
three or four feet away we see another door?
" Uh, it's, like, very frustrating but it's- it's saying to us
"Keep on exploring.
If you, if you're persistent enough, we'll eventually give you the answers.
" So I'm hoping that that answer will come as to how this most mysterious of monuments was actually built and the inspiration that lay behind it.
Certainly, I'm sure it was never a tomb or a tomb only.
Uh, the later pyramids might have been.
Actually, no pharaonic burial has been discovered in any pyramid.
But- but, uh, nevertheless, it's pretty clear that the later pyramids with the pyramid texts written on the walls
like the Pyramid of Unas, fifth dynasty pyramid at Saqqara
uh, were- were tombs.
Um, but- but, uh, the Great Pyramid
to go to that length to create a tomb
to make it a scale model of the Earth
uh, to orient it perfectly to true north
to make it six million tons, this is not a tomb.
Uh, this is something else.
This is a curiosity device.
This is something that is asking us to understand it.
And I hope we will understand it, and I hope
I hope Egyptologists will be willing to set aside that prejudice that they're only looking at a tomb and consider other possibilities.
And as new tech is revealing these previously unknown inner spaces within the Great Pyramid
I think that's gonna become more and more likely.
So not just the how it was built
but the why.
But the why.
And to you it seems obvious that there would be a cosmic motivation.
Yeah.
Very, very much so.
As above, so below.
Yeah.
Uh, you know, which is, which is an idea in the Hermetica.
Uh, the god Hermes for the Greeks was the Greek version of Thoth
the wisdom god of ancient Egypt, and that's where that saying comes from.
It comes from the Hermetica.
Uh, but it's expressing an ancient Egyptian idea to mirror the perfection of the heavens on Earth.
Do you think there's something interesting to be discovered about the how it was built?
I mean, beyond the sort of the- the ideas of the r- using ramps and wet sand?
Yeah.
Ramps won't do it.
Ramps won't do it, nor will wet sand.
Uh, it's true that the ancient Egyptians did haul big objects on sleds on wet sand.
Uh, there are even reliefs that show the process where an individual is standing on the front of the sledge pouring water down to- to lubricate the sand underneath and- and that's a perfectly respectable way to move a 200-ton block of stone
uh, across sand if you.
..
Flat sand, if you have enough people to pull it.
But th- that is not gonna help you get dozens of 70-ton granite blocks 300 feet in the air
uh, to form the roof of the King's Chamber and the floor of the chamber above it and the roof of that chamber and the floor of the chamber above that and so on and so forth.
Wet sand never got those objects up there.
Somehow they were lifted up there.
Now, uh, yeah, ramps are proposed as the solution
but- but where are the remains of those ramps?
If you're going to carry, uh, blocks weighing up to two or three tons right to the top of the Great Pyramid to complete your work
you're gonna need a ramp that's going to extend out into the desert for more than a mile at a 10-degree slope.
And it's calculated that a 10-degree slope is about the maximum slope that human labor can haul objects up a ramp.
Um, and that ramp can't just be compacted sand since heavy objects are being hauled up it.
It's gonna have to be made of very solid material
almost as solid as the pyramid itself.
Where is it?
We don't see any r- any trace of those so-called ramps that are supposed to have been involved in the construction of the pyramid.
I think we don't know.
I think we have no idea it's built.
That's why there's so many different theories.
We haven't got the answer yet.
But the how of it is one of the big mysteries from our past.
I love the Great Pyramids as a kinda puzzle that was created by
uh, the ancient peoples to be solved- Yeah.
.
..
by later peoples.
I mean, y- this is, uh, I don't know if you're aware of the
uh, 10,000 Year Clock, but- I'm not
no.
.
..
oh, that was built by Jeff Bezos and Danny Hillis- Mm-hmm.
.
..
in, uh, Sierra Diablo Mountains in Texas.
Right.
So they're building a clock that ticks once a year for 10
000 years.
Oh, wow.
So it's talking about.
..
It, and it's supposed to sort of run
you know, if there's a nu- nuclear apocalypse
it just runs.
It will keep going.
And it's- it's an example of modern humans thinking like
"Okay.
If 10,000 years from now and beyond- Yeah.
If something goes wrong or, or the future humans that are way different- Mm-hmm.
.
..
come back- Mm-hmm.
.
..
and they, they analyze what happened here
how can we create monuments that they could then analyze?
Yeah.
And is, i- is, in that way be curious about in
in their curiosity discover some deep truths about this current time?
Mm-hmm.
It's an interesting kinda notion of like what can we build now?
That would last.
And the answer is that the majority of what we build now wouldn't last.
Wouldn't.
Uh, it would be, it would be gone
uh, within a few thousand years.
Um, but what would last is massive megalithic structures
uh, like the Great Pyramid.
That would, that would last, uh, and
and it could be, it could be used to send a message to the future.
Uh, I think Gobekli Tepe serves a similar function.
I mean, there it was, it was buried
uh, 10,400 years ago and then for the next 10
000 years nobody touched it, nobody knew it was there.
It, it, it took the genius of Klaus Schmidt
the original excavator, to realize what he'd found and what it
and what it was.
But the great thing about the sealing of Gobekli Tepe
the deliberate burial of Gobekli Tepe, is it means that no later culture trod over it and imposed their organic materials on it and messed up the dating sequences and so on and so forth
or vandalized it or used it as a quarry.
It's all there intact.
So you mentioned that, uh, the pyramids and some of the other amazing things that humans have built has
was the results of us humans struggling with our mortality.
That's the, that's the ultimate, the ultimate goal.
That seems to me what's at the heart of many pyramids around the world is that they're connected in one way or another to the notion of death
uh, and to the notion of the exploration of the afterlife.
And, and this is of course the fundamental mystery that all human beings face.
We may, we may wish to ignore it
we may wish to pretend that it's not gonna happen
but we are of course all mortal.
Uh, every one of us, all eight billion or however many of us that are on the planet right now
we're all gonna face death sooner or later.
And the question is, what happens?
And there are a few cultures that really intensely deeply studied that mystery.
We are not one of them.
The general view of science I think is that we're accidents of evolution.
When we die, the light blinks out
there's no more of us, there's no such thing as the soul.
But that's not a proven point.
There's no experiment that proves that's the case.
We know we die, but we don't know whether there's such a thing as a soul or not.
Yeah, it's the great mystery.
It's the great mystery that we all share
and those cultures that have investigated it, and ancient Eg- ancient Egypt is the best example
uh, have investigated it thoroughly and map out the journey that we make after death.
But that notion of a journey after death
and of hazards and challenges along the way
and ultimately of a judgment, uh, that notion is found right around the world and it
and it even manifests into the three monotheistic faiths that are still present in the world today.
Well, you're one such human.
Uh, and you've said you contemplate your own death.
Yeah.
Are y- are you afraid of it?
No.
I'm not afraid of death at all.
Uh, I'm curious about death.
I think it could be very interesting.
Uh, I think it's the beginning of the next great adventure.
Um, so I don't fear it.
And, and, um, I would like to live as
as long as I'm, my, my body is
is, is healthy enough to make living worthwhile.
Um, but I don't fear death.
What I do fear is pain.
Uh, I do fear the humiliation that old age and the collapse of the faculties can bring.
I do fear the cancers that can strike us down and riddle us with pain and agony.
That I fear very, very much indeed.
But death is gonna come to all of us.
I accept it.
It's gonna come to me.
And I'm not gonna say I'm looking forward to it
but when it happens I'm going to approach it
I hope, with a sense of curiosity and a sense of adventure
uh, that there's something beyond this life.
Uh, it isn't heaven, it isn't hell
but there's something.
The soul goes on.
I think reincarnation is a very plausible idea.
Again, modern science would reject that.
But there's the excellent work of Ian Stevenson
Children Who Remember Past Lives, uh, who
who found that children up to the age of seven often have memories of past lives.
And in cultures where memories of past lives are discouraged they tend not to express that much
but in cultures where memories of past lives are encouraged
like India, they do express it.
And he found several subjects, children under the age of seven in India
who were able to remember specific details of a past life and he was able to go to the place where that past life unfolded and validate those
those, those details.
So if, if consciousness is the basis of everything
if it's the essence of everything and consciousness benefits in some way from being incarnated in physical form
then reincarnation makes a lot of sense.
All the investment that the universe has put into creating this home for life
uh, may have a much bigger purpose than
than just accident.
What a beautiful mystery this whole thing is.
Yeah.
We are immersed in mystery.
We live in the midst of mystery.
We're surrounded by mystery.
And if we pere- pretend otherwise, we're deluding ourselves.
And Graham, thank you so much for inspiring the world to explore that mystery.
Thank you for talking today.
Thank you, Lex.
It's been a pleasure.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Graham Hancock.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you with some words from Charles Darwin
"It is not the strongest of the species that survives
nor the most intelligent.
It is the one that is the most adaptable to change.
" Thank you for listening, and I hope to see you next time.