On the first day, this guy sent me to buy lunch.
And I came back,
and I'd bought lunch for, like, four people,
and I give 'em their lunch.
And then I give the guy back his change.
And I'd recorded exactly how much his change was gonna be.
So his change is something like,
I don't know, £12.74.
And I put it on the desk, "Here's £12.74."
He looks at it, and he's like, "What's that?"
And I said, "It's the change."
And he didn't say anything.
So I just waited. I was like, "It's £12.74."
And he doesn't say anything.
He just slides the money along his desk into the drawer.
And then he looks at me.
He looked at me like he was gonna kill me.
And he said, "On this desk, we keep the change."
Where I grew up is a very poor area, central Ilford.
I lived on a little terraced street called Francis Avenue.
Yeah, a street full of small terraced houses,
the trains out from Essex
went right through the back garden.
Canary Wharf skyscrapers,
I think the first one probably went up
when I was something like seven or eight,
something like that,
and then the latter ones went up
maybe when I was getting sort of 10 or 11.
And we could see 'em go up on the horizon,
and, you know, you're forgetting, obviously,
'cause London's full of skyscrapers,
but at the time,
those were the tallest buildings in the country.
And as kids we were like,
we thought they were enormous.
And you could get the DLR, Docklands Light Railways...
For those who don't know, 'cause not everyone's from London,
it's this set of, like, kind of toy trains with no driver,
and you can sit at the front,
and it went through Canary Wharf.
And I remember as a kid, you take the train through,
I'd look, sit at the front, pretend to be the driver.
And I'd look up all these skyscrapers.
Which at the time, they just seemed enormous.
They seemed enormous to us.
And as kids,
you see those skyscrapers go up on the horizon,
it is a big thing you kind of aspire to.
I was good at English at school,
and I remember my English teacher would say,
"You have a very mathematical style of writing."
And when I was a kid, I was obsessed with rules.
My parents would know,
like, "If you wanna get Gary to do something,
give him a rule."
They would be, they said to me,
"You can have one chocolate bar a week."
And I would be, like, collecting
six chocolate bars under my bed
until my mum would steal them one day.
I would just be, I was that kind of kid,
and in some sense I was a natural economist.
I wanted to optimise the rules that I was given.
It's weird in a way,
but I had to have a system
and a set of rules for everything.
I mean, I knew that my parents were hard up,
and I think I really internalised from a young age
that I didn't wanna take any money from my parents.
I wanted to make my own money.
So as soon as I turned 12 or 13,
or whatever the legal age is,
that's when I started my first paper round.
As soon as I turned 16, I tried to get a Sunday job.
Once we, I got to 15, you know,
people started taking drugs,
and there was a little bit of involvement in that,
and I ended up getting expelled from school
when I had just turned 16,
at the beginning of year 11.
I got expelled from school for drugs.
I was a good student so everybody kind of thought...
And I went to this fancy grammar school,
and that fancy grammar school is called
Ilford County High School.
You go to the... in the hall, they have on the wall
the names of the kids that went to Oxford and Cambridge.
And you just kind of assume,
'I'm gonna be on that wall.'
And then suddenly you're expelled from school,
and everybody thinks you're gonna go to prison, basically.
And it was tough.
I was young, you know. I'd just turned 16.
You're separated from all of your friends...
I remember I woke up the next day,
and my parents were both at work,
my older brother was at work,
my younger sister was at school.
And you're just like, "Well, what am I gonna do?"
You know, you don't have nowhere to go
for the first time in your life.
You know? You don't have anywhere to go.
And I went and I took a shower
in my parents' old house.
You used to sort of,
you'd get this rubber hose
and stick it on the taps and sit in the bath.
I remember sitting in the bath,
like, holding this little rubber hose,
and watching them all go down the drain and thinking,
"That's your life if you don't do nothing."
It was really hard to get into a sixth form, obviously,
because I had all these great grades,
but I'd been expelled from school.
And I couldn't get into any local schools.
And I remember I walked into,
there was a school near me called Valentines,
which is where a lot of my friends
from primary school ended up, going to the local comp.
Their teacher was a famous economics teacher,
and he'd written my economics textbook.
And I walked in randomly in the summer,
and I was like, into the office,
and I was like, "Can I come here for sixth form?"
He was like, "What are your grades?"
And I was like, "Eight A*s, three As."
He said, "Did you take economics?"
And I said, "Yeah, I took economics."
He goes, "What did you get?"
I said, "I got A*."
He said, "What textbook did you study?"
And then I clocked it must be this guy.
And I said, "Oh, your textbook, sir."
And that was it. He accepted me into the school.
I got four As, and I got into LSE,
which is, for those who don't know,
London School of Economics.
It's a super-fancy, prestigious economics university
in Central London, where a lot of
international millionaires and billionaires
send their kids to study.
And I started there when I was 18,
doing maths and economics.
Suddenly at LSE, everybody knew who I was.
And I didn't know it was 'cause of my grades,
'cause my grades weren't the best, basically.
They were good but they weren't the best.
And I said to my mate, Sagamalda, he's a lovely guy.
And I said to him, "Why does everybody know who I am?"
And he was like, "Well, it's 'cause of your grades."
And this guy Salgamalda was number one
in the maths department in first year.
So I was like, "Well, your grade is better than mine."
And he said, "Well, yeah, of course,
but nobody expected it from you."
Suddenly at LSE you realise,
"These posh boys think we're dumb.
They actually think that we're stupid."
And then I think that sort of,
that sort of lit a little bit of a fire,
which made me sort of think,
"Well, you know, let's show 'em that we're not stupid."
Yeah, I think that motivated me as well.
It's a three-year course,
and the first year was quite easy.
You get to second year
and everyone suddenly had gone mental, basically.
And people had become obsessed
with investment banking internships.
They started wearing suits.
People were coming to university in suits for no reason.
And they would, they started,
they were applying for, like, 35 internships at a time.
And they started to speak using,
all they would use,
they would use these acronyms you've never heard of:
CDSes, and CDOs, and MBSes, and MBA, and IBD,
and you'd be like,
"What are you..."
And you'd ask 'em, "What is that acronym?"
And they'd be like, "I don't know."
It's just like, everyone would just start...
And you'd just be like, "What is going on, basically?"
And so you'd speak to your mates,
like, "Why has everybody gone mental?"
Because you're thinking,
"Well, I'm gonna get the best grades,
I'm gonna get the best job."
And then my mate was like,
"Well, this is internship year."
Yeah, okay, what's internship year?
"Well, the way you get a job is you get an internship now.
You can't get a job unless you get an internship now."
And this is a problem, right,
because I don't have my grades yet.
And you know, I'm hoping I'm gonna compete
on the back of my grades,
but you don't have your grades yet.
So you're like, "Okay, well, how do you get an internship?"
and what it is, is you've gotta send a CV and cover letter.
You've gotta send 35 CVs and 35 cover letters, right?
And you know, my grades at undergrad were good,
but everyone at LSE's undergrad grade,
like, A-levels are good.
Everyone at Oxford, Cambridge,
all of their A-levels are good.
So how do you stand out at that level?
It's basically extracurriculars on your CV.
So everyone, all of these guys from rich families,
their families knew this,
and they'd been making sure
they had this extra extracurricular stuff.
So, like, this guy would've been
head of the Junior United Nations,
or this guy would've, like, founded a charity
that drives dirt bikes
through the Sahara Desert for some reason.
This guy would've, like,
played the oboe at the Royal Albert Hall.
So basically you realise,
you come in here and you're, like, 19 years old,
and you realise, "Alright, I see.
These jobs are gonna be distributed
based on how good we are at clarinet."
You realise, like... "There's no way I'm gonna get this job."
And then you can't...
I would like to say that I realised then
that the world was unfair, blah.
But the truth is, I was 19, I was just like,
"Alright, what's the next plan?"
Because I think you're a kid in London
coming from a poor background,
you just kind of expect these doors
to be slammed in your face.
So I was just like,
"All right, fine. I'm not gonna get an internship.
So what are we gonna do next?"
I was in the library one day,
and this lanky northern guy
with kind of like a Beatles haircut,
he wandered up to me.
I'd never met him before.
And he said, "Are you Gary Stevenson?"
And I was like, "Yeah."
And he said...
I'd never met this guy in my life.
He said to me,
"Citibank hires one trader a year through a card game.
It's called The Trading Game,
and if you win it you can get an internship."
And I was like, "Well, that's good,
because I'm terrible at clarinet.
So this is probably something that we can use."
To be honest, I think it's partially
just because it gives them
a little bit of a rep on campus,
like, 'Oh, aren't Citi cool and different.
They're hiring somebody through a trading game.'
But then if you actually go back
and look at the traders
that Citi hired through the trading game,
a lot of them went on to become
extremely successful traders at Citibank.
And I think actually, if you're hiring
30 traders based on how good they are at clarinet,
it kind of makes sense to hire one guy
because he's good at a maths game.
You know, trading is not a maths game, but it is a game.
And if you're able to come into this game and win it,
it probably is a sign that you might
be a good trader, you know?
It's a betting game, basically.
It's kind of a poker-style game.
Basically, they had their own specially-made deck of cards.
So there's some low cards and some higher cards.
We handed the cards out.
So five of us are playing.
We all get a card,
and there's three cards on the middle
which get turned over as we play the game.
And basically we bet with one another
what the total of the cards are gonna be.
And I knew straight away what the LSE students would do.
So if you've studied maths or economics,
or statistics or something like this,
straight away, you're gonna do
this, like, mathematical calculation in your head,
which is to calculate the expected value of the total cards,
given the card that you have in your hand.
This is not complicated maths.
Anyone who's studied maths will be able to do this.
They'll instinctively do that,
and then they'll start betting around
what they think the total is gonna be,
which is a very stupid way to play the game.
Although it's obvious,
because if you know you've got a high card,
and this guy here has a low card,
and you both start quoting based on what your card is,
you'll be betting it's gonna be,
the total is gonna be, say 70,
he'll be betting the total is gonna be, like, 50.
And I can just buy at 50,
sell at 70, buy at 50, sell at 70,
again and again and again and again and again.
So there were two rounds, basically.
There was a LSE round, which I won very easily,
and then there was a final,
where they had students from,
like, elite universities across the country,
Citibanks, target universities, whatever,
Oxford and Cambridge, and this kind of thing.
And at the final,
everyone had already played the game,
so they kind of knew the strategy.
Between the first round and the final,
I just didn't go to class.
I spent three weeks, like, obsessively memorising this game.
So by the time I got to the final,
I was, like, probably the world's
preeminent expert on this game.
I had the strategy,
which again, perhaps typically of myself,
was to be very loud and a bit obnoxious in the game,
and try and bully the market,
basically, bully the price to go
wherever I wanted it to be.
And I had an extremely low card in the final.
And my plan was to, like, bully the price up really high,
and start selling at this high price.
Because I know it can't be that high,
'cause I've got this low card.
And the cards in the middle turn over,
and they were quite high.
So I just pushed the price up
and I was just trading really, really aggressively.
The game finishes and everybody turned their cards over.
There's eight cards in the game,
five players, three in the middle.
I had the lowest card possible.
The other seven cards were the
seven highest possible cards,
which is basically statistically impossible.
It's, like, one in a 10 million chance
or something like this, it's impossible happening.
And you realise straight away,
"The game has been rigged against me."
And of course I lost enormously
because this thing that happened is
basically statistically impossible.
And I was sort of sitting there in this, like,
it was on this high floor
in this Citibank skyscraper, just asking myself, like,
"Why have they rigged the game against me?"
And then the guy who ran the games
comes to the front, and he says,
"The winner of the game was Gary Stevenson."
And he said, "We wanted to see
what he would do if everything turned out against him."
He wanted to see someone who would back himself.
And he did.
So Gary's the winner.
So yeah, they rigged the game against me,
which I think is
a little bit of a metaphor for
the world that we live in, I think.
Yeah.
So it's Canary Wharf, Citibank.
The trading floor is only on the second floor,
it's not on the top floor.
Go in, I was wearing,
I remember I was wearing a blue shirt,
and a yellow tie, a fat yellow tie, which is the...
and a terrible fitting suit jacket from Next,
which is the stuff I used to wear
to, like, go work at DFS,
the sofa store I used to work.
You get taken up these escalators,
and this massive, massive room. The trading floor
is so vast, enormous room.
Like, you walk in and it seems endless,
like, right, left, forwards,
and this, everyone has these massive walls of screens,
nine screens, 12 screens that kind of
go up around them like this.
On the first day, this guy sent me to buy lunch.
And I came back,
and I'd bought lunch for, like, four people,
and I give 'em their lunch.
And then I give the guy back his change.
And I'd recorded exactly how much his change was gonna be.
So his change is something like,
I don't know, £12.74.
And I put it on the desk, "Here's £12.74."
He looks at it, and he's like, "What's that?"
And I said, "It's the change."
And he didn't say anything.
So I just waited. I was like, "It's £12.74."
And he doesn't say anything.
He just slides the money along his desk into the drawer.
And then he looks at me.
He looked at me like he was gonna kill me.
And he said, "On this desk, we keep the change."
Just like that.
And I was like, "These guys are f**king mental, basically."
But then I was like, "Fine. Alright."
And then I started buying everyone lunch
because I was keeping the change,
just making loads of money.
And then they started kind of like testing me by, like,
"Oh, go buy lunch for this guy,
go buy lunch for that guy."
They'd all do really complicated orders
for different things,
to see if I could,
kind of testing me, like,
as if I'm gonna fail to get lunch correctly.
Part of me didn't like to be
treated like that a little bit, but I think...
I was willing to take whatever I had to take
to get where I needed to get, basically.
You know, I grew up in a very poor background.
That job was gonna make me a millionaire.
What is weird is,
you might think coming from a poor background,
I would experience, like, class prejudice,
but the trading floor,
of all the places I've ever been,
these guys loved me from the start.
And I think it's 'cause they have this idea
of this Cockney wideboy trader,
and also they have this idea
that the trading floor is a super-meritocratic place.
So when a kid actually turns up from the local area,
it makes them feel like, "Yeah, we are meritocratic."
And I think also,
like, of all the places that I've been in,
this was the only space where rather than being like,
'Poor kids are dumb,'
they were smart enough to realise,
"If this guy's managed to get this far
looking like that and speaking like that,
he's probably got something about him," basically.
And I met this guy.
He was a very wealthy guy.
He went on to become an amazingly profitable trader.
And then he had his own designated taxi driver who would drive him home
every time he got too drunk.
And his taxi driver told me one time that every time he gets too drunk,
he insists on the way home, I drop him outside the Bank of England
so he can go round
the back of the Bank of England and take a piss on the Bank of England
on the way home.
And I thought he was a f***ing hero.
I work with the maniacs.
There's another guy. He’s called Rupert,
who I think I describe as looking like he was unexpectedly dropped off
at boarding school, eight years old and not picked up till he was 21,
which I later found out to be not far from the truth and this guy was very
I think his dad was in the army, actually, like British blue blood.
Like everything has to be straight.
Everything has to be completely narrow. Nobody can cross the line.
Very rigid, angry.
He told me once, he said to me, I've got a problem, which is
every time I meet someone I need to know straight away
whether they're better than me or whether they’re worse than me.
And if they're better than me.
I hate them.
I hate them because they're better than me.
But if they're worse than me, I despise them.
And I think I realise.
I think that's why he likes hanging out with me,
because we were from such radically different class backgrounds.
I think he felt that he didn't have to compare himself to me
because people like me just don't register, just don't register
on his scale, basically.
And he would take me out like his little Cockney sidekick, in Clapham.
He got me really drunk one time and I got in trouble
because I come in the next day, I threw up, I'd to go to the bathroom
I got sent home and the next day I come in really early.
And the boss, Caleb, said to this guy, Rupert,
“Gary said it was your fault that you got him drunk.”
There was an empty seat next to me and he was once sit there
and I just thought, “Don't look at him because he'll be going mental.”
Gently, at first, I heard him like, like growling
slightly growling
like this.
And I just thought “Just don’t look at him.”
He starts growling like louder and louder and louder.
And I was just really trying not to look until he was growling so loudly
I thought, like, “I’d better look at him.”
I heard this bang and he kicked the
we had these doors, the computer, like towers behind the doors.
He kicked the doors and then go bang against the bracket.
And I looked around at him.
He was turned around to me and he was gnashing his teeth.
“Ahr, ahr”, like that. Like a like a dog, like a wolf,
like growling, barking at me in front of everyone
for like 20 seconds.
This is a room full of millionaires.
People get paid £1,000,000 a year to do this.
I don't want to point fingers too much at these guys individuals
because they're not all bad guys. They're real people
at the end of the day. I think for me, it's
it’s a crazy space and I think it's the space that makes the people go crazy.
My first big bonus was when I was,
was in the beginning of 2010 when I'd just turned 23.
And that was just under £400,000.
And that was so much more than I had been expecting.
I knew traders made a lot of money,
but I think people from my background,
when they think of a lot of money,
they think of, like, a hundred grand.
They think "Oh my God, a hundred grand."
A hundred grand is a lot of money.
And that's what I thought these guys were making.
And in fact, that had been my aim, to make a hundred grand,
and I'd ask my boss,
"What do I need to do to make a hundred grand?"
And he told me, "Make $10 million for Citibank."
So I made $12 million and I got paid this 400 grand.
And I think it was that bonus when I was 23
that kind of blew my mind.
Well, I lost $8 million in a week when it,
when I was, in 2010, when I was still 23.
I lost $8 million in a week.
And that was mad, 'cause I graduated 2008.
So a lot of my mates couldn't get jobs.
Obviously that was the financial crisis, right?
And I was halfway through this week by that point.
I had already lost, like, $5 million in three days.
And all my mates were round just playing Pro Evolution.
And you're just thinking, like,
"I've lost $5 million."
Like, how much more can I lose
before I lose my job?"
It really dehumanises you.
It's the stress and the pressure of it.
And it really, for me,
it really separated me from my,
from my friends and my family.
You can't turn round and tell them,
"I lost $5 million this week."
You know, they're not gonna understand.
And also, like, you don't want to be a d**k.
You know what I mean?
But at the same time, you can't think about nothing else.
You can't think about nothing else.
And then I got called into a meeting early 2011
with one of Citibank's top economists.
And he went through the financial situation
of a lot of the world's governments.
So I don't know if you remember, in 2011,
there was this big crisis
with the governments of Italy, Spain,
Portugal, Greece, Ireland.
This is before that kicked off.
And it was, like, all of these governments
going massively into debt.
Every year, they're spending more than they can make.
They having to sell off their assets,
their debts are exploding.
You know, including the governments of the UK,
the US, Japan, these are the biggest
governments in the world, you know.
And I come out of that meeting, and I was like,
"How can it be that my friends
are losing their houses and going into debt?"
Their families are doing that.
The world's governments
are losing their assets and going into debt.
Where are the assets going?
Who is the debt to?
It's not possible.
We can't all go into debt.
Somebody has to be on the other side of that.
We can't all lose our assets,
somebody has to be getting the assets.
And I was sitting there.
I used to have to take the sandwiches to that meeting.
So I'd had all these sandwiches around me
sitting on the desk coming out of this meeting,
where you realise, like,
all of the governments in the world
are totally f**ked, basically.
And you look around,
and you're surrounded by these, like,
fat millionaires in pink shirts,
and you realise, like,
"It's us, isn't it?
We are, we are the guys who are accumulating..."
You know, I myself was on the verge
of becoming a millionaire at that point.
You know what I mean?
You realise, "This is it.
We are accumulating the assets from the middle class,
from the government."
And then you realise it's not gonna get better,
because if the middle class families
can't afford to pay the bills
when they own their own house,
or their kids definitely won't
when they don't own their own houses,
if governments can't run a balanced budget
when they're not massively in debt,
well, they definitely can't when they are massively in debt.
And what I saw in that moment was it was gonna spiral,
it's gonna get worse and worse and worse.
That wealth would continue to be
sucked out of the middle class and towards the rich.
And I realised straight away,
that there would never be an economic recovery.
And I put this massive bet on...
I was an interest rates trader.
So my specific bet was that interest rates
would stay zero for, like, three years.
Everybody thought interest rates
were gonna come up really quickly.
And that bet was super-successful, basically.
And I made $35 million for the bank,
and I got paid $1 million myself,
basically on the back of this bet that
the global economy would collapse,
and that society would collapse.
Suddenly I was a multimillionaire
surrounded by multimillionaires,
betting the economy was gonna collapse.
And I just thought, "What the f**k am I doing here?
Why am I here?
I don't need any more money."
But at the same time,
I'd worked so hard to get to that space.
You know what I mean?
And I was the best trader in the world at that point.
And you're getting paid millions of dollars a year.
You don't wanna walk away from it.
But I think this is the,
that is the point in my career
and in my life where this voice starts to come in,
that says, "Is it right to be doing this?"
I don't think it's wrong for poor people
to do what they have to do to make money,
as long as you're not directly hurting no one.
I think rich people should be giving more.
I think rich people should be doing more.
And at that stage of my life,
I wasn't a poor person anymore, I was a rich person.
And I think I knew in my heart
I had to be doing more as well.
I got called into a meeting with my boss.
The thing is this, I hated that boss.
I really hated him,
but I had to laugh at his jokes for six months.
And then suddenly I get this bonus,
and I don't have to laugh at the guy's jokes no more.
And I was just ripping the p**s out of this guy every day.
And we start to argue a lot.
And he called me into his office,
and he was shouting at me, screaming at me.
And then I just thought,
"What the f**k am I doing?
What am I f**king doing?"
And I just looked up to my boss and said,
"I need to quit."
And my boss was like...
'Cause at that time I was Citibank's
top trader in the world.
And then senior management went mental,
and eventually they decided,
"Okay, don't quit.
We're gonna move you to Tokyo."
And I thought at the time that was a bad idea,
but I thought, I said to him,
"I don't think that's a good idea."
And he said to me, "You don't understand, you have to go."
And I was like, "Well, if you're gonna be a d**k about it,
then I'll go and take another f**king bonus then."
Which I did.
And I moved to Tokyo.
And that begins the final fight, you could say,
between me and Citibank, me leaving the bank.
I went through a difficult couple of years leaving.
It wasn't easy to leave.
But it was nice that that happened in Tokyo.
I basically had two years of, like, cycling around Tokyo,
eating ramen in little, like, corner ramen bars,
thinking about what it means
to be walking away from a $2-million-a-year job.
It was weird, you know,
but I decided I wanted to do something
about society collapsing.
Maybe I'm a f**king idiot, but that's what I decided to do,
and that's what I've been doing ever since.
I don't want society to collapse.
It's funny people ask me this, you know,
I made millions of pounds
betting that the average British family
will collapse into poverty.
Desperate poverty.
I'm talking about Charles f**king Dickens,
Oliver f**king Twist.
That is the future of this country
if we don't deal with growing inequality.
That is what I see.
It's wealth, I mean, it's wealth inequality.
It's wealth inequality.
Listen, if you allow wealth to flow
at an unbelievably rapid rate out of your middle class,
away from ordinary working families,
away from the government, towards the super-rich,
then living standards will collapse,
housing will become unaffordable.
Distribution matters.
If we're playing chess,
and you take all of my pieces one at a time,
I'm gonna f**king lose that chess game.
That is what I see when I see the economy.
We've seen government debt explode.
We've seen living standards collapse
for ordinary working people.
At the same time, the biggest and fastest ever
increase in the wealth of millionaires and billionaires.
And nobody's connecting these two things.
The reality is,
we've created a world which
tells you you need to be rich to be happy,
you need to be rich to be of value.
And yet, which simultaneously makes it
almost impossible for them to get rich.
Listen, don't buy it. Don't buy the hype on it.
You know? Yeah, work hard to take care of a family,
and be proud of yourself,
be proud of the things that you achieve,
because they're selling you a dream
that they never gave you a chance of getting.
And if you buy that dream,
you're gonna be f**king unhappy.
And I've got friends that work really, really hard,
and struggle to pay the bills.
And I want, I want those people to be proud.
'Cause that was my dad, and my mum.
Yeah. We all want to be proud
of the work that we do and realise that,
that this, these stars they're putting
in your eyes are for them, and not you.