all right, here's what i said.
i said, " describe howard marks in 280 characters.
" here's what he gave you. howard marks is a legendary investor
co and co-founder of oak tree capital. known for his sharp memos, contrarian thinking, and risk focused approach,
he made billions zigging when others zag,
especially in crisises.
when he writes, wall street listens.
pretty flattering.
> > pretty pretty good.
yeah.
[music] okay. well, i i think the best place to start is that kind of zigg while other zag.
so, i want to ask about the s & p
because you don't know much about us, but the the short version of uh
of the guy you see across from you there, sam, is
uh
sam's an entrepreneur.
sam builds his company.
he sold his company
and he took the money that he made and he said, " look, i worked hard for this money.
now, i want this money to work hard for me, but i need it to be safe.
"
and says, " sam went into a a mostly, you know, best practice lowcost index funds in the s & p 500.
and anytime i ask sam about his strategy,
or i tell him, " dude, you got to buy bitcoin, ethereum.
you got to buy this.
you got to put some money over here. " cuz i'm i'm like, you know,
if sam is vanilla, i don't even know what i am.
i'm some flavor off in the side.
that's > > how strange tutti frutti.
> > i'm tutti frutti over here.
and i keep trying to pull him over here, but he says, " no, no, no.
i like vanilla.
" and so he
um
he basically just says the long-term average of the s & p 500 is 10
%.
if i just hold this for 50 years, i'm going to double, you know, this many times, i'm good.
but, you know, i do get a little wary when
um
anything seems too safe or too too certain
or i guess too taken for granted
that this 10 % number over the long term will be the be what it'll be.
i guess what would your message be to sam? is sam
just
you know,
is he right?
is he wrong?
would you give him a caution of warning? if if he was your nephew, he looks like he might be your nephew.
if he was your nephew,
what would you be telling him? well, on the one hand, sam, you're right
because if you
if you have more money
than you need to eat, the first purpose of your money should be to make you comfortable.
it doesn't make any sense.
buffett says, " don't risk what you have and need to get what you don't have and don't need.
" it does makes no sense for somebody with a surplus of money to make their daily life less pleasant
by going to investments that put them under pressure.
> > but there's going to be a butt on your statement. it sounds like > >
but on the other hand, the riskiest thing in the world is the belief that there's no risk.
the risk in the markets does not come from the companies. the securities or the institutions
like the exchanges.
the risk in the markets comes from the behavior of people.
and it's that for that reason that buffett says
when others are imprudent, you should be prudent.
when other people are carefree, you should be terrified because their behavior unduly raises prices and makes them precarious.
when other people are terrified, you should be aggressive because their behavior
their behavior suppresses prices to the point where everything's a giveaway.
so, i don't
i mean, look,
in the long run, you're right about the s
& p
and over the over the coming years, american companies on balance are going to produce prosperity. what
what's that defined as long-term in this? > > well, i would say 20 or more > > is
is
is the
is the real long term.
and i'll tell you in a minute how i get there, but my favorite cartoon, i have a file of cartoons from over the years.
my favorite one, there's a guy, he's got his
there's a car pulled over to the side of the road.
the guy's in a phone booth. so, you know, it's an old uh
cartoon
cuz there are no more phone booths
and there's a f there as a factory going up in the background
and he's screaming into the telephone, i don't give a damn about prudent diversification.
sell my fenwick chemical. in other words,
prudent diversification
calls for certain investment positions and a variety of them in a certain composition.
reality says, " i see fenway chemicals burning to the ground. get me out. " and you have
you can't ignore reality. now, why what's reality in this case for you? reality is recognizing where things stand.
and jp morgan
uh
published a chart around the end of 24
and it was a scatter diagram showing over the years
if you bought
uh
the relationship between the s & p 500 at purchase
and the return over the annualized return over the next 10 years.
and it looked like this. on this axis we had return
and on this axis we had pe ratio
and it was a
it was a a negative correlation
which means the higher the pe ratio you pay
the lower the return you should expect.
makes perfect sense. and it showed there was a number here 23
on the pe ratio axis
and it showed
and which is what the pe ratio on the s & p was at the time.
and it showed that historically
if you bought the s & p
when the pe ratio was 23
in every case there were no exceptions.
in every case, your annualized return over the next 10 years was between 2 and minus 2.
that's all you have to know. > > and what what are we today? what is it today? 23
> > 24
because
why?
because this prices have risen. now maybe the outlook has risen. so maybe it's still 23.
but i think let's say i think 24.
um, so you can say the s & p has returned 10 % a year on average for 100 years.
i i'm happy with 10.
i'm in.
or you can say it doesn't always return 10.
by the way, one of the most interesting things about the s & p, if you do the research,
and i did it for a memo,
on average, it has returned 10 % a year for 100 years.
but do you know that the annual return is almost never between 8 and 12?
> > think about that. > > like it
it kills it
or it
> > dies destroyed. yeah. > > think about what that means. the
the
the norm is not the average.
> > but the the issue for someone like me,
so
um
a lot of our listeners
u
i'm one of them. u
you know i i was fortunate.
i had a business.
i i made a relatively large sum of money at a very young age, > > but i'm not an investor.
> > yeah.
> > like i don't know anything about public markets.
and so when i hear you say that, i think, well, i don't have an alternative.
> > well, you
you do have an alternative.
you could figure out an algorithm to rebalance your position based on relative price
and you could put it on autopilot.
i don't recommend, you know, making judgments about the future
and the appropriateness of today's price for the future you perceive,
but you can do that and and uh
there are ways to do these things even if you just use common sense.
> > what what would you be rebalancing into? so, let's say s & p pe is high.
what would be the second best uh for the sort of non full-time active investor? okay.
so, i i've tried to suppress my tendency to talk my book
until now, but but i i think an alternative is is bonds,
you know,
and in 19
i joined city bank in the investment research department in 1969 as an equity analyst.
and the bank did so horribly that in 78 i was banished to the bond department
and the bond department was the equivalent of siberia.
the good news is that at that time, american corporations pretty much gave lifetime employment.
so, i didn't get sacked, but i'm in the bond department
and i get a phone call from the head of the bond department saying
that there's some guy in in california named something like milin
and he he invests in something called high yield bonds.
can you figure out what that means? and i said, " yes.
" and i became a high yield bond investor.
and and you know what?
when you buy a bond, there's a contract that says the borrower will pay you interest every six months
and give you your money back at the end and you can figure out the return that is implied
by that contract.
and if they
if the borrower doesn't keep that contract,
over generalizing, oversimplifying,
the creditors get the company through the bankruptcy process.
so the borrower has a lot of incentive to pay you
and they almost always pay.
i've been involved in high yield bonds for 47 years and i can tell you they've almost all paid.
so today you can buy high yield bonds
whether it be the us or europe or variations on that theme what we call lowgrade uh credit
and you can buy buy it to get yields of 7 to 8.
now 7 to 8 is pretty close to 10.
so that's that that's a good thing.
the bad thing is you have to pay tax every year on the on the income.
that's a bad thing.
but for those of us who are cautious like you
and me, we might say, i'll take, you know, eight, which in the long run will give me four after tax, as opposed to 10, which after capital gains taxation will give me seven.
or maybe i'll mix them. maybe i'll own a little less s & p and a little more debt
because i'm > > that's what i do now. > > yeah.
because i'm worried. it's not all or nothing.
then that's why i
when i'm on tv shows
and they say, " well, is this a sell or buy? is this risk on or risk off?
" i resist that formulation
because it's never one or the other. it's it's a mix
and the only question that's relevant is what mix.
i think the way
when you manage your portfolio, the the operative continuum to think about is the continu continuum
that runs from aggressive to defensive.
and i think about a speedometer in the car. so zero is no risk.
100 is max risk.
100 % aggressive.
you should have a sense for your appropriate normal posture.
and it sounds to me like sam, you're a little conservative guy.
you've made so much money you can't believe it, but you don't want to give it back.
so, so i would say that you're a
you're a 65
and especially given your youth, you may be a 55 for your cohort.
so i
and
and i think you should figure out every every listener, every investor should figure out the right place for them
and try to stay there most of the time.
we need to get a couch here and you could just i'll call you dr. markx
and you know what i run
i once wrote a memo called on the couch
because i think that once in a while the market needs a trip to the shrink.
i went back
and i read a bunch of old memos
and the one that stood out to me was the uh bubble.
com one.
so, you wrote this back in 2000, and i actually have a few of these,
where i feel like there's been moments in time, maybe 2000, 2008, 2012, 2020, where
uh
it seemed like consensus was going one way,
maybe it was max greed
and you went the other way, or was max fear and panic, and then you
you were actually very aggressive.
um, you did the thing where buffett says, " be fearful
when others are greedy, and greedy when others are fearful.
" it's cool to say, but it's hard to actually do.
and i thought it'd be fun if you could kind of walk us through a couple of those moments.
and i don't know, like, you know, not to go too far down memory memory lane, but just, you know,
take us back to, you know,
the one in 2000.
what'd you see? what'd you do? how did it, you know,
how did it play out? what'd you learn from
that? take us through a couple of those, cuz i think that's your superpower.
first of all,
uh,
one of my sayings is we never know
where we're going, but we sure as hell ought to know where we are.
and at oak tree, uh,
we loudly proclaim our, uh, inability to make macro forecasts and our non-reliance on macro forecasts.
but if we want to do the right thing
visav
the macro, we should be able to figure out what's going on at the present time
and what that implies for the future.
it may not happen the thing you think it implies, but it probably has a higher chance of happening
than not happening if you're logical
and and understand history and patterns.
and i i wrote a book called mastering the market cycle, which was published in 18.
and uh
uh
i always say it's a cheesy title, but it wasn't my idea.
the publisher wanted that title because they thought it would sell more books.
but i like the subtitle and the subtitle says getting the odds on your side.
and i believe that
where we stand in the cycle determines what probably is going to happen and how likely it is.
and understanding that can improve your odds.
it can't make you a sure winner, but it can improve your odds.
and that's the best we can do in an uncertain world beset by randomness.
so, you know, i i don't know if you know that i started writing the memos in 1990. uh
uh
bubble. com on the first day of 2000 was the first one that ever garnered a response.
i went 10 years.
not only did nobody say, " hey, that was good.
" nobody even said, " i got it.
" and and and and so one of the mysteries is why i kept
> >
who who were you sending them to? > > to our clients. > >
how many > > crickets?
well, you know,
in 1990, a h 100red,
> > okay? > >
you know,
and by mail, of course,
i wrote bubble. com january the 2nd of uh 2000,
and it had two virtues. it was right, and it was right fast.
if you're right slow, it it doesn't look like you were right.
one of the great sayings in our business is
that being too far ahead of your time is indistinguishable from being wrong.
so the
the answer is i was not too far ahead. uh
in in the fall of 99
i read a book called devil take the heindostmost. it
it's
a
it's a history of financial speculation. > > were you looking for books about that
cuz you had a hunch or you just randomly read this book? > > no,
i i don't remember why i read it. uh
the idea comes first.
not my books.
my memos are not researchbased.
they're based on ideas that resonate with me.
and so i'm reading this book.
i am interested in financial speculation. i'm interested in cycles. i'm interested in in the extremes of uh
financial behavior.
uh
so that's probably why i read it.
but i'm reading this book
and it talks about all these crazy things that people did, especially in something called the south sea bubble.
uh
britain had this big national debt and they concluded that they could uh
pay it off by starting a company called the south sea company.
uh
and they granted them a license to trade with the south sea
by
which they meant not samoa but brazil
and
and they would charge them a license fee and that would pay off the debt.
and it was one of the one of the great bubbles.
and so i'm reading in the book about what people were doing in 1720
and you know people were quitting their day jobs
and hanging out in alehouses to trade the shares of the south sea company
etc
etc.
and i said that's what's going on now in the tech bubble.
people, you may recall that people were quitting their jobs, becoming day traders.
people with no money could trade stocks as long as they didn't co carry any balance overnight. and um
and
uh
young people were quitting mba programs
because they had an idea and if they waited until they graduated, somebody else would take it.
so so it just resonated.
and one of the quotes i use the most now is from uh
mark twain
who said, " history does not repeat, but it does rhyme.
there are certain themes that rhyme from generation to generation and cycle to cycle
because they are embedded in human nature
and so they recur.
" and so and when you
when you get older in our business, you know,
obviously one of the things i uh hasten to point out is there is no such thing as knowing something about the future.
and if you don't know about the future
and you want to figure out the future, there's no such thing as analyzing the future.
it doesn't exist.
and the only thing you can do to get a handle on the future is look at the past
and uh look for the repetition of patterns as twain said
and try to figure out if they apply today.
so this was very easy. so i wrote this memo bubble. com and it said what they were doing
people are doing today.
and i point tried to point out the folly of what i saw going on.
companies with no profits and no revenues were being highly valued
maybe no product
just an idea.
and that is the epitome of a bubble.
so i wrote the memo
uh
as i say
january the 2nd
sometime around midyear the tech bubble started to collapse.
so as i said in the introduction to one of my books after 10 years i became an overnight success.
and did you actually bet against it
or did you just preserve capital by not fomoing into every you know tech company
basically like
what was the
what was the win of that for you? first of all,
we're not involved.
we're basically not involved in the us stock market and we're not involved at all in technology.
so, we wouldn't have a chance to apply that.
but i think what we did is we recognized that
and by the way,
things don't happen in isolation uniquely.
so when you
when you see something like i describe in the tech bubble, you should realize
that maybe there are ramifications in other world parts of the world.
and we figured out that people were engaging in optimism, not pessimism, greed, not fear,
uh
credulousness,
not skepticism, risk tolerance, not risk aversion.
and when
uh
as buffett says about prudence,
when nobody's afraid,
unwise deals can get done easily. simple as that.
and the people who buy that stuff, it usually ends badly.
> > the way that you explain it, i think everything makes sense and i totally buy into it.
but that's actually quite challenging to understand this like macro environment and to say this is where we are.
> > yeah.
well,
uh,
you have to be clinical. you have to observe and and without emotion
understand what's going on and what the what the implications are.
and of course, the what we call what i call emotion is part of what's called human nature.
if you succumb to human nature, it tends to get you to do the wrong thing at the wrong time.
i came across a great quote within the last year from a guy who's a retired trader.
when the time comes to buy, you won't want to.
and and that in that that that encapsulated encapsulates so much wisdom
because what is it that causes the great moments to buy?
it's probably the point of lowest
uh
consensus.
so, but
when most people don't believe would be the time
that the price is going to be the lowest, right? it's the time with either the most uncertainty
or the most pessimism or the most fear,
most conservatism.
uh
so, you also want to be all those things. > > what causes those things? you're talking about
you're talking about the manifestation. what's the cause? > > bad news. i don't know.
bad news, bad events, > > bad moves, either either exogenous
or geopol or or in the economy, faltering corporate fortunes, declining stock prices, widespread losses,
and a proliferation of articles about how terrible the future looks.
so the point that's why you don't want to buy at the low.
who would want to buy under those circumstances, > > right?
and so you you talked before in your introduction
uh
about zigging when others zag.
the only thing i'm sure of is if you zigg
when they zigg, you're not going to outperform.
do you still feel that fear
uh
you know of you
like when you know you're supposed to buy, do you still feel fearful
or do you feel like nice, hello
my old friend.
i love this emotion.
this is what i'm supposed to do.
right? i mean, it's not easy, but you have to know, you have to do it.
if you think about it, the fortunes of companies and the outlook for companies doesn't change much. what
and i'm
i'm writing a memo about this
that'll come out one of these days.
and what changes is how people think about what's going on and think about the future. and co.
so what changes is the relationship of price to what i'll call value.
sometimes they hate them, sometimes they love them.
when they love them too much, you should expect them to probably go down.
that sounds like a bull market or a bubble.
and when they hate them too much, you should expect them to go up.
that sounds like a bare market or a crash.
and so you have to do the opposite.
and and the the same developments in the environment that that affect everybody else will affect you.
you're subject to them.
you feel them.
you read about them. you hear about them. everybody tells you how dire the outlook is. and you know,
uh
it's hard to ignore them, but you have to do the right thing in the face of them.
1998,
we had
uh
the russian ruble devaluation.
the debt crisis in in southeast asia
and
um
the meltdown of long-term capital management.
and one of our portfolio managers who who was young came to me
and he said, " i think this is it.
i think we're going to melt down. i think it's all over. i'm terribly pessimistic.
" i said, " tell me why.
" he went through his reasoning.
i said, " okay, now go back to your desk and do your job. " a
a
a battlefield hero.
and i don't want to compare what we do to being a battlefield hero.
but a battlefield hero is not somebody who's unafraid.
it's somebody who does it anyway.
and that's that's the way you have to be. > > can i actually
can i ask
let me ask you about that?
because so it's funny.
interesting enough, even though i'm the conservative one, i'm actually way more emotional. sean's like a more
uh
mostly is
is is a pretty stable guy emotionally.
i go up and down, which i think is actually closer to the average for um average folks.
you said something really
you said a bunch of stuff about emotion in the past.
i think you said to be a good investor, you better
uh
be able to invest without emotion or at least act as if you don't have a lot of emotion.
has there ever been anything like a mindset shift
or a practice or something that you've had to use in order to learn to be less emotional
when investing? no, these things are not intentional on my part.
> > you think you were born like that? > > i was born unemotional,
by the way.
and and i want to point out here because my wife's downstairs having lunch that that
uh
i i wrote in my book that it's really important to be unemotional in investing. uh
not so good to be unemotional in life in in arenas like marriage.
uh
so there it's not an advantage. but
no, for me
it came naturally. i don't have to
i don't have to say, " oh, there i go again.
i'm getting emotional. i have to restrain that. " blah, blah, blah. it
and and and my partner, bruce kh,
who's been my partner successfully for 37 years, he's pretty much the same.
so, that makes it easy.
i don't have to restrain him.
> > we we've gassed you up about some of your your best moves.
what's the worst mistake you made due to an emotional mistake
where you you didn't control your temperament properly and you made a mistake?
my worst mistake is not
and i know you're talking about a point in time.
my worst mistake is that i have always been too conservative. my parents were traumatized by the depression.
i always say the question is not whether your parents were alive during the depression
but whether they were adults.
my parents were adults. they were born in the 19s and so in the depression
they were in their 30s and they were
they
you know
and the depression was really traumatic. nobody knows what it was like
and it ground on for over 10 years
and and so you when you grow up with parents of the depression
they say things like don't put all your eggs in one basket save for a rainy day.
you know that kind of stuff.
and i ended up too conservative. and i
i
if
if i wasn't as conservative, i'd be richer today. i'm not sure i'd be happier. uh
because > > what's an example?
what do you mean you were too conservative? like i
i guess
like
how
what makes you say that?
what would you have done differently
had that not
had that wiring not been done in you?
> > well, i mean
uh
i
i don't know.
i might i might have gone to an into an a more aggressive asset class than credit
like equities.
i might have become a venture capitalist
or
uh
you know
like my son andrew or a private or a leveraged buyout investor.
but you know the reason i was talking about the appropriateness of credit for sam is
because while the returns are a little lower
there's much less uncertainty and downside.
so i i would say
that if i i've been in this business 56 years, if i would have spent those 56 years in less conservative asset classes, uh
i would have made more money. having said that,
it happens that i went into things like high yield bonds in 78
and distress debt in 88
and if i had not been a conservative person, i probably wouldn't have had any clients
because they would have been scared off by the risk.
so it served me well in in pioneering in those businesses. but that was my
i
i mean
i ne
we never had a mistake
like we were too defensive at a in a crisis or too aggressive in a bubble.
we just i just was too conservative all my life.
> > and that kind of makes sense because you
i don't think you started oak tree
until your late 40s, right? > > just short of my 49th birthday.
> > yeah.
and so well
i i guess
leading up to it, were you already financially successful? were were you a success leading up to that?
> > yeah.
> > and and so was it a big risk to start oak tree?
> > i was secure. i
i wasn't rich by today's standards
and i may not have been rich by the standards at the time, but i had
i had lot
i had good money
and i lived well.
so i started running money in 78. i joined my oak tree founder partners in 85
88.
we did a great job through a a variety of environments
and we weren't worried about the ability to do a good job
and we had enough money to eat.
so it it wasn't
i mean
but it it it
i had to overcome my innate caution. my wife had to give me a kick in the ass
uh
which she
happily did.
um
i
i may not have done it without her. probably wouldn't have. you
uh
you said you're
you're too conservative, but there's been times when you've been very aggressive and
uh
you know
i think the sort of 0708 financial crisis
i read something that > > as the crisis happens
you go raise $ 10 billion
cuz you see the opportunity and you started deploying something like $ 600 million a week
which is just sounds badass to be honest. i don't
even
maybe
that's
maybe that's not not as crazy in the financial world
but that sounds crazy to me. well, it
your
your fact set is inaccurate in one regard.
we did not raise 10 billion after the crisis hit.
because
remember what i said about the guy who said when the time comes to invest, you won't want to.
you can't raise money in a crisis. you
if you went to people, he say world's melting down.
we're going to buy all this stuff.
it's going to be a bonanza.
we're going to get rich.
nobody will give you money.
why? because the same factors that influence the world influence the people you talk to.
and no, everybody will stick their hands in their pockets and say
maybe later after the after the dust settles
and and like
and a lot of people say
uh
you know we're not going to try to catch a falling knife
and i believe that you you make the big money catching falling knives carefully.
so what happened is we
like i described about the tech bubble in 2000.
we detected in'056 that the world was behaving in a in a carefree manner
and and i i would wear out the carpet between my office and bruce's with the wall street journal
and i'd say, " look at this
look at this piece of junk that got issued yesterday.
there's something wrong.
if a deal like this can get done, the world is exercising inadequate prudence.
> > specifically on mortgage is
or or just > > i didn't know about mortgage.
i never heard of mortgages.
i never heard a sub
i
i don't think i ever heard the word subprime.
i don't think i ever knew what a mortgage back security was.
it just seemed that the world was operating in a prorisk fashion. and when people are pro-risk, they they
they permit bad deals and they pay prices higher than they should.
so what happened was on on the first day of'07, we went out to our clients
and we said we think there's an opportunity.
uh
we didn't
i don't think we raised funds in'05 or six for his
uh
distress debt area,
but on the first day of 07
we went out
and we said we think there's a great opportunity coming and we'd like to have three billion.
the
at that time the biggest distress debt fund in history was our 01 fund
which preceded the enron meltdown and so forth
and it was two and a half billion
and so two and a half
yeah
around there
so
uh
we went out to clients
we said we'd like to have three
that would be the biggest distress to fund in history
so within a month we had eight and we said you know we can't do anything with 8 billion
it's it's
it exceeds our ability to invest it wisely.
so, we're going to take three
and a half billion
and we're going to close the fund, but we would like to have the remainder of your interest in a standby fund
that we'll implement if the stuff hits the fan.
so the first fund was seven and it was three and a half billion
and the next fund was 7b
and by the time we finished raising money for it a year later it was 11 billion
and with and we and fund 7 got fully invested. so we started investing gradually investing 7b
uh
in june of08. it's sitting there on the shelf
and by september 18th 15th
it was
uh
no
18th
it was
uh
12 % invested
so just over a billion and lehman brothers declares bankruptcy.
and so the question which you implied was do you invest it or not?
you're sitting there with all that money, but the it looks like the world's going to melt down.
do you invest it? very simple.
and uh
this,
as you say,
i think this was one of our uh best moments
because i reached a very simple conclusion.
if we invest it and the world melts down, it doesn't matter what we did.
but if i don't invest it and the world doesn't melt down, then we didn't do our job. qed,
you have to move forward.
i also wrote that it's hard to predict the end of the world.
it's hard to assign a high probability to it.
it's hard to know what to do if the world is going to melt down.
if you do those things and the world doesn't melt down, it's probably a disaster
and most of the world time the world doesn't melt down.
that was the
that was the sum of our analysis because there was nothing to analyze.
there had never been a global financial crisis before.
the the meltdown of the financial sector had not been anticipated since the great depression
and there was
there
was
there were no past patterns to extrapolate.
so you have to resort to logic. that was the logic.
so, as you say,
we invested450 million a week for the next 15 weeks in that fund, which was 7 billion.
and oak tree overall invested an average of 650 million a week for the next 50
uh
15 weeks.
> > how did that turn out?
so, that's what you put in.
how did what was the sort of result of that that investing during that time? well, it was great
except for
i mean we got good buys and we made good money, but the fed mobilized
uh
very
astutely
cutting interest rates to zero for the first time in history
at the beginning of 09
and introducing qe
and those two things saved the economy. so we didn't get the meltdown that everybody was afraid of
and there were relatively few bankruptcies
especially outside the financial sector
that res resulted from the global financial crisis. so we had
we've had some barn burner funds in crisis. uh
this was very good but not a barn burner. > > you've you
you've
you've done something that i love
which is
um
well
you
you've quoted a ton of different people.
you've quoted mark twain a bunch of times. you've had all these quotes
which like clearly shows that you retain information that you read
and i imagine you read a lot.
can i ask you about your reading habits? how do you pick what books you read? > > i
i've never read any books about how to be an investor like you know
multiply this by that and add this and subtract that.
and the books i've found most interesting have always been the ones about investor behavior.
and i mentioned
devil take the hindmost
uh
one of the greatest books i ever read was
before that
uh
john kenneth galbra's
book
uh
called the short history of financial euphoria.
that was really pivotal for me
and since i'm a slow reader
uh
i like the fact that it was only about a 100 pages.
and then you know
back in back in uh
i think charlie ellis wrote an article winning the losers game
where he said that because
uh
you can't predict the future
active investing doesn't work
he was a believer in the efficient market. so rather than try to hit winners like the tennis player
you should try to avoid hitting losers and keep the ball in play. um
and that has always defined my uh investing style.
in fact, i wrote a memo in the summer of 24
or 23 called fewer winners, fewer losers or more winners.
and that's the basic choice of investing style. there's a great
i think
like sort of math paradox that you've pointed out
which is that you know a fund
i don't know if it was your fund
but any fund it could be
you know
never above
never in the top 10 % but sort of never in the bottom 50
%
and there's this strategy of >
>
just consistently being above average will place you in the top 5
%
right
it'll
it'll place you in the top percent
uh
can you unpack that idea a little bit
i just i just sort of butchered it
>
in uh
i wrote a memo called the route to performance
and i had uh dinner in minneapolis with my client dave van bencoten
who ran the general mills pension fund.
and he dave explained to me that he had run the fund for 14 years. and in 14 years
the the equities
general mills equity portfolio was never above the 27th percentile or below the 47th percentile.
so 14 years in a row solidly in the second quartile.
now if you said to the normal person not in the investment business, so this thing fluctuated between the 27th
and the 47th.
where do you think it was for the whole period? they would say, well, let me think.
probably around 37th.
the answer is fourth.
so if you
if you can do well for 14 years in a row
and avoid the tendency to shoot yourself in the foot in a bad year,
you can pop up to the top.
at the same time, another investment management firm had a terrible year
because they were deep value investors and they were heavy in the banks
and the banks suffered terribly. so they were at the bottom.
so the president comes out
and of course things people in the investment business are great rationalizers and communicators.
and he says the answer is simple.
if you want to be in the top 5 % of money managers, you have to be willing to be in the bottom.
well, that makes great sense
except that my clients don't care if i'm ever in the top five
and they absolutely don't want to see me in the bottom five.
so, my reaction is the first guy's approach is the right one for me.
so, that's why at oak tree, we go for fewer losers, not more winners.
> > yeah, i love that because it's one of the um unsexy ideas.
i think any idea you can't, you know, make a movie about or won't make you sound really cool
are generally undervalued ideas when they
when they actually logically math out the way the way that one does.
and so i i sort of that was one that stuck out to me is nobody's going to
nobody's
going to give you a motivational video about being consistently above average
and just never shooting yourself in the foot, right? it's all about heroic greatness
and huge risks you can take and, you know,
being willing to do it. and so, you know,
that's all you hear.
> > but, but you know,
uh,
the financial times of london, every saturday they they have an article, uh,
called the lunch with the ft,
and they take somebody to lunch and they write an article about the person, the restaurant, and the food.
and they did that with me in late 22. and uh
i
uh
took the reporter to
my favorite italian restaurant near the office in new york
where i go 100 % of the time if i have a lunch.
and i and i said to her, eating in this restaurant is like investing at oak tree.
always good, sometimes great, never terrible.
now, that to to me
that sounds like a modest boast, but if you can do that for 40
or 50 years, i think it'll compound to great results.
uh,
if you never shoot yourself in the foot, and i think it's
i think i
i don't know if the sec is listening, but i think it's descriptive of what of what we've accomplished.
there's like this um class of investor that's like kind of become like folk hero
you know
like warren buffett's an obvious one where the like a folk hero sort of
uh
they're high integrity
they make greatness seem achievable and relatable
uh
which is like a whole skill in itself
and and you've become one of these
like folk heroes
um
you know
and a lot of them they have in common
where they like write a lot
they write
well
they've got wonderful sayings
uh
they make challenging things easy to understand
did you purposely tried to become like this public figure. > > well,
first of all, you can't ask
uh
somebody who did whether they did
cuz they'll say no.
nobody will admit that.
nobody will say my my public persona is a facade.
> > me and sam were joking before this, we were saying it's cool
how
uh
it's interesting how i think when you started as an investor, there was like no celebrity investors.
there's no like famous person who was doing what you were doing. and then now you have
whether it's buffett or munger,
there's
like the investment guys are now like the philosophers.
> > yeah.
> > the tech ceo nerds are now like the power players of the world, right? > >
uh
podcaster comedians are now like the new trusted media. it's like this very strange shift on all fronts
where
um
you know
influence has sort of shifted.
but i i find the like investment crossover life philosopher to be just like one of the really wholesome ones
that i i personally really like, you know.
> > right. well,
you know, i i i hesitate to put myself in the same category, but i think warren has always tried to just educate people
and share his knowledge
and
and people say, " well, why do you give away your secrets? aren't you afraid
that other people will emulate you
and and catch up with you? " but i i don't think so
because, you know, we can tell them all day long what what you should do, but it's hard to do.
like we said at the beginning of the podcast,
friend of mine, richard oldfield in london wrote a book once entitled simple but not easy.
i think the things we have to do are simple. they're just not easy to do.
i think buffett makes investing seem simple because he boils it down to the essential ingredients.
by the way, you said there were no famous investors. i
but i think buffett started around 53
if i'm not mistaken. uh
he just wasn't famous. uh
yeah.
uh
but
and
and there were a few people who were famous in the investment business, but i don't think anybody was
was
uh
famous in the in the wider world.
well, what's interesting for
like the normal guys like me and and and sean is like
we learn from you about how to live life and you just and you
and
and that's kind of cool
and it
just like investing is just your way of like testing if your way of living is true, > > right?
well, investing is a lot like life.
but but and and by the way,
uh
i'm working on a book along those lines, sam.
> > what's it called? > > uh
i don't know yet.
uh
but
if you wait a few years, i think it'll be out. > > well, we appreciate you coming.
uh
i do want to leave you with what it's a question for for for you.
so, we've asked you a bunch of questions, but i i actually think it would be interesting. um
what question do you think people who listen to this should ask themselves? what's a
what's a useful question that you think people could ask themselves as a
as a final final note here? well, i would think in terms of the mistakes that investors made
and i would ask yourself whether you make them.
uh
so what are the big mistakes investors make? uh
i
i can think of three. number one, do you think you do
you think you understand what the future holds and and do you reasonably think that's accurate?
uh
number two,
i think the biggest single mistake
that investors make is that they think the world will remain the way it is.
that the things that are working today will continue to work.
the things that aren't working will continue not to work.
uh
that the trends are in motion will continue. and that there won't be any new trends.
so do you
do
you
are you part of that?
and then number three is
do your emotions
uh
rise and fall and get you to do what they want as opposed to what you should do.
so
uh
i think you just have to have a checklist.
you know,
in my first book, the most important thing, i had a thing in there called the uh
poor man's guide to market assessment.
and and it says on the left a bunch of things
and on the right there's a bunch of things. and and and it was half tongue and cheek
or maybe more than half.
but i mean, it says, you know,
uh
are the is the market rising
or falling? are are the tv shows about investing popular
or unpopular? if an investor goes to a cocktail party, is he mobbed or shunned?
uh
are do deals get done easily or hard?
do people ra are are deals overs subscribed
or left begging?
you know, that kind of thing.
and you can tell, you can figure out from that checklist whether the market is overheated and too popular
or uh
frigid
and and and too shunned.
and this can tell you a lot of what to do if you're methodical and clinical. > > well,
um
sean and i have have read your stuff forever.
we've listened to so many of your podcasts.
it's been an honor. we really appreciate you doing this. i think the best part of our
uh
best part of our job is we have an excuse to hang out with amazing people who are way out of our leagues
and uh
this is
this is one of those occasions. so, thank you so much. > > well, thank you, sam.