You know what's crazy? That all of this is real. Meaning what?
Don't you think so? All this AI stuff and  all this Bay Area… that it's happening.
Isn't it straight out of science fiction? Another thing that's crazy is how
normal the slow takeoff feels. The idea that we'd be investing 1%
of GDP in AI, I feel like it would have felt like  a bigger deal, whereas right now it just feels...
We get used to things pretty fast, it turns out. But also it's kind of abstract. What does it
mean? It means that you see it in the news,  that such and such company announced such
and such dollar amount. That's all you see.  It's not really felt in any other way so far.
Should we actually begin here? I think  this is an interesting discussion.
Sure. I think your point,
about how from the average person's point of view  nothing is that different, will continue being
true even into the singularity. No, I don't think so.
Okay, interesting. The thing which I was referring
to not feeling different is, okay, such and such  company announced some difficult-to-comprehend
dollar amount of investment. I don't think anyone knows what to do with that.
But I think the impact of AI is going to be felt. AI is going to be diffused through the economy.
There'll be very strong economic forces  for this, and I think the impact is
going to be felt very strongly. When do you expect that impact?
I think the models seem smarter than  their economic impact would imply.
Yeah. This is one of the very confusing  things about the models right now.
How to reconcile the fact that  they are doing so well on evals?
You look at the evals and you go, "Those  are pretty hard evals." They are doing
so well. But the economic impact  seems to be dramatically behind.
It's very difficult to make sense of,  how can the model, on the one hand,
do these amazing things, and then on the other  hand, repeat itself twice in some situation?
An example would be, let's say you  use vibe coding to do something.
You go to some place and then you get a bug. Then you tell the model,
"Can you please fix the bug?" And the model says, "Oh my God,
you're so right. I have a bug. Let me go  fix that." And it introduces a second bug.
Then you tell it, "You have this  new second bug," and it tells you,
"Oh my God, how could I have done it? You're so right again," and brings back
the first bug, and you can alternate between  those. How is that possible? I'm not sure, but it
does suggest that something strange is going on. I  have two possible explanations. The more whimsical
explanation is that maybe RL training makes the  models a little too single-minded and narrowly
focused, a little bit too unaware, even though  it also makes them aware in some other ways.
Because of this, they can't do basic things.  But there is another explanation. Back when
people were doing pre-training, the  question of what data to train on was
answered, because that answer was everything. When you do pre-training, you need all the data.
So you don't have to think if it's  going to be this data or that data.
But when people do RL training,  they do need to think.
They say, "Okay, we want to have this  kind of RL training for this thing
and that kind of RL training for that thing." From what I hear, all the companies have teams
that just produce new RL environments  and just add it to the training mix.
The question is, well, what are those? There are so many degrees of freedom.
There is such a huge variety of  RL environments you could produce.
One thing you could do, and I think this  is something that is done inadvertently,
is that people take inspiration from the evals. You say, "Hey, I would love our model to do
really well when we release it. I want the evals to look great.
What would be RL training  that could help on this task?"
I think that is something that happens, and  it could explain a lot of what's going on.
If you combine this with generalization  of the models actually being inadequate,
that has the potential to explain a lot  of what we are seeing, this disconnect
between eval performance and actual real-world  performance, which is something that we don't
today even understand, what we mean by that. I like this idea that the real reward hacking
is the human researchers who  are too focused on the evals.
I think there are two ways to  understand, or to try to think about,
what you have just pointed out. One is that if it's the case that
simply by becoming superhuman at a coding  competition, a model will not automatically
become more tasteful and exercise better judgment  about how to improve your codebase, well then you
should expand the suite of environments such  that you're not just testing it on having
the best performance in coding competition. It should also be able to make the best kind
of application for X thing or Y thing or Z thing. Another, maybe this is what you're hinting at,
is to say, "Why should it be the case in  the first place that becoming superhuman
at coding competitions doesn't make you a  more tasteful programmer more generally?"
Maybe the thing to do is not to keep  stacking up the amount and diversity
of environments, but to figure out an approach  which lets you learn from one environment and
improve your performance on something else. I have a human analogy which might be helpful.
Let's take the case of competitive programming,  since you mentioned that. Suppose you have two
students. One of them decided they want  to be the best competitive programmer, so
they will practice 10,000 hours for that domain. They will solve all the problems, memorize all the
proof techniques, and be very skilled at quickly  and correctly implementing all the algorithms.
By doing so, they became one of the best. Student number two thought, "Oh,
competitive programming is cool." Maybe they practiced for 100 hours,
much less, and they also did really well. Which one do you think is going to do better
in their career later on? The second.
Right. I think that's basically what's going on. The models are much more like the
first student, but even more. Because then we say, the model should
be good at competitive programming so let's get  every single competitive programming problem ever.
And then let's do some data augmentation  so we have even more competitive
programming problems, and we train on that. Now you've got this great competitive programmer.
With this analogy, I think it's more intuitive. Yeah, okay, if it's so well trained, all the
different algorithms and all the different  proof techniques are right at its fingertips.
And it's more intuitive that with this  level of preparation, it would not
necessarily generalize to other things. But then what is the analogy for what
the second student is doing before  they do the 100 hours of fine-tuning?
I think they have "it." The "it"  factor. When I was an undergrad,
I remember there was a student like this  that studied with me, so I know it exists.
I think it's interesting to distinguish  "it" from whatever pre-training does.
One way to understand what you just said  about not having to choose the data in
pre-training is to say it's actually not  dissimilar to the 10,000 hours of practice.
It's just that you get that 10,000 hours  of practice for free because it's already
somewhere in the pre-training distribution. But maybe you're suggesting there's actually
not that much generalization from pre-training. There's just so much data in pre-training, but
it's not necessarily generalizing better than RL. The main strength of pre-training is
that: A, there is so much of it, and B,  you don't have to think hard about what
data to put into pre-training. It's very natural data, and it
does include in it a lot of what people do:  people's thoughts and a lot of the features.
It's like the whole world as projected by  people onto text, and pre-training tries
to capture that using a huge amount of data. Pre-training is very difficult to reason about
because it's so hard to understand the manner  in which the model relies on pre-training data.
Whenever the model makes a mistake, could it be  because something by chance is not as supported
by the pre-training data? "Support by  pre-training" is maybe a loose term.
I don't know if I can add  anything more useful on this.
I don't think there is a  human analog to pre-training.
Here are analogies that people have proposed  for what the human analogy to pre-training is.
I'm curious to get your thoughts  on why they're potentially wrong.
One is to think about the first 18, or 15,  or 13 years of a person's life when they
aren't necessarily economically productive,  but they are doing something that is making
them understand the world better and so forth. The other is to think about evolution as doing
some kind of search for 3 billion years, which  then results in a human lifetime instance.
I'm curious if you think either of  these are analogous to pre-training.
How would you think about what lifetime  human learning is like, if not pre-training?
I think there are some similarities between both  of these and pre-training, and pre-training tries
to play the role of both of these. But I think there are some
big differences as well. The amount of pre-training data is very,
very staggering. Yes.
Somehow a human being, after even 15 years  with a tiny fraction of the pre-training
data, they know much less. But whatever they do know,
they know much more deeply somehow. Already at that age, you would not
make mistakes that our AIs make. There is another  thing. You might say, could it be something like
evolution? The answer is maybe. But in this case,  I think evolution might actually have an edge.
I remember reading about this case. One way in which neuroscientists can
learn about the brain is by studying people with  brain damage to different parts of the brain.
Some people have the most strange symptoms  you could imagine. It's actually really,
really interesting. One case that  comes to mind that's relevant.
I read about this person who had some kind  of brain damage, a stroke or an accident,
that took out his emotional processing. So he stopped feeling any emotion.
He still remained very articulate  and he could solve little puzzles,
and on tests he seemed to be just fine.  But he felt no emotion. He didn't feel sad,
he didn't feel anger, he didn't feel animated. He became somehow extremely bad at making any
decisions at all. It would take him
hours to decide on which socks to wear. He would make very bad financial decisions.
What does it say about the role of our built-in  emotions in making us a viable agent, essentially?
To connect to your question about pre-training,  maybe if you are good enough at getting everything
out of pre-training, you could get that as well. But that's the kind of thing which seems...
Well, it may or may not be possible  to get that from pre-training.
What is "that"? Clearly not just directly  emotion. It seems like some almost value
function-like thing which is telling you what  the end reward for any decision should be.
You think that doesn't sort of  implicitly come from pre-training?
I think it could. I'm just  saying it's not 100% obvious.
But what is that? How do you think about emotions? What is the ML analogy for emotions?
It should be some kind of a value function thing. But I don’t think there is a great ML analogy
because right now, value functions don't play  a very prominent role in the things people do.
It might be worth defining for the audience what  a value function is, if you want to do that.
Certainly, I'll be very happy to do that. When people do reinforcement learning,
the way reinforcement learning is done  right now, how do people train those agents?
You have your neural net and you  give it a problem, and then you
tell the model, "Go solve it." The model takes maybe thousands,
hundreds of thousands of actions or thoughts or  something, and then it produces a solution. The
solution is graded. And then the score  is used to provide a training signal
for every single action in your trajectory. That means that if you are doing something
that goes for a long time—if you're training  a task that takes a long time to solve—it
will do no learning at all until you  come up with the proposed solution.
That's how reinforcement learning is done naively. That's how o1, R1 ostensibly are done.
The value function says something like,  "Maybe I could sometimes, not always,
tell you if you are doing well or badly." The notion of a value function is more
useful in some domains than others. For example, when you play chess and
you lose a piece, I messed up. You don't need to play the whole
game to know that what I just did was bad, and  therefore whatever preceded it was also bad.
The value function lets you short-circuit  the wait until the very end.
Let's suppose that you are doing some kind  of a math thing or a programming thing,
and you're trying to explore a  particular solution or direction.
After, let's say, a thousand steps of thinking,  you concluded that this direction is unpromising.
As soon as you conclude this, you  could already get a reward signal
a thousand timesteps previously, when  you decided to pursue down this path.
You say, "Next time I shouldn't pursue this  path in a similar situation," long before you
actually came up with the proposed solution. This was in the DeepSeek R1 paper— that the
space of trajectories is so wide that  maybe it's hard to learn a mapping
from an intermediate trajectory and value. And also given that, in coding for example
you'll have the wrong idea, then you'll  go back, then you'll change something.
This sounds like such a lack  of faith in deep learning.
Sure it might be difficult, but  nothing deep learning can't do.
My expectation is that a value function should  be useful, and I fully expect that they will
be used in the future, if not already. What I was alluding to with the person
whose emotional center got damaged, it’s more  that maybe what it suggests is that the value
function of humans is modulated by emotions in  some important way that's hardcoded by evolution.
And maybe that is important for  people to be effective in the world.
That's the thing I was planning on asking you.
There's something really interesting about  emotions of the value function, which is that
it's impressive that they have this much utility  while still being rather simple to understand.
I have two responses. I do agree that compared to  the kind of things that we learn and the things
we are talking about, the kind of AI we are  talking about, emotions are relatively simple.
They might even be so simple that maybe you  could map them out in a human-understandable way.
I think it would be cool to do. In terms of utility though,
I think there is a thing where there is this  complexity-robustness tradeoff, where complex
things can be very useful, but simple things are  very useful in a very broad range of situations.
One way to interpret what we are seeing is that  we've got these emotions that evolved mostly
from our mammal ancestors and then fine-tuned a  little bit while we were hominids, just a bit.
We do have a decent amount of social emotions  though which mammals may lack. But they're
not very sophisticated. And because they're  not sophisticated, they serve us so well in
this very different world compared to the  one that we've been living in. Actually,
they also make mistakes. For example, our  emotions… Well actually, I don’t know.
Does hunger count as an emotion? It's debatable.  But I think, for example, our intuitive feeling
of hunger is not succeeding in guiding us  correctly in this world with an abundance of food.
People have been talking about scaling  data, scaling parameters, scaling compute.
Is there a more general  way to think about scaling?
What are the other scaling axes? Here's a perspective that I think might be true.
The way ML used to work is that  people would just tinker with
stuff and try to get interesting results. That's what's been going on in the past. Then
the scaling insight arrived. Scaling laws, GPT-3,  and suddenly everyone realized we should scale.
This is an example of how language  affects thought. "Scaling" is just
one word, but it's such a powerful word  because it informs people what to do.
They say, "Let's try to scale things." So you say, what are we scaling?
Pre-training was the thing to scale. It was a particular scaling recipe.
The big breakthrough of pre-training is  the realization that this recipe is good.
You say, "Hey, if you mix some compute  with some data into a neural net of
a certain size, you will get results. You will know that you'll be better if you
just scale the recipe up." This is also great.  Companies love this because it gives you a very
low-risk way of investing your resources. It's much harder to invest your resources
in research. Compare that. If you research,  you need to be like, "Go forth researchers
and research and come up with something",  versus get more data, get more compute.
You know you'll get something from pre-training. Indeed, it looks like, based on various
things some people say on Twitter, maybe it  appears that Gemini have found a way to get
more out of pre-training. At some point though,
pre-training will run out of data. The data is very clearly finite. What
do you do next? Either you do some kind  of souped-up pre-training, a different
recipe from the one you've done before, or  you're doing RL, or maybe something else.
But now that compute is big, compute  is now very big, in some sense we
are back to the age of research. Maybe here's another way to put it.
Up until 2020, from 2012 to  2020, it was the age of research.
Now, from 2020 to 2025, it was the  age of scaling—maybe plus or minus,
let's add error bars to those years—because  people say, "This is amazing. You've got to
scale more. Keep scaling." The one word:  scaling. But now the scale is so big.
Is the belief really, "Oh, it's so big, but if you  had 100x more, everything would be so different?"
It would be different, for sure. But is the belief that if you just
100x the scale, everything would be transformed?  I don't think that's true. So it's back to the age
of research again, just with big computers. That's a very interesting way to put it.
But let me ask you the  question you just posed then.
What are we scaling, and what  would it mean to have a recipe?
I guess I'm not aware of a very clean  relationship that almost looks like a law
of physics which existed in pre-training. There was a power law between data or
compute or parameters and loss. What is the kind of relationship
we should be seeking, and how should we think  about what this new recipe might look like?
We've already witnessed a transition from one  type of scaling to a different type of scaling,
from pre-training to RL. Now people are scaling  RL. Now based on what people say on Twitter,
they spend more compute on RL than on  pre-training at this point, because RL
can actually consume quite a bit of compute. You do very long rollouts, so it takes a lot
of compute to produce those rollouts. Then you get a relatively small amount
of learning per rollout, so you  really can spend a lot of compute.
I wouldn't even call it scaling. I would say, "Hey, what are you doing?
Is the thing you are doing the most  productive thing you could be doing?
Can you find a more productive  way of using your compute?"
We've discussed the value  function business earlier.
Maybe once people get good at value  functions, they will be using their
resources more productively. If you find a whole other way
of training models, you could say, "Is this  scaling or is it just using your resources?"
I think it becomes a little bit ambiguous. In the sense that, when people were in the
age of research back then, it was,  "Let's try this and this and this.
Let's try that and that and that. Oh, look, something interesting is happening."
I think there will be a return to that. If we're back in the era of research,
stepping back, what is the part of the  recipe that we need to think most about?
When you say value function, people  are already trying the current recipe,
but then having LLM-as-a-Judge and so forth. You could say that's a value function,
but it sounds like you have something  much more fundamental in mind.
Should we even rethink pre-training at all and not  just add more steps to the end of that process?
The discussion about value function,  I think it was interesting.
I want to emphasize that I think the value  function is something that's going to make RL more
efficient, and I think that makes a difference. But I think anything you can do with a value
function, you can do without, just more slowly. The thing which I think is the most fundamental
is that these models somehow just generalize  dramatically worse than people. It's super
obvious. That seems like a very fundamental thing. So this is the crux: generalization. There are two
sub-questions. There's one which is about sample  efficiency: why should it take so much more data
for these models to learn than humans? There's  a second question. Even separate from the amount
of data it takes, why is it so hard to teach  the thing we want to a model than to a human?
For a human, we don't necessarily need a  verifiable reward to be able to… You're probably
mentoring a bunch of researchers right now, and  you're talking with them, you're showing them your
code, and you're showing them how you think. From that, they're picking up your way of
thinking and how they should do research. You don’t have to set a verifiable reward for
them that's like, "Okay, this is the next part of  the curriculum, and now this is the next part of
your curriculum. Oh, this training was unstable."  There's not this schleppy, bespoke process.
Perhaps these two issues are actually  related in some way, but I'd be curious
to explore this second thing, which is more  like continual learning, and this first thing,
which feels just like sample efficiency. You could actually wonder that one possible
explanation for the human sample efficiency  that needs to be considered is evolution.
Evolution has given us a small amount  of the most useful information possible.
For things like vision, hearing, and  locomotion, I think there's a pretty
strong case that evolution has given us a lot. For example, human dexterity far exceeds… I mean
robots can become dexterous too if you subject  them to a huge amount of training in simulation.
But to train a robot in the real world  to quickly pick up a new skill like
a person does seems very out of reach. Here you could say, "Oh yeah, locomotion.
All our ancestors needed  great locomotion, squirrels.
So with locomotion, maybe we've  got some unbelievable prior."
You could make the same case for vision. I believe Yann LeCun made the point that
children learn to drive after 10  hours of practice, which is true.
But our vision is so good. At least for me,
I remember myself being a five-year-old. I was very excited about cars back then.
I'm pretty sure my car recognition was more than  adequate for driving already as a five-year-old.
You don't get to see that  much data as a five-year-old.
You spend most of your time in your parents'  house, so you have very low data diversity.
But you could say maybe that's evolution too. But in language and math and coding, probably not.
It still seems better than models. Obviously, models are better than the average
human at language, math, and coding. But are they better than
the average human at learning? Oh yeah. Oh yeah, absolutely. What I meant
to say is that language, math, and coding—and  especially math and coding—suggests that whatever
it is that makes people good at learning is  probably not so much a complicated prior,
but something more, some fundamental thing. I'm not sure I understood. Why
should that be the case? So consider a skill in which
people exhibit some kind of great reliability. If the skill is one that was very useful to our
ancestors for many millions of years, hundreds  of millions of years, you could argue that maybe
humans are good at it because of evolution,  because we have a prior, an evolutionary prior
that's encoded in some very non-obvious  way that somehow makes us so good at it.
But if people exhibit great ability, reliability,  robustness, and ability to learn in a domain that
really did not exist until recently, then  this is more an indication that people
might have just better machine learning, period. How should we think about what that is? What is
the ML analogy? There are a couple of interesting  things about it. It takes fewer samples. It's
more unsupervised. A child learning to drive a  car… Children are not learning to drive a car.
A teenager learning how to drive a car is not  exactly getting some prebuilt, verifiable reward.
It comes from their interaction with  the machine and with the environment.
It takes much fewer samples. It seems  more unsupervised. It seems more robust?
Much more robust. The robustness  of people is really staggering.
Do you have a unified way of thinking about  why all these things are happening at once?
What is the ML analogy that could  realize something like this?
One of the things that you've been asking about is  how can the teenage driver self-correct and learn
from their experience without an external teacher? The answer is that they have their value function.
They have a general sense which is also,  by the way, extremely robust in people.
Whatever the human value function is,  with a few exceptions around addiction,
it's actually very, very robust. So for something like a teenager
that's learning to drive, they start to drive, and  they already have a sense of how they're driving
immediately, how badly they are, how unconfident.  And then they see, "Okay." And then, of course,
the learning speed of any teenager is so fast. After 10 hours, you're good to go.
It seems like humans have some  solution, but I'm curious about
how they are doing it and why is it so hard? How do we need to reconceptualize the way
we're training models to make  something like this possible?
That is a great question to ask, and it's  a question I have a lot of opinions about.
But unfortunately, we live in a world where  not all machine learning ideas are discussed
freely, and this is one of them. There's probably a way to do it.
I think it can be done. The fact that people are like that,
I think it's a proof that it can be done. There may be another blocker though,
which is that there is a possibility that the  human neurons do more compute than we think.
If that is true, and if that plays an important  role, then things might be more difficult.
But regardless, I do think it points to  the existence of some machine learning
principle that I have opinions on. But unfortunately, circumstances
make it hard to discuss in detail. Nobody listens to this podcast, Ilya.
I'm curious. If you say we are back in an era  of research, you were there from 2012 to 2020.
What is the vibe now going to be if  we go back to the era of research?
For example, even after AlexNet, the  amount of compute that was used to
run experiments kept increasing, and the  size of frontier systems kept increasing.
Do you think now that this era of research will  still require tremendous amounts of compute?
Do you think it will require going back  into the archives and reading old papers?
You were at Google and OpenAI and Stanford, these  places, when there was more of a vibe of research?
What kind of things should we  be expecting in the community?
One consequence of the age of scaling is that  scaling sucked out all the air in the room.
Because scaling sucked out all the air in the  room, everyone started to do the same thing.
We got to the point where we are  in a world where there are more
companies than ideas by quite a bit. Actually on that, there is this Silicon
Valley saying that says that ideas  are cheap, execution is everything.
People say that a lot, and there is truth to that. But then I saw someone say on Twitter
something like, "If ideas are so cheap,  how come no one's having any ideas?"
And I think it's true too. If you think about research progress in terms
of bottlenecks, there are several bottlenecks. One of them is ideas, and one of them is your
ability to bring them to life, which  might be compute but also engineering.
If you go back to the '90s, let's say,  you had people who had pretty good ideas,
and if they had much larger computers, maybe they  could demonstrate that their ideas were viable.
But they could not, so they could only  have a very, very small demonstration
that did not convince anyone. So the  bottleneck was compute. Then in the
age of scaling, compute has increased a lot. Of course, there is a question of how much
compute is needed, but compute is large. Compute is large enough such that it's not
obvious that you need that much more  compute to prove some idea. I'll give
you an analogy. AlexNet was built on two GPUs. That was the total amount of compute used for it.
The transformer was built on 8 to 64 GPUs. No single transformer paper experiment used
more than 64 GPUs of 2017, which would be  like, what, two GPUs of today? The ResNet,
right? You could argue that the o1 reasoning was  not the most compute-heavy thing in the world.
So for research, you definitely need  some amount of compute, but it's far
from obvious that you need the absolutely  largest amount of compute ever for research.
You might argue, and I think it is true, that  if you want to build the absolutely best system
then it helps to have much more compute. Especially if everyone is within the same
paradigm, then compute becomes  one of the big differentiators.
I'm asking you for the history,  because you were actually there.
I'm not sure what actually happened. It sounds like it was possible to develop
these ideas using minimal amounts of compute. But the transformer didn't
immediately become famous. It became the thing everybody started
doing and then started experimenting on top of  and building on top of because it was validated
at higher and higher levels of compute. Correct.
And if you at SSI have 50 different ideas, how  will you know which one is the next transformer
and which one is brittle, without having the  kinds of compute that other frontier labs have?
I can comment on that. The short  comment is that you mentioned SSI.
Specifically for us, the amount of compute  that SSI has for research is really not that
small. I want to explain why. Simple math  can explain why the amount of compute that
we have is comparable for research than one might  think. I'll explain. SSI has raised $3 billion,
which is a lot by any absolute sense. But you could say, "Look at the
other companies raising much more." But a lot of their compute goes for inference.
These big numbers, these big loans, it's  earmarked for inference. That's number one.
Number two, if you want to have a product  on which you do inference, you need to
have a big staff of engineers, salespeople. A lot of the research needs to be dedicated to
producing all kinds of product-related features. So then when you look at what's actually left for
research, the difference becomes a lot smaller. The other thing is, if you are doing something
different, do you really need the  absolute maximal scale to prove it?
I don't think that's true at all. I think that in our case, we have sufficient
compute to prove, to convince ourselves and  anyone else, that what we are doing is correct.
There have been public estimates that companies  like OpenAI spend on the order of $5-6 billion
a year just so far, on experiments. This is separate from the amount of
money they're spending on inference and so forth. So it seems like they're spending more a year
running research experiments than  you guys have in total funding.
I think it's a question of what you do with it. It's a question of what you do with it.
In their case, in the case of others, there  is a lot more demand on the training compute.
There’s a lot more different work streams, there  are different modalities, there is just more
stuff. So it becomes fragmented. How will SSI make money?
My answer to this question is something like this. Right now, we just focus on the research, and then
the answer to that question will reveal itself. I think there will be lots of possible answers.
Is SSI's plan still to straight  shot superintelligence?
Maybe. I think that there is merit to it. I think there's a lot of merit because
it's very nice to not be affected by  the day-to-day market competition.
But I think there are two reasons  that may cause us to change the plan.
One is pragmatic, if timelines turned  out to be long, which they might.
Second, I think there is a lot  of value in the best and most
powerful AI being out there impacting the world. I think this is a meaningfully valuable thing.
So then why is your default plan  to straight shot superintelligence?
Because it sounds like OpenAI, Anthropic, all  these other companies, their explicit thinking
is, "Look, we have weaker and weaker intelligences  that the public can get used to and prepare for."
Why is it potentially better to  build a superintelligence directly?
I'll make the case for and against. The case for is that one of the challenges
that people face when they're in the market is  that they have to participate in the rat race.
The rat race is quite difficult in  that it exposes you to difficult
trade-offs which you need to make. It is nice to say, "We'll insulate ourselves
from all this and just focus on the research and  come out only when we are ready, and not before."
But the counterpoint is valid too,  and those are opposing forces.
The counterpoint is, "Hey, it is useful  for the world to see powerful AI.
It is useful for the world to  see powerful AI because that's
the only way you can communicate it." Well, I guess not even just that you can
communicate the idea— Communicate the AI,
not the idea. Communicate the AI. What do you mean, "communicate the AI"?
Let's suppose you write an essay about AI, and  the essay says, "AI is going to be this, and AI is
going to be that, and it's going to be this." You read it and you say, "Okay,
this is an interesting essay." Now suppose you see an AI doing this,
an AI doing that. It is incomparable. Basically  I think that there is a big benefit from AI
being in the public, and that would be a  reason for us to not be quite straight shot.
I guess it's not even that, but I do  think that is an important part of it.
The other big thing is that I can't think of  another discipline in human engineering and
research where the end artifact was made  safer mostly through just thinking about
how to make it safe, as opposed to,  why airplane crashes per mile are so
much lower today than they were decades ago. Why is it so much harder to find a bug in Linux
than it would have been decades ago? I think it's mostly because these
systems were deployed to the world. You noticed failures, those failures
were corrected and the systems became more robust. I'm not sure why AGI and superhuman intelligence
would be any different, especially given—and I  hope we're going to get to this—it seems like
the harms of superintelligence are not just about  having some malevolent paper clipper out there.
But this is a really powerful thing and we don't  even know how to conceptualize how people interact
with it, what people will do with it. Having gradual access to it seems like a
better way to maybe spread out the impact  of it and to help people prepare for it.
Well I think on this point, even in the straight  shot scenario, you would still do a gradual
release of it, that’s how I would imagine it. Gradualism would be an inherent
component of any plan. It's just a question of what is the first
thing that you get out of the door. That's number  one. Number two, I believe you have advocated
for continual learning more than other people,  and I actually think that this is an important
and correct thing. Here is why. I'll give you  another example of how language affects thinking.
In this case, it will be two words that  have shaped everyone's thinking, I maintain.
First word: AGI. Second word: pre-training.  Let me explain. The term AGI, why does this
term exist? It's a very particular term. Why  does it exist? There's a reason. The reason
that the term AGI exists is, in my opinion, not  so much because it's a very important, essential
descriptor of some end state of intelligence, but  because it is a reaction to a different term that
existed, and the term is narrow AI. If you go back to ancient history
of gameplay and AI, of checkers AI, chess  AI, computer games AI, everyone would say,
look at this narrow intelligence. Sure, the chess AI can beat Kasparov,
but it can't do anything else. It is so narrow, artificial narrow intelligence.
So in response, as a reaction to this,  some people said, this is not good. It
is so narrow. What we need is general AI,  an AI that can just do all the things.
That term just got a lot of traction. The second thing that got a lot of traction
is pre-training, specifically  the recipe of pre-training.
I think the way people do RL now is maybe  undoing the conceptual imprint of pre-training.
But pre-training had this property. You  do more pre-training and the model gets
better at everything, more or less uniformly.  General AI. Pre-training gives AGI. But the
thing that happened with AGI and pre-training  is that in some sense they overshot the target.
If you think about the term "AGI",  especially in the context of pre-training,
you will realize that a human being is not an AGI. Yes, there is definitely a foundation of skills,
but a human being lacks a  huge amount of knowledge.
Instead, we rely on continual learning. So when you think about, "Okay,
so let's suppose that we achieve success and we  produce some kind of safe superintelligence."
The question is, how do you define it? Where on the curve of continual
learning is it going to be? I produce a superintelligent
15-year-old that's very eager to go. They don't know very much at all,
a great student, very eager. You go and be a programmer,
you go and be a doctor, go and learn. So you could imagine that the deployment
itself will involve some kind of  a learning trial-and-error period.
It's a process, as opposed to  you dropping the finished thing.
I see. You're suggesting that the thing  you're pointing out with superintelligence
is not some finished mind which knows how  to do every single job in the economy.
Because the way, say, the original OpenAI charter  or whatever defines AGI is like, it can do every
single job, every single thing a human can do. You're proposing instead a mind which can
learn to do every single job,  and that is superintelligence.
Yes. But once you have the learning algorithm,
it gets deployed into the world the same way  a human laborer might join an organization.
Exactly. It seems like one of these two things
might happen, maybe neither of these happens. One, this super-efficient learning algorithm
becomes superhuman, becomes as good  as you and potentially even better,
at the task of ML research. As a result the algorithm
itself becomes more and more superhuman. The other is, even if that doesn't happen,
if you have a single model—this is explicitly  your vision—where instances of a model
which are deployed through the economy doing  different jobs, learning how to do those jobs,
continually learning on the job, picking up  all the skills that any human could pick up,
but picking them all up at the same time,  and then amalgamating their learnings,
you basically have a model which functionally  becomes superintelligent even without any sort
of recursive self-improvement in software. Because you now have one model that can do
every single job in the economy and humans  can't merge our minds in the same way.
So do you expect some sort of intelligence  explosion from broad deployment?
I think that it is likely that we  will have rapid economic growth.
I think with broad deployment, there are two  arguments you could make which are conflicting.
One is that once indeed you get to a point where  you have an AI that can learn to do things quickly
and you have many of them, then there will be  a strong force to deploy them in the economy
unless there will be some kind of a regulation  that stops it, which by the way there might be.
But the idea of very rapid  economic growth for some time,
I think it’s very possible from broad deployment. The question is how rapid it's going to be.
I think this is hard to know because on the  one hand you have this very efficient worker.
On the other hand, the world is just  really big and there's a lot of stuff,
and that stuff moves at a different speed. But then on the other hand, now the AI could…
So I think very rapid economic growth is possible. We will see all kinds of things like different
countries with different rules and the  ones which have the friendlier rules, the
economic growth will be faster. Hard to predict. It seems to me that this is a very precarious
situation to be in. In the limit,
we know that this should be possible. If you have something that is as good
as a human at learning, but which can merge its  brains—merge different instances in a way that
humans can't merge—already, this seems like  a thing that should physically be possible.
Humans are possible, digital  computers are possible.
You just need both of those  combined to produce this thing.
It also seems this kind of  thing is extremely powerful.
Economic growth is one way to put it. A Dyson sphere is a lot of economic growth.
But another way to put it is that you will have,  in potentially a very short period of time...
You hire people at SSI, and in six  months, they're net productive, probably.
A human learns really fast, and this thing  is becoming smarter and smarter very fast.
How do you think about making that go well? Why is SSI positioned to do that well?
What is SSI's plan there, is  basically what I'm trying to ask.
One of the ways in which my thinking has been  changing is that I now place more importance on
AI being deployed incrementally and in advance. One very difficult thing about AI is that we are
talking about systems that don't yet  exist and it's hard to imagine them.
I think that one of the things that's happening is  that in practice, it's very hard to feel the AGI.
It's very hard to feel the AGI. We can talk about it, but imagine
having a conversation about how it is  like to be old when you're old and frail.
You can have a conversation, you can try to  imagine it, but it's just hard, and you come
back to reality where that's not the case. I think that a lot of the issues around AGI
and its future power stem from the fact  that it's very difficult to imagine.
Future AI is going to be different. It's going  to be powerful. Indeed, the whole problem,
what is the problem of AI and AGI? The whole problem is the power.
The whole problem is the power. When the power is really big,
what's going to happen? One of the ways in which I've
changed my mind over the past year—and that  change of mind, I'll hedge a little bit, may
back-propagate into the plans of our company—is  that if it's hard to imagine, what do you do?
You’ve got to be showing the thing. You’ve got to be showing the thing.
I maintain that most people who work on AI also  can't imagine it because it's too different from
what people see on a day-to-day basis. I do maintain, here's something which
I predict will happen. This is a prediction.  I maintain that as AI becomes more powerful,
people will change their behaviors. We will see all kinds of unprecedented
things which are not happening right now. I’ll  give some examples. I think for better or worse,
the frontier companies will play a very important  role in what happens, as will the government.
The kind of things that I think  you'll see, which you see the
beginnings of, are companies that are fierce  competitors starting to collaborate on AI safety.
You may have seen OpenAI and Anthropic doing  a first small step, but that did not exist.
That's something which I predicted in  one of my talks about three years ago,
that such a thing will happen. I also maintain that as AI continues
to become more powerful, more visibly  powerful, there will also be a desire from
governments and the public to do something. I think this is a very important force,
of showing the AI. That's number one.  Number two, okay, so the AI is being
built. What needs to be done? One thing that  I maintain that will happen is that right now,
people who are working on AI, I maintain that the  AI doesn't feel powerful because of its mistakes.
I do think that at some point the AI  will start to feel powerful actually.
I think when that happens, we will see a big  change in the way all AI companies approach
safety. They'll become much more paranoid.  I say this as a prediction that we will
see happen. We'll see if I'm right. But I think  this is something that will happen because they
will see the AI becoming more powerful. Everything that's happening right now,
I maintain, is because people look at today's  AI and it's hard to imagine the future AI.
There is a third thing which needs to happen. I'm talking about it in broader terms,
not just from the perspective of SSI  because you asked me about our company.
The question is, what should  the companies aspire to build?
What should they aspire to build? There has been one big idea that
everyone has been locked into, which is  the self-improving AI. Why did it happen?
Because there are fewer ideas than companies. But I maintain that there is something that's
better to build, and I think  that everyone will want that.
It's the AI that's robustly aligned to  care about sentient life specifically.
I think in particular, there's a case to  be made that it will be easier to build
an AI that cares about sentient life than  an AI that cares about human life alone,
because the AI itself will be sentient. And if you think about things like mirror
neurons and human empathy for animals, which you  might argue it's not big enough, but it exists.
I think it's an emergent property from  the fact that we model others with the
same circuit that we use to model ourselves,  because that's the most efficient thing to do.
So even if you got an AI to care about  sentient beings—and it's not actually
clear to me that that's what you  should try to do if you solved
alignment—it would still be the case  that most sentient beings will be AIs.
There will be trillions,  eventually quadrillions, of AIs.
Humans will be a very small  fraction of sentient beings.
So it's not clear to me if the goal is some kind  of human control over this future civilization,
that this is the best criterion. It's true. It's possible it's not
the best criterion. I'll say two things. Number  one, care for sentient life, I think there is
merit to it. It should be considered. I think it  would be helpful if there was some kind of short
list of ideas that the companies, when they are  in this situation, could use. That’s number two.
Number three, I think it would be really  materially helpful if the power of the
most powerful superintelligence was somehow capped  because it would address a lot of these concerns.
The question of how to do it, I'm not sure, but I  think that would be materially helpful when you're
talking about really, really powerful systems. Before we continue the alignment discussion,
I want to double-click on that. How much room is there at the top?
How do you think about superintelligence? Do you think, using this learning efficiency idea,
maybe it is just extremely fast at  learning new skills or new knowledge?
Does it just have a bigger pool of strategies? Is there a single cohesive "it" in the
center that's more powerful or bigger? If so, do you imagine that this will be
sort of godlike in comparison to the rest of human  civilization, or does it just feel like another
agent, or another cluster of agents? This is an area where different
people have different intuitions. I think it will be very powerful, for sure.
What I think is most likely to happen  is that there will be multiple such
AIs being created roughly at the same time. I think that if the cluster is big enough—like
if the cluster is literally continent-sized—that  thing could be really powerful, indeed.
If you literally have a continent-sized  cluster, those AIs can be very powerful.
All I can tell you is that if you're  talking about extremely powerful AIs,
truly dramatically powerful, it would be nice if  they could be restrained in some ways or if there
were some kind of agreement or something. What is the concern of superintelligence?
What is one way to explain the concern? If you imagine a system that is sufficiently
powerful, really sufficiently powerful—and you  could say you need to do something sensible like
care for sentient life in a very single-minded  way—we might not like the results. That's really
what it is. Maybe, by the way, the answer is  that you do not build an RL agent in the usual
sense. I'll point several things out. I  think human beings are semi-RL agents.
We pursue a reward, and then the emotions  or whatever make us tire out of the
reward and we pursue a different reward. The market is a very short-sighted kind of
agent. Evolution is the same. Evolution  is very intelligent in some ways,
but very dumb in other ways. The government has been designed
to be a never-ending fight between  three parts, which has an effect.
So I think things like this. Another thing that makes this discussion
difficult is that we are talking about systems  that don't exist, that we don't know how to build.
That’s the other thing and  that’s actually my belief.
I think what people are doing right now  will go some distance and then peter out.
It will continue to improve,  but it will also not be "it".
The "It" we don't know how to build, and  a lot hinges on understanding reliable
generalization. I’ll say another thing.  One of the things that you could say about
what causes alignment to be difficult is that  your ability to learn human values is fragile.
Then your ability to optimize them is fragile. You actually learn to optimize them.
And can't you say, "Are these not all  instances of unreliable generalization?"
Why is it that human beings appear  to generalize so much better?
What if generalization was much better? What would happen in this case? What would
be the effect? But those questions  are right now still unanswerable.
How does one think about what  AI going well looks like?
You've scoped out how AI might evolve. We'll have these sort of continual
learning agents. AI will be very powerful.  Maybe there will be many different AIs.
How do you think about lots of continent-sized  compute intelligences going around? How dangerous
is that? How do we make that less dangerous? And how do we do that in a way that protects an
equilibrium where there might be misaligned  AIs out there and bad actors out there?
Here’s one reason why I liked "AI  that cares for sentient life".
We can debate on whether it's good or bad. But if the first N of these dramatic
systems do care for, love, humanity  or something, care for sentient life,
obviously this also needs to be achieved. This  needs to be achieved. So if this is achieved
by the first N of those systems, then I can  see it go well, at least for quite some time.
Then there is the question of  what happens in the long run.
How do you achieve a long-run equilibrium? I think that there, there is an answer as well.
I don't like this answer, but  it needs to be considered.
In the long run, you might say, "Okay, if  you have a world where powerful AIs exist,
in the short term, you could say  you have universal high income.
You have universal high income  and we're all doing well."
But what do the Buddhists say? "Change is the  only constant." Things change. There is some
kind of government, political structure thing, and  it changes because these things have a shelf life.
Some new government thing comes up and  it functions, and then after some time
it stops functioning. That's something that
we see happening all the time. So I think for the long-run equilibrium,
one approach is that you could say maybe every  person will have an AI that will do their bidding,
and that's good. If that could be
maintained indefinitely, that's true. But the downside with that is then the AI
goes and earns money for the person and advocates  for their needs in the political sphere, and maybe
then writes a little report saying, "Okay,  here's what I've done, here's the situation,"
and the person says, "Great, keep it up." But the person is no longer a participant.
Then you can say that's a  precarious place to be in.
I'm going to preface by saying I don't  like this solution, but it is a solution.
The solution is if people become  part-AI with some kind of Neuralink++.
Because what will happen as a result is  that now the AI understands something,
and we understand it too, because now the  understanding is transmitted wholesale.
So now if the AI is in some situation, you  are involved in that situation yourself fully.
I think this is the answer to the equilibrium. I wonder if the fact that emotions which were
developed millions—or in many cases, billions—of  years ago in a totally different environment are
still guiding our actions so strongly  is an example of alignment success.
To spell out what I mean—I don’t know  whether it’s more accurate to call it
a value function or reward function—but the  brainstem has a directive where it's saying,
"Mate with somebody who's more successful." The cortex is the part that understands
what success means in the modern context. But the brainstem is able to align the cortex
and say, "However you recognize success to be—and  I’m not smart enough to understand what that is—
you're still going to pursue this directive." I think there's a more general point.
I think it's actually really mysterious  how evolution encodes high-level desires.
It's pretty easy to understand how  evolution would endow us with the
desire for food that smells good because smell  is a chemical, so just pursue that chemical.
It's very easy to imagine  evolution doing that thing.
But evolution also has endowed  us with all these social desires.
We really care about being  seen positively by society.
We care about being in good standing. All these social intuitions that we have,
I feel strongly that they're baked in. I don't know how evolution did it
because it's a high-level concept  that's represented in the brain.
Let’s say you care about some social thing,  it's not a low-level signal like smell.
It's not something for which there is a sensor. The brain needs to do a lot of processing to
piece together lots of bits of information  to understand what's going on socially.
Somehow evolution said, "That's what you should  care about." How did it do it? It did it quickly,
too. All these sophisticated social things that we  care about, I think they evolved pretty recently.
Evolution had an easy time  hard-coding this high-level desire.
I'm unaware of a good  hypothesis for how it's done.
I had some ideas I was kicking around,  but none of them are satisfying.
What's especially impressive is it was desire  that you learned in your lifetime, it makes sense
because your brain is intelligent. It makes sense why you would
be able to learn intelligent desires. Maybe this is not your point, but one way
to understand it is that the desire is built into  the genome, and the genome is not intelligent.
But you're somehow able to describe this feature. It's not even clear how you define that feature,
and you can build it into the genes. Essentially, or maybe I'll put it differently.
If you think about the tools that  are available to the genome, it says,
"Okay, here's a recipe for building a brain." You could say, "Here is a recipe for connecting
the dopamine neurons to the smell sensor." And if the smell is a certain kind
of good smell, you want to eat that. I could imagine the genome doing that.
I'm claiming that it is harder to imagine. It's harder to imagine the genome saying
you should care about some complicated computation  that your entire brain, a big chunk of your brain,
does. That's all I'm claiming. I can tell  you a speculation of how it could be done.
Let me offer a speculation, and I'll explain  why the speculation is probably false.
So the brain has brain regions. We have  our cortex. It has all those brain regions.
The cortex is uniform, but the brain  regions and the neurons in the cortex
kind of speak to their neighbors mostly. That explains why you get brain regions.
Because if you want to do some kind of  speech processing, all the neurons that
do speech need to talk to each other. And because neurons can only speak to
their nearby neighbors, for the  most part, it has to be a region.
All the regions are mostly located in  the same place from person to person.
So maybe evolution hard-coded  literally a location on the brain.
So it says, "Oh, when the GPS coordinates  of the brain such and such, when that fires,
that's what you should care about." Maybe that's what evolution did because
that would be within the toolkit of evolution. Yeah, although there are examples where,
for example, people who are born blind have that  area of their cortex adopted by another sense.
I have no idea, but I'd be surprised if the  desires or the reward functions which require a
visual signal no longer worked for people who have  their different areas of their cortex co-opted.
For example, if you no longer have vision, can  you still feel the sense that I want people
around me to like me and so forth, which  usually there are also visual cues for.
I fully agree with that. I think there's an  even stronger counterargument to this theory.
There are people who get half of  their brains removed in childhood,
and they still have all their brain regions. But they all somehow move to just one hemisphere,
which suggests that the brain regions,  their location is not fixed and so
that theory is not true. It would have been cool
if it was true, but it's not. So I think that's a mystery.
But it's an interesting mystery. The fact is  that somehow evolution was able to endow us
to care about social stuff very, very reliably. Even people who have all kinds of strange mental
conditions and deficiencies and emotional  problems tend to care about this also.
What is SSI planning on doing differently? Presumably your plan is to be one of the
frontier companies when this time arrives. Presumably you started SSI because you're like,
"I think I have a way of approaching how  to do this safely in a way that the other
companies don't." What is that difference? The way I would describe it is that there
are some ideas that I think are promising and  I want to investigate them and see if they
are indeed promising or not. It's really that  simple. It's an attempt. If the ideas turn out
to be correct—these ideas that we discussed  around understanding generalization—then I
think we will have something worthy. Will they turn out to be correct? We
are doing research. We are squarely an "age of  research" company. We are making progress. We've
actually made quite good progress over the past  year, but we need to keep making more progress,
more research. That's how I see it. I see it  as an attempt to be a voice and a participant.
Your cofounder and previous CEO left to go to  Meta recently, and people have asked, "Well,
if there were a lot of breakthroughs being  made, that seems like a thing that should
have been unlikely." I wonder how you respond. For this, I will simply remind a few facts that
may have been forgotten. I think these facts which
provide the context explain the situation. The context was that we were fundraising at
a $32 billion valuation, and then Meta came  in and offered to acquire us, and I said no.
But my former cofounder in some sense said yes. As a result, he also was able to enjoy a lot of
near-term liquidity, and he was the  only person from SSI to join Meta.
It sounds like SSI's plan is to be a company  that is at the frontier when you get to this
very important period in human history  where you have superhuman intelligence.
You have these ideas about how to  make superhuman intelligence go well.
But other companies will  be trying their own ideas.
What distinguishes SSI's approach  to making superintelligence go well?
The main thing that distinguishes  SSI is its technical approach.
We have a different technical approach that  I think is worthy and we are pursuing it.
I maintain that in the end there  will be a convergence of strategies.
I think there will be a convergence of strategies  where at some point, as AI becomes more powerful,
it's going to become more or less clearer  to everyone what the strategy should be.
It should be something like, you need to find  some way to talk to each other and you want
your first actual real superintelligent AI to  be aligned and somehow care for sentient life,
care for people, democratic, one  of those, some combination thereof.
I think this is the condition  that everyone should strive for.
That's what SSI is striving for. I think that this time, if not already,
all the other companies will realize that  they're striving towards the same thing.
We'll see. I think that the world will  truly change as AI becomes more powerful.
I think things will be really different and  people will be acting really differently.
Speaking of forecasts, what are your  forecasts to this system you're describing,
which can learn as well as a human and  subsequently, as a result, become superhuman?
I think like 5 to 20. 5 to 20 years?
Mhm. I just want
to unroll how you might see the world coming. It's like, we have a couple more years where
these other companies are continuing  the current approach and it stalls out.
"Stalls out" here meaning they earn no more  than low hundreds of billions in revenue?
How do you think about what stalling out means? I think stalling out will look like…it will
all look very similar among  all the different companies.
It could be something like this. I'm not sure because I think
even with stalling out, I think these  companies could make a stupendous revenue.
Maybe not profits because they will need  to work hard to differentiate each other
from themselves, but revenue definitely. But something in your model implies that
when the correct solution does emerge, there  will be convergence between all the companies.
I'm curious why you think that's the case. I was talking more about convergence
on their alignment strategies. I think eventual convergence on
the technical approach is probably going  to happen as well, but I was alluding
to convergence to the alignment strategies. What exactly is the thing that should be done?
I just want to better understand  how you see the future unrolling.
Currently, we have these different companies, and  you expect their approach to continue generating
revenue but not get to this human-like learner. So now we have these different forks of companies.
We have you, we have Thinking Machines,  there's a bunch of other labs.
Maybe one of them figures  out the correct approach.
But then the release of their product makes  it clear to other people how to do this thing.
I think it won't be clear how to do it, but  it will be clear that something different is
possible, and that is information. People will then be trying
to figure out how that works. I do think though that one of the things not
addressed here, not discussed, is that with each  increase in the AI's capabilities, I think there
will be some kind of changes, but I don't know  exactly which ones, in how things are being done.
I think it's going to be important, yet  I can't spell out what that is exactly.
By default, you would expect the company that  has that model to be getting all these gains
because they have the model that has the skills  and knowledge that it's building up in the world.
What is the reason to think that the benefits  of that would be widely distributed and not
just end up at whatever model company gets  this continuous learning loop going first?
Here is what I think is going to happen. Number one, let's look at how things have
gone so far with the AIs of the past. One company produced an advance and the
other company scrambled and produced some similar  things after some amount of time and they started
to compete in the market and push the prices down. So I think from the market perspective,
something similar will happen there as well. We are talking about the good world, by the way.
What's the good world? It’s where we have these  powerful human-like learners that are also… By
the way, maybe there's another thing we haven't  discussed on the spec of the superintelligent
AI that I think is worth considering. It’s that you make it narrow, it can
be useful and narrow at the same time. You can have lots of narrow superintelligent AIs.
But suppose you have many of them and you  have some company that's producing a lot of
profits from it. Then you have another
company that comes in and starts to compete. The way the competition is going to work is
through specialization. Competition loves  specialization. You see it in the market,
you see it in evolution as well. You're going to have lots of different
niches and you're going to have lots of different  companies who are occupying different niches.
In this world we might say one AI company  is really quite a bit better at some area
of really complicated economic activity and a  different company is better at another area.
And the third company is  really good at litigation.
Isn't this contradicted by what human-like  learning implies? It’s that it can learn…
It can, but you have accumulated  learning. You have a big investment.
You spent a lot of compute to become really,  really good, really phenomenal at this thing.
Someone else spent a huge amount  of compute and a huge amount of
experience to get really good at some other thing. You apply a lot of human learning to get there,
but now you are at this high point where  someone else would say, "Look, I don't want
to start learning what you've learned." I guess that would require many different
companies to begin at the human-like continual  learning agent at the same time so that they
can start their different tree  search in different branches.
But if one company gets that agent first, or gets  that learner first, it does then seem like… Well,
if you just think about every single job in  the economy, having an instance learning each
one seems tractable for a company. That's a valid argument. My strong
intuition is that it's not how it's going to go. The argument says it will go this way, but my
strong intuition is that it will not go this way. In theory, there is no difference between theory
and practice. In practice, there is. I  think that's going to be one of those.
A lot of people's models of recursive  self-improvement literally, explicitly state
we will have a million Ilyas in a server that are  coming up with different ideas, and this will lead
to a superintelligence emerging very fast. Do you have some intuition about how
parallelizable the thing you are doing is? What are the gains from making copies of Ilya?
I don’t know. I think there'll definitely be  diminishing returns because you want people
who think differently rather than the same. If there were literal copies of me, I'm not sure
how much more incremental value you'd get. People who think differently,
that's what you want. Why is it that if you look
at different models, even released by totally  different companies trained on potentially
non-overlapping datasets, it's actually  crazy how similar LLMs are to each other?
Maybe the datasets are not as  non-overlapping as it seems.
But there’s some sense in which even  if an individual human might be less
productive than the future AI, maybe there’s  something to the fact that human teams have
more diversity than teams of AIs might have. How do we elicit meaningful diversity among AIs?
I think just raising the temperature  just results in gibberish.
You want something more like different scientists  have different prejudices or different ideas.
How do you get that kind of  diversity among AI agents?
So the reason there has been no diversity,  I believe, is because of pre-training.
All the pre-trained models are pretty much the  same because they pre-train on the same data.
Now RL and post-training is where  some differentiation starts to emerge
because different people come  up with different RL training.
I've heard you hint in the past  about self-play as a way to either
get data or match agents to other agents of  equivalent intelligence to kick off learning.
How should we think about why there are no public  proposals of this kind of thing working with LLMs?
I would say there are two things to say. The reason why I thought self-play was
interesting is because it offered a way to  create models using compute only, without data.
If you think that data is the ultimate bottleneck,  then using compute only is very interesting.
So that's what makes it interesting. The thing is that self-play, at least the
way it was done in the past—when you have agents  which somehow compete with each other—it's only
good for developing a certain set of skills. It  is too narrow. It's only good for negotiation,
conflict, certain social skills,  strategizing, that kind of stuff.
If you care about those skills,  then self-play will be useful.
Actually, I think that self-play did find  a home, but just in a different form.
So things like debate, prover-verifier, you  have some kind of an LLM-as-a-Judge which is
also incentivized to find mistakes in your work. You could say this is not exactly self-play,
but this is a related adversarial  setup that people are doing, I believe.
Really self-play is a special case of  more general competition between agents.
The natural response to competition  is to try to be different.
So if you were to put multiple agents together  and you tell them, "You all need to work on some
problem and you are an agent and you're inspecting  what everyone else is working," they’re going to
say, "Well, if they're already taking this  approach, it's not clear I should pursue it.
I should pursue something differentiated." So I  think something like this could also create an
incentive for a diversity of approaches. Final question: What is research taste?
You're obviously the person in  the world who is considered to
have the best taste in doing research in AI. You were the co-author on the biggest things
that have happened in the history of deep  learning, from AlexNet to GPT-3 to so on.
What is it, how do you characterize  how you come up with these ideas?
I can comment on this for myself. I think different people do it differently.
One thing that guides me personally is an  aesthetic of how AI should be, by thinking
about how people are, but thinking correctly. It's very easy to think about how people are
incorrectly, but what does it mean to think  about people correctly? I'll give you some
examples. The idea of the artificial neuron  is directly inspired by the brain, and it's a
great idea. Why? Because you say the brain has  all these different organs, it has the folds,
but the folds probably don't matter. Why do we think that the neurons matter?
Because there are many of them. It kind of feels right, so you want the neuron.
You want some local learning rule that will  change the connections between the neurons.
It feels plausible that the brain does it. The idea of the distributed representation.
The idea that the brain responds  to experience therefore our neural
net should learn from experience. The brain learns from experience,
the neural net should learn from experience. You kind of ask yourself, is something fundamental
or not fundamental? How things should be.  I think that's been guiding me a fair bit,
thinking from multiple angles and looking  for almost beauty, beauty and simplicity.
Ugliness, there's no room for ugliness. It's beauty, simplicity, elegance,
correct inspiration from the brain. All of those things need to
be present at the same time. The more they are present, the
more confident you can be in a top-down belief. The top-down belief is the thing that sustains
you when the experiments contradict you. Because if you trust the data all the time,
well sometimes you can be doing the  correct thing but there's a bug.
But you don't know that there is a bug. How can you tell that there is a bug?
How do you know if you should keep debugging or  you conclude it's the wrong direction? It's the
top-down. You can say things have to be this way. Something like this has to work,
therefore we’ve got to keep going. That's the top-down, and it's based on this
multifaceted beauty and inspiration by the brain. Alright, we'll leave it there.
Thank you so much. Ilya, thank you so much.
Alright. Appreciate it. That was great.
Yeah, I enjoyed it. Yes, me too.