okay well
welcome here i said
i would try and talk a little bit about the history of physics that's particularly
pertinent to me right now because for the last several months i've been very busily working on physics
and actually
have some super exciting
things that i figured out that
i'm hoping to talk about early next week
so this consider to say a precursor
of some of the things that i want to talk about next week about
sort of progress in understanding fundamental physics
what
i wanted to do here today was to discuss a bit some
of the some of the history of physics as a field
and how we've kind of got to where we are now
so
um
let's start at the beginning the question is
how does the world come to be the way it is and in
every culture there
have been creation myths you know
some of the more extreme ones
you know the world is made on the back of a turtle and
it's turtles all the way down and so on but there are there's always a creationist
and when it was written it was written in the terms of explanations
which were available
at the time and some of these creation myths seem to us these days mere
analogies allegories etc actually
they often have quite interesting things to say
if one sort of is prepared to translate them back into the sort of explanatory
framework of the time but
i suppose that you know if we look at ancient civilizations the ones about
which we probably know the most in terms of their thinking are the babylonians
and the greeks both of them had sort of important precursors to physics
and we should start off talking about those so as far as the babylonians were concerned
but first of all you know the babylonians kind of did
one thing very right which was that they wrote down things on clay tablets and
those clay tablets survived
and like i even see if i actually can
pull it out there
we go yeah sample
clay tablet there we go let's
say that's a little babylonian tablets not a very exciting one it's just
what i happen to have that's a it's a it's a barley contract
about somebody delivering
selling barley delivering it in different months and so on but this thing is about three
four thousand years old and what's
what's neat about abalone e'en things is that they've survived
and you know other civilizations that wrote another media
didn't survive so what do we know about what the babylonians
did in terms of physics they had astrologers
who would try
and predict things they would try and predict you
know where planets would be at a certain time in the future whether
it would rain tomorrow who would win or lose a battle turns
out they were right that there's a systematic way for scientists in effect to predict
where plants will be there's not such a systematic way to predict weather rain tomorrow
and there's not really a good scientific
way to predict weather or a king will win or lose a battle
so
it's kind of interesting to see that in those times
it wasn't play which of these would be will be the relevant
thing but they studied a lot astronomical phenomena
and they had essentially an empirical theory of lots
of things about the motion of the moon and so on they had pretty elaborate mathematical calculations that gave
essentially
sort of formulas in terms of what would we would today call us that were primitive version
of fourier analysis that
describe the motion of the moon and they they would
keep data about that over the course of hundreds
and hundreds of years and that's
how we know and some of the ancient astronomers knew things about eclipses
and were able to measure all
sorts of features of of the heavens based on the records that the babylonians had kept but
the real tradition i think in babylon starting
maybe four thousand years ago was
this kind of empirical tradition of let's
observe the heavens let's fit the data let's
make what amounts to a mathematical formula
for what we see and that's
what we talk about now
maybe they had more kind of conceptual things but they didn't those those were not recorded
so in different tradition there was kind of the the the greek tradition of
thinking about things
which was very much more of a philosophical tradition very much more of a theoretical we
can come up with ways to understand the world just by thinking about stuff
and you know from early times like folks like pythagoras 500 ish bc
the was thinking about sort of can we use numbers to explore everything
and you didn't really make a distinction between numbers to understand musical harmony numbers
to understand kind of the soul numbers
to understand the physical world it was just like there's there's an abstract framework with
which we can think about the world that was kind of the the meta thing that
he was thinking about well then
but particularly there pre-socratic philosophers 400 bc things like that people like democritus
and so on they were very big on on let's just have a philosophical
foundation for
how the world is made and democritus
famously thought about atoms automa
as these indivisible units from
which the world will be made i think the most important thing that we
see from some of this early philosophical thinking about the world is this idea that yes
you know the world can be made of lots of for example identical objects
and there's kind of a formal theory of how the world might be made
now
you know there were thoughts that you know maybe the world is made out of lots
of little platonic solids conveniently
here there are a couple of convenient photonic
solids in this gets made out of wood rather than out of that the
stuff the universe might be made out of but none of those the idea
that you know so
one of the five platonic solids might represent water
one might be fire things like this and that somehow there was a way to explain
how the world was made in these kind of formal
essentially mathematical terms
well you
know i suppose the lot
of kind of the wisdom of the ancients was passed down to more modern times through
the works of aristotle i mean i sort of view aristotle as the great cataloger
i mean he would write lists of animals
and plants
and causes of things structures of arguments that were turned into logic
and he also had kind of a a sort of a catalogue of the
way the physical world works
and had sort of explanations
based on kind of pure philosophy of how to think about them the way the physical world works
so
that was kind of the tradition of the
the things that it's like we can figure out the world just by thinking about it i
i think that one of the more interesting examples of that
person called lucretia roman
person maybe 60 bc
who wrote a book called on the nature of things fairly fairly general sounding title but
um you know he was trying to understand
how the world works and
how one could put together a thing
like the world and he had it kind of an interesting analogy
which i liked very much he said maybe the world is put together from underlying
elements like atoms in kind
of the way that we might put together a sentence out of words with
a certain grammatical structure
so it's kind of a way of describing a formal structure from which through
which the world can be built from sort of underlying elements
and i think kind of you know i think he was kind of right about the
way it would work he
didn't have any of the tools he didn't have computers
he didn't have all these kinds of things to
to to work with him to think in terms of
but that was kind of an interesting idea
i mean of course he at the time there
were little computers there were mechanical
computers like the antikythera device
which
you know was found in a shipwreck
it's this sort of lump of things with a bunch of cogs that's
a surprisingly elaborate mechanical
computer actually i think cicero mentions the existence of such a thing we
don't know how common or not those were in the ancient world but in a sense this clockwork
computer type idea did
exist in ancient times at least we have one sample of its existence
so it's sort of interesting that
what
might have emerged if kind of computation
had become more widespread in those times i mean it's it's worth understanding that
this notion of sort of the clockwork way of things working
that different from the mathematical structure of the way the babylonians thought about kind of the their
explanation of for the positions of planets and the moon and things like this well
okay so so in terms of ancient times i mean another kind
of tradition of ancient another sort of thing in ancient times with the development of mathematics
and mathematics
had been partly developed as
sort of a practical thing in babylon for doing commerce
for computing financial kinds of things for doing land surveying that was kind of the origins of arithmetic
and of geometry
but it kind of reached a different
level of kind of philosophical
significance through the work of people like euclid maybe 300 bc euclid
tried to axiom atomics
he tried to say these are just things that we can say are true that
we can then build up as a purely logical matter of deduction all
of the things that we might know about for example geometry
and it was completely unclear at the time to
what extent like physics might be axia metal
and to what extent the statement that euclid makes you know two parallel lines never meet to
what extent that was a statement that was sort of a a fact
that must be true about the world that was somehow in you know associated with physics
or something that was merely a mathematical assertion from
which you could prove things and it really took a long long time before
sort of this this distinction between physics things
that happen to be true about the world and mathematics
things that are sort of deducible pure thought could really be distinguished
and in fact i i would say that in very modern times we maybe are almost
back to the point where we might be able to turn physics
into a branch of mathematics again
but that's for for the future but in a case the so
you know this this tradition of kind of
geometric reasoning
and
so on that euclid practiced
and that very
much fit him with a kind of greek tradition of let's figure out everything by pure thought now
there was actual physics done like archimedes 250
bc he did actual physics he computed things using mathematics
but i think that he wasn't really in the let's understand
and how the universe is really constructed
he was more like
well we kind of its kind of obvious in some sort of euclidean geometrical
axiomatic way that such and such a thing is true about things in the world let's just compute
how it works
and that
he was able to compute all kinds of things about volumes of solids and things like that and
and connect some of those things to physics with things like you know his principle of displacement
of volume by you know figuring out is this gold or not by by
figuring out the density by knowing that things displace their own volume of something like water
okay
so the
into in terms of other things that
sort of happened in the ancient world by
the time one was approaching
sort of zero ad
there were people like cabacas´s early astronomer who made a very nice star catalog
and made lots of observations and
so on by the time ptolemy 120 ad ish was
around ptolemy kind of put together all these observations into this think of the almagest which
for many many years was kind of the standard of
how astronomy worked and the almagest was in
a sense not really work of physics it was a work of kind of euclidian style mathematics applied
to observations of astronomy
and it was something
where in the end he had this idea of epicycles
which were
essentially came from the babylonian tradition of let's let's make something
where we can work
out the motions of planets and things in his case by lots of kind of lots of spheres
kind of rolling around on each other with certain particular sizes
and particular detailed elaborate structures that were essentially a representation of mathematical formulas
and i think that's most of what somebody like ptolemy really
cared about was just the mathematical
formulas that allowed you to predict things rather
than the interpretation in terms of
you know spheres rolling on each other which i i'm not sure how much that
was really thought about or
how much anybody cared about that interpretation i think it was much more the practical
let's see how we can make astronomical predictions
well
okay
so so then
after that i mean for a long long time the works of hipparchus ptolemy
and so on most
of the works of the pockets i think were lost so it was really ptolemy's almagest that
was kind of the standard for astronomy
/ physics for more
than a thousand years it
finally got kind of people start cleaning it up a person called regiomontanus was
was big on sort of doing a big cleanup of of the sort of post you
know could one make the next step in physics
or astronomy after ptolemy
and really you
know one of the significant next steps was copernicus all the way in 1514 i think
where
copernicus was kind of working in the ptolemaic british tradition in terms of epicycles
and you know you can understand
that these sort of things roll on these things and you can understand
the motions of planets that way and so on and you realized well actually it's
a lot simpler you can you can make a sort of technical
change in the way things work
and you can make it a lot simpler
if you don't imagine that
the sun goes around the earth doesn't
really matter to the mathematics whether
the sun goes around the earth or the earth goes around the sun but
you can avoid some technical
details if you assume
that the sun is at the center
and the earth is going round isn't the other planets going around those
and
so he kind of introduced that as largely a technical innovation very late in his life
and i think
what was interesting in a sense to me about that is that
yes
it was a technical innovation didn't
even give better results
didn't get better results than ptolemy actually i think he gave worse results than ptolemies
way of setting things up
but in a sense there was a a certain it started kind of a shockwave of a realization that
what you think is true like you think the earth is stationary
and stuff is moving around you might not be true you
might be able to do something that is kind of a scientific thing
and work out something
which is completely another obvious to our senses
and i think that was kind of the at
a meta level the really significant feature of what copernicus did and
in fact there was sort of much more philosophical runoff from what copernicus did then there was scientific
kind of developments of what he did that came rather slowly the philosophical implications i think were
in many ways much bigger they were like the you know science
really knows what it's talking about
and might it might be different than what you can perceive with your senses
but science is going to be right and your senses are going to be wrong and
that's kind of a tradition
that has existed pretty
much to the present day and has been sort of amplified
over time i think
there's some problems with that tradition actually and
um
which we may talk about towards the end here well anyway
so
after copernicus
there was well
i suppose the next the next sort of really big set
of things that started happening were things that galileo was doing late 1500s you
know really galileo's i think big
initial contribution was the idea of yeah
you can really use math to
talk about physical kinds of things so for example the discovery that a parabola might
be relevant for the motion of a projectile the
the realization that they're things like things that are really mathy
i mean things like parabolas had been have been discovered as algebra well
they did they'd had could have precursors in in antiquity
but they'd really sort of come to the fore when algebra started getting developed in the 1400s
and so on um the i think the
so
so kind of the the the next big step was
yes mathematics could sort of be directly
and trained with
with physics by the way it had already been known in antiquity that in optics kind
of the the theory of kind of optics is very close to geometry it's all about lines
and angles and things like this and even euclid for example had actually written a book about optics
which is lost
and it
was it was something considered to be sort of almost a branch of mathematics so to speak
so there had been tradition there of sort of mathematical things applied to ideas like optics
but when it came to mechanics that hadn't really been been such a tradition
and galileo was kind of the one who really really started pushing that well then the
sort of the big the big surprise was 1608 when
when galileo you know the telescope had just been invented
and galileo
sort of found out about it and improved it there's
sort of a possibly apocryphal story that galileo had galileo
who was kind of a rather
pugnacious fellow and and quite an activist
but he was also he got himself a lot lots of kinds of trouble
but but there's a perhaps apocryphal
story that he had sold
the rights to his version of the telescope to the merchants of venice because
they really wanted to go up that that
big tower in the middle of venice that's
still there and figure
out you know whose ship be
the first person to figure out whose ship had come over the you
know whether whether a particular ship was was
going to come home or not and look out at the horizon and having
a telescope to be able to do that was really a big advantage it kind of has has
a reminiscence of modern times with high-frequency trading
and so on where it's you know get a better faster fiber-optic cable to know what's
happening in london if you're in new york and things like this but back
in those days that was you
know the merchants of venice with galileo telescope
running up that that
big tower in the middle of venice and so on but anyway so the apocryphal
story perhaps was that galileo had sold the exclusive
rights to terrestrial uses of the telescope to the merchants of venice so
he had no choice but to then try using it for something different point
the telescope to the side sky those rights were not used were
not will not sold and in 1608 that's
what he did and probably
the most dramatic thing he discovered was the moons of jupiter why
was it dramatic to discover the moons of jupiter well
because you know it had been claimed by copernicus
and
so on that you know the earth was going around the sun things like that this
was kind of like a miniature solar system that
was operating around jupiter and it kind of also gave
the sense that some of these kind of principles of physics that
we kind of had an idea applied
and the terrestrial domain also would apply to things in the heavens
and things that were like things orbiting jupiter
and so on so it was sort of a big a big realization that
that these kinds of
essentially mathematical
type principles that had been that
was starting to be applied to mechanics in a terrestrial domain could also apply to mechanics
everywhere else and it kind of was the it started to speak to kind of the universality
of physics across
the whole universe that it really wasn't any different what
was going on in the heavens than what was going on on earth and
and so on and that kind of started
a chain of thinking that i guess we could say led to most modern mathematical science
and a lot of modern technology and engineering and
so on so anyway that was that was the sort of a big moment for for science
um
later on galileo started having
oh i don't know principles of describing science
and important bombers but these days called galilean invariance the
idea that it's really no different if you're stationary
or if you're traveling at a certain speed the
laws of physics always look the same that was important
if you wanted to describe look you
know the earth doesn't have to be stationary the earth can just be moving at constant
speed and it will seem like everything is the same as
if it was stationary
and that's that's why we can't tell with our sensors that
the earth is moving around the sun rather than the other way around well
okay once the moons of jupiter were discovered all
kinds of things for example the fact that the speed of light was not infinite was discovered by
1670 1680
by making observations on the moons of jupiter
so it was already known that light didn't travel at infinite speed i'm not sure but
any great significance was
put on that it
was known of course that sound didn't travel at an inference speed it
was came clear that light travelled much faster than sound but
okay
well meanwhile
there was there was all sorts of question about sort of the nature of light for instance like
snell's law which is the law that determines
how refraction
works when you when you have a light ray that goes from like air to to to
water that that law of that sort of trigonometric law of of
the angle that the light ray will take snell's law that was in 1620
and then
through the 1600s there
were a bunch of kind of what we might say the obvious linear
laws of physics that got discovered
so for example boyle's law for gases mid 1600s hookes
law for springs that the the force on the extension of a spring is linearly proportional to to
how much you extend it there was like 16 sixties i think um then
the friction law or the law of friction that says that
the the frictional force is proportional to a constant that depends on the material times
the normal force times the amount of force
that that pushes the thing down onto
the surface and that
was kind of a late 1600s thing well i think leonardo davinci
already had some ideas
about how friction worked i mean it's kind of interesting that all those laws we understand boyle's
gas law very well now we
understand hookes law for springs very well now the
law of friction we actually still don't understand that well it's
still kind of mysterious exactly
how
and why that works and
and
so on so it's kind of interesting that these things that get discovered
just like when the babylonians couldn't
figure out you know which will be easier to predict the motion of planets whether
it would rain tomorrow it's
sometimes you have to have a big conceptual framework before it becomes clear
what
what is easy to understand
and what is not easy to understand
well
okay
so so one
thing had been discovered even in antiquity was various electrical phenomena static
electricity was no and there
was also various magnetic magnetic materials were no and kind of curiosities no
no great significance to them people then volta
kind of started understanding that for example the you know the muscles were somehow electrical
and then
it became sort of it started to get more they started to be more and more interest in
kind of what is electricity coulomb's law was
late 1700s it was discovered that the force of attraction between charged objects is the
is proportional to the inverse
one over the the distance squared of the the between the objects
and then
so
you know sort of slow progress on electricity magnetism things like that um i guess
by this point let's see we're hitting about the 1800s
so
what happened then well let's see there was some
beginning of the 1800s people like thomas young had his wave theory for light and then as
soon as that came in people
were able to start
doing all kinds of calculations i
mean it had been very unclear
what light was people knew about about
interference of light the the for example newton's
rings you know when you see a layer
of oil you'll see these kind of light and dark rings
and
so on that are associated with the the we
now know are associated with the thickness of the oil and
how
many wavelengths of light it corresponds to things like that i'm
bill anyway there were they were kind of phenomena
like that that had been seen and they were also phenomena
that made it look like light was just
a bunch of corpuscles
a bunch of particles that
would just go in straight lines kind of like a big big
stream of these things and so
i mean that we
now know that there's sort of a duality between this light as photons
and lightest waves thing
but that didn't come until they until the 1900s
but back in 1800
pound 1801 i think thomas
young was talking about you know the wave theory of light
and that became a sort of more formal thing
and within a decade or so people
were able to do all kinds of elaborate calculations of diffraction
and light and interference
and so on it became kind of a thing that had been mathematics
i mean it's it's worth mentioning that term in
in
oh
yeah we forgot an absolutely critical piece of history
which i i'm i'm shocked that i forgot
because it's one of my kind of favorites
and i'm just
um i'm i was i was talking about kind of things in the 1600s
and these kind of empirical laws of
of
how things work before
we get to the 1700s before we get to electricity before
we get to light and so on we have to talk about newton
and we have to talk about the the things that newton did actually the main things
his big year was 1665
which happened to be the year that cambridge university was closed
because of the plague
and newton went and hung out at his sort of ancestral home in lincolnshire
i think um and ah
and was thinking about stuff
and came up with two pretty good ideas one was his law of gravity
and the other was calculus
um
he didn't publish those things until 1687 his big book principia mathematica i
mean it's the sort
of the title of the book already tells you kind of something of the philosophical implications
the title the book of the full title is translated into english mathematical
principles of natural philosophy
so sort of pre newton the the general thinking about
how one thought about nature was
as kind of a branch of philosophy as
a natural philosophy the the the the basic thinking had been one
just figures out how nature works by pure thought just like how aristotle
had done it just like how democritus
had done it and so on and but
what newton was saying was no actually there are mathematical principles of natural philosophy now
galileo had had some precursors to this but newton was kind of the full fledged you
can figure out how the world works using mathematical principles
and
so he developed some mathematical principles particularly his laws of motion for a second
and third law for example the you
know the first law an object remains
an object that isn't acted on by a force just remains in in motion
in the same way it's been moving before at
the second law it's
you know force as mass times acceleration and
so on now
you know you might say in modern
times the first law is obvious
we know if you set
something in motion it'll
and you don't act on it by a force you know it's a it's a something
on a on their table on a you know puck on an ice rink something like this you
set it in motion we'll just keep going unless acted on by a force that
seems really obvious to us today it's
a lot less obvious
if you don't have things
where friction has been reduced to almost zero if you
were dealing with kind of well we just you
know you're pushing something through mud or
you're just rolling something on the ground it's
far from obvious that it will keep going
and with
if and that if a force isn't acting on it because actually a force
is usually acting on it it's the force of friction and
so this was a the idea that there was this sort of perfect
version of this where the thing will just keep going
and without
if there's no force acts on it wasn't self-evidently
obvious it was a it was really a mathematical
idealization that was significant
and that was newton's first law well
newton then with his forces mass times acceleration and
so on that immediately started asking
well can you actually compute given
that you know that forces equal the mass times acceleration what
are the forces that act on things so
one very important force that newton thought about when you think about astronomy was
the force of gravity
and then he had to work out well what is the force that gravity exerts
and that's when he came up with his inverse square law of gravity this
is universal law of gravity that between any two
objects the force of gravity is the mass of one object times
the mass of the other object divided
by the square of distance between them all multiplied by some universal constant we
now call capital g the
so that was his kind of idea
and his idea was that was gonna be the law of gravity that applied to everything whether
it was the moons of jupiter whether it was the sun around the earth whether
it was a comet in the solar
system all these things the law of gravity would apply
and
the
you know i've realized i i forgot another important term piece of this story
which was let
me i'm sorry to backtrack
here but i just want to fill in one more one more piece which
was around the time that galileo was was observing the moons of jupiter the
another
another important a little bit before then actually another important development was was kepler
kepler was
actually a very capable mathematician who
had a completely wacky theory of the solar system it was kind of a an evolved
version of the sort of copernican meets ptolemaic idea
and his idea actually was to use the platonic solids as a representation of the of
the motions of planets and to
have these sort of concentric
concentric platonic solids
which happened by the mathematics the mathematical results on the on the distances of platonic solids
if you threw it in estill the platonic solids inside each other it
so happens that the results you would get for the ratios of their sizes agreed
rather well with the known planets which went out to saturn at the time in
in the solar system so
so kepler was like we've derived this from mathematics we've got from mathematics we have derived
what
how
the solar system works
when the moons of jupiter were discovered
he had to start having rhombic polyhedra
as the way to describe those and it all got kind of kind of wacky but
but kepler was even though his underlying theory was complete nonsense the
the mathematics that he did was perfectly good and the mathematics he did both on polyhedra
and more importantly
the mathematics he did and realizing that the orbits of planets could
be represented as ellipses
and coming up with kepler's laws which
were essentially empirical laws for the motion of planets derive
from the mathematics of ellipses i had sort of forgotten to mention that i'm sorry that
was something that that newton was then was
then able to leverage because
what newton did was to say okay given this universal law of gravity
and these laws of motion then
it's just a matter of mathematics to derive kepler's
result that the motion of planets should be ellipses
and the the just a matter of mathematics required
some mathematical sophistication and that mathematical sophistication was the was the what originated calculus
what caused newton to invent invent calculus was
the attempt to work out given that force is equal to mass times acceleration acceleration is the
rate of change of the rate of change of position how
do you work out what the position is given that okay
you use calculus to do that and
so he had to invent the way to do that
so that was 1687
and
and kind of what emerged from
what newton did was some you
could then just use newton's law of gravitation newton's
laws of motion and calculus to compute all kinds of things one
thing that was interesting was that you could compute stuff
but it wasn't easy and that
was kind of a new thing because it had tended to be the case that the things that
one could actually compute
from sort of first principles in a sense were kind of easy to compute
i mean although the babylonians
and the ptolemy
and so on have had pretty elaborate empirical
formulas the things were it looked it felt like you were starting from first principles
had always been easy to compute actually
it's sort of an interesting thing when newton was trying to compute the position of the
motion of the moon it's
kind of a kind of a good example and a lesson
for those of us who do theoretical science newton
had got all of his whole universal law of gravitation
and this and that and then he tried to compute the motion of the moon
and he has this long chapter of his principia
where he computes it and the last sentence says but
the apse of the moon is twice as great in
other words newton got the wrong answer by a factor of two so you
know one might be taught for in sort of the bacon ian tradition of experimental
science if the experiment disagrees with your theory abandoned the theory
but one
thing that i've learnt in in my efforts of doing science when
the stuff when the theory is strong enough when the theory has enough
things going for it and has enough of a sort of aesthetic
integrity to it keep going with the theory sometimes
the experiments will turn out to be wrong
or sometimes there's something wrong with the chain of deduction from the theory to
the prediction for the experiments in the case of newton the problem was with the chain of deduction computing
the three-body problem the problem of the earth moon and sun all having
gravitational attraction to each other that's a very difficult mathematical problem
in fact we now know that it isn't soluble
in some sense in terms of sort of algebraic functions
and things like this it's a it's a problem in which in
which chaotic
phenomena happen it's a very elaborate problem that's the problem where i think that
it will turn out you can make any computation
you can have a three body system that
does any computation you want in other words the three body system is as sophisticated as any computation
so the
but anyway newton was
able to work out sort
of almost work out the motion of the moon other people later on steadily
tightened that up by around 1901
had really pretty good calculations of the motion of the moon one
gets to test those every time there's a total eclipse it's a rather sensitive prediction of exactly
where the moon is like
when the most recent total
solar eclipse that was visible from the us a couple years ago we
were able to use sort of modern techniques to predict to the second when
the when the path of totality would would
hit in any particular point in
on its path and i was a little bit concerned whether that would actually be correct
because it involved all kinds of elaborate things including relativistic corrections
and like kind of stuff
so we were we had a website
which lots of people used to work out when
eclipse would arrive i was a little worried whether it would actually work correctly
we had a person who
worked at our company who happened to be on the the very western
extremity of the of the us where the way they clips for sort of first touched
and
so
it was was good to verify
that yes at least when the eclipse first around it was indeed correct but
in a case um you
know back back to newton one of these sort of interesting there you
can realized this thing about the fact that you know you can have a calculation that is
where you can specify the rules for the calculation
but it may be really hard to actually calculate
what happens so he has a nice passage
where he talks about some way he's very concerned about the the motion of the planets
and things he says we don't know how the planets
kind of originated in their motion and
and that's kind of the hand of god to put them where they start
but once they have started then we can in principle calculate
where they will where they will end up but
he says but to know from planets with all of their mutual effects on each other
where
they'll end up exceeds
if i'm not mistaken he said the force of any human mind so
in other words he was he was recognizing the fact that there was a computational
difficulty in in working out the consequences of the theory that he developed well in practice
lots of people
worked
on it and through the course of the 1700s into the 1800s there
was more and more sophistication in the use of essentially
calculus to do mechanical calculations
i think in in ai was used both in terms of astronomical
calculations celestial mechanics and also terrestrial
calculations i think for some reason particularly
british tradition was studying
the motion of tops
and these bizarre these
the pole hoed and the hubble hood and all these all these weird phenomena about how
tops move that was sort of a became
i think a particularly british mathematical physics tradition an obsession
but - in any case there was a increasing level of sophistication of
what could be worked out using calculus
and using
essentially newtonian mechanics ideas
and that was kind of the big development of the 1700s - to the early 1800s
and i might say that that you
know at the time of newton if you'd ask somebody
what is the world fundamentally made of probably
the answer that you would have got is it's made of corpuscles don't
really know what those are but those are a little bit maybe like democratizes
atoms we don't even know what they are um they're
- somehow bound together by forces
and post newton it was like well maybe they're bound together by gravitational forces
but that was kind of the the meta idea for
what the world might be made of although it
wasn't something that was really studied in great and tremendous detail
um when
electrical stuff started becoming
sort of a big thing in the 1800s i think
people were more tended to say that there were electrical forces that were holding
things together but sort of the the the thing of the 1800s
in addition to sort of very elaborate development of of theories that were spin-offs of newton's mechanics
and calculus
i mean they're the main spin-offs that develops were
solid mechanics and fluid mechanics
the theory of stresses
and solids
and the theory of the flow of fluids stresses
and solids turns out to be a much easier problem
the flow of fluids the flow of fluids has this very complicated
issue of fluid turbulence when a fluid flows rapidly
a fluid is flowing slowly just sort of slides around objects
and it does it in a laminar smooth layered way
but when it moves quickly you get this kind of random turbulence that develops
and to
find a theory of turbulence is still something that hasn't been done i've tried to make some contributions
to that myself and i think i understand
now sort of the the the immediate answer to the question why is there randomness
and turbulence i think we can now answer that question
but in the in the 1800s as the theory of fluids was developing turbulence
was sort of off the table
it was just working out the the partial differential equations things like the navier-stokes equations that
described sort of the the
parts of fluid flow that you could work out using by solving differential equations using calculus
and so on so
anyway those were those were two big traditions of that time the
the other the other big thing that was happening was electricity
and magnetism
i think the there were both observations
and theories the i think the the faraday michael faraday 1830
discovered
electromagnetic induction the fact that when you wave a magnet around you you produce
a voltage in a wire you can induce a current in a wire very
critical thing for electrical machinery
but that was discovered by faraday purely experimental ii then
gradually was sort of the the idea of the notion of an electric field
or a magnetic field a sort of a thing that was out there that had an effect
so for example faraday was you know used to have make these do these demonstrations and
so on where you have iron filings little tiny bits of iron sprinkled
around and you put a magnet there and you'll see this actual pattern of the iron filings
that is sort of produced by this thing you can't see that is the
what he termed the magnetic field
faraday wasn't that mathematically
oriented but it sort of quickly became clear that that notion of a field was
all connected with partial differential equations
and then
this sort of the the big thing that happened by
the 1870s was was james clerk maxwell coming
up with his maxwell's equations
which were these sort of unified equations that described electric
and magnetic fields
um and it was
it was very
remember exactly when this was yeah
so
so it was it was actually within a decade
after maxwell's equations one of one of the implications of maxwell's equations and
one of the things that was sort of realized through the experiments
that faraday had done was that electricity
and magnetism were very closely connected that
you could use magnets to make electricity you could use out tricity to make magnetism
and
so on and those that kind of that that unification really came together in maxwell's equations
which are four equations partial differential equations that describe the the
the the mechanics of electromagnetic fields they tell you how charges
and currents electric charges electric currents make electric
and magnetic fields
and they tell you how electrical magnetic fields fit together and you
know maxwell was a good mathematician and invented
vector analysis something that all those div grad curl all those things that's all maxwell's although
he he originally wanted to call curl twirl
which might have been charming for the calculus students of the future um
but anyway he settled on on curl eventually
um
but the
but
but anyway so maxwell's equations have made these statements about
how electric
and magnetic fields would work one of the implications of those was
that there will be it would be possible to produce waves electromagnetic waves
and within a decade hertz had observed electromagnetic
waves and had figured out and had basically created the first radio
and it didn't take very long it took come less
than a decade before there was actual real radio being used
and people were transmitting messages the had been given done on wires with telegrams
and so on they were using you know in morse code they were sending messages
purely through electromagnetic waves
so that was kind of the the realization that tim that
that came out of the mathematics that maxwell had done that
there should be a magnetic waves and by golly there actually were electromagnetic
waves and they made radio
so
so that was kind of the big
development of of the late 1800s was this idea of electromagnetism
electrical magnetic fields things like radios
and those those sorts of things
so
the another
so another thing that was happening in
yeah i should have somebody on livestream is commenting on discovery of the vacuum
so that was in around the time of the french revolution right
so
that was some
so that was in the the 1700s the the realization that the air that is not
that there's a notion of there being nothing there
so to speak that you could make things where there isn't any air
and
where there's something
where there's nothing there i'm not sure i think
for chemistry that was an important realization i'm not sure that that was
well ingested by the physicists
and
in fact there were a bunch of issues about what you
know what the role the notion of whether a vacuum really really had nothing there
so one of the important ones of those was some people knew about sound
and they knew that sound was compression
waves in in the air and you
could also have sound in solids it was compression waves and solids
and things like that and and people like helmholtz i think 1860s ish had
developed a pretty complete theory mathematical theory of sound that
um
and
rayleigh
i think had had a version of this in fact his his book as i realm
holtz and raley's books on sound i certainly
have copies of them and i think they're pretty modern actually
and there's not a lot time you can say more with more more
or techniques
but they pretty much had nailed the way sound works
and the mathematics of sound waves and so on um
but you know there was a question come to a little bit more later
but but there was a question for electromagnetic waves we know that sound waves are compression
and rarefaction waves in air in a material question is what are electromagnetic
waves waves in and
so
this notion developed of this thing called the ether the so
called in a very victorian sounding
name the luminiferous ether the light carrying ether that
was the the idea was that tim there was this this uncie unseen thing that
was the analog of what air was to sound the luminiferous ether was to electromagnetic
waves and that was kind of at the time of maxwell
and people like that that was kind of the way people thought things worked
so
um the
well another another important
developments in the eighteen hundred sixteen hundreds were you know there's a physics
really started galloping along after
galileo and newton you
know physics kind of got in gear and things really started to happen um
and you know there's a lot of different kinds of phenomena in the world another
important area is heat the the theory of heat the idea of temperature the theory of heat those
kinds of things there's
a big debate in the 1800's
what is heat
um
and
so
it got a little bit weird
and funky i mean it was already suspected in the eighteen in the 1600s
that heat was somehow associated with the microscopic motion of the
things that made up matter and even for example one of the bernoulli's had figured out that
you know gases might be little molecules
or bouncing around that was in the mid 1700s
but that nobody really particularly cared about that
i mean people were very much concerned about heat
and and then when steam engines were invented
it was important to understand kind of what
was possible in steam engines sadi carnot worked
out the the notion of an idealized steam engine
and tried to work out how much how much energy
you get from an idealized steam engine these kinds of things
but this notion of what is heat what is the thing that corresponds to heat wasn't clear
and it got kind of weird a little bit like the ether there
was this notion of things like for gist on this this substance
that would suffice things
and that corresponded to heat
um
and
this this idea that it was a that there was that heat wasn't a substance that
was a property it was just a property of things not its own separate sort
of you know separated kind of substance that was
that took until the mid 1800s
before that started to become clear and there started we experiment
spew like jewel who
did did experiments sort of about the inter convertibility of heat as
and
and other forms of energy
and things that were known
from mechanics things about the the energy of motion that
was understood from mechanics
and
and by the way following newton
and so on the idea of the conservation momentum
the conservation of mechanical energy these
were things that had emerged from mechanics
but it wasn't clear sort of how heat fitted into that well then 1850
ish sort of big big
point the first law of thermodynamics the
idea that heat is a form of energy and that the energy
and mechanical work
energy of mechanical work like kinetic energy is sort of interchangeable with the energy of heat and so
that was that was kind of a thing of around 1850 people
like klaus i think was involved in that um the this this notion of heat
as a form of energy interconvertible
with mechanical energy well the only thing was that it was clear it wasn't completely interconvertible
because
if you had something that was hot you couldn't immediately turn
that thing that was hot you
know into useful mechanical work
and so it was kind of like why is that you
know what was what's going on there and that's
what became the second law of thermodynamics
what we now often refer to as the law of entropy increase
but back in those days it was kind of this this
law that said you can't get my chemical work out of heat energy that easily
um
and
so for example a common version of it would be the statement that heat
doesn't spontaneously flow from
a colder body to a hotter body that
was one one version of the second law of thermodynamics
but it became slowly clearer
what
um
what the second law might be um
and
and this notion that i mean we now know that the issue is mechanical work involves
you know you take this big lump of stuff
and you started in motion
and that means all the atoms
and that big lump of stuff are all going in one particular direction
if you just make the lump of stuff hot it
means the atoms are moving around they're moving around very quickly
but they're moving around in random ways and we can't kind of decode that randomness
so that we can kind of organize it into this sort of systematic mechanical motion
and that that failure to be able to organize
it is i think the origin of the second law but we'll come to that um
but anyway back in those days this notion of of the second law sort of emerged
eighteen
sixties ish kind of it was starting to be really talked about two big things happen
so james clerk maxwell actually
before he'd worked on electromagnetism i worked on kinetic theory he was he
worked on a prize
essay about the moons of saturn
um
and in it he invented
what is now called kinetic theory he
invented kind of the mathematical
theory that describes you have a bunch of gas molecules bouncing around what
can you say about
the properties of those molecules so one big thing he said was the distribution
of velocities of those molecules is this gaussian like distribution e to the minus mv squared
um distribution
that is now called the maxwell boltzmann distribution
so that was a sort of a mathematics meets the kind of the mathematics
meets the idea that gases are really a bunch of little little
particle like things bouncing around that was a maxwell
idea then along came ludwig boltzmann
and
eighteen seventy he had
proved this thing called the h theorem
so
okay so they've been this idea
and trying to characterize
what heat was relative to other forms of energy they've
been that idea i think due to klaus s that
you could define a notion of what's called entropy
which he defined as a thing that was essentially heat divided by temperature
okay
so what
what boltzmann
proved was on the basis of little
gas molecules bouncing around he proved this thing called eh theorem that
he said meant that he'd
proved that the entropy as defined by classiest always increases
and that's equivalent to statements like heat doesn't spontaneously flow from
a colder body to a hotter body so
covered through a lot of other kinds of statements
um and
so boltzmann
said he proved that now his
proof was kind of a bit of a sham it's an interesting mathematical proof but
because it turns out the laws of physics are reversible at least in the sense in
the sense that they whatever whatever
the laws of mechanics have the property
that if you can have two things that collide
like this and go
out like that you
could sort of run the movie in reverse
and they could come in from where they start from where they ended up and go
back and get back to where you started from and
so that reversibility was kind of boltzmann had gone from taking that a mechanical
just like that and it proved that something irreversible happened was the so-called reversibility objection
and that
was a very obscure thing in fact it's one of my sort of favorite physics misguided ness
things is that in textbooks modern textbooks they're
often talk about the second law of thermodynamics they'll
show boltzmann's proof of the h theorem they'll say well yes you can run everything backwards
and
how
can it not how
can you then conclude that entropy increases rather than decreases they'll
often end with statements like the last sentence being this point is often puzzling to the student well
actually been puzzling to everybody else too i think i finally figured
out in the 1990s actually
how this works
and really
the story is well
it's it's the story is that it's happening is the everything is reversible
but the dynamics of the system is effectively doing encryption on the initial
conditions of the system so
while in principle you could reverse it you
need to be a crypt analyst to do it so to speak and in practice
when we do experiments
or make observations we're not as computationally sophisticated
as we would need to be to do that reversal
so even though looked
at at a microscopic
level everything is perfectly reversible it doesn't appear
that way to an actual observer that that was a kind of an idea that
josiah willard gibbs one of the early american physicists some from the early 1900's
um he was big on this notion of coarse graining in statistical mechanics
which was coming his version of saying the observer can't
contem
can't figure out at the level sort of molecule by molecule what's
going on he didn't really have this computation
idea but he just had the idea of you can't look at the individual molecules in what's happening
i mean maxwell already had this thing called maxwell's demon but
you've had a thought experiment we said imagine
there are these two two
sides of a box and there's a trapdoor in between them
and there's this little very tiny creature who is watching when molecules arrive at that trapdoor
and is deciding
whether to send them to the left or to the right and with
that demon you can always get a violation of the second law of thermodynamics by
having sort of intelligence like that in the loop you can
get this violation second law and that's kind of like saying that's
a kind of the beginnings
of saying you sort of need a crypt analysts to figure out what how to untangle
the inexorable increase of entropy associated with the second law actually
i should mention that one feature of the second law was
that particularly late 1800s it was some it
was kind of there was this whole question of was there a life force was
there something about living systems about biology that
was fundamentally different from physical systems
and it's been a long-standing question of you know is there some spark of life that his goings
beyond the physics the chemistry and
so on and that was some that was what tim
so the second
law was often kind of invoked
you know well most things show the law of entropy increase
but living systems can
sort of do the opposite well they can't really they can only do it temporarily and
they can only do it in a sort of the maxwell's
diminish kind of way at the level of individual molecules
but doesn't really last but in a case that didn't become clear until
well into the 1900s
and
what really happened is this this notion of what were the foundations of the second law which
i think is a fascinating thing
it's one of the things got me interested in physics back
when i was about 12 years old or something in 1972 was
understanding things about the second law of thermodynamics
and it's sort of a sort of shocking that that
so little work has been done on it and when i finally figured
out how i think it actually works i don't
think anybody cares um
but i think it's i think it's really interesting
okay back to um i should
mention you know by
the way i mean by the time after
the whole life force things sort of dissipated by
probably the 1930s people had the point of view that the
second law was just true it was a fundamental true fact about nature we
sort of maybe kind of didn't maybe even need to prove it maybe or maybe boltzmann
approved it or people
were kind of confused about
it i mean the the idea of entropy got kind of a boost in 1940s
when claude shannon introduced
the idea of information as
a measure of sort of the compressibility of data
because basically his information measure is exactly - the
boltzmann's entropy measure
okay
so another big thing from the 1600s
from the from sorry from the 1800s was
was
the the whole notion of atoms really becoming real and you
know it had been known chemistry had developed a lot lots
of chemical elements were known by the 1860 mendel sixties
mendel af was sort of writing his chemistry textbook
and making up the periodic table all those kinds of things people
this this notion that there was a systematization of chemistry was becoming clear meanwhile
people like dalton even
the beginning of the 1800s had
notice things about chemical reactions they noticed that when
you wrote down chemical reactions you could things worked very nicely when
there was sort of integer multiples of things that showed up all over the place it
was like there were two units of oxygen
and one unit of hydrogen whatever
it is for four different kinds of things or or and that
but sort of it was a it was very convenient
if you could just sort of numerologically
arrange things by saying there's there's a discrete amount of hydrogen
and there's you know there's twice as much hydrogen as there is oxygen in water
and some sense and that there were these sort of simple multiples
and so he kind of developed this idea that there must be an atomic theory that would underlie chemistry
but it was done more at the level of sort of explaining chemical reactions meanwhile it
had sort of been known for a while but it kind of was was was really um became
clearer with a guy called robert brown discovered brownian motion
it was they'd have been known for a long time that things like this happened that
if you have a light enough thing he was looking at pollen grains it
would be sort of discreetly kicked around
if you
were looking at it under a microscope and that discreet kicking around people
sort of started identifying oh that's actual molecules
that are like doing the kicking discreetly
and so this notion that you know atoms that things are made of discrete stuff
um was was pretty much established
and by the time maxwell
was talking about kinetic theory there was like yeah things are made of discrete stuff discrete atom like things
what
were atoms people didn't know actually one of my favorite kind of theories due to william
thompson later lord kelvin was the idea that atoms were knots in the ether
so remember this ether the luminiferous ether that that was supposed to fill the universe
and be the thing that was the sort of carrier of light
as air is the carrier of sound waves well
so the idea was that knots you
know there are discrete
kinds of knots that you can time pieces of string there are different different
kinds you can classify the knots that exist
and kelvins
idea was well you
know it may be that
we know there are discrete
kinds of atoms maybe
the kinds of atoms
all correspond to knots and the ether a completely non stupid
theory that turns out to be basically wrong
at least in those let of that level but definitely not a not a foolish thing
to think about and
in fact the the whole the a lot of knot theory was was
produced by a childhood friend of maxwell's
no cousin called tate who started classifying
knots to try and see would
there be 92 of them just like there were chemical
elements of that that number of chemical elements
and so on
okay
so anyway
so this takes us some
let's see i think come i'm looking at questions from the live stream here this some
this kind of takes us to pretty much the end of the 1800s in
terms of what was happening so
a couple of things happen
right at the tail end of the 1800s first
1895 discovery of x-rays by rod caen um discovery
that you could have these these these
things that would kind of go through matter
and you
know would make nice pictures of bones and wouldn't be would
would not go through bones but would go through other pieces of us so to speak then
very soon thereafter becker all discovered natural radioactivity
and then 1897
thompson
discovered the electron discovered that electricity was
also made of discrete stuff just like matter was made of discrete atoms so electricity
was made of discrete things namely electrons well
okay
so there been a bunch of things that have been studied
one thing that had emerged in the think 1880s
or so was this notion of blackbody radiation
so
the question was when you heat something up it glows we know that what
color does it glow what is the distribution of colors that what are the distribution of of
colors of
of electromagnet of so we know that light is a form of electromagnetic radiation
and so
when something is heated up and glows what colors
does it produce as a function of temperature so there
was a way of calculating that based
on kind of standard based
on the fact that there might be little generators
little oscillators that would be like little radio transmitters
except for light in the at in the in the material
and there might be lots of these and they might all produce
a certain spectrum of electromagnetic
radiation problem was that calculation gave completely the wrong answer
and by 1900 there were pretty precise measurements of what the actual blackbody spectrum was
and
so a chap called max planck decided he would fit that data
and he realized that you could
get a really good fit to that data if you assumed that somehow the that'd
be that whatever it was that were these little oscillators
that were producing lateral radiation
was somehow quantized were in lumps a little bit like and he got him it
wasn't it wasn't maxwell's distribution of of them
from kinetic theory of distribution of speeds of molecules
but was something a little like that a little bit different from that
what we now call the bose einstein distribution
that that
would govern if if there were if sort
of electromagnetic radiation was quantized it would be that would be the the form of blackbody
of the spectrum of blackbody radiation
so that was kind of the first idea of of quanta
of quantization of something of in this case quantization of light effectively
so it was already known there were discrete atoms there were discrete electrons for electricity
but
what about light well planck sort of had this empirical fit that said there could also be discreteness
in light
okay
there was a thing called the photoelectric effect you
shine light on something on some materials
and they emit electrons basically
they produce that the photoelectric
effect is what's used for photo cells is what you what's used
ultimately for the its
yes i guess it's what's used for the imaging device that is the camera that i'm waving
my arms that you guys using is that same photoelectric effect um
but in any case the the photoelectric effect there were things knowing about the photoelectric effect about
what frequencies of light would produce electrons etc etc etc 1905 albert einstein figured out that
um
if you believe planck's idea of discrete
discreteness in electromagnetism
if you had the notion of a photon a discrete particle of light you
could explain the photoelectric effect um that's
actually what einstein eventually
won his nobel prize for cuz well it's of it he was way too too controversial still
um was the the explanation of the photoelectric effect
so also another
thing that was happening right at the end of the 1900s
was a thing called a michelson morley experiment
michelson morley experiment was an attempt to detect
what was called the ether drift so assume that the universe is full of luminiferous ether
um the loomer the earth must be moving through the luminous verse ether at some speed
but that means that somehow
just like sound waves if you if
you're moving through the air sound waves work differently than if you're stationary in the air
and it should have been possible to detect that that change in the luminiferous ether as
a result of the earth going around the sun at
different times of year and so on you should see
a different term different
features of the transmission of light well
they didn't see that and so
that meant there was no ether drift this
idea that there was this ether that sort of filled the universe
and that was the carrier of light something was wrong with that idea
now in the one of these typical ironies of history that kind of is a luminiferous ether
and we kind of know that because it's
well in some of the fundamental physics theory that that i have you'll see there's
something it's a little bit bizarrely abstracted
but it's something a little bit like that luminiferous ether
but even this idea that
there's nothing in the universe that sort of addressed that we're moving through that's not true
the cosmic microwave background defines a rest frame for the whole of our universe
and the earth is moving through it at one thousandth of the speed of light in a particular direction
so this idea that there's sort of there is no ether drift it they've been incredibly
precise with their experiments
and they observed
you know like by a light scattering from the cosmic microwave background an effect way
below even what we can see today they
would have seen an ether drift but they didn't
and so that led to a whole world how can this possibly work there
was a a feature of maxwell's equations for electromagnetism that implied that somehow
the speed of light was constant independent of
how fast things were moving
so however fast the object y
or whatever
a flashlight that's you're that you're taking on a spacecraft the spacecraft is moving rapidly but yet the
the actual
light that comes out of the flashlight isn't
moving relative to somebody at rest any
faster than the speed of light it's not speed of light plus meters spacecraft
and you would have expected from the galilean principle that you
can't tell in your emotion you would have expected that you
would have something where the speed of the of the photons that
were coming out of the flashlight would be the speed of the thing that was that
you were emitting them from plus the speed of light but that isn't
what happened according to maxwell's equations
okay
so then 1905 einstein
and then special relativity
and special relativity was invented as this way to reconcile
what maxwell's equations said with the lack of an ether drift and to explain
how the speed of light can really be constant
and what einstein realized was that well
you can think about the speed of light being
constant if you change your notion of what's
how space
and time work if you have time dilation if if if observers
who are moving fast see
time moving at a different rate than observers who are at rest and
so on well actually to the observer the
time seems to be moving at the same rate but to somebody else observing them their
time seems to be moving at a different rate
i mean it's a little bit spoiler alert i think we now know exactly why that happens
and how that all works
but that's that's
coming when i when i get to talk about what
we figured out about sort of a new fundamental
theory for physics but in the time of einstein
what einstein did was in a very kind of euclid style way was
to sort of write down what
essentially were axioms things like you
know physics is independent of reference frame in for
inertial reference frames for frames but it's kind of like newton's first law type type motion where whether
it's just things are just moving without
without being acted on by a force and similarly
and things like the speed of light is constant and given these axioms
he was able to derive in this very kind of almost greek
type way this these
facts about the world that were the facts of special relativity things like time dilation length contraction all
these kinds of features of special relativity people
were very suspicious at
the time they said how can you be doing this this isn't like the way physics
was supposed to be practiced it
was a very non mathematical
paper in many ways then
einstein wrote a very short paper to introduce special relativity
and people were very confused
and it was another kind of copernicus
like moment you know you can't believe what you think you see type thing now
actually from special relativity came
this notion that space
and time is somehow the same kind of thing because in the mathematical formalism of special relativity they
it's very clean
personal common makovski
um was
kind of big on pointing this out that the equations of special relativity work
in a really clean way
if you
can kind of treat space
and time as being sort of just aspects of the same thing well
i actually think that particular idea was a wrong turn and i think that particular idea
kind of set back physics by
a long time but we'll talk about that we'll
talk about that soon this notion that
space and time are really the same
kind of thing i don't think it's correct
um they appear the same kind of thing for purposes as things like special relativity
but at a conceptual
level they really aren't the same kind of thing and they probably don't seem to us intuitively
like they're the same kind of thing but you
have to kind of invent
all these thought experiments that
make them seem like they're the same kind of thing anyway
so special relativity in 1905
not a huge impact when it first came out there wasn't a lot of experimental
measurement that could be done based on special relativity it
was just like okay that's cool type thing so
meanwhile a lot of other stuff was going on particularly
stuff with radioactivity a lot of things with with that um big
thing 1911 i think was
the discovery of atomic nucleus
so people
had you know they they were beginning to think okay there are atoms they're discrete
units of matter but you know what's you know is there something inside those atoms
so rutherford took alpha particles helium nuclei a form of radioactivity
and we just was just scattering them against atoms
and discovered that most of the time you know most of an atom from most
of the time you shoot now for particle
and atom it just goes straight through
but just very rarely it's it's deflected a long way and
so rather food's interpretation of that was most of the atoms kind of just empty space but
there's something in the middle maybe of an atom that is a hard lump a nucleus that will will
bounce the alpha particle back and so that was the discovery of the atomic nucleus
and soon
it was understood that there were protons in the atomic nucleus that
were sort of particles that were part of the that
along with electrons formed atoms it
was known that isotopes existed
and it was a little bit confusing
how that worked and it wasn't until the 1930s that separate free neutrons were observed
i mean the the really weird thing about neutrons you know the tonic nucleus is made of protons
and neutrons
and in all the sort of matter that we are used to that isn't radioactive the protons
and neutrons just sit there in the nucleus of the atom they're
just completely stable they don't nothing happens to them
but
if you have a free neutron if you just manage to separate
out just a neutron on its own the neutron undergoes radioactive decay in about 15 minutes
so
if you could separate out a free neutron independent
of being bound into the nucleus of an atom it decays
and
and that's one of many confusing things about about
how it all works
but anyway so
so a tank nucleus 1910 ish
sort of a that was a a discovery there were another another thing that had been observed
and was was pretty well known was this idea of spectroscopy the
idea that when an atom absorbs light it
absorbs it different kinds of atoms absorb
light at different frequencies
and when you have a
if you
have a prism for example you can split the light into its constituent colors different frequencies
and you'll see that particular different
gases for example when they're excited like in a fluorescent light
bulb or something like that will produce characteristically
different spectra they will have discrete lines that correspond to you
know when you separate out the light in with a prism
or with the diffraction grating or something they'll have discrete lines that correspond to emitting
light of very specific frequencies
or absorbing by two very specific frequencies
so that was known and there was a whole sort of elaborate descriptive
theory of spectroscopy the question is what how
did that all work and it's sort of in the 1920s
this all started to become clear and that
was when quantum mechanics really emerged
and sort of the notion of quantum mechanics was ok
lots of things are quantized lots of things are discrete like i think 1923 the stern-gerlach
experiment the discovery of electron spin that electrons
can be in a sense either spinning
up or spinning down and it's a discrete kind of thing and the
so
there was kind of a realization
that these spectra these lines spectra were all associated with quantization that there
was a discreteness to things and then
debris in 1919 20s had this idea that maybe just like light could
be thought of in some ways like a particle like a photon in some ways like a wave
so maybe matter
and things like electrons could also be thought of partly
like a wave and partly like a like a particle
and that was a sort of influential underlying idea that helped launch quantum mechanics
so the real launch of quantum mechanics was probably the mention of the schrodinger equation
and heisenberg's matrix mechanics in 1925 ish
and
so these were both well
the schrodinger equation was a partial differential equation very
much in the sort of tradition of mechanics from the 1800s heisenberg
had a slightly more newfangled math thing that
had to do with matrices
matrices that were invented rather obscurely
i mean matrices are a very simple concept but
they've been invented in the 1800s particularly by cayley as
a results of fairly elaborate mathematical considerations
but anyway heisenberg applied those
and it turned out that schrodinger
and heisenberg view of
how things worked were were actually equivalent although the mathematics looked fairly different and
kind of the notion was that somehow
everything would be discretely
quantized a little bit like you know if you have a
so shown are just version you know you have kind of a string
and you
can pluck it in the middle and it'll make you
know a sort of single sine wave you
can pluck it in a different way and we'll make a double sine wave triple
sine wave but it's quantized
they if the string is is kind of held at both ends
they're only a limited number of configurations
that the string can be in and that's kind of what schroder just said was happening
for for example electrons
and atoms that there are only a discrete set of possible configurations
that these that these electrons can be in he described the thing that was being sort
of that represented that configuration
as well he called the wave function of the of the electron
and
so there was so
what what chandra figured
out was you could make these equations
that would describe the kind of properties of the wave function
and from those properties
you could compute all kinds of things you could start computing atomic spectra
you can compute the spectrum of the hydrogen atom all
those kinds of things and it'll
work very well you
might ask well what was the wave function
what did it actually mean well that
was where things started getting a lot squiggly
up and it was well
the wave function is kind of related to the probability that the electron will
be doing this thing or that thing um
and there was a one interpretation of quantum mechanics which are emerge around the same time was
okay just think of it as the wave function
which is a function of complex function real
imaginary parts that you can work out the probability when you actually say
you want to know what happened in the atom you can
just say i'm going to measure it and then
what
happened will be governed by a probability
that is the modulus squared of the wave function
and that was kind of the the interpretation
that was given to
two quantum mechanics it was like don't look under the covers too much you'll
get confused just compute
what happens
and you'll get the right answer
and that's kind of been the story of quantum mechanics from the 1920s until today it's
like it's a mathematical theory don't
look too closely because you'll get confused
and my friend dick feynman always used to say you know nobody really understands quantum mechanics
and i think that's i think that that that's been traditionally true
exciting you know spoiler alert for the new kind of theory of fundamental physics i think we actually
now understand quantum mechanics
and why it works and
how it's
set up but that's that's
that's for the future we're talking about history of physics today
but in the history of physics quantum mechanics with
very rapid developments in the 1920s by
the end of the 1920s a
lot of quantum mechanics was understood a lot of quantum field theory was also have been developed
so quantum mechanics is about did
the electron go this way or that way and there's just a particular electron
and we're dealing with that electron
and we're looking at it and so on when
you want to describe things
like an electromagnetic field you
have to deal with the fact that well
you don't really know how many photons are there a photon
could be created a photon could be destroyed it's
a little bit of a more complicated story the mathematics is considerably more complicated
the quantum field theory as compared to quantum mechanics
but by the late 1920s there
was already the the the elements of quantum field theory had already been developed although the mathematics
are working out the consequences were
still still somewhat in the future ok
so that was that was kind of the idea of
oh the another important thing so the schrodinger's equation was an equation for nonrelativistic
things
like electrons electrons that were traveling
at a speed very
small compared to the speed of light um
and
the that was very
soon within a couple of years after chandra's equation came out paul dirac came
up with a thing called the dirac equation the dirac equation was an equation for a relativistic electron
and it was a very mathematically elegant thing that dirac did
and but it had a very weird prediction it said there in addition to there being electrons
there should also be anti electrons particles
just like the electron same mass same properties
but with the negative charge from
the electrons that the electron usually is said to have charge minus one these
will be +1 charge
particles with charge plus 1 called them positrons
and positrons were the anti particles of the electron
and the claim was that as soon as you put relativistic mechanics into
but as you soon you tried to put relativity into quantum
mechanics you would end up with the inevitable
prediction of antimatter of anti particles to
all these different kinds of particles so that was sort of a prediction a mathematical
prediction made but basically on the basis of the aesthetics of the theory back in in the 1920s
that there would be anti particles to the electron the proton etc etc etc
another
thing from around that time was howley exclusion principle this is sort of important for understanding
well is it's a it's a thing that adds a great deal of mathematical complexity to
quantum mechanics but it's basically the principle
that when you have quantum mechanical things like electrons in particular you
can't stuff too many electrons into the same state
and that's kind of what leads to the
fact it leads to a lot of what we see in chemistry
is we get these kind of shells of electrons and some conceptual
sense in different kinds of atoms because
we can't have electrons all sort of clumping together in the same state
and that's what leads to probably leads to many
features of the stability of matter it's
a very important feature of our world
and that was something came in quite early as somewhat later it was understood that photons
the exact opposite thing from the exclusion principle they
like to come together and much later that led to the invention of things like lasers
and so on um that was
so
um
let's see the silicate
so then we're continuing our sort of trip through through quantum mechanics
and so on so 1930s well actually let me i mentioned something happened in the 1910s
so as soon as radioactivity had been discovered
and been discovered in things like uranium
and
so on there
was the question it was a weird thing people had balloons even
before the wright brothers did their thing there were balloons that could go out to pretty high altitudes
and it was observed that
if you went up to a high altitude you started seeing radioactivity just in in the air okay
and that was the discovery you think 1912 if i remember correctly of cosmic rays that
is that there are there is there
as there are particles that are streaming mostly
from the sun at least the low-energy ones come from the sun into
the upper atmosphere of the earth and the most of them are absorbed
by the time they reached the surface of the earth or there's still some residue on
the surface of the earth but as you go higher up less
of it has been absorbed and there's this cosmic radiation cosmic rays
okay
so cosmic rays were our best source of high-energy particles
and so
people did all kinds of experiments they have these emulsion stacks kind of like old-fashioned film and
and that would work when it's like don't
put your x-ray film through the don't
don't put your film high-quality film
through the x-ray scanner
because it will get the x-rays will will you know eject
the silver atoms in the in this in the film emulsion of its old-fashioned film well
that was the kind of the thing
that was done to detect particles back in the day in these for example balloon experiments
or experiments on mountains
and so on where people would have these emulsion stacks
and they would look for tracks of particles going through them okay
so that happened in the
so people did that
in in the 1930s in particular and
um was it time trying to remember the
yeah the positron
which is the anti electron discovered in 1932 the
and
so that was
so
dirac's prediction from the mid 1920s that
just sort of on a mathematical
basis antimatter must exist there
must be an antiparticle for the electron that was verified by
actually seeing one in a cosmic ray experiment in 1932 well
there were also a bunch of other particles that was seen in cosmic ray experiments people
didn't know quite what they were one of my favorites 1937
the muon the muon is just like an electron
but 206 times heavier
and still to this day we don't really know what muons are other
than just the description i gave you
um but anyway there was a kind of a zoo of particles that have been discovered
um that were discovered starting in the 1930s through the 1940s
and
so on there's another thing that happened in the 1930s a chap called hideki yukawa
tried to solve the following problem so atomic nucleus is a bunch of protons
and neutrons all stuck together okay it was known since coulomb
and that like
charges like electric charges repel so
that meant all the protons in the atomic nucleus would all want to fly apart they
all wanted to repel each other because they all have the same charge
so they were all you know trying to trying to sort of break up the nucleus
so how come the nucleus stuck together well there had to be some other force
and
so your kawa proposed that there was another force it was a little bit like the
force of electromagnetism but instead of being a force that was
trans would go an infinite distance it was a limited length force that
um would
go only a fixed distance and he had the idea that
that force could be associated with the exchange of a particle
so
by the way i should have mentioned that the photon one
feature of the photon that became pretty quickly is that photons are massless they
have zero mass the electron has a definite mass the proton has a definite mass the
foe town has zero mass
or zero
so far as we can tell interesting question
for my new theory whether it's really true that the elect the photon has absolutely zero mass
that is an interesting question which i actually don't know the answer to
but i can discuss
how to figure that out um in any case the for
all practical purposes the photon has zero mass if it has a mass it's really really microscopic on
anyway the
so
but your car was suggested that maybe there was something that was kind of like a photon
but there had a pretty big mass that was a mass kind
of like maybe a tenth the mass of a proton that would
be the the the electron as one 1800s the mass of a proton actually
it's very light compared to a proton
um
so the
that
there would be um this other particle i'm
not sure if he named it anyway it became called the pi on or
the pi meson i'm
not sure if your caller named it um
but anyway the he suggested that there might be such a particle
and that the exchange of those particles between protons might
be responsible for the binding
the strong nuclear force that bound the protons together into the atomic nucleus
and his idea was because it's
just a feature of quantum mechanics
that if it was a massive particle it has finite range it can only go
those that little exchange the process of making what are called virtual particles that
that can sort of pop into existence
and then disappear again for a for a for a photon that can happen over a long
distance leading to the similar square law
but for a massive
particle that can happen only over a short distance and the force law has to die off exponentially
and that was your car was proposal well by the 1940s
the pi on the carrier of the strong nuclear force had been observed
and it was clear that that theory was correct then
there started to be a whole zoo of other particles observed
now you know another thing that happened late 1930s nuclear fission was discovered
and nuclear
fission of course led to the development of both it of the the nuclear pile for power stations
but also to nuclear weapons
and
those were first tested in 1945
and that was it became clear that um
the
so
that was you know the manhattan project was
kind of a big triumph for physics in a sense it was a you
know it was take this effect that had been predicted
well this phenomenon of nuclear fission discovered in the late 1930s
and packaged
it up and actually
make a nuclear weapon out of it in a few years and it
was a i knew
many of the people who were involved in that term that
project it was a it was a very very
remarkable kind of scientific achievement independent of what
one can say about its military uses
and so on as a pure matter of science it was a remarkable remarkable achievement
and i think one of the things it did in the u.s. particularly
was it really launched physics as being this is an important thing i
mean it also helped that radar
had been invented in world
war two and that
was another sort of physics related thing
although it was a little bit more on the electrical engineering side
but the manhattan project was
really front and center this is physics this is what physics can do for you and basically
the few billion dollars that was spent on the manhattan project sort of turned into a many
many millions billions of dollars spent on physics research particularly in the u.s.
after
the second world war that i think in many ways was sort of a a thank-you
for the for the for the success of the manhattan project that
kind of lasted right up until the 1980s
it kind of lasted for a whole sort of generation
or two of physicists that
was and that that so the manhattan project really kind of launched the interest in
in in kind of applying
and sort of the extreme versions of physics
and particularly in particle physics and nuclear physics
and so on in fact um robert
oppenheimer the person who led the the the manhattan project
his his sort of other interest his other big interest was in the theory of stars
and in things about sort of extreme states of matter in stars
and so on um the
okay
so so coming back to by
the way i see people asking questions on the live stream about things like antimatter bombs
and so on i'll probably do another one of these science q and a's for
kids and others that's a be a great topic for for
that but let me not to derail on that subject here
um the
so
the question
it's only way one of the consequences of the manhattan project was it really launched let's study nuclear
physics at the lowest possible level let's study particle physics let's study subatomic particles let's study
what were then often called elementary particles that study high-energy physics it
it launched the idea of building particle accelerators particle accelerators are big the
kind of a big adventure and electromagnetic come you
know they're their typical particle accelerator you've got some bunch of magnets
and you're using those to accelerate particles along a track sometimes
those tracks are like twenty kilometers in circumference
and the particles go very very very fast 99.999
percent or more of the speed of light and it's usually either electrons positrons or protons
or anti protons that are accelerated in those things
and they're also linear accelerators a big one of those if you drive down
oh gosh
what is the freeway in california
i'm forgetting the one that's parallel for the 101 in silicon valley -
ten - ten all right no forget anyway
if you if you're crossover the stanford linear accelerator center this big long
big long linear accelerator that accelerates electrons um
and as place where a bunch of physics discoveries were made but in any case i'm the
in a case the the the thing that
so particle accelerators started
sort of coming online late 1940s early 1950s lots
of particles got discovered in particle accelerators a whole zoo of particles got discovered
um
and so one of the big sort of challenges was what are all these particles
and
okay that was that was sort of one branch was
what are all these particles what's this whole zoo of particles the other branch was let's
take quantum field theory the thing that sort of been invented in late 1920s
more seriously let's try in particular
and just nail one thing the interaction of photons with electrons
um
and let's try and figure out what was called quantum electrodynamics
and so in the 1940s that
was a sort of a big thing figure out quantum electrodynamics
um well
a lot of things could be figured out but there was some some serious problems
one might say the most important serious problem was that when you tried to compute things
in quantum electrodynamics the answer you usually got was infinity usually
you would get integrals
which were of the form basically dx
over x and the world integrals d k over k where k is momentum
you would say i want to consider this sort of virtual
particle that had a momentum that was as large as you want and when
the momentum was sufficiently large the contribution to for example the probability that
an electron would scatter a photon was
proportional to this integral dk over k which which increased logarithmically as that's
an integral where they were the answer
if you take the upper limit to be infinity the answer is infinite
okay
so so
that was kind of a big downer for quantum electrodynamics
was the answers ended up all being infinite umm
now meanwhile i should
have said that two people
had you know where there's a big wave of excitement about quantization
everything must be quantized you know matter is quantized protons electrons spin is quantized light is quantized angular
the all sorts of other things about some the mechanics of particles are quantized everything
must be quantized even space people imagine mainly space is quantized well
they didn't manage to make work that was always a something incompatible
with with relativity to make space quantized coming
next week you might see something different there but at
least at that time it was spaces
is a continuous thing not something made of discrete elements in any way
so the
but in a case back in the 1940s
people tried to compute things about quantum electrodynamics big problem with infinities person
who was a good friend of mine dick feynman one of his early contributions was
to kind of explain away the infinities
and be
able to calculate even in the face of the infinities he
never really liked what he did okay he invented this thing called realization
and the idea was you get an infinity
but that infinity is when you actually make a measurement on an electron
you are really
you're measuring but let's see if you started
off with a bare electron
electron didn't have any photons around it at all then you'd
you'd say it has a certain mass for example but then you let the photons
interact with it and so on and then you get an infinite answer for things okay fine well
now you say well actually maybe
i could have taken the bare mass of the electron to be minus infinity and
so this infinite amount that
you're adding to it that's associated with all the photons interacting
with it it's just minus infinity plus infinity and
it's like well we can just say the answer is the mass of the electron a little
bit more satisfactorily
you would say well all of this infinite stuff
that's going on that's happening to every electron
what we really care about is the is the difference between what
happens to this electron
that we poked this way and this electron we didn't poke and so we
can just think about it as mineralization is kind of this way of saying we'll
just look at the difference between these
things ignoring the infinities
and so it turned out that there were just three infinities in quantum electrodynamics and
once you said okay we'll we'll just say
that all those three infinities are sort of factored out then
everything else in quantum electrodynamics was
computable it's really computable
i mean you can actually compute to like you know eight
decimal digits of accuracy you can actually compute
all of these things it's it's the most elaborate successful
calculation in all of physics is calculations
they used to take it used to be done with algebraic computation systems in
the early days and they used to take years of cpu
time and so on to
compute that the big thing was the anomalous
magnetic moment of the electron was
the thing which was sort of most elaborately computed
and you would you would be able to write down thus
essentially power series for that in powers of the so-called fine structure constant one over hundred thirty-seven
and you
could the computing the coefficients
was like this years of computer time thing and you
could measure it and it was exactly right there's
very impressive result of quantum electrodynamics through
from the 1940s onwards after analyzation
had gotten rid of the the
kind of oh we don't know what's going on type type thing that was what happened
so
okay
so that was that was quantum electrodynamics
so another thing that came up in the 1940s was sort of a reinterpretation of quantum mechanics the
sort of schroeder introversion the heisenberg version these were ways to compute things in quantum mechanics
um the
it's some
it's
some this thing called the path integral also
invented by dick feynman is this way to to
say what is quantum mechanics really well
his version of it was that quantum mechanics quotes is something
where you're summing over all possible
paths you're saying this could happen in all these possible ways and it gives you essentially a prescription
for saying the probability that the thing will happen is the sum of the paths of some
of all possible paths with a certain weighting factor that's mathematically determined
and by
the way and i know i'm this is really bad i shouldn't
be doing this it's like i i'm we
now know why the particle works it's very exciting
and it has a very beautiful correspondence
to the way things work and grab it in the theory of gravity
but any case that's some see
i'm i'm actually very
poor at being patient and doing
these things but i want to get it so that i've actually got sort of more
or less the full story ready to say and that will happen next week but any case the
coming back to
what happened
so quantum field theory quantum electrodynamics great successes 1940s through 1960s meanwhile
1950s to early 1960s
this whole zoo of particles being discovered they have all kinds of exotic names you
know the the well they were the mesons the baryons the hyper owns the they
have all kinds of names i when
i was a kid i used to
really be into particle
physics and i could tell you they probably recite
the the names you know there were the pi ons there were the kaos
there was the eight a particle those amazon's
there was the there
were things like go there was the 5s
on the f mazon then
there were the baryons the the lambda
hyper on the sigma hyper ons that i'm
drawing them in a picture
because they usually arranged
that these some theory of lee groups gives us a way to sort
of have this way of arranging these particles in these definite configuration
anyway lots and lots of particles discovered
so the point where there were hundreds of these things knowing
and the question was
what
um
you know what what are you know
what are all these particles you
know how can we explain them you know we this was supposed to be elementary particles
the world was supposed to be made of these things but
now we've got hundreds of them this is not you
know the world is made of something simple
okay
so there were two basic theories that developed the the first theory
which came out of a thing called s matrix theory
and another thing that sort of came out of a quantum field theory tradition
so the the s matrix idea
which kind of emerged all that first was the following idea
so it was like like
just think about particles
colliding with each other and just say when
particles collide you can describe the probabilities of those collisions
and then you will write down essentially mathematical relations between different particle collision probabilities
and that was packaged up in a thing called the s matrix and there
were properties of the s matrix the s matrix was a function of many complex variables
it had all kinds of elaborate kind of consistency
conditions about the s matrix
and the idea of s matrix theory was it just said look don't
worry how it actually works inside just
know that there are these constraints
on the s matrix and try and compute what must happen and from
that came this thing called the bootstrap hypothesis for particles
which
was the idea that no particle is really any more elementary
than any other all
these particles just sort of emerge as
some sort of consistency condition from each other
okay
so that was theory number one okay
theory number two which
emerged in 1964 ish particularly
another friend of mine named murray gell-mann um was
responsible for this one together
with person called george reich who is also a good friend of mine i'm the
was this idea of of quarks
so
the idea of course was maybe
these particles like protons aren't actually elementary maybe
inside a proton there are actually in the case of a proton three quarks
and originally
marika man kind of invented that idea a little bit like the way that you know dalton
had done the atomic theory of just sort of counting things and looking at how
what constituents
would have to exist just to make the numbers work out although
murray sort of packaged that in a somewhat more elaborate theory of li algebras
and li groups theory of sort of fancy mathematics of symmetries
but in case what it really came down to was you just count if
there are quarks they have to have these properties
and then you could make three quarks would make a proton
a quark and an antiquark would make a pi on there
will be three kinds of quarks
and up down a strange they were originally called pn
and lambda
but but in modern times they called up down and strange
um the in a case the the that was the idea that inside
the proton that we'd be three quarks now
there was a problem there
because it was like well why don't we seek walks out
and out in the wild well
there would have to be some mechanism that would confine the quarks unlike
an atomic nucleus which could undergo fission
and
where the pieces of the nucleus the neutrons
and things like that would just sort of you know you know come out that
couldn't be the case with quarks because what seemed like we didn't see any free quarks
so that was kind of a weird feature of that theory
okay
so then that
was quark theory versus the of
the the s-matrix theory it seemed like the s-matrix theory was winning in the 1960s
it really seemed like it was winning
um actually one of the things that got made from from that s-matrix
theory was a very elaborate piece of mathematics that
was string theory well at least it was the first version of string theory it
was a theory of strong
interactions that was sort of mathematically derived from the whole s-matrix setup
okay
so by the late 1960s
something that was being done was the thing called deep inelastic scattering
so just like rutherford discovered the nucleus by
bouncing by by shooting alpha particles at um at atoms
and noticing
that most of the time i just went
through but some of the times they got bounced back so
um
a particular person called hofstadter father
of douglas hofstadter um was was one of the main people who was involved in
and there was several other people involved in that um involved
particularly at slac actually the stanford linear accelerator center the thing that
you can see from the freeway whose name i've now forgotten um the
that's
gonna drive me crazy that i can't remember
that but anyway maybe somebody
can put it on the live stream i'm the
in any case the
so
same idea
but for protons instead of for for atoms shoot high-energy electrons at protons
and see what happens
so what happened in most of the time the electron would go straight through but some
of the time it would bounce back
and
so that meant that there was some kind of hard bit inside
the proton well at least that was one interpretation of what was observed in deep inelastic scattering
so
um
the that was
well
actually dick feynman was involved in in inventing
this thing these things he called part ons which
was supposed to be the parts of protons well it became clear
that basically
that it looked like part ons might be quacks it
looked like in these experiments one might be seeing some sort of constituents
inside inside protons um ok
they've been another development in the 1950s a thing called the yang-mills theory was
invented yang-mills theory was a generalization of the theory of electromagnetism
but electromagnetism can
be thought of as
a so-called gauge theory a theory
that's associated with a local symmetry a local
and it's associated with a local symmetry group there's just rotations around a circle
so yang
and mills had
this idea well maybe there's a generalization of that that
involves not just the symmetry of going around a circle
but a cemetery that would be for example essentially of going anywhere
around a sphere or something like this or or some slight generalizations of that um
and
so they invented this thing they called yang-mills theory it was a pure sort of it
was a pure sort of theoretical idea
and maybe they thought it might be related to the strongly perforce
some way but they didn't quite know how ok
so that led in
to
that that theory
so
called non abelian gauge theories led to well
actually led to two things i i'm getting them see
this is now that
this history gets more complicated for me because we're head hitting the part of this history
where i was actually involved in certain ways so um
by the time i got involved in particle physics around 1974
um
and
so it's always
it's always the worst is always
remembering the history that involved
that that one was involved in but any case the
okay another little sideshow here
oh yeah 280 that's that that's the freeway that that
i was forgetting that's
the one that crosses over the stefan
area accelerators hunter i'm the
in any case the
okay
so so back to this i'm i'm gonna try
and i don't have too much more to talk about but
but i was gonna try
and get us up to modern times
um and then
yeah
okay
um
we're
still in the 1950s we're talking about some yang-mills
theory i'm gonna mention one more thing that happened
okay
so
when atomic nuclei decay in radioactivity there are three forms of radioactivity that were embedded were identified
pretty early alpha beta and gamma decay they're
all their mechanisms are completely different alpha
decay is just like throwing out a piece of helium nucleus
and beta
decay is an interesting one beta decay involves the emission of an electron or
positron from a nucleus
and that is a form of the way in which it decays
and
many
famous things like carbon-14 decays that way a lot lots of things decay that way so the
beta
decay not really well understood i
talked about the strong nuclear force beta
decay was often said to be associated with the weak nuclear force
okay
well the people didn't know that much about the weak nuclear force but one thing that was
observed in beta decay in 1957 i think was a very weird phenomenon called parity violation
okay
so when
you think about the laws of physics there are certain invariances
that are usually true like for example we
don't imagine that if we
if we just turned
something turn some physical system upside down ignore gravity we
turn it upside down we'd
think it still worked the same way the laws of physics will be the same if we turn
the thing upside
down you might also think the laws of physics will be the same if we reflect the
whole thing in a mirror we
would still it wouldn't be that it will be the case that just
as something could happen this way if we reflect in a mirror it could
happen the way we would see in the reflection in the mirror
okay well that's all very well
and good except
that it turned out that that mirror reflection symmetry didn't apply to nuclear beta decay
and it was discovered in 1957 that basically the that
you could have an asymmetry
in nature in the emission of in the in the angular distribution of electrons in the decay of
of nuclei
there was this thing called parity violation the violation of
invariants under
under just sort of mirror reflection of everything
much later it was realized
so another feature of beta decay was that it seemed like something weird was happening
because there was a question of how momentum was conserved because electrons would come out and
it was like they would shoot off in some direction
but the nucleus wouldn't recoil the way you would expect from a momentum conservation and
so then pauli suggested the idea that maybe there was an unseen particle
and neutrino he called it and that was a particle
that wasn't detected that was in neutral electrically neutral particle
you couldn't see with a particle detector was going off the opposite direction from the electron
and turned
out the the the main result actually is that neutrinos are always left-handed there's you you well with
a slight exception about neutrino oscillations
but let's not worry about that for the most part neutrinos are always left-handed
and that's why this that's a way of understanding this parity violation phenomenon
you don't find equal numbers of left and right-handed neutrinos you only find left-handed neutrinos
and so that's the so that was the sort of explanation
which became clear only a number of years later for
parity violation but anyway that was a phenomenon discovered 1957
discovery of sort of features of the weak nuclear force there
was kind of a question of how did the weak nuclear force relate to other
things we knew like electromagnetism feature of the weak nuclear force it's really weak compared to electromagnetism
it has a really short range
so strong
and close force has certain range weak nuclear force has a much smaller range weakly
a force in some sense has a range that is about
2,000 times smaller than the range of the strong nuclear force it
wasn't known how that worked was suggested 1967
or so byam
steve weinberg
and abdus salam that
that there was kind of a possible theory of the weak nuclear force
and a way to sort of unify it with electromagnetism
and in in kind of a tradition of we don't have enough particles yet typed thing they they're
what came out of that was the idea that there were yet more particles just
like there were photons that were carriers of electromagnetism there
would also be w bosons
and z bosons that will be carriers of the weak nuclear force
but they would have a very high mass which would
lead to this short range for the weak nuclear force
okay
so that was that was something that emerged that was a that
was an example of a local gauge theory
it was a local gauge theory based on the group su 2 cross u 1
okay
so then in the in the by the early 70s this idea of local
gauge theories was like all the rage and there was another local gauge theory
that was suggested for the strong nuclear force
and su3 local gauge theory in
which the carriers of that force will be things that got called gluons like
quarks they would be confined inside the proton
but they would be another thing it
was kind of like a photon
except not really like a photon
except they were massless except unlike photons
which don't interact with each other directly gluons
would have a an interaction glue on to glue on interaction
so
okay so that was all sort of a nice mathematical thing
but honestly people didn't really believe people believed the s-matrix theory of strong interactions
was the way it went until 1973 1973
a phenomenon called asymptotic freedom was discovered
the
and
this was came out of a kind of mathematical development
called the renormalization group that
had been part of that had been sort of an offshoot of the renovation idea
but basically what was discovered was that
if you kind of looked at a strong interaction
if you looked at one of these gluon interactions at
a very short range if you were like the
way that things working in quantum mechanics through the uncertainty principle is short
distance is kind of equivalent to high energy or high momentum transfer
so
if you kick something a lot it's like probing it at a very short distance so
what
what this said was this asymptotic freedom idea said one could do a calculation
which showed that if you kick things really hard in this
su3 gauge theory that was called qcd quantum chromodynamics
um that
that it would be the case that
um that the um
the quarks
and the gluons would behave
as if they were almost free particles
as if they didn't really have this very tight binding
the strong nuclear force associated with them um
and
so that was kind of so that was kind of a theoretical idea
but it became clear that these deep inelastic scattering experiments
have pretty much seen this phenomenon they'd
seen the idea that when you kick the thing hard enough it behaves
like it's a very free
particle that can just bounce around anyway at once rather
than being this this tightly confined thing
that can't do much so
that was in 1973 sort of big transition in physics the
realization quantum field theory is it you know we can compute things with quantum field theory
and there was a huge
sort of i was
involved in particle physics at that time there was sort of a huge
rush of excitement about
what one could do in in physics using
the ideas of quantum field theory actually it was really fueled in 1974 by
the fact that there was two very surprising discoveries one was electrons
and positrons annihilated other they turned into two photons
or into other kinds of things the
when you sort of crashed them into each other at high high energy it
turned out the probability that they would annihilate went
up in a way that people didn't expect and then
i think was in november 1974 i think of the japes aught jpi particle was discovered
it was a new particle that had
a mass of 3 point 1 gev about
3 times the mass of the proton
and nobody really expected it would be that big surprise
so
that was that was sort of the the the beginning
of the sort of supercharging of particle physics which kind of lost it through the 1970s
and people like me i was 14 years old at the time kind of got excited about
what was this particle can we explain
what was going on etc etc etc um turned
out that particle was actually evidence of a new kind of so-called charm quark
and that was sort of an unexpected discovery in physics
and that really made it clear that this whole gauge theory kind of quantum
field theory thing that was really it that was kind of really
the thing that was working
so that kind of fueled
a lot of work another
sort of unexpected discovery
was made in 1977
the thing called the b quark was discovered also
a thing called the tau leptin
which was i mentioned the muon
which is kind of like just like the electron
but 206 times heavier there's also the tau leptin
which is just like the the muon
but gosh it has a mass of about 1.7
gev i'd
have to do the math which i can't immediately do in my head but it's about
um it's about
it's about
thousands of to thousand times three thousand times heavier than me i'm than the electron
um anyway
so those things were all discovered the the other big thing that happened
okay i'm leaving out the thing
called spontaneously broken gauge theory so one of the issues have been renormalization important
idea let you calculate things in quantum electrodynamics question
was were these other gauge theories including these ones that involved things like the w
and z particles that were very high mass particles
or even just electrons that had nonzero mass were these things also realisable
and in the simplest way of setting things up they were not realizable
you couldn't i mentioned
that in qed in quantum electrodynamics there
were just these three infinities
that showed up in these other theories you'd
compute something you get an infinity you compute something else you get another infinity
you just kept on getting new infinities
and that meant really couldn't predict anything you didn't have a finite number of infinities that
you had to just sort of get rid of um the
so in any case then
it was some when was that that must have been early 70s
it was it
was realized that through
the higgs mechanism for generating mass you would be able to get massive particles
without breaking realisability
and it was proved that in fact these theories were renormalizable
the higgs particle was kind of this weird way this
weird thing that i always thought was a total cluj
and i was pretty disappointed when the hid particle was actually discovered in what 2015
or so
because
i'd really thought this cluj cannot possibly actually be right anyway
it was it's a way of of understanding
how mass arises for particles like electrons and
so on and kind of the idea is well
the particle doesn't really have a mass but throughout the universe we're back to ether again throughout
the universe there's
this higgs field that sort of is
spread throughout the universe and as the electron goes through this higgs field it's effectively a generating
a mass and again
there is no ether
but there is an ether but
and the ether is now the a recent
version of the ether is the field i'm any case the
okay
so well that was so particle physics you know lots of good things happened by
the late 1970s there was this idea maybe
it will be possible to unify the strong interactions that weak interaction electromagnetism everything bundled together into
a grand unified theory
and that grand unified theory we i mentioned these gauge
groups the grand unified theory might have a group that was like su v a bigger group by
these other groups will be subgroups
and somehow there will be particles with masses of 10 to the 15 gev
and so on that would be associated
with this bigger gauge group and so on everything would be great one
prediction the prediction was the proton will decay with
a lifetime of 10 to the 30th years
um
okay
so people busily around 1980 were
looking for proton decay because it was a prediction of these grand unified theories
and they
didn't find it no proton decay has ever been observed so
far as people know protons are completely stable particles
so that was a big downer and that kind of the energy of looking
at some kind of grand unified theories decayed
meanwhile experiments
were going on you know tens of billions of dollars were being spent on particle accelerators
particularly at fermilab in the us and at cern and geneva switzerland
and
1984 the w and z particles were duly discovered actually
after
the the b quark was discovered
it was known that there also had to be a bottom
quark there was also t quark a top quark that must exist that
was discovered in 1995 actually
i had figured out with
a prison called david poet sir back in the late 1970s that
there was an upper limit on the
masses that courts could possibly have if the universe wasn't going to become unstable and we
believed the universe isn't unstable
right now and the the top quark actually comes pretty close to our upper bound on how massive
a court could possibly be anyway
so those were discovered in 2000 i guess it's
2012 maybe the the higgs particle
which
was something what was predicted from this whole higgs mechanism that
was discovered as well there emerged this kind of standard model of particle physics
which allowed you to compute things and everybody just kind of the
everybody just was able to go ahead and
compute a lot of things in particle physics in it it became sort of a thing
where one didn't really have to when didn't really think about the fundamentals
of what was going on almost more just thinking about the the computing
of things i noticed on live stream with question how can there three different infinities
the point is that the the mathematical
formulas that generate those infinities is slightly different and the issue is they are all related to different
physical properties of electrons that one is right of the mass of the electron one
is related to a coupling of the electron to the photon
and
what's the other one self energy the vertex
king polarization
yeah the the other one is associated with the propensity of a photon to turn into a virtual
electron-positron pair
and those are just the three independent differently
computed kinds of infinities in quantum electrodynamics z 1 z 2 z 3 usually they're called
um
okay well
so particle physics kind of hit the 1980s
and sort of the standard model got established
and it was all just calculation from then on out in a first approximation so
particle physics kind of put it on a shelf more
or less done in some sense with the slight footnote
oh grand unified theories hadn't worked out
okay there's another branch i'm gonna try
and go fairly quickly on this um the another
branch of the story of physics is gravity
so
gravity had a much
so newton had this idea this universal law of gravitation 1687
inverse square law pretty much nothing happened in gravity until 1915
and in 1915 einstein had this idea of general relativity
and his idea was let's try
and he what he wanted to do is to generalize the sort of logical deductive
ideas of special relativity was sort of an axiom it ization of physics implying things to
deal with the general features of space
and gravity and
so he had this thing called the principle of equivalence that
was sort of a thing that was another principle it said that the you
can't kind of tell the difference between acceleration
and being in a gravitational field those are those are sort of two things that seem
the same if you just look at mechanical properties of what's going on
so anyway he
invented this idea he used kind of very highfalutin mathematics of the time differential geometry and
theory of things like riemann tensors
and so on he
always used to say and i i actually in my own efforts in fundamental
physics now i i now deeply sympathize with what he said he
he would always tell people people would say you using this all this elaborate mathematics
you must be very good at mathematics
and he would say you
know look this mathematics is kind of the outer limit of what i understand
but i happen to be able to apply it to physics
and then physics i've been doing recently there's wonderful
and beautiful mathematics that applies and i i i feel very barbaric in
my uses of it because i'm sure there's there's a much more elegant version
of it that will eventually be discovered
but i'm using it in a barbaric way as i
think einstein felt that he was using differential
geometry in a sort of barbaric way but nevertheless it worked and the
main thing that einstein did was to show that that
you could think about gravity
as corresponding to curvature in space-time so you know when you shine
a laser beam it'll
go in a straight line what is a straight line mean well
a straight line if you think that space is curved a straight
line would be something
just like a straight line going on a sphere is curved a straight
line could be something that deviates
and so
what einstein suggested
and his einstein equations is that matter mass
causes
deformation in space-time causes
space-time to be curved and that means that what you thought was a straight line isn't
what
you would otherwise consider
a straight line and so that accounts for the fact that for example if you you
know if you something
that would otherwise be moving in a in a sort of newton's first law a straight line if there's
a piece of the massive object space-time is curved around that massive object
and so the thing really is moving in a straight line
but it's moving the straight line in curved space-time and that causes it to to
deviate its trajectory in just the way that gravity says it should evie ate the trajectory
so general relativity had a prediction it said that the deflection
of light around the sun will be twice as great as will be expected from other theories
essentially there was a form of gravitational magnetism a gravitational log of magnetism that
essentially doubled the effect of gravity on on a photon going around the sun and then
in 1919 there was sort of a big excitement
it's not completely clear how genuine
this experiment was but big sort of excitement of going to observe a total solar eclipse
and discovering that einstein was actually correct that term that there was twice the deflection
so general activity had its first big test and it worked just fine
okay general somebody is a very mathematically complicated theory
and it
was very hard to work out its consequences already it was known by 1916
a guy called karl schwarzschild had had
worked out a solution stein stein's equations they corresponded to a spherical object like a star
and the gravity associated with that and that solution
had a prediction it said that there would be four in certain cases an event horizon
but it was completely not understood
what that meant at that time it was some see these equations are complicated
and there's a question of of the event horizon was sort of a similarity in the equations
and that the thing is that it's easy to get singularities
and equations for example let's say using latitude
and longitude to describe a position on the earth if you use latitude
and longitude
what happens at the north pole you have kind of a weird singularity of of the of the longitude
at the north pole because that the actual north pole is sort of all the longitudes
are are stuck together
but that's just a mathematical singularity
it's not a genuine
feature it's not like there's something weird at
the north pole of the earth with
respect to it's just that that's a matter of our description
so
the thing that term so anyway general relativity developed quite slowly
um one of the things in general activity that einstein had the most simple-minded
version of einstein's equations implied
something that einstein thought was completely on sense it implied that the universe expands
so einstein put in this thing called the cosmological term
which was intended to compensate for
what would otherwise be a necessary expansion of the universe we're all needless to say in 1929
a guy called hubble observed that the universe is expanding einstein
always said that that was sort of the biggest mistake of his physics life was the cosmological term
because it didn't
need to be there because actually the universe is expanding and really his equations
if he'd really trusted them predicted
that the universe should expand anyway hubble observed that galaxies were receding and
actually la mettrie had already proposed
what is now called the big bang theory that the universe started as something small and
and progressively has expanded
okay well meanwhile by the 1940s
people like oppenheimer actually will looking at sort of what would happen when stars collapsed
and it was slowly
becoming clear that black holes were a thing it
wasn't clear whether black holes will sort of have this singularities
associated with them they have this event horizon actually laplace in the 1700s
had already thought about what
if the escape velocity of a thing is more than the speed of light does
that mean that light couldn't escape from it well
that was what was happening in these equations in
what einstein's equations predicted
but people weren't sure was that a coordinate singularity was just a piece of mathematics
or was it something real
but it became more
and more clear that there would really be this this phenomenon
there should be this phenomenon sufficiently
massive stars when they collapse should
undergo gravitational collapse and form these event horizons
where light couldn't escape from them
so
that was sort of a feature of of generality that generality in a sense describes its own failure
because it says that at the very center
of it like a schwarzschild black hole there's a singularity in space-time
and that means that the equations by their nature can't describe that singularity
so it's kind of explaining its own its own limitation
but nevertheless it was there was a lot of mathematical complexity around that well
meanwhile the the notion of the big bang and the expansion of the universe been developed some 1940s
people were talking about that and so on people didn't know whether it was really real 1964
some guys at bell labs were trying to do satellite communications
and they observed that there was this this irreducible background radiation whichever
way they pointed their antennas
and it was then realized gosh that's just a relic of the big
bang that's a relic of the
essentially the photons that have been created in the very early universe had
now been sort of red
shifted they'd now been cooled down to the point where they were this very low-energy
2.7 degrees above absolute zero
radiation
that was in all directions in the universe so that was kind of evidence 1964
really evidence for the big bang theory of the universe
it hadn't been clear whether that theory was correct or whether there was a steady state theory
that was really correct
where you know the universe was just steadily producing new galaxies
popping up in different places by
the way one thing that was also a confusion
that lasted a long time was
the question of antimatter
and where was the antimatter in the universe because
the the most obvious theories the big bang would produce equal amounts of matter and antimatter it
was discovered in 1964 a thing called cp violation
also
related to time reversal violation it's
a phenomenon whereby there's sort of a difference between particles
most things about particles
and antiparticles the same but some particles
and antiparticles have a strain have some strange small differences particularly
the neutral k on so the original example
um
but
in any case there was still this mystery
and when i was a kid still a big mystery
why is there more matter you
know why don't we see a bunch of you
know could there be antimatter galaxies
could the andromeda galaxy be made of antimatter we didn't know actually
i some of my early science
had to do with trying to figure out what what the consequences of antimatter galaxies would be and
and things about separation between matter and antimatter in the universe and
so on actually in the 1919
late 1970s i worked on using cp violation to understand
what i think is now the generally accepted theory
for why there isn't as much antimatter
as matter in the universe that there
was cp violation in the early universe that
caused a small difference
between the amounts of matter and antimatter and all the stuff that wasn't different annihilated
away but we got left with a small residue one part one hundred million basically
but is everything we know that's
the matter in the universe so that's that's one kind of weird
feature by the way they the one thing about antimatter is antimatter
still falls doesn't have negative mass still
has positive mass i now understand why that's true but tim that was that was originally
kind of just a fact from quantum quantum mechanics any
case back to general tivity
so
what happened in relativity was some sort of progressive measurements
things got more accurate you know the of very nice experiments done on the effect of gravitational
redshift all kinds of other things predictions of general relativity binary
pulsars neutron stars orbiting each other
emitting gravitational waves just like you can emit electromagnetic waves when you have moving moving electric charges
so you can mit emit gravitational waves when you have moving
moving masses that was a prediction of einstein's general relativity
and
so
that was the that was kind of that
was there was i was in direct observation of gravitational waves through
these binary pulsars things like that you know generalist everything was working great theory
from 1915 no changes working great and in
fact to this day it's worked great and the big thing in one was it 2015
discovery of gravitational waves by ligo was
this is the merger of two black holes causing
a very violent thing
where about two
times the mass of the sun is dissipated in energy in a matter of a second about
a third of the way across the universe
and that produced this intense pulse of gravitational waves that
was detected by gravitational waves deform space-time
and so
what ligo does is it basically is looking at the length of a big thing
and it's basically
saying if there's a defamation in space-time like a wave comes through space-time
the length will change just a little tiny bit a tiny fraction
of the distance across an atom the length will change to
represent the passage of the gravitational wave more or less and
and that was observed in 2015 a fantastic
um that validation of general relativity and of the existence of black holes
okay
so the one thing that
you know it's like the
one kind of big flag that something doesn't really quite work in physics is the
fact that this whole structure of quantum field theory is completely
inconsistent with the theory of gravity so
the the problem is you
try and make a quantum theory of gravity the most obvious way to do it is replace
photons by gravitons
and stir
the pot so to speak well if you do that you
get a theory that isn't realizable
and this big mess so
people starting in the 1980s really
got excited about doing quantum gravity finding
a way to merge kind of quantum field theory and gravity
and there were these different schemes things like super gravity schemes
that said let's add more particles well those particles weren't observed other
kinds of schemes for merging gravity
and and and quantum mechanics another thing that emerged was a retooling
of string theory string theory were originally invented as a well ultimately unsuccessful
theory of strong interactions
but it was sort of re retooled
and put to work as a theory that would unify quantum
field theory and gravity a sort of a consistency
condition of string theory is is general relativity etc
etc etc it had some weird predictions like the universe is really 26 dimensional
but most of those dimensions are rolled up in little tiny balls and so on kind
of weird things that to many people
might be kind of a sign there might be something
unconvincing about this theory
but people didn't have much choice so physics
community kind of barreled right along and a lot of physicists started working on string theory um
and and there were some excitements in the mid 1990s there was a thing called m-theory
which would sort of emerge from some sophisticated theory for whatever it's done in physics
and whatever it will do in physics it is spun off a lot of very nice mathematics
and the sort of merger of mathematics with physics that
has been associated with it is really very powerful i
mean i might say that in the physics
that i've been doing recently i think that
string theory it's mathematics is quite relevant although its underlying structure
is not the same but you know string theory has been re
sort of recast once before i think it can happen again
and still leave the same string theory structure intact
so to speak but the thing that that happened in
so quantum gravity big thing in the 1980s 1990s
and
so on one piece of that had been
1974 stephen hawking worked
out this idea of hawking radiation which was sort of a a a rather rickety
kind of calculation of sort of a merger of quantum field theory of
what happens to quantum field theory near a black hole and the basic
answer is you can have situations
where virtual particle pairs are made particle-antiparticle
pairs are made one of the pair falls into the black hole and the other one is emitted
to infinity
and that leads to a black hole not really being black
but emitting radiation hawking radiation hasn't been observed yet
but it's some it has it's a great theoretical interest
and actually i think we have some very interesting new things to say about it
but in any case that led to a bunch of a bunch of kind of theories
around
kind of thinking of black holes so black holes even
though they're big you
know kilometers across and so on or whatever it is or even bigger than that
um they are in a sense very perfect there's
you know if you have a black hole it
sort of doesn't have any hair there's a no-hair theorem for black holes actually but
but it's basically like all you
have to know about a black hole is its mass how
fast it's spinning and maybe it's electric charge and
and everything else it's like a particle really
but it's just a great big particle
and
so
that idea of a black hole is just like a particle is
something that has sort of wound its way into theories of sort of attempting to merge quantum mechanics
and gravity particularly
from the late 1990s a thing called the a dsc ft correspondence it's a correspondence
between anti-de sitter space
which is a version of the solution to einstein's equations
and i think called conformal field theory
which is kind of a limiting case of quantum field theory
and there's a very beautiful mathematical
correspondence between these things which i think actually is
a precursor of something that we now understand much better um
but that has to do with the merger of relativity
and quantum mechanics
but anyway i think we're pretty much from
well that's that's kind of a well
i've been talking there about fundamental
physics in another there
are two big branches i haven't talked about maybe another time i'll talk about these -
condensed matter physics things
like theory of superconductivity and
so on that
was a field that really really started to engage you
know really impressively in the 1980s
um
and
the other big thing i haven't talked about is quantum computing that's
something i actually worked on that with dick feynman actually back in around 1981 not too
long before people had mostly heard of quantum computing
but that's a that's a thing that's sort of a way of taking the formalism of quantum mechanics
and trying to apply it to computing
they'll probably more to say about that i talked about fundamental
theory of physics um
and there's
things that um that
we can probably say now about quantum computing all right i'll take there is some quick come
quick come
[music]
questions here i haven't been paying attention [music]
all right well there seems to be enthusiasm for you know i think
what we've discovered is
um
it's kind of a it's something i started working on thirty years ago and and for
a variety of reasons stopped
and stopped
and then finally last
fall i kind of had a little bit of a breakthrough that i made and then i started
working with a couple other people very
energetically on this and it's spectacular
and i think you know these things
which kind of i've known about for
what
kind of close to 50 years now about physics that always seemed a bit mysterious i
think we really understand
how they work and it's really
really cool and i can't wait to talk about it and we'll have a bunch of material ready
sometime next week and
i'll be doing some live streams
i'll be doing
live streams kind of explaining the main point it's
the main point is not that trivial to explain
i mean not super surprising that
if you have a fundamental theory of the universe it's
not like a one line thing to explain
how it all works but then i'll be doing some more technical q&a a physicists
and mathematicians
and computer scientists later on
and no it's not a cellular automaton
if you if you want to know what it's like go
read go look at chapter 9 of my book a new kind of science
which you can find online that's
really the that's the that's the precursor to what term to what i'm talking about
okay well
um all right
we should play wrap up here i went on a lot longer than i expected i guess there's
more in the history of physics that i then
i thought i remembered um
but
thanks for thanks for joining me and i look forward to saying
more about the future of physics
next week so thanks a lot bye