all right, saxs, how you doing, brother?
wait, wait, what's this?
why are you wearing a tie?
i'm in dc today, so it's a it's a government day.
ah, so you suited up with the ties.
you suited up with ties.
well, maybe i'll join you.
maybe i'll join you.
oh, look.
what is this box i just got?
oh, that's for my guy tom.
oh, just for jcal, mr.
jason calakas.
let's see what's in the box here.
oh, what's going on here?
tom ford sent you something.
oh, tom sent me a nice tie.
and you don't go i i heard that moose ate your invitation to the white house.
he did.
sorry about that.
[music] let your winners ride.
rainman david.
we open sources to the fans and they've just gone crazy with it.
all right, everybody.
welcome back to the number one podcast in the universe in the universe.
it's been proven time and time again.
oh, this i'm not putting the tie up.
ah, it.
it's just it's enough already.
i i guess friday.
we we moved the show to friday.
sorry you're getting this on saturday.
you can't come to the white house.
you can't figure out a tie.
yeah.
well, maybe you could show me how to do this next time i'm in town.
i got to practice with you.
we'll go in the mirror.
you could.
that'd be great.
bit you behind me.
show me how to do a tie.
we didn't have ties in brooklyn.
what do you want me to do?
all right.
well, it was an eventful week.
some of our besties,
some,
not all, were invited apparently to a a little suare
at the white house with the president,
saxs and cham.
here's a photo.
some pretty good seeing arrangement here.
looks like zuckerberg got the pole position on the right hand of the father
followed by saxi pooh and chimath and amo
sitting right across from sam alman and tim cook.
what a crowd.
what was the
um what was the impetus for this dinner?
sachs, tell us.
well, this was a tech dinner at the white house.
i think it originally started with a group
that chimath
organized in silicon
valley and they were kind of the core nucleus
of this and then
more and more people just wanted to
come and try to get in and
the president invited some of the top tech leaders and
pretty soon it turned into the room that you saw there.
i mean it's really pretty amazing president trump's ability to convene all these people.
you normally don't get these people in a room together.
many of them are competitors and it's remarkable.
you pretty much had i'd say like maybe half the tech industry was there
by market cap.
certainly.
by market cap for sure.
yeah.
and chimath, you obviously were involved here and you got a pretty good seat.
any great inside stories?
any inside baseball?
what did they serve?
by the way, i'm curious what gets served at a dinner like this.
that was a very elegant menu.
and they they try to keep it light so that it's not
overwhelming, which i think can get in the way.
so it was like so no prime rib, right?
there was a barata
salad and then there was a a fillet and then a nice raspberry
dessert.
okay, here's what i'll tell you.
sax said it well.
what was incredible for me just to frankly be in the room felt very surreal.
you're seeing the leaders of the most important companies in the world sitting together
and i just felt like there was a sense of alignment and cooperation
and that was really cool.
i think none of those folks
have to really show up anywhere that they don't have to.
i think they're at a place in their career and the importance
of the businesses
that they run.
but the fact that the president can convene them, i think says
a lot about him and the agenda.
and then they
to a one were incredibly
supportive of what he has done and
clearing the way and allowing them to build their businesses with a lot more clarity.
it was just very clear the juxtaposition
of
what it was like and the difficulty under biden versus what it was now.
and you saw some very truly hard cast liberals who have now completely embraced president trump.
folks like tim cook, folks like bill gates.
and i think that that's an incredible testament to him and his agenda.
and then the second thing, which is more personal, is i was so proud of sachs.
every single one of these guys, and you're talking like the titans of titans,
they took a moment to say that he was just doing an incredible
job and the president was really proud of it.
it was like as a brother.
it's like you're seeing your brother just get completely it was it was great.
so, that was really special.
freeberg, any any take on this?
i i noticed you didn't make it.
you didn't make the cut.
my invite got eaten by moose obviously as we heard earlier, but
i thought you for sure would get a seat.
what happened for you?
bring no seat for you.
i work in agriculture, jay cal.
so, we're doing the agriculture dinner next month.
it's going to be great.
the president and i are arranging a round table.
it's going to be fantastic.
yeah, just kidding.
no, but i was in dc.
so, if i eat my vegetables, i can come to them.
no, no, i was in dc with the guys.
i actually did an interview with
senator
rand
paul,
which you'll
which i think is out on youtube
now
and
on our
podcast channels.
it was great to sit down with the senator.
what was the highlight of the of the the paul interview?
i didn't get to watch it yet.
apologies.
as i was getting ready for the summit.
but did you have a highlight or two you want to share with us?
i mean he he's an interesting guy.
a lot of people have challenged him because he's an independent thinker.
he really is true kind of libertarian
views and libertarian beliefs and he's held firm to them despite bucking with the party
which he did recently on the big beautiful bill.
you know he was one of three republicans to vote against it.
so he's criticized and chastised and, you know, ousted
in a lot of different circles in dc because he doesn't kind of fall in line.
but i do think that dissent
and debate is critical and important for us to find the better path forward.
and i i like the role that he plays.
and i think he's very first principled.
and i think his talking about his ability to get elected
despite not being willing to always fall in line with the party
is a really important point.
and he hopes it will inspire other politicians
to follow the same path and for voters to see that there is a role
for independent thinkers in congress.
yeah, i mean that is something we need.
it seems like these parties just get locked step.
they're expected to vote the same.
they're vote on party lines and
sachs that is definitely a weakness i think of the two-party system.
your thoughts on ran paul and his
you know being a bit of an agitator maybe like
mansion was that there's a role for this.
yeah.
in our democracy.
well, i think it's good to hear from a libertarian
voice once in a while they're going to have a different sort of conservative
once in a while.
i caught that too.
they're going to have a different sort of viewpoint that could be called conservative.
so, i like grandp.
but can we just go back to the the dinner?
i want to just yeah build on a point that chimath
made about the level of sort of comey
in in the room.
i think that the the people in the room there it was remarkable even though
a lot of these companies are competing with each other they
were largely on the same page with respect to what was happening
in the economy
and the world
and
with the kind of support they needed
for
the tech industry
to do well
and
for the us economy
to do well.
and i think the reason why they were largely happy with the trump administration
is because the trump administration has been pro- innovation, pro- infrastructure,
which includes being pro- energy, pro- export, so these companies can sell their products internationally.
and then also the thing that's been very important to the trump administration is proworker.
and you heard the president make all of those points in his
critical ai speech
that he gave on july 23rd at the ai summit that we co-sponsored
with hill and valley.
so i think a lot of the compliments that we received were due to the agenda
that the president articulated
so well at the ai
summit
and
the people in that room are largely
supportive
of that policy.
so,
i don't know if i would call it a love fest,
but i think it was an opportunity
for
these tech leaders to articulate their concerns where they could use help.
and i think the president, he's a great listener, and
he wanted to take in their feedback and
figure out how to make the economy grow even faster.
i had so many questions from, you know, behind the scenes, etc., like
seating arrangement, how's that discussed?
the first thing i'll say is the president takes tremendous control over these details.
so i've said this before about how conscientious
he is, but one of the things that he noticed before
was it was very difficult to host
press conferences or world leaders outside in the rose garden.
so the way that it started was around 4:00
what happened was that
david, and i'll tell you because there was a joke about this at dinner.
david asked the president, "can we do a tour of the oval
for all of the fans of allin?" and the president said, "absolutely." so me, freeberg,
sachs, we went and caroline levit meets us and walks us in.
by the way, if you want to see a star of stars,
like i've i've met few people like this who exudes this level of competence.
i mean, i think it was the first thing that freeberg
said after maybe like two minutes of interacting with her.
it's like, "wow, this may be the most competent person i've ever spoken to.
she's outrageously
good."
so,
she gets us all,
she cleans
up some stuff that had to be cleaned up,
walks
us in,
and the president gave us this tour.
and the beautiful thing about the tour, if you are
a student of american history, is the history is on the walls.
i mean from george washington to abe lincoln to even ben franklin
and the declaration of independence jason.
and so
we were able to see all of that and and
see all of that in detail and he was able to talk about it and then
as it kind of always does it veers where
you know he does the weave and he's like guys
what do we want to talk about and
free
was able to ask some questions and saxs
and i and then it just became a little bit more freewheeling
like well it turned into like a hang a hang.
yeah.
we we hung with the president
and then
after we hung we turned the cameras
off
and then we hung like another half hour 45
minutes with him.
people are coming in the oval
but it's literally like an episode of west wing
meets vep meets like you know it was like everyone's just chatting going in and out.
you meet all the characters.
so then that
ends
and sax had to do some meetings in the oval with the president.
so we all leave and we're escorted into i think it's the roosevelt room.
sax, is that right?
is that so when we get into the roosevelt room, this is where it becomes surreal.
you're seeing the most powerful people that have built these incredible businesses.
i think there's 30 people, but the table can only fit like 15 people.
and so you have like
tim and sam and satia
sitting on the couch over here by these two chairs just like dylan
field and alan
wag.
and it's like the funniest scene because everybody
at that moment
all the ears are gone because they know the context in which they're they're there.
yeah.
in their own worlds, they're like kings.
but in the white house, you're back.
you're sharing the backbench.
you're an american citizen who's there to meet the president, right?
but there were some incredible people there.
some people i i'd not really met before.
safatz, lovely, and her husband.
and then there were some other people that were just amazing.
jared isaacman, which is wonderful to see him.
there was a whole group of folks that were there.
and then
they say, "hey guys, can you just get into a single file line?"
and so again, it's like a it's like a surreal scene where it's like
sundar satya, bill gates, survey
these people in a single file line.
i mean, you guys sound like you went backstage at a zeppelin concert.
incredible.
no, dude.
and then we're we're escorted into the oval
and this is like what's so kind about what he does.
he sits at the at the resolute desk
and mirith or who's incredible,
she introduces everybody one by one so that they hear their name.
i don't i it may sound like a a weird thing, jason, but like
to hear your name called
in the oval and then you stand beside the president.
he's seated and they have a photo.
they take this beautiful photo
and then the first person was saffra and her husband and her husband
says, "could i take a pen?" i swear.
so
the president
says, "of course, that's what they're there for."
so he gives him a challenge coin
and a pen.
everybody takes one.
so again, you're seeing the leaders of these incredible businesses.
one by one, they get announced.
they go stand by the president.
they take a beautiful picture and they take a coin and a pen.
and then we're all just kind of milling in the oval after that's all done.
and he says, "well, guys, we're going to talk at dinner, but
do you want to just start?"
and it was amazing because sergey, does he sit behind the desk then?
he's still sitting at the he's still sitting.
so anyways, sergey asks a few questions,
really starts to get the conversation going, which i which i think was really good.
and then he says, "okay guys, let's continue this conversation
at dinner." and so we exit into the rose garden
and this is where our friend
sunonny madro
says
on the way like as we're walking says sir i hear you have a playlist.
can we hear the music?
and so he takes the ipad
turns the music on
and he apparently
had been tuning it and so now it's like
he's got a great playlist by the way.
it's like fleetwood mac.
i mean like you're hearing like all the classics and it's just blasting in the rose.
i mean blasting.
lisa sue posted one of the photos.
you can see them all because like the oval is small.
okay.
so, just to be clear.
so, then that's dinner.
oh, wow.
there you go.
it's stuffed.
i mean, i'm
right to the left of tim and jamie simmonoff is right at the end.
i and i think it's vc rana dbe who's the owner of the kings
is right there of the sacramento kings started typical and then i think it's me.
i think i was standing kind of more in the front there.
anyways, so we leave.
so, so if you just pause there.
so that window
that's sham sankar who's the cto of palanteer
and behind him is dave limp and then you can see
dylan field the founder and ceo of figma.
that's the door you exit.
you go into the rose garden and then you walk through and
we walk down the hallway.
you guys have seen that before.
and we go into the to the east wing and they say
want to introduce the first lady.
so what happens is you walk into the east wing, you walk upstairs
and there's a very elegant seating chart that they make.
it's actually a really good way of doing it because normally
what you would do is you would
walk around the table.
yeah.
no, this is a much better system.
so you actually have a
small model of the table
and so what happens is you go you you can see where everybody is sitting
and then you see where you're sitting and then there's an escort that takes you to
your seat.
so, it's a really it's it's done really well.
i mean, for it's very thoughtful.
yeah, it's very thoughtful.
it was in the east room where we also
did the crypto
summit
at the white house and there's been
other events
there.
but let me just give a shout out to the first lady, melania trump.
she's very interested in this topic of ai.
and in fact, earlier that day, we did an event at the white house
with the ai education task force, which she's chairing.
and she's very passionate about making sure that every school child in america has access
to ai
so they can get ai education.
and we had dozens of companies there at the white house making pledges
of resources to make sure that
teachers and students and families will be able to have everything they need
for kids to learn ai so they have the skills
for this critical tool.
so this is a topic she's very interested in.
so she wanted to be at that dinner.
so then we get seated
and
people
are talking a little bit and he goes, "guys,
if it's okay with you, we're just going to let the press in." and i thought
what that meant was
a few people, i mean,
i've never seen anything like this before.
it it's like a zoo entered the east wing like cameras, boom, microphones.
oh, the gaggle.
the gaggle.
they start screaming
because like everybody's trying to shout over each other to try to
be able to ask questions.
but then, you know, the president kind of imposes control and says, "guys,
hold on." and then he allowed
the ceos of the of the big companies
to say something and then gates said something
and then that kind of set the tone and obviously he said something
and then he said, "anybody have any questions?" and then they just start screaming.
i mean, and there are people running around with mics.
i don't know
how you pick who gets to say something quite honestly because the question
procedure it's out of control.
no, but but you know what's crazy is the questions are so all over the place.
i don't know how you can be prepared like he knows what he's saying.
he's very purposeful with what he's saying.
i don't know how you do that
because
the questions
are all over the place and you could tell like cuz one of them asked zuck
questions.
zuck was like what's going on zuck?
zuck zuck what about your 12 houses in palo alto zuck?
i mean, no, it was a tougher question.
what was that?
i it was about free speech and the uk and he did a pretty good job.
zach, my instagram account's locked.
can you help me?
my instagram.
anyway,
so then so then they leave
and then
well, by the way, they have to be like thrown
out,
you know.
they don't just leave.
they're out of control.
they make coral, you know.
yeah.
and then we had this
lovely three course dinner and then right after the appetizer,
i think like he starts going around and people just start
talking and saying things and things that are on their mind.
and i'm i'm not going to share anything from that from that.
but i thought i thought that was pretty illuminating and pretty awesome.
let me ask you a candid question.
and challenge him on any topics.
were there any i mean we saw there's a lot of agilation.
people thank you mr.
president.
there's a lot of difference.
anybody throw him a fastball, curveball?
was there any challenging question in that format?
it's not about asking him questions like you're interviewing him.
but there are people that brought up challenging things that they are dealing with.
yeah, that's what i mean.
but that no, that is not what you said.
so, no, no, it's something that maybe is
not aligned with maybe how the administration is doing things.
that's what i'm sort of getting at.
okay.
no, but that's again you're trying to like nobody's there to gotcha.
people are like, "sir, i'm dealing with this specific issue in this specific country.
can you help?" ah, got it.
well, i was thinking like immigration, high skilled in immigration.
that seems like a topic everybody cares about in our industry.
i'll tell you what we talked about.
the issues that they had are
many and they have to deal with how american companies can build businesses
in a seamless, straightforward way.
and what they said is
since biden, what trump has done is clean the decks and allowed them.
they all said that.
they didn't they weren't forced to say that.
they all said it, which i thought was really cool.
this is again why i said earlier, super proud of what david has done.
like it was palpable the respect that all these guys had for him, which is awesome.
but then what the president says is, i could take care of this.
i can do that.
that's not going to stand.
he's like what you see is you have these american titans of industry.
i've said this before, jason.
the whole premise of the american dream, i think, rests on economic and military supremacy.
that is derived from technical supremacy.
that group of people are the geniuses that create the technical supremacy for the world.
and he is their biggest advocate.
and that's inspiring because it's like
they are like sir here's what we need
and he's like great
i'm going to go to that for you and try to get what you need.
and so there was that conversation and then there was a joke
and he said at the end something to along the lines of ah you know
i had to
it's a tough day or something like i had to
i had to film a segment
for
david's
dumb
podcast.
just said it like as a joke.
so everybody everybody everybody starts laughing and then zuck piles on.
he goes, "well, the only dumb parts are chimat's parts and
everybody else starts laughing." but when zuck said it, he's leaning back.
and then he loses his balance.
sax saxs with the tism is just looking straight ahead at timco.
i i am like i don't know what to do.
nat caught zuck.
nat pulls her arm.
i don't know how she got there.
it was a really sweet moment.
and then i had a favorite moment actually.
it occurred after you guys left the white house.
here it is.
this is chimat's greatest moment.
there is a chimat super fan.
as you can see there, that's a chimat super fan.
and he's signing multiple pictures from all different eras.
those will be on ebay later.
look at this guy.
i just want to back up and say
one of the reasons why i thought it would be
cool for us to kind of do this
interview
in the oval
where the president
kind of gave us a tour
of the changes he had made to the white house
is
i was getting a tour
with my family
one weekend of the white house and the guides
who do these tours
were telling us about how much care the president takes in
the condition of the white house and all the upgrades
that he's made.
and they've seen him walking around and he'll pick out paintings and art.
they'll move things around.
he got a whole bunch of paintings out of storage.
all the paintings that are now in the oval office are ones that he directly
picked out.
and they also said that when he sees something wrong,
like with the landscaping
or, you know, he'll
call a gardener over and give him notes on
how to make it look better.
and the president himself posted a truth
a few days ago where the new pavers on the rose garden patio
got damaged.
there was like a big scratch and see that video.
he caught them online.
he caught the he caught he caught the delivery guys.
he went to the tape to figure out who did it.
yeah.
that's that's a new york developer.
and not only that, he fired them
and he's making them pay for it and they got to buff it or something.
yeah.
it's funny.
he told us the story at the dinner that the the contractor
who got fired was devastated.
so, he's probably going to have to hire them back cuz, you know, he's
he's too nice.
and he asked everybody.
he's like, "do you guys think i should hire him back?" we're like, "yes,
i heard the guy." he's like, "i'll probably hire him back." it started as a tour.
it was supposed to be a tour.
we were going to see the rose garden and other things.
and then it rained
and so we just stayed in the oval and then it became
like
more of like a hang.
oh, wow.
you guys are going to make that into an episode.
that's going to be an episode.
oh, that's incredible.
okay.
so, jason, like look, you see
the couple days before and the president tweeted about this, nick.
i sent that to you.
you have india, russia and china kind of like fratinizing
and then one or two days later
the president convenes this dinner of
i think you know some incredible entrepreneurs building
a lot of the really important things that the world needs in the future.
i don't know what your reaction is when you see the kind of like
i mean yeah there's a legion of doom there the putin and she and
not modi maybe but he he's obviously making a point
but you know overall i had a lot of thoughts about it.
but i did a i did a press hit.
of the 20 people there or so, i'm not sure what the exact number was.
i'm just eyeballing it here.
i think we're at 2930. i think about 19 of them
are lifelong democrats who have switched to this party.
and and i i think the democrats need to look at this.
this opportunity was always there for the democrats.
but what did they choose?
they chose to take the position of ban the billionaires
and an agenda that makes no sense.
and if you had invited this group of people, if you were biden
or kamla
and you invited
this group of people to come to the white house, they would have come as well
and you could have a really thoughtful
conversation about them.
what the democratic positions might be, you know, wages,
healthcare,
and and this same group of people would have engaged,
but they were not allowed
to access the white house.
they were not allowed to have a dialogue.
and i think they pursued, you know, very weird agenda.
and you got nancy pelosi out there day trading.
got aoc and the socialists, you know, pursuing some crazy agenda.
what do you expect
people to do if you tell them we don't want to hear your concerns?
we don't want to engage with you in debate.
you can have all kinds of differences with trump on style.
i do.
you could have policy issues.
but as a moderate,
when i see something like this, i just got to give,
you know, you a lot of credit,
saxs,
for being able to
give
access to the president and give the president
access to these individuals
and let
an all these important discussions
happen and then the group can act as one
in the american people's interest.
and i think it's very important for
the democrats to learn something here, which is 90% of americans
aspire to be billionaires.
and 10% maybe they're you know socialists
moon
communists
whatever they are it's fine they can pick
and choose what
they
believe is important in the world
but americans
love these individuals
they love these products and services and 70%
of the top 50 companies in the world by market cap are american companies
this is the best of america this is the best of the american dream
and
it's great that they can go and have debates
with the president
that was you know to my earlier
question
like i know a lot of these guys have some issues with the president
or
certain issues
tariffs
etc.
this is an important i think moment in time to just say trump 2.0 i know
is engaging the business community
and meeting them where they are and saying how can i help you grow faster?
how can we compete?
america is not the only game in town.
now, as you saw with modi,
you know, creating this alliance with she and putin,
it's imperative for the american companies to excel and create jobs.
and we have the lowest unemployment.
we'll talk about employment today.
there's some new statistics.
we have the lowest unemployment of our lifetimes.
it's for a reason.
it's not because of any president.
it's because of these great companies.
we should be celebrating them.
and the president's done an exceptional job of doing what all americans do.
we celebrate these companies.
we love the iphone.
we love teslas.
we we love these products and services people are building.
people love google.
they love chat gbt.
it's fantastic.
and so it's easy to be cynical,
you know, about business or business leaders,
but this was really, i think, a great show of force
and it shows the country's getting in sync on what matters and that
has it should be independent
of political parties.
so i was very proud of you, david, that you built this bridge
and you built it brick by brick and i think
yet to come.
well, i mean,
just to be clear, i mean, obviously
the president already
had access
to all these people and in fact, many of them
were already on speed
dial and he already knew
them
and he he's the one who convened
them at the white house.
i've just been helping with policy.
so, i don't want to just be clear about that.
well, i'm not overstating
it, but i'm i'm i'm even going back six months
when you guys held the fundraiser
and then just, you know, you see like a very close friend of mine, mark pinkis,
lifelong democrat, has donated,
you know, probably
eight figures
to the dems
in total over the years
and he got frustrated
at a certain point that he couldn't get his calls returned or he couldn't
have important discussions.
well, here we are.
he was at that dinner.
i think that's a very important lesson.
the democrats need to feel moderates, business leaders.
they got their bob igor,
they got jamie
diamond,
they got a bunch of people who could help,
you know, build an agenda that's not lunacy.
yeah.
and what i would say is is look, maybe half the people at the dinner
have actually moved to the center or to the right relative to where they were.
and i think mark pinkis has basically put himself in that category.
so there's people who have like been red pilling and moving over to our side.
and then i'd say the other half
people in the room haven't necessarily
changed their politics and they're just there to do business.
they want to have a good relationship with the government.
but the same is true on the part of the president.
you i saw some conservative influencers
saying, "how can the president meet with this person or that person?
he's been such an opponent in the past."
i mean, look, the president is doing business as well.
he asks all the attendees
of the dinner, "how much are you investing in america?"
you know, what do you need to invest more?
he wants to see the infrastructure investment.
why?
because it benefits all americans, not just software companies.
it benefits the construction industry, the trades, the electricians,
the carpenters, the energy companies,
fracking
and so on.
so he he's there representing the interests of the country
and then many of those ceos are representing the interests of their companies
and there's a dialogue
going on
and it doesn't mean that everyone has to like suddenly
become a republican
or change their politics.
but it's constructive and this is all in furtherance of having the us economy grow better.
all right, perfect segue.
we got lots to talk about in terms of the economy.
and first story here, trump's tariffs got overturned in court.
federal appeals court ruled 74 that trump exceeded his authority when it comes to the
emergency economic powers act.
okay, we'll get into the details here.
historically, congress was in charge of tariffs, but under an emergency, a national emergency,
the president can get involved with tariffs.
and they cited
the 47th administration fentinyl crisis at the borders, mexico, canada, china, etc., and the trade deficits.
well, the white house got sued by a group representing small businesses.
in may, two federal courts ruled that he wrongfully
invoked the ea and the white house appealed that.
they've now lost and trump's tariffs will remain in effect until october 14th
allowing the supreme court to appeal this.
these tariffs have been tremendously unpopular in the business sector.
i think maybe 70 80% of business leaders in a recent survey
sack said that they don't they're not crazy about them.
but they have on the other side generated over $150
billion in revenue in a couple of short months.
so they could generate trillions of dollars in the next decade according to estimates.
i guess the question i have for you sachs is you guys are moving
at the white house there in this administration, the executive branch at startup speed,
moving fast and break things is something we talk about doing in our
industry and is this just the natural extension of that?
the president is doing a lot of aggressive things and sometimes
they're going to be allowed, sometimes they're not.
what's your take?
well, i'm not concerned about the fate of tariffs at the supreme court,
even though it's probably
a coin flip, whether the supreme court's going to allow the tariffs under aipa,
but there are five different
laws under which the president has the authority to impose these tariffs.
so, there's a chart here that we can throw up on the screen.
there's section 232, there's section 2011, section 301, section 122, section 338.
there are at least five different bases for the president's
authority to impose tariffs.
so, at the end of the day, i think it's actually quite unlikely
that the supreme court's going to force a change in tariff policy.
and i don't think the supreme court
sees it as this urgent matter that requires a a quick resolution.
so, i'm not particularly worried about it.
in terms of the popularity of the tariffs,
my guess is that they're not going to be reversed
in the future by a future president because i think they actually are quite popular
with the country, with workers.
among the business elite, it's more mixed.
i'll grant you that.
but if you change the way you ask the question
from are you in favor of these tariffs to
are you in favor of
raising
4 trillion
in revenue over the next decade through tariffs
to fund
a tax cut
like we had in the big beautiful bill
then that might change people's perception of it.
so that's really the question is is
how do you want to raise revenue for the government?
and between big beautiful bill
and the tariffs, what you see is a substitution from taxing americans to taxing
foreign companies unless those foreign companies then make a big investment in america.
so look, there's no great way to extract revenue from the private sector.
all taxation is is unfortunate and undesirable
and be better if we didn't have to tax so much.
but the reality is i think that if you have a choice between
taxing american people or imposing tariffs,
i think tariffs may be the better way to do it.
and i just want to note that the cbo
has now increased their projection
of what tariffs will raise to 4 trillion over the next decade.
so 400 billion a year.
it's pretty significant, right?
and initially it started as a lower number and it completely pays
for the one big beautiful bill.
chimoth, here's the chart.
tar trump's tariffs were meant to help manufacturers.
do manufacturing firms think they're helping?
has your business been impacted by higher tariffs this year?
and here negative impact 72% of manufacturers.
3.7% think it helped and 17% said no impact.
7% don't know yet.
your thoughts on tariffs?
are obviously unpopular with people in retail manufacturing
in those businesses,
but as
axe points out,
hey, maybe the american
people like them and they like the idea of a new revenue
stream.
what are your thoughts, shiman?
i think that the tariffs on balance are a pretty smart master stroke of strategy.
i think that we did not understand
what the impact of tariffs would be except for hypothetical econ wonk talk.
and so that hypothetical
econ wonk talk basically said that tariffs
were always going to be a disaster.
and if you ask them, well, what is the actual practical
data that you would point to?
they didn't have any.
it was just more hypothesis.
but what is the practical data now?
i think that the united states is going to book
probably close to half a trillion of of incremental revenue.
it's actually forced a stabilization in the dollar,
which i think that people were always very concerned with.
what's going to happen to the dollar complex?
everybody always screams like with a like their hair is on fire.
but the dollar complex has stabilized, i think, because of tariffs.
so, there's been some real positives.
and what sax says is right, which is whoever is president over the next,
you know, 5, 10, 15,
20, 30 years, there'll be some democrats, there'll be some republicans.
it's going to be very hard to justify why you would undo this now
because this source of revenue is going to be an incredibly important one.
well, and also it's not just the fact that the revenue is very important.
you rais a great point, which is the us government's
going to become dependent
on that revenue, but also
just workers.
i think the tariffs are very popular with bluecollar workers.
auto workers really like it.
well, here's what i was going to this the the pie chart that you showed
is not accurate.
and the reason it's not accurate is that the investment cases
that you would underwrite because of tariffs and the big beautiful bill haven't happened.
so, i'll give you an example.
i am a person that started a business that is building a factory
to make batteries in my specific example in michigan.
so to delever away from china
for the battery supply chain
and what i will tell you jason is after the big beautiful
bill and because of tariffs
it is much easier now for me to underwrite.
why?
because i have 100% depreciation across all my capex
it's a complete changer on the irra of these projects.
so before where i would have to raise billions of dollars from outsiders,
i can subsidize a lot more of it internally
because i can actually underwrite to a better gain because the the tax savings are
so meaningful.
same thing for this data center that i'm building in arizona.
so
in all of these cases,
i think that
a you have this uptick in revenue because of tariffs on the short term and b
the important thing is to redo this pie chart in probably a year.
like for example, our groundbreaking in michigan will be in july of next year
for that factory.
it'll be online 2 years after that.
the real story, jason, of all of this will be really known in that period.
but right now, what i'll tell you is the underwriting
case for putting a ton of money into the united states
has changed to the positive because of these because that 100% depreciation.
it's a huge deal.
yeah.
whether you're buying plane, yum yum.
all in aviation.
freeberg, here's your poly market.
will tariffs generate greater than 250 billion?
it's peaked at like 30%, it's come back down to five.
most people are betting.
so, this could be a case of
free money
if people want to go get it on poly
market
because it has a pretty good chance of hitting that.
but well, the number the number i said, jason, is like a yearly run rate.
so, technically,
if you just look at the calendar
25,
you you only get a stub of eight months because it starts april 1st.
8 months, 50k a month, 50 billion a month to get to 400 billion.
so they should be able actually think they're going to hit that bogey.
but freeberg, the reports from people who have been impacted by tariffs.
obviously these could become inflationary,
but the people who are being impacted said they've been eating them to date,
but they're not going to be able to eat them forever.
so it could become inflationary.
what are your thoughts on the tariff kfluffle here and and the legal battle over them
as well as the impact it might have on inflation
which is something we do not want to see come back and we have been teetering
just under that 3%
number
which then puts the fed obviously in difficult
position with their mandate
to get to two freeberg
i'll address the legal kurfuffle
point which i think is a good one because i do think
that the great debate that's going to happen from this presidency
and will likely shape the next set of presidencies
will be the right for presidents to declare emergencies to move forward their legislative agenda
and arguably the tariff
institution by many members of congress should have gone through a congressional process.
in the meeting i did with ran paul this week which has now been posted,
he talked about
the challenge that they have had with democratic presidents biden and
prior to that
using emergency authorization
vested to them under the national emergencies act which is a 1976
statutory authority to take action and then in order for
the emergency
powers to be turned off,
congress actually has to vote
and they can only do so after 30 days.
and when congress makes that vote, the president can veto their vote.
so the president
can then say, "send it back." so then they have to get a two-third
supermajority
to get it to pass.
so it creates a system whereby the president can have this emergency authorization
to progress much of their legislative agenda under the guise of emergency powers,
which
you know, for many people they would say is not the right way to do it.
so,
senator paul and others have proposed bills,
for example, that the president has to get any emergency
power reauthorized
after 30 days
and then it can only be a maximum of 90 days without
congress enacting
a a renewal.
and so, it requires actual congressional action to continue the authority
of that emergency power depending on what the supreme court does or doesn't do.
i think it is going to catalyze
a legislative push
and the republicans
are likely not going to embrace it this presidency or this term because
president trump is in office.
but i think the conversation
that some,
you know, out of the box republicans
like senator paul and others are saying is, well, what's going to happen next time?
what's going to happen when there's a democrat president and we don't aoc is going to
emergency powers to do something you might not like, right?
is that your point?
yeah.
and so as it relates to both the aipa of 1977,
which is the act that this case is about,
but also the national emergencies act of 1976,
should they go back and pass a new law that basically
forces
the president to have to get congressional
approval
for any emergency to last longer than 30 days?
so
i do think that's
going to be the big debate
that's
going to come out of this.
as it relates to the tariff revenue,
i am most worried about the fact
that we use the tariff revenue,
as i said before,
to offset spending
and basically keep a baseline of spending without actually getting ourselves to that deficit
target.
right now, we are going to vaporize and create debt of $2 trillion this fiscal year.
so,
we're using the
the tariff revenue under the cdo scoring
to basically say, "hey, we can do these tax cuts because it's offset."
but the goal shouldn't be to offset.
the goal should be to get cuts to actually reduce the deficit.
and so, that's the biggest concern i have with respect to the tariffs long term
is it's
now a new revenue
source that we don't actually treat as
incremental
to reduce deficit.
we just use it as a way to introduce new spending or continue spending.
sachs, just to
um you know talk about the three branches of government, wouldn't
it also be an option for the president
just to go to congress
with some of these tariffs
and say, "hey, can i get these approved?"
would that be the worst thing in the world?
wouldn't they vote for it?
i mean, but yeah, things take time.
do you have concerns that president aoc
might do some things with executive powers that the republican
party might be opposed to if she
winds up winning in 2028?
that's an important question, sax, is if aocc's president and then she uses her emergency authorization
to do things that you disagree with,
wouldn't the republicans
then feel regret that they didn't pass one of these acts that
limits emergency authorization and power?
well, look, i i think that in general,
when you have a policy
that you want to last
for a long time, the best thing to do is to codify it into law
because executive orders obviously
only last until the next president decides they don't want them anymore.
so yeah, it may make sense after the administration
hopefully wins its case to seek to codify these things into law.
we have a few years to do that,
but i don't think it makes sense to wait for congress
to act because they may never act.
and in fact, it was president trump who shifted the whole debate on this topic.
i mean, the whole establishment of both the republican and democrat parties were
very against tariffs and it's pretty obvious that nothing would have happened on this issue
and he's completely moved the debate.
so, this is just one where i think he's acted unilaterally because he had to.
but i think that once these tariffs are in place for a few years, i don't
think they're
going to get
pulled
back by a future president
because i think they're going to
it's too much money become
quite popular.
it's too much money.
okay.
in the other cases, two more lower courts have ruled against trump.
one said the deployment of the marines and the national guard were illegal.
one said he can't freeze research funds for harvard.
so, again, back to moving fast and breaking things.
these cases are making their way through the courts and there has been some resistance
to
sending in the national guard which is something there's been a bit of saber rattling chimoth
about maybe going into chicago next.
what are your thoughts on the national guard issue?
they should look here's the thing.
who is against safety and security?
who and why?
i don't understand.
so if you can't do your job, look, you have to remember jason,
let's take where we live in california, where you used to live.
yep.
not anymore.
13% of our income goes towards state coffers
and then we pay
real estate taxes and all of the stuff that goes to local municipalities.
what are you doing with that money if you're not making the places we live safe?
and then the second thing would be making the schools good.
and so if you can't do it, if you can't do it, of course
somebody else should step in.
and frankly, what i have heard consistently
is even though the talking point has to be, "oh my god, woe is me.
we can do the job."
everybody behind the scenes like, "oh, thank god they're here." anybody who is being impacted
by crime would like to see the national guard come in and remove encampments
or drug dealers or get drugs off the
streets.
saxs, you know, you're a
um
my perception would be that you think
that there should be separations between the executive branch and
maybe the states and that this rule breaking
of sending in the national guard that would go against
the rules of the sovereignty of the states.
so, putting aside chamat's
point, which is completely valid, that they haven't done a good job here and
it it is illegal as the judges are pointing out, do you have concerns about that?
okay.
well, first of all, i reject this characterization
that it's the trump administration that's moved fast and breaking things.
if you recall fast, let's just say moving fast.
well, i think the president is taking swift executive actions that are popular.
and you see this actually in his poll ratings.
he got the highest approval rating he's ever had just in the last week.
and a big part of it is because of the reduction in crime in dc.
i think he got to 55% approval on poll rating.
and even in dc, by the way,
the mayor and her staff have said all sorts of positive things about the help
they've received now from the national guard and from the federal government.
and the citizens are extremely happy.
crime is down.
i think we had the first two weeks where there was no murders
in the capital in a long time.
the residents are very happy.
so, this is definitely working.
now, with respect to california,
let me just point out that
the national guard wasn't called in specifically to enforce laws on the street.
what happened was that you had ice and homeland security agents
and workers were doing their job
and they were conducting some deportations and then you had protests
turn into riots and those protesters were threatening to burn down
their headquarters and that's why the national guard had to be sent in.
so, it wasn't the trump administration breaking things.
it was riers who were breaking things.
i can't understand for the life of me why
the administration wouldn't be able to send in the national guard to protect
federal workers against riers, but apparently that's the case.
so, look, i think the court reached a very specific decision about what happened in california.
we still haven't had a case adjudicating the question of whether
the proposed interventions
in in these blue states to clean up crime
will be allowed over the objections of democrat governors.
we don't know.
i think it's pretty clear that the dc intervention will be allowed and it's extremely popular.
and look, the dc one he's legally allowed to do.
so yeah, he's got he's got his what was it?
a 30-day mandate.
he can take it over.
and so here's your popularity from the economist.
it is ticking up, but
um trump and the country still seems pretty divided.
41% approved, 55% disapproved, 3% unsure, but he has moved up significantly in the last week.
today, some big news came out friday with the soft jobs report.
pretty much bad across the board.
jobs came in super light, 22,000 added versus 75,000 expected.
most of the gains came from part-time jobs.
us lost 357 full-time jobs while gaining 597,000 part-time jobs last month.
and this is after a bunch of revisions.
you guys remember we talked about here a couple of times with these revisions.
and we'll show up some charts with long-term revisions.
july revised up slightly by 6k, 73,000 to 79. in june was revised down significantly.
remember that impacted the market by 27,000.
this makes june the first month with a net loss of jobs since july of 2021.
so there's an account on xcov letter and they did this revisions chart.
it's pretty crazy as you can see.
may and june revisions
were
in the six figures and they're constantly revising these down it seems.
all right.
free break had some internet connectivity issues apparently.
but shimoth, let's talk about the revisions here and the softness in the job market concerning.
did maybe the fed take too long to get towards cuts in september?
what what is what's your read on this and the endless revisions?
look, i think that i've said this yes last week, i think, right?
so i'll just say it again this week.
you can't run the most sophisticated
economy in the world if you have data that is completely unreliable in either direction.
and so
the problem with this jobs report is there are already two competing versions of the truth.
one group of people are trying to paint the jobs report as everything is working.
there's nothing to see here.
another group of people are saying, "oh, well, hold on.
there's a birth stats number where if you
extract that out the jobs numbers is actually negative.
i don't know
which one is actually better in terms of
where we want to be right now going into a rate cut cycle.
so my general commentary is the following.
the bls and their approach is incredibly brittle.
it doesn't work.
i think commerce has taken the first right step which is to start publishing
useful economic data into the blockchain.
i think we need to figure out a way and this is where congress
should get their act together
and pass an incentive or a requirement
for certain parts of the critical economic infrastructure of america
to report their data in an anonymized way into a broad set of blockchains.
and the reason is that you will have very astute and precise pricing oracles
help distill that information.
so if you're adp, if you're american express, if you're stripe,
there's an imperative now for you to contribute the information you have into a broad
collection
of information
so that we have an accurate
sense of what the hell is actually
going on.
because i can't react to this number because i don't know how it's going to change.
it could literally swing by 200,000 in either direction.
jason, this is a i think a really good point.
here's some research.
i had my put one of my researchers at launch on this.
here's 2021 and the initial reading first revision and we did this for the year sach.
so, as you can see in 2021, they missed it by 1.9 million
which was about 15%.
2022 they miraculously nailed it.
2023 they were off by 10%.
2024 it looks like they were off again by 10%.
all this is revising down by the way.
in the first half of this year.
let me just finish the chart.
first half of this year, initial reading 985,
first revision 732,
second revision 497. so they were off by 50% so far this year alone.
this chart is itself inaccurate.
the table is and and it's because it's coming from the same people that measured.
so you're asking the people that measured to grade themselves
and i suspect that the answer is actually much worse than all of this.
now, what is the implication of it?
the implication of it is if you take the most positive
view possible,
it's that the people that then control the levers of the economy
don't actually have accurate data.
so, they'll be hesitant to act until the data is overwhelming.
the most important lens of that will be the fed and what they do with rates.
and so, everybody's like, "oh, wow.
there's a 99% chance of a 25 basis point cut."
that may be wildly wildly wildly conservative in terms of the the total amount
that they need to be thinking about and how they should phase that in.
but how would i actually prove that to you?
i can point to a whole litany of private data,
but the problem is the federal actors use public data
and this data is not useful.
and i think that when you get private data into your hands, which i know that
other folks have, hedge funds, banks,
the white house, what they see is different
than what the fed sees.
so what i would tell you from this jobs report is it's going to start again
this clamor of what is your plan?
clapping is not a strategy.
so a 25 basis point cut to a $32 trillion economy is not a strategy.
and i
think that the reason they
don't know what to do exactly
is because they have extremely
faulty data.
again,
this is not i'm i'm not taking a position on this
or framing it as if i'm taking a position.
i'm just reporting the data here as they've reported it.
so i'm i'm just doing that here just to be clear here that i'm not endorsing
any side of this.
i'm an independent.
i'm a moderate.
i'm just giving you the data as it stands.
here's the fred chart just so we can zoom out and see unemployment since the 50s.
we're still at historic lows and there's a slight uptick 4.3%
which is the highest unemployment since 2021 but it's absurdly low historically.
so even we're looking historically sachs we're still at very low but do you have concerns
that the economy could be slowing and that we could have a jobs issue?
that i guess is the question that
is filling the airwaves on cnbc
and that everybody's talking about in group chats.
are we
maybe didn't make the fed cuts in time for what clearly is some amount of slowing?
now, we could argue over if they're getting the data right or not.
the fed says they look at all data, not just this data.
they say they look at the private data as well.
but what are your thoughts here, sachs?
well, we had 22,000 jobs added in august.
and yet, while the number of jobs went up, unemployment
rose, like you said, from 4.2
to 4.3%.
which is a little bit of a contradiction, but that happened because more people started looking
for jobs.
yeah.
but there are huge error bars around this data.
like jamal said, i mean, like you showed, there's roughly 50% revisions
to all of this data over time over the course of a year.
so, we don't really have great visibility in what's going on.
and that's why you see such huge disparities in how people are interpreting this data.
so if you want to look at some of the people who are pessimistic,
you've got coobe letter, but they're pessimistic about everything.
you've got moody's economist mark xandandy.
he says we're on the precipice of a recession
and he has a bunch of reasons why.
but then if you look at poly market, people on poly market
are strongly betting against a recession this year.
i think the number is at about 8%.
so, it appears that most people still feel like the economy is doing well.
and remember, we just had a 3.3%
gdp growth rate for q2. so, i i'd be surprised if if there's a recession.
i think there's a lot of factors against it.
i guess i would also note that if there's any weakness in the job numbers,
it's coming from foreignb born workers
more than native born workers.
around 2 million more americanborn workers have jobs in 2025 so far.
and i think meanwhile about a million foreignb born workers roughly have lost jobs.
so the net increase is about a million.
but what you're seeing is a repatriation in a way of jobs within the economy.
the other thing that's happening is a reprivatization of the economy.
so in august the federal government shed about 15,000 jobs
and there's been 100,000 federal jobs lost
over the course of the whole year.
so that makes the overall numbers look worse than they are.
but i a lot of us would argue that
having fewer
federal
workers
is a good thing for the economy.
so you've got those factors.
then you've got blue collar real wages are rising the second fastest in history.
you had 3.7% wage growth this year versus 2.7% average inflation.
so you have a net 1% wage growth during most of the biden presidency.
it was negative.
and then i would also point to
i think several factors which would make me optimistic about
the economy moving ahead.
you've had massive investment in the us by both private companies and foreign governments.
you know, according to these new trade deals, i think roughly $8 trillion of new investment.
you've got this ai boom you're seeing.
and that's going to land over the next year, right?
that hasn't actually been dumped in.
so we should see that in 2027, maybe late 2026. yeah.
yeah.
this is the outlook for 2026 and beyond.
i mean, this would be the bull case is number one,
$8 trillion
of of new investment
in the us economy
by private companies
and by foreign governments.
number two, the ai boom.
you've got this massive buildout of data centers and ai infrastructure underway.
and that includes energy and the manufacturing sectors are going to boom alongside tech.
number three, this has been the most affordable summer at the pump since 2021,
and low gas prices don't seem to be going anywhere anytime soon.
so, lowest gas prices since 2021.
number four, you have these huge new tax incentives for business expansion.
you've got the accelerated depreciation on equipment purchases, on r&d.
i think those are going to kick in once the big beautiful bill goes into effect.
and then the last thing i would say is that interest rate cuts are coming.
i would say that now in light of the latest jobs report,
pal should really cut 50 basis points.
i doubt he will in september 25. yeah, i doubt he will.
it's probably be 25 and then hopefully another 25.
but i think you can make the case that they should do 50 now and then
25 after that.
but regardless of what it is, i think that most people think interest rates are coming
and that's going to juice the economy and further improve our fiscal position.
so look for 26, i think there's a lot of bullish factors here.
all right, just
before we wrap here, google,
uh, as we know, was found liable in this antitrust case, but
the sanctions
seem to
not be as harsh as people thought they would be.
judge meta rejected the request that google have to spin off chrome, android,
and pointed out that google is having massive competition.
so we had four years of lena khan, you know, in these aggressive cases.
there were there were tactical things we talked about here like dark patterns,
etc. that we all agreed with.
i think there was consensus there, but this one we found a little confusing because
gosh, google's under so much pressure.
what are your thoughts on i thought this was excellent.
unpack it all.
essentially,
the crux of the ruling
was look, there are some restrictions that google has to live by.
don't get me wrong, but the most punitive remedies that were suggested were thrown out.
and the reason they were thrown out was because the judge very eloquently cited
competition in a fair and free and open market.
and that is incredibly refreshing because the real question is
would this judge have had the wherewithal
and the courage to actually be able to rule this way
a few years ago when there would have been an enormous amount of political pressure.
they
probably
would have found a way to to
run this
case in a in
a different
place
etc etc. but now what you saw was just
very simple logic
intervene.
and at the core of it was,
you know, when we started this lawsuit, things like openai and chat gpt didn't exist.
and when you fast forward, it's incredibly fastm moving.
we are reallocating hundreds of millions or billions of users intentions.
as a byproduct, we're reallocating tens of maybe hundreds of billions of dollars of revenue.
and so the judge said the most severe
remedies aren't necessary because the free market is doing its job.
yes.
so i i just think that's incredibly refreshing because we forget
that if the market is left to deal with these issues on its own,
they do a very good job of cleaning things up.
and it's because as you said earlier, jason, consumers want creative destruction.
they want the next best thing.
they want to be better prices better services.
it's it happens by the free market.
they're willing they're willing to reward better companies and better products.
so i think the the great news for google is that this takes an enormous
risk off the table.
and now i think that they probably have even more
ambition
and energy
to just go for it and try to compete
because
they're not going to be worried
about everybody on the outside
and probably
some percentage of employees on the inside
who are always trying to slow things down.
yeah.
and and
it out correctly and i'll let you comment on this sachs
is that they did get some tactical,
you know, penalties here.
uh, and they make sense doing
deals that are exclusive when you are a monopoly player, like getting
firefox and apple to only do an exclusive deal with you.
they're not going to be allowed to do that.
and man, that would change the game on the field if somebody like duck.go
or bing or a new entrant, proplexity,
whoever who's doing search would be able to say to apple,
we will outbid google for 10% of the searches.
we'd like to buy 5% of the searches
from the
safari
browser
going to firefox
and saying, "hey, we'd like to
one
up and we'd
like some percentage
of that." so, that seemed like a good part of the ruling.
your thoughts overall about this?
so on this podcast,
i think it was two or three years ago when this case first came up.
i think i took the position that google street broken up into two or three companies
because i thought it was this invulnerable
monopoly and i don't think monopolies are great for the sar ecosystem.
and what i mean by that is they had the
google search monopoly and that youtube
business which is basically a monopoly and so forth and so on.
so, i i
was in favor of breaking
this up, but i've
got to admit
i
was wrong
about
that
for
the reasons that the judge said, which is
google for the first time in a long while, is existentially threatened
by what's happened with ai.
i mean, their cash cow, the core of their business is search,
and people are starting to substitute in droves
from traditional
google search, which they own, or keyword search, where they have this monopoly or dominant share
to ai.
and if you look at ai revenue,
i think something like 90% of it is going to
open ai.
i mean, they have the dominant position among consumers for now for now.
and there's,
let's say, five major ai
companies that are hot on their heels and very competitive
and performing equally if not better on performance benchmarks.
so the point is just i think everyone can now see
that the search business
is
either going away or transforming into something else
which is it's basically merging with the it's called ai chatbot
business.
it's an answers business now.
it's not a like give me links.
it's just give me the damn answer, right?
and we've been talking about this for a while where it's so obvious that
having ai just give you the answer is better than 20 blue links.
especially as the quality improves and it gets better
at synthesizing those 20 blue links into the exact right answer
and the speed improves.
one of the things that google's really good at is just fast responses.
you they've always shown you in milliseconds
how long it takes to give you the search result.
and obviously
if you're looking for something quick and an ai chatbot's
going to take 30 seconds, you're going to go with google.
but that's going to get better, too.
so i think google is kind of in the fight of its life right now.
and i think this is why sergey's come back.
you know, we saw him at the
at the dinner at the white house yesterday
and he said he's
very involved
in
google
deep mind.
he's going to the office all the time.
yeah.
right.
and so you're seeing that founder
involvement
again because they know that they've got a real existential threat to their business.
and this is the argument that
opponents
of strong antitrust enforcement have always made,
which is that the free market will eventually break up, even the strongest monopolies,
if you just give it the chance to do it.
and that's what appears to be in motion right now.
by the way, i'm not saying that google's going to get destroyed.
i'm not saying it's going away.
i'm just saying that they have to pivot here in a big way.
their business is being disrupted and they suddenly have competition
i think in their core business like they've never had before.
so i do think that we don't need to bring the hammer down
on them in the same way that maybe we did a few years ago.
i still would not let them pursue anti-competitive
tactics against say applications in the android store where they basically have a duopoly.
so i'm not saying i would let them do anything
but i certainly
agree with this judge that we don't need to break up that company right now.
yeah.
and there's there's rules in the field that need to be adjudicated.
so having
a very simple approach
with the ftc
of saying, "hey, these exclusive
deals when you have 90%
market share, that's not allowable.
but you can compete and you can fight versus the five new entrance and
have at it and and give consumers a better product at a cheaper price."
that's really the goal of the ftc
is to to have some basic rules of the field.
we saw it in the media business as well.
we spend a decade or two trying to
fight the consolidation
of media companies and then netflix
has trounced them all and youtube as well in terms of viewership.
netflix and youtube are crushing
the cable
monopolies
that we spend all this time trying to regulate.
all right everybody, there's your episode.
we have to get back to work and get to los angeles for the amazing
fourth edition of the allin
summit.
it's going to be amazing
and all the great content including some surprise speakers
that'll be released over the next week or two after the event.
so, you're going to get massive amounts of content.
make sure you go to the youtube channel, subscribe,
and click that bell so you get alerts.
go to allin.com, put your email in.
we'll invite you to more events.
chamath and i might be doing something in the poker space.
that could be a lot of fun.
my guy tk and i, we might be doing a little back gammon tournament.
all right, everybody.
thanks for tuning in to the all-in podcast.
we're finished.
bye-bye, besties.
love you.
love you guys.
let your winners ride.
[music] we open sourced it to the fans and they've just gone crazy with it.
love you.
[music]
besties are gone.
that is my dog taking a notice in your driveway.
oh man, my dasher will meet.
we should all just get a room and just have like one big huge
orgy
cuz they're all just useless.
it's like this like sexual tension that they just need to release somehow.
wet your feet.
we need to get merch.
[music]
i'm going all in.