the following is a conversation with jeff hawkins a neuroscientist seeking to understand the structure function
and origin of intelligence in the human brain
he previously wrote the seminal book on the subject titled on intelligence
and recently a new book called a thousand brains
which presents a new theory of intelligence
that richard dawkins for example has been raving about calling the book quote brilliant
and exhilarating
i can't read those two words
and not think of him saying it in his british accent
quick mention of our sponsors codecademy
bio optimizers
expressvpn a-sleep
and blinkist check them out in the description to support this podcast
as a side note let me say that one small
but powerful idea that jeff hawkins mentions in his new book
is that if human civilization were to destroy itself all of knowledge
all our creations will go with us
he proposes that we should think about
how to save that knowledge in a way that long outlives us whether that's on earth
in orbit around earth
or in deep space
and then to send messages that advertise this backup of human knowledge to other intelligent alien civilizations
the main message of this advertisement is not that we are here
but that we were once here
this little difference
somehow was deeply humbling to me that we may with some non-zero likelihood destroy ourselves
and that an alien civilization thousands
or millions of years from now may come across this knowledge store
and they would only with some low probability
even notice it not to mention be able to interpret it
and the deeper question here for me is what information in all of human knowledge is even essential
does wikipedia capture it
or not at all this thought experiment forces me to wonder
what are the things we've accomplished
and are hoping to still accomplish that will outlive us
is it things like complex buildings bridges cars rockets is it ideas like science physics
and mathematics is it music
and art is it computers computational systems
or even artificial intelligence systems
i personally can't imagine that aliens wouldn't already have all of these things
in fact much more
and much better to me the only unique thing we may have is consciousness itself
and the actual subjective experience of suffering of happiness of hatred of love
if we can record these experiences in the highest resolution directly from the human brain
such that aliens will be able to replay them
that is what we should store
and send as a message
not wikipedia
but the extremes of conscious experiences
the most important of which of course is love
this is the lex friedman podcast
and here is my conversation with jeff hawkins
we previously
talked over two years ago
do you think there's still neurons in your brain that remember that conversation
that remember me
and got excited
like there's a lex neuron in your brain that just like finally has a purpose
i do remember our conversation
or i have some memories of it
and i formed additional memories of you in the meantime
um i wouldn't say there's a neuron
or a neurons in my brain that know you there are synapses in my brain that have formed
that reflect my knowledge of you
and the model i have of you in the world
and whether
the exact same synapses were formed
two years ago it's hard to say because these things
come and go all the time
but we know from
one thing to know about brains is that
when you think of things you often erase the memory
and rewrite it again
so
yes but i have a memory of you and i have that's instantiated in synapses
there's a simpler way to think about it like so you have
we have a model of the world in your head
and that model is continually being updated
i updated this morning you offered me this water you said it was from the refrigerator
i remember these things
and so we and so the model includes
where we live the places we know the words the objects in the world it's a monstrous model
and it's constantly being updated
and people are just part of that model
so we're animals
or other physical objects
so our events we've done
so
um it's there's no special in my mind special place for the memories of humans
i mean obviously
i know
you know i know a lot about my wife
um
but
and friends and so on but it's not like a special place for humans over here
but we model everything
and we model other people's behaviors too so if i said you're a
copy of your mind in my mind it's just because i know how humans i've learned
how humans behave
and
um
and i've learned some things about you
and that's part of my world model
well i just also mean the collective intelligence of the human species
i wonder if there's something
fundamental to the brain that enables that
so modeling other humans with their ideas
you're actually jumping into a lot of big topics like collective intelligence is a separate topic
that a lot of people like to talk about we can talk about that
but
um
and so that's interesting like you know we're not just individuals we live in society
and so on
but from our research point of view
and so again let's just talk we study the neocortex
it's a sheet of neural tissue it's about 75 of your brain
it runs on this very repetitive algorithm it's a very repetitive circuit
and
so you can apply that algorithm to lots of different problems
but it's all underneath it's the same thing we're just building this model
so from our point of view
we wouldn't look for these special circuit someplace
buried in your brain that might be related to other
you know understanding of the humans it's more like
you know how do we build a model of anything
how do we understand
anything in the world and humans are just another part of the things we understand
so there's nothing
there's nothing to the brain that knows the emergent phenomena of collecting the intelligence
well i certainly know about that i've heard the terms i've read
no but that's right right well okay right as an idea
well i think we have language
which is is sort of built into our brains
and that's a key part of collective intelligence
so there are some you know prior assumptions about
the world we're going to live in when we're born
we're not just a blank slate
um
and so you know did we evolve to take advantage of those situations
yes
but again we study only part of the brain the neocortex
there's other parts of the brain are very much involved in societal interactions
and human emotions
and
um
and how we interact
and even societal
um
issues about you know
how we are how we interact with other people when we support them when we're greedy
and things like that
i mean certainly the brain is a great place
where to study intelligence i wonder if it's the fundamental
atom of intelligence well i would say it's it's it's absolutely an essential component
even if you believe in collective intelligence as
um
hey that's where it's all happening that's what we need to study
which i don't believe that by the way i think it's really important
but i don't think that is the thing
um
but even if you do believe that then you have to understand
how the brain works in doing that
um it's you know it's more like we are intelligent
and we are intelligent individuals
and together we are much more magnified
our intelligence we can do things that we couldn't do individually
but even as individuals we're pretty damn smart
and we can model things
and understand the world and interact with it
so
um to me if you're going to start some place
you need to start with the brain
then you could say well how do brains interact with each other
and
what is the nature of language
how do we
share models that i've learned
something about the world
how do i share it with you
which is really what
you know sort of communal intelligence is i know something you know something
we've had different experiences in the world i've
learned something about brains
maybe i can impart that to you you've learned something about
you know whatever physics
and you can part that to me
but it also comes down to even just the epistemological question of well what is knowledge
and how do you represent it in the brain right
and it's not that's where it's going to reside right or in our writings it's obvious that
human collaboration human interaction is
how we build societies right
but some of the things you talk about
and work on
some of those elements of what makes up an intelligent entity is there with a single person
oh absolutely
i mean it'd be we can't deny that the brain is the core
element here in in at least i can't i think it's obvious
the brain is the core element in all theories of intelligence
it's where knowledge is represented it's where knowledge is created
we interact we share we build upon each other's work
but without a brain you'd have nothing you know there would be no intelligence without brains
and so
um
so that's where we start
i got into this field because i just was curious
as to who i am you know how
you know how do i think what's going on in my head when i'm
what i'm thinking
what does it mean to know something
you know i can ask what it means for me to know something independent
of how i learned it from you
or from someone else or from society
so what does it mean for me to know that i have a model
of you in my head what does it mean to know i know what this microphone
does and how it works physically even though i can't see it right now
how do i know that
what does it mean
how the neurons do that at the fundamental level of neurons
and synapses
and so on those are really fascinating questions
and i'm happy to be just happy to understand those if i could
so in your um in your new book
you talk about our brain our mind as being made up of many brains
so the book is called the thousand brains
a thousand brain theory of intelligence
what is the key idea of this book the book has three sections
and it has sort of maybe three big ideas
so the first section is all about what we've learned about the neurocortex
and that's the thousand brains theory
just did we complete the picture the second section is all about ai
and the third section is about the future of humanity
so the thousand brains theory
the the big idea there if i had to summarize into one big idea
is that we think of the the brain the neocortex is learning this model of the world
but what we learned is actually there's tens of thousands of independent modeling systems going on
and so each
what we call a column in the cortex is about 150
000 of them is a complete modeling system
so it's a collective intelligence in your head in some sense
so the thousand brains theory says well
where do i have knowledge about you know this coffee cup
where is the model of this cell phone
it's not in one place it's in thousands of separate models that are complementary
and they communicate with each other through voting
so this idea that we have we feel like we're one person
you know that's our experience we can explain that
but reality there's lots of these like almost like little brands like
but they're they're sophisticated modeling systems about 150
000 of them in each of the human brain
and that's a totally different way of thinking about
how the neural cortex is structured than
we or anyone else thought of even just five years ago
so you mentioned you started
this journey
and just looking in the mirror trying to understand who you are
so if you have many brains
who are you then
so
it's interesting we have a singular perception right
you know we think oh i'm just here i'm looking at you
but it's it's composed of all these things like there's sounds
and there's
and there's this vision
and there's touch
and all kinds of inputs
yeah we have the singular perception
and what the thousand brain theory says we have these models
that are visual models
we have a lot of models of auditory
models models of toxin models
and so on
but they vote
and so
um they send in the cortex
you can think about these
columns as that like little grains of rice 150
000 stacked next to each other
and each one is its own little modeling system
but they have these long-range connections that go between them
and we call those voting connections
or voting neurons
um
and
so the different columns
try to reach the consensus
like what am i looking at okay you know each one has some ambiguity
but they come to a consensus
oh there's a water bottle i'm looking at
um we are only consciously
able to perceive the voting
we're not able to perceive anything that goes on under the hood
so the voting is what we're
we're aware of the results
of the vote yeah the velocity well it's it's you can imagine it this way
we were just talking about eye movements a moment ago
so as i'm looking at something my eyes are moving about three times a second
and with each movement a completely
new input is coming into the brain it's not repetitive
it's not shifting it around it's completely new
i'm totally unaware of it i can't perceive it
but yet if i looked at the neurons
in your brain they're going on and off i don't know
but the voting neurons are not the voting neurons are saying you know we all agree
even though i'm looking at different parts of this is a water bottle right now
and that's not changing
and it's in some position
and
and pose relative to me
so i have this perception
of the water bottle about two feet away from me at a certain pose to me
um
that is not changing that's the only
part i'm aware of i can't
be aware of the fact that the inputs
from the eyes are moving
and changing
and all this others happening
so these long range connections
are the part we can be conscious of the individual activity in each column is doesn't go anywhere else
it doesn't get shared
anywhere else it doesn't
there's no way to extract it
and talk about it
or extract it and even remember it to say oh
yes i can recall that
um
so
but these long-range connections are the things that are accessible to language
and to our you know it's like the hippocampus
or our memories you know our short-term memory systems
and so on
so we're not aware of 95
or maybe it's even 98 of what's going on in your brain
we're only aware of this sort of stable somewhat stable
voting outcome of all these things that are going on underneath the hood
so
what would you say is the basic element in the thousand brains theory of intelligence of intelligence
like what's the atom of intelligence when you think about it is it the individual brains
and then what is a brain well let's let's
can we just talk about what intelligence is first
and then
and then we can talk about the elements are
so in my in my book intelligence is the ability to learn a model of the world
so to build internal to your head
a model that represents the structure of everything
you know to know what this is a table
and that's a coffee cup and this is a gooseneck lamp and all this to know these things
i have to have a model
in my head i just don't look at them and go what is that
i already have internal representations of these things in my head
and i had to learn them i wasn't born of any of that knowledge
you were
you know we have some lights in the room here
i you know that's
not part of my evolutionary
heritage right it's not in my genes
so
um
we have this incredible
model and the model includes
not only what things look like and feel like but where they are relative
to each other and how they behave
i've never picked up this water bottle before
but i know that if i took my hand
on that blue thing and i turn it it'll
probably make a funny little sound
as the little plastic things detach
and then it'll rotate
and it'll look a certain way it'll come off
how do i know that right because i have this model in my head
so the essence of intelligence as our ability to learn a model
and the more sophisticated our model is the smarter we are not that there is a single intelligence
because
you can know about
you know a lot about things that i don't know and i know about things you don't know
and we can both be very smart
but we both learn the model of the world through interacting with it
so that is the essence of intelligence then we can ask ourselves
what are the mechanisms in the brain that allow us to do that
and what are the mechanisms of learning not just the neural mechanisms
what is the general process
but how we learn a model
so that was a big insight for us it's like what are the
what is the actual things that
how do you learn this stuff it turns out you have to learn it through movement
um you can't learn it just by
that's how we learn we learn through movement we learn
um so
you build up this model by observing things and touching
them and moving them and walking
around the world and so on so either you move or the thing moves somehow
yeah you obviously
can learn things just by reading a book something
like that but think about if i were to say oh
here's a new house
yeah i want you to learn you know
what do you do you have to walk
you have to walk from room to the room you have to open the doors
look around see what's on the left what's on the right
as you do this you're building a model in your head it's just
that's what you're doing
you can't just sit there and say i'm going gonna grock the house no
you know or you could
you don't even want to sit there and read some description of it right
yeah
you literally physically interactive
the same with like a smartphone
if i want to
learn a new app i touch it and i move things around
i see what happens when i when i
do things with it so that's the basic
way we learn in the world and by the way when you say model you mean something
that can be used for prediction in the future it's it's used for prediction
and for behavior
and planning
right um
and does a pretty good job in doing so
yeah
here's the way to think about the model
a lot of people get hung up on this so
um
you can imagine an architect making a model of a house
right so there's a physical model that's small
and why do they do that well we do that because you can imagine
what it would look like from different angles
you could say okay
look at them here look in there and you can also say well
how
how far to get from from the garage to the
to the swimming pool or something like that right you can imagine
looking at this you can say what would be the view from this location
so we built these physical models to let you imagine the future
and imagine that behaviors
now we can take that same model
and put it in a computer
so we now today they'll build models of houses
and a computer
and they
and they do that using a set of
um
we'll come back to this term in a moment reference frames but eventually
you assign a reference frame for the house
and you assign different things for the house in different locations
and then the computer can generate an image
and say okay this is what it looks like in this direction
the brain is doing something remarkably
similar to this surprising
um it's using reference frames it's building these it's similar to a model in a computer
which has the same benefits of building a physical
model it allows me to say what would this thing
look like if it was in this orientation
what would likely happen if i push this button i've never pushed this button before
or
how would i accomplish something i want to i want to
um
convey a new idea i've learned
how would i do that i can imagine in my head well i could talk about it
i could write a book
i could do some podcasts
i could
um you know maybe tell my neighbor you know
and i can imagine
the outcomes of all these things before i do any of them
that's what the model lets you do it let's just plan the future
and imagine the consequences of our actions prediction
you asked about prediction
prediction is not the goal of the model prediction is an inherent property of it
and it's how the model corrects itself
so prediction is fundamental to intelligence it's fundamental to building a model
and the model's intelligent
and let me go back and be very precise about this prediction
you can think of prediction
two ways one is like
hey what would happen if i did this that's the type of prediction
um that's a key part of intelligence
but using predictions like oh what's this this is
this water bottle gonna feel like when i pick it up you know
and that doesn't seem very intelligent
but the way to think one way to think about intelligence prediction is
it's a way for us to learn
where our model is wrong
so if i picked up this water bottle
and it felt hot i'd be very surprised
or if i picked up was very light it would be very i'd be surprised
or if i turned this top
and it didn't i had to turn the other way i'd be surprised
and so almost
might have a prediction like okay i'm gonna do it i'll drink some water
i'm okay okay do this there it is i feel opening right
what
if i had to turn it the other way or what if it it split in two
then i say oh my gosh i i misunderstood
this i didn't have the right model of this thing my attention
would be drawn to i'll be looking at it going well how
the hell did that happen
you know why did it open up that way
and i would update my model
by doing it just by looking
at it and playing around with that update
and say this is a new type of water bottle
but you
so you're talking about sort of complicated things like a water bottle
but this also applies for just basic vision just like seeing things
it's almost like a precondition of just perceiving the world is predicting
it's just everything that you see is first passed through your prediction everything you see
and feel
in fact this this is the insight i had back in the late 80s
and excuse me early 80s
and
um another people reach the same idea is that every sensory input you get not just vision
but touch
and hearing you have an expectation about it
and
um a prediction sometimes you can pick very accurately sometimes you can't i can't predict
what next word is going to come out of your mouth
but as you start talking about better and better predictions
and if you talk about some topics i'd be very surprised
so i have this sort of background prediction that's going on all the time
for all my senses
again the way i think about that
is this is how we learn it's it's more about how we learn
it's the test of our understanding our predictions are our test
did is this really a water bottle if it is i shouldn't see
you know a little finger sticking out the side
and if i saw a little finger
stick and i was like
what the hell is going on
you know that's not normal
um
i mean that's fascinating that just let me linger on this
for a second i it really honestly feels that prediction is fundamental
to everything to the way our mind operates to intelligence
so like
it's just a different way to see intelligence
which is like everything starts at prediction
and prediction requires a model
you can't predict something unless you have a model of it right
but the action is prediction it's like the the thing the model does is prediction
and
but it also
yeah
and you but you can then extend it to things like
what would happen if i took this today i went and did this
what would be like that
or
how you can extend predictions like oh i want to get a promotion at work
um
what action should i take
and you can say if i did this i predict
what might happen if i
spoke to someone i predict what
might happen so it's not just low level predictions
yeah it's all prediction it's all predictions like this black box
so you can ask basically any question
low level or highlight so we start off with that observation
it's all it's like this non-stop prediction
and i write about this in the book about
and then we ask
how do neurons actually make predictions
physically like what does the neuron do when it makes a prediction
and
um
what the neural tissue does when it makes predictions
and then we ask what are the mechanisms
by how we build a model that allows you to make prediction
so we started with prediction as sort of the fundamental
research agenda if in some sense like
and say well we understand
how the brain makes predictions we'll understand
how it builds these models
and how it learns
and that's core of intelligence
so it was like it was the key that got us in the door
to say that is our research agenda understand predictions
so in this whole process
where does intelligence originate
would you say
so it
if we look at things that are much less intelligent to humans
and you start to build up a human the process of evolution
where is this magic thing that has a prediction model
or a model that's able to predict
that starts to look a lot more like intelligence is there a place where
richard dawkins wrote an introduction to your to your book an excellent introduction
i mean it puts a lot of things into context
and it's funny just looking at parallels for your book
and darwin's origin of species
so darwin wrote about the origin of species
so
what is the origin of intelligence
well we have a theory about it and it's just that it's a theory
theory goes as follows
as soon as living things started to move
they're not just floating in sea they're not just
a plant you know grounded some place as soon as they started the move
there was an advantage to moving intelligently to moving in certain ways
and there's some very simple things you can do you know bacteria
or single cell organisms can move towards a source of gradient of food
or something like that
but an animal that might know where it is
and know where it's been
and how to get back to that place or an animal
that might say oh
there was a source of food someplace
how do i get to it or there was a danger
how do i get to there was a mate
how do i get to them
um
there was a big evolution
advantage to that so early on there was a pressure to start understanding
your environment like where am i
and
where have i been
and what happened in those different places
so we still have this neural mechanism in our brains
um it's in in the in the mammals it's in the hippocampus
and internal cortex these are older parts of the brain
um
and these are very well studied
um we build a map of the of our environment
so these neurons in these parts of the brain know where i am in this room
and
where the door was
and things like that
so a lot of other mammals have this all mammals have this right and
almost any any animal that knows
where it is
and get around must have some mapping system
must have some way of saying i've learned
a map of my environment
i have hummingbirds in my backyard
and they
and they go the same places all the time they have to they must know
where they are they just
know where they are when they're
they're not just randomly
flying around they know
they know particular flowers
they come back to
so we all have this
and it turns out it's very tricky to get neurons to do this
to build a map of an environment it's just
and so we now know there's this these famous studies that's still very active about place cells
and grid cells
and these other types of cells in the older parts of the brain
and how they build these maps
of the world it's really clever it's obviously been under a lot of evolutionary
pressure over a long period of time to get good at this
so animals not know where they are
what we think has happened
and there's a lot of evidence to digest this is that that mechanism
we learn to map like a space
is was repackaged
the same type of neurons was repackaged into a more compact form
and that became the cortical column
and it was it was in some sense genericized
if that's a word it was turned into a very specific thing about learning
maps of environments to learning maps of anything
learning a model of anything not just your space
but coffee cups and so on
and it got sort of repackaged
into a more compact version a more universal version
and then replicate it
so the reason we're so flexible is we have a very generic
version of this mapping algorithm
and we have 150
000 copies of it sounds a lot like the progress of deep learning
how so so take neural networks that seem to work well for a specific task
compress them
and multiply it by a lot
and then you just stack them on top of it it's like the story of transformers
and yeah
but interesting
networks they end up you're replicating an element
but you still need the entire network to do anything right here
what what's going on each individual element is a complete learning system
this is why i can take a human brain cut it in half
and it still works
it's it's pretty amazing it's fundamentally distributed it's fundamentally distributed complete modeling systems
so
but that's that's our story we like to tell
i i i would guess it's
it's likely largely right
um
but you know it's there's a lot of evidence supporting that story this evolutionary story
the thing which brought me to this idea is that the human brain
got big very quickly
so that that
led to the proposal
a long time ago that well there's this common element just
instead of creating new things
it just replicated something
we also are extremely flexible we can learn things that we had no history about right
and
so that tells it that the learning algorithm is very generic it's very kind of universal
because it's it doesn't assume any prior knowledge about what it's learning
and
so you combine those things together
and you say okay well how did that come about
where did that universal
algorithm come from it had to come from something that wasn't universal
it came from something that was more specific
and
so anyway this led to our hypothesis that you would find grid cells
and place cell equivalents in the neocortex
and when we first published our first papers on this theory
we didn't know of evidence
for that it turns out there was some but we didn't know about it
and since then
um so then we became aware of evidence for grid cells in parts of the neural cortex
and then
now there's been new evidence coming out there's some
interesting papers that came out just january of this year
so our one of our predictions was if this evolutionary hypothesis
is correct we would see grid cell place cell equivalents cells that work like them
through every column in the near cortex
and that's starting to be seen
what does it mean that why is it important that they're present
because it tells us well we're asking about the evolutionary origin of intelligence right
so our theory is that these columns in the cortex are working on the same principles
they're modeling systems
and it's hard to imagine
how neurons do this and so we said
hey
it's really hard to imagine how neurons could
learn these models of things
we can talk about the details of that if you want
but let's
um
but there's this other part of the brain we know that learns models of environments
so could that
mechanism to learn to model this room be used to learn a model the water bottle
is it the same mechanism
so we said it's much more likely the brain is using the same mechanism
which case it would have these equivalent cell types
so it's basically the whole theory is built on the idea that
um these columns have reference frames
and they're learning these models
and these these grid cells create these reference frames
so it's it's basically the major in some sense the major predictive
part of this theory
is that we will find these equivalent mechanisms in each column in the near cortex
which tells us that's that that that's
what they're doing they're learning these sensory motor models of the world
so just we're pretty confident that would happen
but now we're seeing the evidence
so the evolutionary process nature does a lot of copy
and paste
and see what happens
yeah
yeah there's no direction to it but
but
um it just found out like hey if i took this these elements
and
and made more of them what happens
and let's hook them up to the eyes and let's look up the ears
and
um and that seems to work pretty well
yeah like for us again just to take a quick step back to our conversation of collective intelligence
do you sometimes
see that as just another
copy
and paste aspect is copying pasting these brains
and humans
and making a lot of them
and then creating
social structures that then almost operates as a single brain
i wouldn't have said it but you said it sounded pretty good
so to you the brain is fundamental is is like is its own thing right
i mean our goal is to understand
how the neural cortex works we can argue
how essential that is to understand a human brain
because it's not the entire human brain you can argue
how essential that is to understanding human intelligence you can argue how essential it is to
um to you know a sort of communal intelligence
um i i'm not
i didn't our goal was to understand the neocortex
yeah so what is the neural cortex
and where does it fit in
um the various
aspects of what the brain does like how important is it to you well obviously
again we i mentioned again in the beginning it's it's it's about 70 to 75
of the volume of a human brain
so it's you know it dominates our brain in terms of size
not in terms of number of neurons
but in terms of size
size isn't everything jeff
i know
but it's it's nothing it's nothing it's not that we know that all high-level vision hearing
and touch happens in the air context we know that all language occurs
and is understood in the neurocortex
whether that's spoken language written language sign language with language of mathematics language of physics
music math you know we know that all high-level planning
and thinking occurs in the new york cortex
if i were to say you know what part of your brain designed a computer
and understands programming
and and creates music it's all the neural cortex
so then that's kind of undeniable fact if
but then there's other parts of our brain are important too right our emotional states
our body regulating our body
um
so the way i like to look at it is you know could you can you
understand the neocortex about the rest of the brain
and some people say you can't
and i think absolutely you can
it's not that they're not interacting
but you can understand them can you understand the neocortex without understanding the emotions of fear
yes you can you can understand
how the system works it's just a modeling system
i make the analogy in the book that it's it's like a map of the world
and
how that map is used depends on who's using it
so how our map of our world in our neocortex
how we
how we manifest as a human
depends on the rest of our brain what are our motivations
you know what are my desires am i a nice guy or not a nice guy
am i a cheater
or a you know or not a cheater
um you know
how important
different things are in my life
so
um
but the new projects can be understood on its own
and
and i say that as a neuroscientist
i know there's all these interactions
and i want to
say i don't know them and we don't think about them but from a layperson's
point of view you can say it's a modeling system
i don't tend to think too much about the communal aspect of intelligence
which you brought a number of times already
um
so that's not really been my concern i just wonder if there's a continuum
from the origin of the universe like
this com pockets of complexities that form
yeah living organisms i wonder if if we're just
if you look at humans we feel like we're at the top
but i wonder if there's like just
where everybody probably every living type pocket of complexity
is probably thinks they're the pardon the french they're the
yeah they're they're they're at the top of the parent well if they're thinking
um well then then what is thinking
what the all right in this sense the whole point is in their
sense of the world they
their sense is that they're at the top of it i think
what is it turtle
but you're you're you're bringing up you know the the problems of complexity
and complexity theory are you know it's a huge interesting problem in science
um
and you know i think we've made surprisingly
little progress in understanding complex systems right in general
um
and
so
you know the santa fe institute
was founded to to study this and and even the scientists
there will say it's really hard we haven't
really been able to figure out exactly you know
that science isn't really congealed
yet we're still trying to figure out the basic elements of that science
what
you know where does complexity come from
and what is it and how you define it whether it's dna creating bodies
or phenotypes
or if it's
individuals creating societies
or ants
and you know markets
and so on it's it's a very complex thing i'm not a complexity theorist person right
um
and i i think they ask well the brain itself is a complex system
so can we understand that
um i think we've made a lot of progress understanding
how the brain works
so
but i haven't
brought it out to like oh well where are we on the complexity spectrum
you know it's like
um that's a great question
i'd prefer for that answer to be we're not special
it seems like if we're honest
most likely we're not special
so if there is a spectrum
we're probably not in some kind of significant place
there's one thing we could say that we are special
and and again only here on earth
i'm not saying i'm bad is that if we think about knowledge
what we know
um we clearly
human brains have
um the only brains
that have a certain types of knowledge
we're the only brains on
on this earth to understand
what the earth is
how old it is that the universe is a picture as a whole the only organisms understand dna
and the origins of you know of species
no other species on on this planet has that knowledge
so if we think about
i like to think about
you know one of the endeavors of humanity is to understand the universe
as much as we can
um
i think our species is further along in that undeniably
um whether our theories are right or wrong we can debate
but at least we have theories you know we we know that
what the sun is and how it's fusion is and how
what black holes are and you know we know general theory relativity
and no other animal has any of this knowledge
so in that sense that we're special are we special in terms of the the hierarchy of complexity
in in the universe probably not
can we look at a neuron
yeah you say that prediction happens in the neuron
what does that mean
so neuron traditionally seen as the basic element of the the brain
so we i mentioned this earlier that prediction was our research agenda
yeah we said okay
um
how does the brain make a prediction like i i'm about to grab this water bottle
and my brain is predicting
what i'm going to feel
um
on all my parts of my fingers
if i felt something really odd on any part here i notice it
so my brain is predicting
what it's going to feel as i grab this thing
so what is that how does that manifest
itself in neural tissue right we got brains made of neurons
and there's chemicals
and there's neurons
and there's spikes
and the connect you know
where
where is the prediction going on
and one argument could be that well when i'm predicting something
um a neuron must be firing in advance it's like okay this neuron represents
what you're going to feel and it's firing it's sending a spike
and certainly that happens to some extent
but our predictions are so ubiquitous
that we're making
so many of them which we're totally unaware of just the vast majority
we have no idea that you're doing this
um
that it
wasn't really we were trying to figure how could this be where where is these
where are these happening right
and i won't walk you through the whole story unless you insist upon it but
we came to the realization
that
most of your predictions are occurring inside individual
neurons especially these the most common are in the pyramidal cells
and there are there's a property of neurons
we everyone knows or most people know that a neuron is a cell
and it has this spike called an action potential
and it sends information
but we now know that there's these spikes internal to the neuron they're called dendritic spikes
they travel along the branches of the neuron
and they don't leave the neuron they're just internal only
there's far more dendritic spikes than there are action potentials
far more they're happening all the time
and
what we came to understand that those dendritic
spikes the ones that are occurring are actually a form of prediction
they're telling the neuron the neuron is saying i expect that i might become active shortly
and that internal
so the internal spike is a way of saying
you're going to you might be generating external spikes soon
i predicted you're going to become active
and
and we we've we've we wrote a paper in 2016
which explained
and
how this manifests itself in neural tissue
how it is that this all works together
but the vast ma we think it's there's a lot of evidence supporting it
um
so we
that's where we think that most of these predictions are internal
that's why you can't
be per their internal
neuron you can't perceive them
from understanding the the prediction mechanism of a single neuron
do you think there's deep insights to be gained about the prediction capabilities
of the mini brains within the bigger brain
and the brain oh yeah yeah yeah
so having a prediction side of the individual neuron is not that useful you know what
so what
um the way it manifests itself in neural tissue is that
when a neuron a neuron emits these spikes or a very singular type event
if a neuron is predicting that it's going to be active it makes it spike very
a little bit sooner just a few milliseconds
sooner than it would have otherwise it's like
i give the analogy in the book there's like a sprinter
on a on a starting
blocks in a race
and if someone says get ready set you get up and you're ready to go
and then when your race starts you get a little bit earlier start
so that it's that that ready set is like the prediction
and the neuron's like ready to go quicker
and
what happens is when you have a whole bunch of neurons together
and they're all getting these inputs
the ones that are in the predictive state the ones that are anticipating to become active
if they do become active they they happen sooner they disable
everything else and it leads to different representations in the brain
so you have to
it's not isolated just to the neuron the prediction occurs within the neuron
but the network behavior changes
so
what happens under different predictions different inputs have different representations
so how i
what i predict
um it's going to be different under different contexts you know
what my input will be is different under different context
so this is this is a key level theory
how this works
so the theory of the thousand brains
if you were to count the number of brains
how would you do it the thousand main theory says that basically every cortical column
in the in your neurocortex is a complete modeling system
and that when i ask
where do i have a model of something like a coffee cup
it's not in one of those models it's in thousands of those models
there's thousands of models of coffee cups that's what the thousand brains there's a voting mechanism
then there's a voting mechanism
which leads
which is the thing you're
which you're conscious of which leads to your singular perception
um that's why you perceive something
so that's the thousand brains theory the details
how we got to that theory
um are complicated
it wasn't you just thought of it one day
and one of those details is we had to ask
how does a a model make predictions
and we've talked about just these predictive neurons
that's part of this theory it's like saying oh it's a detail
but it was like a crack in the doors
like how are we going to figure out how these neurons
build do this you know what is going on here
so we just looked at prediction as like well we know that's ubiquitous
we know that every part of the cortex is making predictions
therefore whatever the predictive system is it's going to be everywhere
we know there's a gazillion predictions happening at once
so let's see if we can start teasing apart you know ask questions about
you know how could neurons be making these predictions
and that sort of built up to now what we have the thousand brains theory
which is complex you know it's just some i can state it simply
but we just didn't think of it we had to get there step by step very
it took years to get there
and where does reference frames fit in
so
yeah
okay
so again a reference frame i mentioned
um earlier about the you know a model of a house
and i said if you're going to build a model of a house in a computer
they have a reference frame and you can then reference them like cartesian
coordinates like x y and z axes
so i can say oh i'm going to design a house
i can say well the the front door is at this location xyz
and the roof is at this location xyz
and so on that's a type of reference frame
so it turns out for you to make a prediction
and then i walk you through the thought experiment in the book where i was predicting
what my finger was going to feel when i touched the coffee cup
it was a ceramic coffee cup but this one will do
um
and
what i realized is that to make a prediction with my finger's
going to feel like it's just
going to feel different than
this which would feel different
if i touch the hole
or the thing on the bottom
make that prediction
the cortex needs to know where the finger is the tip of the finger
relative to the coffee cup
and exactly relative to the coffee cup
and to do that i have to have a reference
frame for the coffee
up it has to have a way of representing
the location of my finger to the coffin up
and then we realize of course
every part of your skin has to have a reference frame relative
things to touch and then we did the same thing with vision
but
so the idea that a reference frame is necessary to make a prediction when you're touching something
or when you're seeing something
and you're moving your eyes you're moving your fingers it's just a requirement to know what to predict
if i have a if i have a structure
i'm going to make a prediction i have to
i have to know where it is i'm looking or touching it
so then we say well how do neurons make reference frames it's not obvious
you know xyz coordinates don't exist in the brain it's just not the way it works
so that's when we looked at the older part of the brain the hippocampus
and the antorano cortex
where we knew that in that part of the brain there's a reference frame for a room
or reference name for environment
remember i talked earlier about how you could know make a map of this room
so we said oh
um
that they are implementing reference frames there
so we knew that reference frames needed to exist in every cortical column
and so that was a deductive
thing we just deduced it has to go
so
you take the old mammalian
ability to know where you are in a particular space
and you start applying that to higher
and higher levels
yeah you first you apply it to physical like where your finger is
so here's what i think about it
the old part of the brain says where's my body in this room
yeah the new part of the brain says where's my finger
relative to this this object
yeah
where is the a section of my retina
relative to this object
like where where is i'm looking at one little corner where is that relative
to this patch of my retina
yeah
um
and then we take the same thing and apply it to concepts mathematics physics
you know humanity whatever you want to think eventually you're pondering your own mortality well whatever
but the point is when we think about the world when we have knowledge about the world
how is that knowledge organized lex
where do you where is it in your head the answer is it's in reference frames
so the way i learn the structure of this water bottle
where the features are relative to each other when i think about history
or democracy
or mathematics
the same basic underlying structures
happening there's reference frames for where the knowledge that you're assigning
things to so in the book i go through examples like mathematics
and language
and politics
but the evidence is very clear in the neuroscience the same mechanism
that we use to model this coffee cup we're going to use to model high level thoughts
your your your demise of the humanity whatever you want to think about
it's interesting to think about
how different are the representations of those higher dimensional concepts
higher level concepts
how different the representation there is in terms of reference frames versus spatial
but interesting thing it's it's it's a different application
but it's the exact same mechanism
but isn't there some aspect to higher level concepts that they seem to be hierarchical
like they just seem to integrate a lot of information into
so is our physical objects
so take this water bottle i'm not particular to this brand
but this is a fiji water bottle
and it has
um a logo
and i use this example in my book our company's coffee cup has a logo on it
but this object is hierarchical
it is it's got like a cylinder
and a cap but then has this logo
on it and the logo has a word
the word has letters
the letters of different features
and
so i don't have to remember
i don't think about this so i said oh there's a fiji logo
on this water bottle
i don't have to go through and say
oh what is the fiji logo
it's the f and i and the j and i and there's a hibiscus flower
and
oh it has the pest you know the stamen
on it i don't have to do that i just incorporate
all of that in some sort of hierarchical representation i say
um you know put this logo on this water bottle
yeah
and
and then the logo has a word and the word has letters all hierarchical
just all that stuff is big it's amazing that the brain instantly
just does all that yeah the idea that there's
there's water it's liquid
and the idea that you can drink it when you're thirsty the idea that there's brands
yeah
and then there's like all of that information is instantly
like built into the whole thing once you proceed
so i wanted to get back to your point about hierarchical representation
the world itself is hierarchical right
and i can take this microphone in front of me i know inside
there's going to be some electronics
i know there's going to be some wires
and i know there's going to be a little diaphragm that moves back and forth
i don't see that but i know it
so everything in the world is hierarchical
you just go into room it's composed of other components the kitchen has a refrigerator
you know the refrigerator has a door the door has a hinge the hinge has screws
and pin yeah i mean
so anyway the the the modeling system that exists in every cortical column
learns the hierarchical structure of objects
so it's a very sophisticated modeling
system in this grain of rice
it's hard to imagine
but this grain of ice can do really sophisticated
things it's got a hundred thousand neurons in it
it's very sophisticated
so
that same mechanism that can model a water bottle
or a coffee cup can model conceptual objects as well it's if that's the beauty of
this discovery that this guy vernon mount castle made many many years ago which is that
there's there's a single cortical algorithm underlying everything we're doing
so
so common sense concepts
and higher level concepts are all represented in the same way they're set in the same mechanisms
yeah it's a little bit like computers right all computers are universal turing machines
even the little teeny one that's in my toaster
and the big one that's you know running some cloud server or someplace
um they're all running on the same principle they can apply different things
so the brain is all built on the same principle
it's all about learning these models
structured models using movement
and reference frames
and it can be applied to something
as simple as a water bottle in a coffee
cup and it can be
just thinking like what's
the future of humanity
and you know
why do you have a hedgehog on your on your desk i don't know nobody knows
i think it's hedgehog
that's right it's a hedgehog in the fog
it's a russian reference
does it give you any
inclination
or hope about how difficult it is to engineer common sense reasoning
so
how complicated this is this whole process
so looking at the brain
is this a marvel of engineering
or is it pretty dumb stuff stacked on top of each other over and over
can it be both can it be both right
i don't know if it can be both
because if it's an incredible engineering job that means it's v
so evolution did a lot of work it yeah but then
but then it just copied that
right so
as i said earlier the figuring out how to model something
like a space is really hard
and evolution had to go through a lot of trick
and these
these these cells i was talking about these grid cells and place cells they're really complicated
this is not simple stuff
this neural tissue works on these really unexpected weird mechanisms
um
but it did it it figured it out
but
but now you can just make lots of copies of it
but then finding
yeah so it's a very interesting idea that's a lot of copies of a basic mini brain
but the question is
how difficult it is to find that mini brain that you can copy
and paste effectively
okay today
we know enough to build this i'm sitting here with
you know i know the steps we have to go there's
still some engineering problems to solve
but we know enough
and this is not like oh this is an interesting idea
we have to go think about it for another few decades no
we actually understand in pretty well details
so not all the details
but most of them
so it's complicated
but it is an engineering problem
so in my company we are working on that we are basically a road map
how we do this
um it's not going to take decades it's better a few years
um [music] optimistically
but i think that's possible
um
it's you know complex things if you understand them you can build them
so in which domain do you think it's best to
build them are we talking about
robotics like entities
that operate in the physical
world that are able to interact with that world are we talking about entities
that operate in the digital world are we talking about something more like
more specific like is done in the machine learning community
where you look at natural language
or computer vision
where do you think is easiest
it's the first it's the first two more than the third one i would say
um
again again let's just use computers as an analogy
um the pioneers of computing people like john van noyman
and
um turing they created this thing you know we now call the universal turing machine
which is the computer right
did they know how it was going to be applied
where it was going to be used
you know could they
envision any of the future no they just said this is like a really interesting computational
idea about algorithms
and
how you can implement them in in a machine
and we're doing something similar to that today like we are we are building this sort of universal
learning principle
that can be applied to many many different things
but the the robotics piece of that okay the interactive
okay all right let's be specific
you can think of this cortical column
as this what we call a sensory motor
learning system it has the idea
that there's a sensor
and then it's moving
that sensor can be physical it could be like my finger
and it's moving in the world it could like my eye
and it's physically moving it can also be virtual
so it could be
um an example would be i could have a system that lives in the internet
that that actually samples information on the internet
and moves by following links that's that's a sensory motor system
so
something that echoes
the the process of a finger
moving along a car but in a very very loose sense it's it's like
again learning is inherently about the subbing the structure in the world
and discover
the structure of the world you have to move through the world
even if it's a virtual world
even if it's a conceptual world
you have to move through it you don't it doesn't exist in one
it has some structure to it
so
here's here's a couple of predictions that getting
what you're talking about in humans
the same algorithm is does robotics right it moves my arms my eyes my body right
um
and so in my in the future to me robotics
and ai will merge they're not going to be separate fields
because they're going to the the the algorithms to really controlling
robots are going to be the same algorithms we have in our brand the
brain at these sensory motor algorithms i
today we're not there but i think that's going to happen
and
and then
so
but not all ai systems will have b robotics
you can have systems that have very different types of embodiments
some will have physical movements some will have non-physical movements
it's a very generic
learning system again it's like computers
the turing machine is it's like it doesn't say how it's supposed to be implemented
it doesn't tell how big it is doesn't tell you what you apply it to
but it's an interesting it's a computational principle
cortical column equivalent is a computational principle is about learning it's about how you learn
and it can be applied to a gazillion things this is what i think this is
i think this impact of ai is going to be as
large if not larger
than computing has been in the last century by far
because
it's it's getting at a fundamental thing it's not a vision system
or a learning system it's a it's not a vision system or a hearing system
it is a learning system it's a fundamental principle
how you learn the structure in the world
how you can gain knowledge
and be intelligent
and that's what the thousand brain says what's going on and we have a particular implementation
in our head but doesn't have to be like that at all
do you think there's going to be some kind of impact
okay let me ask it another way
what do increasingly intelligent ai systems do with us humans in the following way like
how hard is the human in the loop problem
how hard is it to to interact
the finger on the coffee cup equivalent of having a conversation with a human being
so how hard is it to fit into our little human world
i don't i think it's a lot of engineering problems i don't think it's a fundamental problem
i could ask you the same question
how hard is for computers to fit into a human world right that i mean that's
essentially
what i'm asking like how
um
much are we elitist are we as humans
like we try to keep out systems i don't know i i sure i think
i'm not sure that's the right question
let's let's look at computers as an analogy
computers are million times faster than us they do things we can't understand
most people have no idea what's going on when they use computers right
how do we integrate them in our society
um
well they're that we don't think of them as their own entities they're not living things
um we don't afford them rights
um we we rely on them our survival as a seven billion people
or something like that is relying on computers
now
um don't you think that's a fundamental problem
that we see them as something we can't we don't give rights to
so computers
so
yeah computers
so robots computers intelligence systems it feels like for them to operate successfully
they would need to have
a lot of the elements that we would start having to think about like
should this entity have rights i i don't think so i i think
it's tempting to think that way
personally i don't think anyone
hardly anyone thinks that for computers today
no one says oh this thing needs
a right i shouldn't be able to turn it off or you know
if i throw it in the trash can you know
and hit it with a sledgehammer i might
perform a criminal act no no one thinks that
um
and now we think about intelligent machines
which is where you're going
um
and
and all of a sudden like well
now we can't do that
i think the basic problem we have here is that people think intelligent machines will be like us
they're going to have the same emotions
as we do the same feelings
as we do
what if i can build an intelligent machine that have absolutely
could care less about whether it was on or off or destroyed
or not it just doesn't care it's just like a map it's just a modeling system
it has no desires to live
nothing is it possible to create a system
that can model the world deeply
and not care
about whether it lives or dies absolutely
no question about it to me that's not 100 percent obvious
it's obvious to me so okay we can debate it if you want
yeah
where does your
where does your desire to live come from it's an old evolutionary
design
i mean we could argue does it really matter if we live or not objectively no
right we're all going to die eventually
um
but evolution
makes us want to live
evolution makes us want to fight to live evolutionists want to care
and love one another
and to care for our children
and our relatives
and our family
and
and so on
and those are all good things
but they come about not because we're smart
because we're animals
that grew up you know the the hummingbird in my backyard
cares about its offspring you know
the every living thing in some sense cares about you know surviving
but when we talk about creating intelligent machines we're not creating life
we're not creating evolving creatures we're not creating living things
we're just creating a machine that can learn really sophisticated stuff
and that machine it may even be able to talk to us
but it doesn't it's not going to have a desire to live
unless somehow we put it into that system
well there's learning right the the thing is
but you don't learn to like want to live that's built into you it's wow
people like ernest becker argue
so
okay there's the fact the finiteness of life
the way we think about it is something we learn perhaps
so
okay
yeah
and some people decide they don't want to live
and some people decide you know
you can but the desire to live is built in dna right
but i think
what i'm trying to get to is in order to accomplish goals
it's useful to have the urgency
of mortality is what the stoics talked about is meditating in your mortality
yeah it might be a very useful
thing to do to die
and have the urgency of death
and to realize that to conceive yourself as an entity
that operates in this world that eventually will no longer be a part of this world
and actually conceive of yourself as a conscious entity might be very useful
for you to be a system
that makes sense of the world otherwise you might get lazy well
okay we're going to build these machines right
and so we're talking about building ais
what
but we're we're building the
the the the equivalent of the cortical columns the the neocortex the neocortex
and the the question is
where do they arrive at
because we're not hard-coding everything in
where well well in terms of if you build the neocortex equivalent
it will not have any of these desires
or emotional states
now you can argue
that that neocortex won't be useful
unless i give it some agency
unless i give it some desire
unless i give it some motivation otherwise you'll be as lazy and do nothing
right you could argue that
um
but on its own it's not going to do those things
it's just not it's not going to sit there and say
i understand the world therefore
i care to live
no it's not going to do that it's just going to say i understand
the world why is that obvious to you
why why why don't
do you think it's
okay let me ask it this way do you think it's possible
it will
at least assign to itself
agency
and
perceive
itself in this world as being a conscious entity
as a useful way to operate in the world
and and to make sense of the world i think intelligent machine could be conscious
but that doesn't not again imply any of these
um these desires
and goals
and
and that you're worried about
it we can i have a
we can talk about what it means for the machine to be conscious
and by the way not worry about but get excited about it's not necessarily
that we should worry about it so i think there's a legitimate problem
or not problem a question asked
if you build this modeling system what's it gonna model
yes right what's it what's its desire
what is it what's its goal
what are we applying it to right
so that's an interesting question
um
one thing if it and it depends on the application
it's not something that inherent
to the modeling system it's something we apply to the modeling system in a particular way
so if i wanted to make a really smart car
it would have to know about driving in cars
and what's important in driving in cars
it's not going to figure that out
on its own it's not going to sit there and say you know
i've understood the world
and i've decided
you know no no no
we have to tell
it we're going to have to say like
so i imagine i make this car really smart it learns about
your driving habits it learns about the world
and it's just you know is it one day going to wake up and say
you know what i'm tired of driving
and doing what you want
i think i have better
ideas about how to spend my time well
okay
no it's not going to do that
part of me is playing a little bit of devil's advocate
but part of me is also trying to think through this because i've
studied cars quite a bit
and i studied pedestrians
and cyclists quite a bit
and there's part of me that thinks
that there needs to be
more intelligence than we realize in order to drive successfully
that game theory of human interaction
seems to require some deep understanding of
of human nature
that
okay when a pedestrian crosses the street there's some sense
they they look at a car usually
and then they look away there's
some sense in which they say i believe
that you're not going to murder me
you don't have the guts to murder me
this is the little dance of pedestrian car interaction
yeah is saying i'm going to look away
and i'm going to put my life in your hands
because i think you're human you're not gonna kill me
and then the car in order to successfully
operate in like manhattan streets has to say no no no i am going to kill you
like a little bit there's a little bit of this weird inkling of mutual murder
yeah
and that's a dance
and then somehow successfully
operate through do you think you were born of that did you learn that social interaction
i think it
might have a lot of the same elements that you're talking about which is we're leveraging
things we were born with
and applying them in the context that
all right i would i would
answer that i would have said that that kind of interaction is learned
because you know people in different cultures have different interactions
like that if you cross the street in different cities
and different around the world they have different ways of interacting i would say that's learned
and i would say an intelligent system could learn that too
but that does not lead
and the intelligent system can understand
humans it could understand that you know just like i can study an animal
and learn something about that animal you know i could study apes
and learn something about their culture
and so on i'd have to be an ape to know that
um i may not be completely
but i can understand something
so intel's
machine can model that that's this part of the world is this part of the interactions
the question we're trying to get at
will the intelligent machine have its own personal agency that's beyond
you know what we assign to it or it's its own personal you know goals
or will it evolve
and create these things
my confidence comes from understanding the mechanisms i'm talking about creating
this is not hand wave stuff
it's down in the details we i'm
going to build it
and i know what it's going to look
like and i know it's going to behave
i know what the kind of things
it could do and the kind of things it can't do
just like when i build a computer
i know it's not going to on its own decide to put another
register inside of it it can't do that
no way no matter what your software does it can't add a register to the computer
um
so in this way when we build ai systems
we have to make choices about the the the under the
how we embed them
so i talked about this in the book i said you know
it's a brain intelligence
system is not just the neocortex equivalent
you have to have that
but it has to have some kind of embodiment physical a virtual
it has to have some sort of goals it has to have some sort of
ideas about dangers about things it shouldn't do like
you know like we
we build in safeguards into systems
we have them in our bodies we have put them into cars
right you know my car follows my directions
until the day it sees i'm about to hit something and it ignores my directions
and puts the brakes on
so we can build those things in
so that's a very interesting problem
um
how to build those in i think my my
my differing opinion about the risks of ai for most people
is that people assume that somehow those things will just appear automatically it'll evolve
and intelligence itself
begets that stuff
or requires it
but it's not intelligence of the neural cortex equipment doesn't require this the new cartridge equipment just says
i'm a learning system
tell me what you want me to learn
and
i'll tell you ask me questions
i'll tell you the answers
but in that again it's again like a map it doesn't a map has no intent
about things but you can use it
um to solve problems
okay
so the building engineering the neural cortex
in itself is just creating an intelligent prediction system modeling system sorry modeling system
yeah you can use it to then make predictions
and then
but you can also put it inside a thing that's actually acting in this world
you have to put it inside something it's
again think of the map analogy right map on its own doesn't do anything right
it's just inert it's just it can learn but it's just
so we have to embed it somehow in something to do something
so
so what's your intuition here you had a conversation with sam harris recently that was sort of um
you've had a bit of a disagreement
and you're sticking on this point you know elon musk stuart russell
kind of have us worry existential
threats of ai
what's your intuition why if we engineer an increasingly intelligent neural cortex type of system in the computer
why that shouldn't be a thing that we it was interesting we used the word intuition
and sam harris used the word intuition too
and
and when he used that intuition that word i immediately stopped and said oh that's the problem
he's using intuition i'm not speaking about my intuition
yes i'm speaking about something i understand something i'm going to build something i am building
something i understand completely
or at least well enough to know what it's all i'm guessing
i know
what this thing's going to do
and i think most people who are worried
they have trouble separating out they don't have they don't have the um knowledge
or the understanding about like what is intelligence
how is it manifest in the brain how is it separate from these other functions in the brain
and so they imagine it's going to be human-like
or animal-like it's going to have it's going to have the same sort of drives
and emotions we have
but there's no reason for that
that's just because there's there's unknown
if you're if the unknown is like oh my god
you know i don't know what this is going to do we have to be careful
it could be like us but really smarter
i'm saying no it won't be like us it'll be really smart
but it won't be like us at all
and
um
but i i'm coming from that not because i just guessing i'm not intuitive
using intuition i'm basically
like okay i understand
this thing works this is what it does
let me explain it to you
okay
but to push back
so i also disagree with the the intuitions that sam has
but
but i also disagree with
what you just said
which you know what's a good analogy
so
if you look at the twitter algorithm in in the early days just recommender systems you can understand
how recommender systems work
what you can't understand in the early days is when you apply that recommender
system at scale to thousands
and millions of people
how that can change societies
yeah
so the question is
yes you're just saying this is how an engineer in neurocortex works
but the ques like when you have a very useful
tic toc type of service that goes viral when your neural cortex goes viral
and then millions of people start using it cannot destroy the world no
well first of all this is back one thing i want to say is that
ai is a dangerous technology
i don't i'm not denying that all technology is dangerous well an ai maybe particularly
so yeah
okay
so
um
am i worried about it yeah i'm totally worried about it the the thing where
the narrow component we're talking about now is the existential
risk of ai right
so i want to make that distinction
because i think ai can be applied poorly
it can be applied in ways that you know people are going to
understand the consequences of it
these are all potentially very bad things
but they're not the ai system creating this existential risk on its own
and that's the only place i disagree with other people right so
so i i think the existential
risk thing is um
humans are really damn good at surviving
so to kill off the human race it'd be very very difficult you can even
yes
but you can even i'll go further i don't think ai systems are ever going to try to
i don't think ar systems are ever going to like say
i'm going to ignore you i'm going to do what i think is best
i don't think that's going to happen
at least not in the way i'm talking about it
so you the twitter recommendation algorithm this interesting example
let's let's use computer as an analogy again right
i build a computer it's a universal computing machine i can't predict
what people are going to use it for they can build all kinds of things they can
they can even create computer viruses
it's you know all kinds of stuff
so there's some unknown about its utility about
where it's going to go
but on the other hand i pointed out that once i build a computer
it's not going to fundamentally change
how it computes it's like i use the example of a register
which is a part internal part of a computer
um you know i say it can't just say
because computers don't evolve
they don't replicate they don't evolve
they don't you know the physical manifestation
of the computer itself is not gonna
there's certain things it can't do
right so we can
break into things like things
that are possible to happen we can't predict
and things are just impossible to happen
unless we go out of our way to make them happen they're not going to happen
unless somebody makes them happen
yeah so there's there's a bunch of things to say one is the physical aspect
which you're absolutely right
we have to build a thing
for it to operate in the physical world
and you can just stop building them you know
the moment
they're not doing the thing you want them to do or just change the design
or change the design
the question is i mean there's
it's possible in the physical
world this is probably longer
term is you automate the building
it makes
it makes a lot of sense to automate the building there's a lot of factories
that are doing more and more and more automation to go from raw resources to the final product
it's possible to imagine that it's obviously much more efficient to keep to create a factory that's creating
robots that do something
you know do something extremely useful for society it could be personal assistance it could be
it could be it could be your toaster
but a toaster that's much has deeper knowledge of your culinary preferences
yeah
and and that could
well i think now
you've hit on the right thing the real thing we need to be worried
about lex is self-replication
right that is the thing that we're in the physical world
yeah
or even the virtual world self-replication
because self-replication is dangerous it's probably more likely to be killed by a virus
you know or a human engineered virus
anybody can create you know this the technology is getting so almost anybody
but not anybody
but a lot of people could create a human-engineered virus that could wipe out humanity
that is really dangerous no intelligence required just self-replication
so
um
so we need to be careful about that
so
when i think about you know ai
i'm not thinking about robots building robots don't do that don't build a you know
just well that's because you're interested in creating intelligence
it seems like self-replication
is a good way to make a lot of money well fine but
so is you know maybe editing
viruses is a good way to i don't know the point is if as a society
when we want to look at existential risks
the existential risks we face that that we can control almost all evolve around self-replication
yes the question is i don't see a good
way to make a lot of money by engineering viruses
and deploying them in the world there could be there will be applications that are useful
but let's separate out let's separate out
i mean you don't need to you only need some you know terrorists
who wants to do it because it doesn't take a lot of money to make viruses
um let's just separate out what's risky
and what's not risky
i'm arguing that the intelligence
side of this equation is not risky it's not risky it's not risky at all it's the self-replication
side of the equation is risky
and i'm not dismissing that i'm scared as hell it's like the paperclip
maximizer thing
yeah
those are often like talked about in the same conversation
um
i think you're right like creating ultra-intelligent super-intelligent
systems is not necessarily coupled with the self-replicating arbitrarily self-replicating systems
yeah and you don't get evolution unless you're self-replicating
yeah
and
so
i think that's the gist of this argument that people have trouble separating those two out they just think
oh
yeah intelligence is like us and look how look at the damage we've done to this planet
like how we've
you know destroyed all these other species
yeah well we replicate we're eight billion of us are seven million of us now
so
um i think the idea is that the the more intelligent
we're able to build systems the more tempting
it becomes from a capitalist
perspective of creating products the more tempting it becomes to create self
reproduction systems all right
so let's say that's true
so does that mean we don't build intelligent systems no that means we regulate
we we understand the risks
we regulate them
yeah you know look there's a lot of things we could do a society
which have some sort of financial benefit to someone
which could do a lot of harm
and we have to learn how to regulate those things
we have to learn how to deal with those things
i will argue this i would say the opposite i would say having intelligent machines
at our disposal will actually help us in the end more
because it'll help us understand
these risks better and help us mitigate these risk riders
there might be ways of saying oh
well how do we solve climate change problems
you know how do we do this or how do we do that
that just like computers are dangerous in the hands of the wrong people
but they've been so
great for so many other things
we live with those dangers
and i think we have to do the same with intelligent machines we just
but we have to be constantly vigilant about
this idea of a bad actors doing bad things with them and b
um don't ever ever create a self-replicating system
um
and by the way i don't even know if you could create a self-replicating
system that uses a factory that's really dangerous
you know nature's way of self-replicating is so amazing
um you know it doesn't require anything it just me know the thing
and resources
and it goes right
yeah
if i said to you you know what we have to build
our goal is to build a factory that can make that builds new factories
and it has to end to end supply chain
it has to
mine the resources get the energy
i mean that's really hard it's
you know no one's doing that in the next
you know 100 years i've been extremely
impressed by the efforts of elon musk
and tesla to try to do exactly that not not from raw resource
well he actually i think states the goal is to go from raw resource
to the the final car in one factory
yeah that's that's the main goal of course it's not currently possible
but they're taking huge leaps well he's not the only one to do that
this has been a goal for many
industries for a long long time
um it's difficult to do well a lot of people
what they do is instead they have like a million suppliers
and then they like there's everybody's men they all co-locate them
and they tie the systems together it's it's a fundamentally distributed even
i think that's that also is not getting at the issue i was just talking about
um
which is self-replication it's
i mean self-replication means there's
no entity involved other than the entity that's replicating
um right
and so if there's humans in this in the loop that's not really self-replicating right it's
unless somehow we're duped
but it's also i i don't necessarily
agree with you because you've kind of mentioned that ai will not say no to us
i i just think they will
yeah
so like
i think it's a useful feature to build in i'm just trying to like
put myself in the mind of engineers to sometimes say no
you know if you you
yeah well
i gave an example earlier right i get an example of my car
yeah right my car turns the wheel
and and applies the accelerator
and the brake as i say until it decides there's something dangerous
yes
and then it doesn't do that
yeah
now
that was something it didn't decide to do is something we programmed into the car
and so good it was a good idea right
the question again isn't like if we create an intelligent system will it ever
ignore our commands of course it will on sometimes
is it going to do it because it came up came up with its own goals
that serve its purposes
and it doesn't care about our purposes no i don't think that's going to happen
okay so let me ask you about these super intelligent cortical systems that we engineer
and us humans
do you think with these entities operating out there in the world
what does the future most promising future look like is it us
merging with them
or is it us
like how do we keep us humans around when you have increasingly intelligent beings is it
one of the dreams is to upload our minds in the digital space
so can we just
give our minds to these systems
yeah
so they can operate on them is there some kind of more interesting merger
or is there more
more in the third part of my book i talked about all these scenarios
and let me just walk through them sure
um
the uploading the mind one
yes extremely
really difficult to do like like we have no idea how to do this even remotely right now
um
so it would be a very long way away
but i make the argument you wouldn't like the result
um
and you wouldn't be pleased with the result
it's really not what you think it's going to be
um imagine i could upload your brain into into a computer
right now and now the computer's
sitting there going hey i'm over here great
get rid of that old bio
person i don't need them you're still sitting here
yeah
what are you gonna do no no
that's not me i'm here right yeah are you gonna feel satisfied that then you
but people imagine look i'm on my deathbed
and i'm about to you know expire
and i push the button
and now i'm uploaded
but think about it a little differently
and and
so i don't think it's going to be a thing
because people by the time we're able to do this if ever
because you have to replicate the entire body
not just the brain it's it's really
it's i walk through the issues it's really substantial
um
do you have a sense of what makes us us is there is there a shortcut
to what can only save a certain part
that makes us truly
ours no but i think that machine would feel like it's you too right right
if you people just like i have a child
i have a child right i have two daughters
they're independent people i created them well partly
yeah
and
um
i don't
just because they're somewhat
like me i don't feel i'm them
and they don't feel like
i'm me so if you split it apart
you have two people
so we can come back to what what makes
what consciousness we want we can talk about that
but we don't have a remote consciousness
i'm not sitting there going oh i'm conscious of that you know i mean that system over there
so let's say let's let's stay on our topic
okay so one was uploading a brand
yep ain't gonna happen in a hundred years maybe a thousand
but i don't think people are gonna wanna do it the
merging your mind with you know the neural link thing right like
again really really difficult
it's it's one thing to make progress to control a prosthetic
arm it's another to have like a billion
or several billion you know things and understanding
what those signals mean like it's the one thing they're like okay
i can learn to
think some patterns to make something happen
it's quite another thing to have a system a computer
which actually knows exactly
which cells it's talking to and how it's talking to them and interacting in a way like that
very very difficult we're not getting anywhere closer to that
um interesting can i can i ask a question here
what
so for me
what makes that merger very difficult practically in the next 10 20
50 years is like literally the biology side of it which is like
it's just hard to do that kind of surgery in a safe way
but your intuition is even the machine learning
part of it where the machine has to learn
what the heck it's talking to that's even hard i think it's even harder
and it's not it's it's easy to do when you're talking about hundreds of signals
it's it's a totally different thing to say you're talking about billions of signals
so you don't think it's the raw
it's a machine learning problem you don't think it could be learned
well i'm just saying
no i think you'd have to have detailed knowledge
you'd have to know exactly
what the types of neurons you're connecting to
i mean in the brain there's these they're neurons
that do all different types of things it's not like a neural network it's a very complex
organism system up here
we talked about the grid cells or the place cells
you know you have to know what kind of cells
you're talking to and what they're doing
and how their timing works
and all all this stuff
which you can't today there's no way of doing that right
but i think it's i think it's a i think the problem
you're right that the biological
aspect of like who wants to have surgery
and have this stuff inserted in your brain that's a problem
but this is when we solve that problem
i think the the information coding aspect is much worse
i think that's much more
it's not like what they're doing today today
it's simple machine learning stuff
because you're doing simple things
but if you want to merge your brain like i'm thinking
on the internet i'm merge my brain with the machine
and we're both doing
i that's a totally different issue
that's interesting i i tend to think if
okay
if you have a super clean signal
from a bunch of neurons
at the start you don't know what those neurons are i think that's
much easier than the getting of the clean signal i think
if you think about today's machine learning that's what you would conclude
right i'm thinking about what's going on in the brain
and i don't reach that conclusion
so we'll have to see sure
but i don't think even even then i think there's kind of a sad future
like you know do i
do i have to like plug my brain into a computer i'm still a biological organism
i assume i'm still going to die
so what
what have i achieved right you know
what have i achieved to do some sort of oh i i disagree
we don't
know what those are but it seems
like there could be a lot of different applications
it's like virtual reality is to expand your brain's capability to to to like to read wikipedia
yeah but but fine but but you're still a biological organization
yes yes you know you're still you're still mortal you're still all right so
what are you accomplishing you're making your life in this short period of time better right just like
having the internet made our life better yeah
yeah okay
so i i think that's of of if i think about all the possible
gains we can have here that's a marginal one it's an individual
hey i'm better you know i'm smarter
um
but you know fine i'm not against it i just don't think it's earth-changing i
but
so this is the true of the internet when each of us individuals are smarter
we get a chance to then share our smartness we get smarter
and smarter together as like as a collective this is kind of like this ant colony
but why don't i just create an intelligent machine that doesn't have any of this biological nonsense
this is all the same it's it's everything except don't burden it with my brain
yeah right it has a brain it is smart it's like my child
but it's much much smarter than me
so i have a choice between
doing some implant doing some hybrid weird you know biological thing that bleeding
and all these problems
and limited by my brain
or creating a system
which is super smart that i can talk to
um that helps me understand the world they can read the inter you know read wikipedia
and talk to me i i guess my the open questions there are
what does the manifestation of super intelligence look like
so like
what are we going to
you talked about why do i want to merge with ai like what
what's the actual marginal benefit here
if i if we have a super intelligent
system
yeah
how will it make our life better
so
let's let's that's a great question but let's break it down to little pieces all right
on the one hand
it can make our life better in lots of simple ways you mentioned like a care robot
or something that helps me
do things it cooks
i don't know what it does right
little things like that we have soup better smarter
cars we can have
you know better agents
and aids helping us in our work environment
and things like that to me that's like the easy stuff the simple stuff in the beginning
um
and so in the same way that computers made our lives better in ways
many many ways i will have those kind of things
to me the really exciting thing about ai
is sort of its transcendent transcendent quality in terms of humanity we're still biological
organisms we're still stuck here on earth
it's going to be hard for us to live anywhere else
i don't think you and i are going to want to live on mars anytime soon
and
um
and we're flawed
you know we may end up destroying ourselves it's totally possible
we if not completely we could destroy our civilizations
you know it's let's face the fact we have issues here
but we can create intelligent machines
that can help us in various ways for example one example i gave another
sounds a little sci-fi
but i believe this if we really wanted to live on mars
we'd have to have intelligent systems that go there
and build the habitat for us not humans
humans are never going to do this it's just too hard
um
but could we have a thousand
or ten thousand you know engineer workers up there doing this stuff building things terraforming
mars sure maybe we can move to mars
but then
if we want to if we want to go around the universe
should i send my children around the universe
or should i send some intelligent machine
which is like a child
that represents me and understands our needs here on earth that could travel through space
so it's sort of it in some sense intelligence allows us to transcend
our the limitations of our biology
with
and
and don't think of it as a negative
thing it's in some sense my children transcend
my the my biology too
because they they live beyond me
yeah
um
and we impart they represent me and they also have their own knowledge
and i can impart knowledge to them so intelligent machines will be like that too
but not limited like us
but the question is um
there's so many ways that transcendence can happen
and the merger with ai
and humans is one of those ways so you said intelligent
basically beings
or systems propagating throughout the universe representing us humans
they represent us humans in the sense they represent our knowledge
and our history
not us individually
right right
but
i mean the question is is it just the database
with with the really damn good model no they're conscious conscious just like us
okay
but just different they're different
just like my children are different they're like me but they're different
um these are more different
i guess maybe i've already
i kind of i take a very broad view of our life here on on earth
i say you know why are we living here are we just living because we live
is are we surviving
because we can survive are we fighting just because
we want to just keep going what's the point of it yeah right
so to me the point if i ask myself what's the point of life is
what transcends that
ephemeral sort of biological experience is to me this is my answer
is the acquisition of knowledge to understand more about the universe
and to explore
and that's partly to learn more right
i don't view it as
a terrible thing if the ultimate
outcome of humanity is we create systems that are intelligent that are our offspring
but are not like us at all
and we stay we stay here and live on earth as long as we can
which won't be forever
but as long as we can
and
but that would be a great thing to do
it's not a it's not like a negative thing well
would you'd be okay then if the human
species vanishes
but our knowledge is preserved
and keeps being expanded by intelligent systems
i want our knowledge to be preserved
and expanded
yeah am i okay with humans dying no i don't want that to happen
but if if if it does happen
what if we we were sitting here and this is
we're the last two people on earth we're saying lex we blew it
it's all over right yeah
wouldn't i feel better if i knew that our knowledge was preserved
and that we had agents
represent that knew about that that were trans you know they were that left earth
i would want that
it's better than not having that you know i make the analogy of like you know the dinosaurs
the poor dinosaurs
they live for you know tens of millions of years
they raised their kids they
you know they they fought to survive
they were hungry they they
they did everything we do
and then they're all gone
yeah like you know
and and if we didn't discover their bones
nobody would ever know that they ever existed right
do we want to be like that
i don't want to be like that but there's
a sad aspect to it and it's kind of it's jarring to think about
that it's possible that a human-like
intelligent civilization has previously existed on earth
oh yeah the reason i say this is like
it is jarring to think that
we would not if they weren't extinct we wouldn't be able to find evidence of them
after a sufficient amount
after a sufficient amount of time of course there's like
look basically humans like if we destroy ourselves
now
human civilization destroy ourselves
after a sufficient
amount of time we would not be we'd find the evidence of the dinosaurs
we would not find evidence of those humans
yeah that's kind of an odd thing to think about although
i'm not sure if we have enough knowledge about species going back
for billions of years that we could we could
we might be able to eliminate that possibility
but it's an interesting question of course this is a similar question to
you know there were lots of intelligent species throughout the without our galaxy
that have all disappeared
yeah that's super sad that
um there
exactly that there may have been much more intelligent alien civilizations
in our galaxy that are no longer there
yeah
um you actually talked about this
um that humans might destroy ourselves
yeah
and
how we might
preserve our knowledge
yeah
and advertise that knowledge to other
advertisers a funny word to use
from a pr person there's no financial gain in this
you know like make it like from a tourism perspective make it interesting can you describe
how well there's a couple things i broke it down to the two parts
actually three parts one is
um
you know there's a lot of things we know that
what if what if we were to what if we ended up our civilization collapsed
yeah i'm not talking tomorrow
yeah we could be a thousand years from now alex you know we don't really know but
but historically would be likely at some point time flies when you're having fun
yeah that's a good way to put it
um you know could we
and then then intelligent life evolved again on this planet
wouldn't they want to know a lot about us
and what we knew when they wouldn't be able to ask us questions
so one very simple thing i said how would we archive
what we know
that was a very simple idea i said you know what
that wouldn't be that hard but a few satellites
you know going around this the sun and we upload wikipedia every day and
um that kind of thing
so you know we can end up killing ourselves well it's
up there and the next intelligence piece
will find it and learn
something that would be they would like that
they would appreciate that
so that's one thing the next thing i said well what if you know
how to outside of our solar system
we have the seti program we're looking for these intelligent signals from everybody
and if you do a little bit of math
which i did in the book
and you say well what if intelligent species only live for 10 000 years
before you know technologically intelligent species
like ones are really able to do this we're just starting to be able to do
um
well the chances are we wouldn't
be able to see any of them because they would have all been disappeared by now
um they would they've lived for 10 000 years
and now they're gone
and
so we're not going to find these signals being sent from these people
because
i said what kind of signal could you create
that would last a million years or a billion years that someone would say
damn it someone smart lived there we know that that would be a life-changing event
for us to figure that out well what we're looking for today in the study program
isn't that we're looking for very
coded signals in some sense
and so i asked myself
what would be a different type of signal one could create
i've always thought about this throughout my life and in the book i gave one one possible suggestion
which was
um
we now detect planets going around other other suns
other stars excuse
me and we do that by seeing this the the slight dimming of the light as the planets
move in front of them that's
how we detect planets elsewhere in our galaxy
um
what if we created something like that that just rotated around our around the sun
and it blocked out a little bit of light in a particular pattern
that someone said hey
that's not a planet
that is a sign
that someone was once there you can say
what if it's beating up pi you know three point whatever
um
so the idea of a distance you can from a distance broadly broadcast
takes no continue activation
on our part this is the key right
no one has to be seen here running a computer
and supplying it with power it just goes on
so we go it's continues
and
and i argue that part of the study program should be looking for signals like that
and to look for signals like that you ought to figure out what the
how would we create a signal
like what would we create that would be like that that would persist
for millions of years
that would be broadcast broadly you could see from a distance that was unequivocal
it came from an by an intelligent species
and so i gave that one example
um because they don't know what i know of actually
and then and then finally right
if if our ultimately our solar system will die at some point in time you know
how do we go beyond that
and i think it's possible
if at all possible we'll have to create intelligent machines that travel throughout
this throughout the the solar system or throughout the galaxy
and i don't think that's going to be humans
i don't think it's going to be biological organisms
so these are just things to think about
you know like what's the you know like
i don't i don't want to be like the dinosaurs
i don't want to just live and okay
that was it we're done you know
well there is a kind of presumption that we're going to live forever
which i i think it is a bit sad
to imagine that the message we send as as you talk about is that we were once here
instead of we are here well it could be we are still here
but it's more of a it's more of an insurance
policy in case we're not here you know well
i don't know but there's something
i think about we as humans don't often think about this but
it's like like whenever i
um [music]
record a video i've done this a couple times in my life i've recorded
a video for my future self
just for personal just for fun
and it's always just fascinating
to think about
that preserving yourself for future civilizations
for me it was preserving myself for future
me but that's a little
that's a little fun example
of archival these podcasts are are preserving you and i in a way yeah for future
hopefully well
after we're gone
but you don't often we're sitting here talking about this
you are not thinking about the fact that you and i are going to die
and there will be like 10 years
after somebody watching this
and we're still alive you know in some sense i do
i'm here because i want to talk about ideas right and these ideas transcend me
and they transcend this time in on our planet
um we're talking here about ideas that
could be around a thousand years from now or a million years from now
i when i wrote my book
i had an audience of mine
and one of the clearest audiences was aliens no
were people reading this 100 years from now yes i said to myself
how do i make this book relevant
to summer reading this 100 years from now what would they want to
know that we were thinking back then
what would make it like that was an interesting it's still an interesting book
i'm not sure i can achieve that but that was
how i thought about it because these ideas
like especially in the third part of the book the ones we're just talking about
you know these crazy it sounds like crazy ideas about you know storing our knowledge
and
and you know merging our brains of computers
and sending you know our machine down to space is not going to happen in my lifetime
um
and they may not have been happening the next 100 years it may not happen
for a thousand years who knows
but we have the unique opportunity right now we you me and other people like this
um to sort of at least propose the agenda
um that might impact the future like that that's a fascinating way to think both like writing
or creating
try to make
try to create ideas try to create things that hold up in time
yeah you know understanding
how the brain works
we're gonna figure that at once that's it it's gonna be figured out once
and after that that's the answer
and people will people will study that
thousands of years now we still
we still you know venerate newton
and einstein
and
um
and you know
because
because ideas are exciting even well into the future
well the interesting thing is like big ideas even if they're wrong are still useful like
yeah especially if they're not completely wrong like
right newton's laws are not wrong they're just einsteins they're better
um well it's
so yeah
i mean but we're talking with newton and einstein we're talking about physics i wonder
if we'll ever achieve that kind of clarity
but understanding
um like complex systems
and the this particular manifestation of complex systems
which is the human brain i'm
totally optimistic we can do that i mean we're making progress at it
i don't see any reasons why we can't completely
i mean completely understand in the sense
um you know we don't really completely understand
what all the molecules in this water bottle are doing
but you know we have laws that sort of capture it pretty good
um
and so we'll have that kind of understanding
i mean it's not like you're gonna have to know what every
neuron in your brain is doing
um
but enough to first of all to build it
and second of all to do you know do what physics does which is like have concrete experiments
where we can validate
we're we're this is happening right now like it's not this is not some future thing
um you know i'm very optimistic about because
i know about art our work and what we're doing
i have to prove it to people
um
but
i i consider myself a rational person
and
um
you know until fairly recently
i wouldn't have said that but right now i'm where i'm sitting right now i'm saying you know we
can this is going to happen
there's no big obstacles to it
um we finally have a framework for understanding what's going on in the cortex
and
um
and that's liberating it's it's like oh it's happening
so i i can't see why we wouldn't be able to understand it i just can't
okay
oh so
i mean on that topic let me ask you to play devil's
advocate is it possible for you to imagine
luck look a hundred years from now
and looking at your book in which ways might your ideas be wrong
oh i worry about this all the time
um
yeah it's still useful
yeah
i think there's
you know
um
well i can i can best relate it to like things i'm worried about right now
so we talk about this voting idea right it's happening there's no question that's happening
but it could be far more [music]
there's there's enough things i don't know about it that it might be
working in ways differently i'm thinking about the kind of what's voting who's voting you know
where are representations
i talked about you have a thousand models of a coffee cup like that
that could turn out to be wrong
because it may be
maybe there are a thousand models that are sub models
but not really a single model the coffee cup
um
i mean there's things these are all sort of on the edges
things that i i present as like oh it's so simple
and clean well it's not that it's always going to be more complex
and
um
and there's parts of the theory
which i don't understand the complexity well
so
i think i think the idea is brain is a distributed modeling system is not controversial
at all right that's not that's well understood by many people
the question then is are each quarter of a column an independent modeling system right
um
i could be wrong about that
um i don't think so
but i worry about it my intuition not even thinking
why you could be wrong is the same intuition i have about any sort of physicist
like strength theory
that we as humans desire for a clean explanation
and 100 years from now intelligent systems might look back at us
and laugh
at how we try to get rid of the whole mess
by having simple explanation when the reality is it's it's way messier
and
in fact it's impossible to understand you can only build it it's like this idea of complex systems
and cellular automata
yeah you can only launch the thing you cannot understand it
yeah i think that you know the history of science suggests that's not likely to occur
the history of science suggests that look as a theorist
and we're theorists you look for simple explanations right
fully knowing
that whatever simple explanation you're going to come up with is not going to be completely correct
i mean it can't be
i mean it's just it's just more complexity
but that's the role of theorists play they they sort of they give you a framework
on which you now can talk about a problem
and figure out
okay
now we can start dig in more details
the best frameworks stick around while the details change
you know again
you know the classic example is newton and einstein right you know
um
newton's theories are still used they're still valuable they're still practical they're not like wrong
it's just they've been refined
yeah but that's in physics it's not obvious
by the way it's not obvious for physics either
that the universe should be such that it's amenable to these simple
but
so far it appears to be
as far as we can tell
um
yeah
i mean
but as far as we could tell
and
but it's also an open question whether the brain is amenable to such clean theories
that's the not the brain
but intelligence well i i
i don't know i would take intelligence out of it just say you know
um
well
okay
um the evidence we have suggests that the human brain is a at the one time extremely messy
and complex
but there's some parts that are very regular
and structured that's why we started the neocortex it's extremely
regular in its structure
yeah
and unbelievably
so
and then i mentioned earlier the other thing is it's it's universal abilities
it is so flexible to learn
so many things we don't we haven't figured
out what it can't learn
yet we don't know
but we haven't figured
out yet but to learn
things that it never
was evolved to learn
so those give us hope
um that's why i went into this field because i said you know this regular structure it's
doing this amazing number of things there's got to be some underlying principles
that are that are common
and other other scientists have come up with the same conclusions
um
and so it's promising it's promising
and
um
and that's
and whether the theories play out exactly this way or not that is the role that theorists play
and
so far it's worked out well even though you know maybe
you know we don't understand all the laws of physics
but so far it's been pretty damn useful the ones we have
are our theories are pretty bit useful
you mentioned that
we should not necessarily be
at least to the degree that we are worried about the existential risks of artificial intelligence
relative to human risks from human nature being existential risk
what aspect of human nature worries you the most in terms of the survival of the human species
i mean i'm disappointed
in humanity as humans
i mean all of us i'm one so i'm at disappointed myself too
it's kind of a sad state
there's two things that disappoint me
one is
how it's difficult for us to separate our rational component of ourselves from our evolutionary heritage
which is you know not always pretty you know
rape is a is an evolutionary good strategy
for reproduction
murder can be at times too you know
making other people miserable at times is a good strategy for reproduction it's just
and it's just and
and so
now that we know that
and yet we have
this sort of you know we and i can
have this very rational discussion
talking about you know intelligence
and brains
and life and so on
so it seems like it's so hard it's just a big transition to get humans
all humans to to to make the transition from be like let's pay no attention to all that
ugly stuff over here let's just focus on the instances
what's unique about humanity is our knowledge
and our intellect
but the fact that we're striving is in itself amazing right
the fact that we're able to overcome that part
and it seems like we are more
and more becoming successful
and overcoming that that is the optimistic view and i agree with you
yeah
but i worry about it i'm not saying
i'm worrying about i think maybe that was your question i still worry about it yes
um you know we could be end tomorrow
because some terrorists could get nuclear bombs
and you know blow us all up who knows right
the other thing i think i'm disappointed is
and it's just i understand
it it's i guess you can't really be disappointed
it's just a fact is that we're so prone to false beliefs
that we you know we have a model in our head
the things we can interact with directly physical objects people that model is pretty good
and we can test it all the time
right i touch something i look at it i talk to you see my model's correct
but so much of what we know is stuff i can't directly
interact with i can't i don't know because someone told me about it yeah
and so
so we're prone inherently prone to having false beliefs
because if i'm told something how am i going to know it's right or wrong right
and
so then we have the scientific process
which says we are inherently flawed
so the only way we can
get closer to the truth is by looking for
um contrary evidence
yeah
um like this
conspiracy theory this this theory that scientists keep telling me about that the earth is round
as far as i can tell when i look out it looks pretty flat
yeah
so
yeah there is there's a tension
but it's also
um
um i tend to believe that we haven't figured out most of this thing right
most of nature around us is a mystery
and so it um
but that doesn't work does that worry you
i mean it's like oh that's that's like a pleasure more to figure out right
yeah that's exciting
but i'm saying like there's going to be a lot of quote unquote wrong ideas
i mean i've been thinking a lot about engineering systems like social networks
and so on
and i've been worried about censorship
and thinking through all that kind of stuff
because there's a lot of wrong ideas there's a lot of dangerous ideas
but then i also read a history
read history
and see when you censor ideas that are wrong
now this could be a small-scale censorship
like a young grad student who comes up
who like raises their hand and says some crazy idea
yes a form of censorship could be i shouldn't use the word censorship
but i think you may just like like de-incentivize
them from no no no this is the way it's been
yeah yeah you're you're a foolish kid don't do it yeah yeah yeah foolish
so in some sense
those wrong ideas
most of the time end up being wrong
but sometimes
i agree with you
so i don't like the word censorship
um
at the very end of the book i i
ended up with a sort of a a plea
or a recommended course of action
and the best way i could
i know
how to deal with this issue that you bring up is if everybody understood
as part of your upbringing in life
something about how your brain works that it builds a model of the world
how it works you know how basically builds that model the world
and that the model is not the real world it's just a model
and it's never going to reflect the entire world
and it can be wrong
and it's easy to be wrong
and here's all the ways you can get the wrong model in your head right
it's not prescribed what's right or wrong just understand that process
if we all understood the process then i got together
and you say i disagree with you jeff and i said lex
i disagree with you that
at least we understand
that we're both trying to model something we both have different information
which leads to our different models
and therefore i shouldn't hold it against you and you shouldn't hold it against me
and we can at least agree that well
what can we look for in in its common ground to test our our beliefs
as opposed to so much as our we raise our kids on dogma
which is this is a fact
and this is a fact
and these people are bad
and
and you know
where ever if everyone knew just to to be skeptical of every belief
and why
and how their brains do that i think we might have a better world
do you think the human mind is able to comprehend reality
so you talk about sort of this creating models that are better
and better
how close do you think we get to to reality there's
so the wildest ideas is like donald hoffman saying we're very far away from reality
do you think we're getting close to reality well
i guess it depends on what you define reality
we are getting we have a model of the world that's very useful
right for basic well for our survival
and our the pleasure whatever right
um
so that's useful
i mean it's really useful
oh we can build planes we can build computers we can do these things right
i don't think
i i don't know the answer to that question
um
i think that's part of the question we're trying to figure out right like
you know obviously if you end up with a theory of everything
that really is a theory of everything
and all of a sudden everything comes into play and there's no room for something else
then you might feel like we have a good model of the world
yeah but we if we have a theory of everything
and somehow
first of all you'll never be able to really conclusively
say it's a theory of everything but say somehow
we are very damn sure it's the theory of everything we understand
what happened at the big bang
and how
just the entirety of the physical process i'm still not sure that gives us
an understanding of the next
many layers of the hierarchy
yeah abstractions that form well also
what if string theory turns out to be true
and then you say well
we have no reality
no modeling what's going on in those other dimensions
that are wrapped into it on each other you're right
or or the multiverse
you know i i honestly don't know
how for us for human interaction for ideas of intelligence
how it helps us to understand that we're made up of vibrating strings that are
like tend to the whatever times smaller than us
yeah i don't you know you could probably build better weapons
and better rockets
but you're not going to be able to understand intelligence
i guess i guess maybe better computers
no you won't be able i think it's just more purely knowledge
you might lead to a better understanding of the of the beginning of the universe
right it might lead to a better understanding of
i don't know i guess i think the acquisition of knowledge has always been one where you
you pursue it for its own pleasure
um
and you don't always know
what is going to make a difference
yeah
you're pleasantly surprised by the the weird things you find do you think
for the for the neocortex in general
do you think there's a lot of innovation to be done on the machine side you know
you use the computer as a metaphor
quite a bit is there a different
types of computer that would help us build
i mean what are the intelligences like the manifestations of intelligent machines
yeah
or is it
oh no it's going to be totally
crazy we have no idea how this is going to look out yet
but you can already see this today we of course remodel these things on traditional computers
and now
now gpus are really popular with with
you know neural networks
and so on
um
but there are companies coming up with fundamentally new physical substrates
that are just really cool i don't know if they're going to work or not
but i think there'll be decades of innovation here
yeah totally do you think the final thing will be messy like our biology is messy
or do you think
um
it's it's the it's the old bird versus airplane question
or do you think we could just build airplanes
yeah
that that fly way better than birds in the same way we can build uh electrical
and
yeah
you know can i can i can i refund
the bird thing a bit because i think it's interesting
people ability misunderstand this the wright brothers
um
the problem they were trying to solve was controlled flight
how to turn an airplane
not how to propel an airplane they weren't worried about that interesting
yeah they already had at that time there was already wing shapes
which they had from studying birds there was already gliders that carry people
the problem is if you put a rudder on the back of a glider
and you turn it the plane falls out of the sky
so the problem was how do you control flight
and they studied birds
and they
actually had birds in captivity
they watched birds in wind tunnels
they observed in the wild
and they discovered the secret was the birds twist their wings when they turn
and so that's what they did on the wright brothers
flyer they had these sticks you would twist
the wing and that was
that was their innovation not their propeller
and today airplanes
still twist their wings
we don't twist the entire
wing we just just the tail end of it
the the the flaps
which is the same thing so today's airplanes fly on the same principles as birds
which is observed by so everyone get that analogy wrong
but let's step back from that right once you understand
the principles of flight you can choose
how to implement them yeah no one's going to use bones
and feathers
and muscles
um
but they do have wings
and we don't flap them we have propellers
so when we have the principles of
of computation that goes on to modeling the world in the brain
we understand those principles very clearly
we have choices on how to implement them and some of them will be biologically
like and some won't
and
um
but i do think there's going to be a huge amount of innovation here
just think about the innovation we're in the computers they had to invent the the transistor
they invented the the silicon ship they had the invent you know then this software
i mean zillions of things they had to do memory systems
um we're gonna do it's gonna be similar well it's interesting that the deep learning
um
the effectiveness of deep learning for a specific
task is driving a lot of innovation in the hardware
which may have effects
for actually allowing us to discover
intelligent systems that operate very differently
or that's much bigger than deep learning yeah interesting
so ultimately
it's good to have an application that's making our life better
now
because the the the capitalist process
if you can make money yeah yeah that works
i mean the other way
i mean neil degrasse tyson writes about this
is the other way we fund science of course is through military
so like yeah conquest
so here here's an interesting thing we're doing on this regard
so we've decided we we used to have a series these biological principles
and we can see how to build these intelligent machines
but we've decided to apply some of these principles to today's machine learning techniques
so one of the we didn't talk about this principle one is sparsity in the brain
um
most of the neurons are active at any point in time as far as and the connectivity
is sparse and that's different than deep learning networks
um
so we've already shown that we can speed up existing deep learning networks
anywhere from 10 to a factor of 100
i mean literally 100
and make it more robust at the same time
so this is commercially very very valuable
um
and
so
you know if we can prove this actually in the larger systems that are commercially applied today
there's a big commercial
desire to do this well sparsity is something that doesn't run really well on existing
hardware it doesn't really run really well on gpus
um
and on cpus
and so
that would be a way of sort of bringing more and
more brain principles into the existing system on a on a commercially valuable basis
another thing we can think we can do is we're going to use the dendrites
models of we
i talked earlier about the the prediction occurring inside of neuron
that that basic property can be applied to existing neural networks
and allow them to learn continuously
which something they don't do today
and so
yeah well we wouldn't model this spikes but the idea that you have
that neuro today's neural networks have something called the point neuron
which is a very simple model of a neuron
and by adding dendrites to them with just one more level of complexity
that's in biological systems you can solve problems in continuous learning
um
and rapid learning
so we're trying to take we're trying to bring the existing field
and we'll see if we can do it we're trying to bring the existing
field of machine learning
commercially
along with us you brought up this idea of keeping you know paying for it commercially
along with us as we move towards the ultimate goal of a true ai system
even small innovations on neural networks are really really exciting
yeah
because it seems like such a trivial model of the brain
and applying different insights
that just even like you said continuous learning
or making it more asynchronous
or maybe making more dynamic
or like incentivizing
making it fast even just from robots
and making it somehow much better
incentivizing sparsity somehow
yeah well if you can make things 100 times faster then there's plenty of incentive
people people spending millions of dollars you know just training some of these networks
now these these transformer networks
let me ask you a big question
how for young people listening to this today in high school
and college
what advice would you give them in terms of which career path to take
and
um
maybe just about life in general
well in my case
um
i didn't start life with any kind of goals
i was when i was going to college
i was like oh what did i say well
maybe i'll do electrical
engineering stuff you know
um
it wasn't like you know today you see some of these young kids are so motivated
they're going to change the world i was like you know whatever
and
um
but then i did fall in love with something
besides my wife but i fell in love with this like
oh my god it would be so cool to understand
how the brain works
and then i
i said to myself that's the most important thing i could work on
i i can't imagine anything more important
because if we understand
how brains work you'd build telescope machines
and they could figure out all the other big questions of the world right
so
and then i said i want to understand
how i work so i fell in love with this idea
and i became passionate about it
and
this is you know a trope people say this but it was it's true
because i was passionate about it i was able to put up almost
so much crap
you know
you know i was i was in that you know i was like person
said you can't do this i was
i was a graduate student at berkeley
when they said you can't study this problem
you know no one's gonna solve this or you can't get funded for it you know
then i went to do you know mobile computing
and it was like people say you can't do that you can't build a cell phone
you know
so
but all along i kept being motivated
because i wanted to work on this problem
i said i want to understand
the brain works and if i got myself
male i got one lifetime
i'm gonna figure it out do the best i can
so by having that
because you know these it's really
as you point out lex it's really hard to
do these things people it's just
there's so many downers along the way
so many ways obstacles are getting your way yeah
i'm sitting here happy all the time but trust me it's not always like that that's
i guess the the happiness
that the the passion is a prerequisite
for surviving the whole
yeah i think so i think that's right
um
and
so i i
don't want to sit to someone and say you know you need to find a passion
and do it no maybe you don't
but if you do find something you're passionate about then
then you can follow it as far as your passion will
let you put up with it do you remember
how you found it this is
how the spark happened
why specifically for me
yeah like because you said it's such an interesting
so like almost like later in life
by later i mean like not in when you were five
yeah you you didn't really know
and then all of a sudden you fell in love with that yeah yeah
there was there was there's two separate events that compounded one another one
when i was probably a teenager might have been 17
or 18.
i made a list of the most interesting problems i could think of
first was why does the universe exist it seems like not existing is more likely
yeah
the second one was well given exists why does it behave the way it does
you know it's laws of physics
y is equal to m c squared not m c cubed you know attention
question i don't know
third one was like what's the origin of life
um
and the fourth one was what's intelligence
and i stopped there i said well that's probably the most interesting one
and i put that aside
um as a teenager
but then when i was 22
and i was reading the
um
no it was excuse me i was 70 it was 1979 excuse me 1979
i was reading
so i was at that time i was 22. i was reading
the september issue of scientific american
which is all about the brain
and then the final essay
was by francis crick who of dna fame
and he had taken his interest to studying the brain now
and he said you know
there's something wrong here he says we got all this data
oh this fact this is 1979 all these facts about the brain tons
and tons of facts about the brain
do we need more facts
or do we just need to think about a way of rearranging
the facts we have maybe we're just not thinking about the problem correctly
you know
because he says this shouldn't be it shouldn't be like this you know
so i read that and i said wow
i said
i don't have to become like an experimental neuroscientist
i could just look at all those facts
and try to and become a theoretician
and try to figure it out
and i said that
i felt like it was something i would be good at
i said i wouldn't be a good experimentalist
i don't have the patience for it
but i'm a good thinker
and i love puzzles
and this is like the biggest
puzzle in the world it's the biggest
puzzle of all time
and i got all the puzzle pieces in front of me
damn that was exciting
and there's something obviously you can't convert it towards it just kind of sparked this passion
and i have that a few times in my life just something
um
yeah just just like you it grabs you
yeah i thought it was something that was both important that i could make a contribution to
yeah
and so all of a sudden it felt like
oh it gave me purpose in life
yeah
you know i honestly
don't think it has to be as big
as one of those four questions
no no i think you can find those things in in the smallest
oh absolutely i'm with
david foster wallace said like the key to life is to be unborable i'm
i think i think it's very
possible to find that intensity of joy in the smallest absolutely
i'm just you asked me my story
yeah yeah i'm actually speaking to the audience
yeah it doesn't have to be those four
you happen to get excited
by one of the bigger questions of
in the universe
but but that even the smallest things
and watching the olympics
now just just giving yourself life giving your life over to the study
and the mastery of a particular sport is fascinating
and
and if if it sparks joy
and passion you're able to in the case of the olympics
basically suffer for like a couple of decades to achieve
i mean you can find joint passion just being a parent
i mean
yeah
yeah the the parenting one is funny
so i always not always
but for a long time wanted kids
and get married
and stuff and especially that has to do with the fact that
i've seen a lot of people
that i respect
get a whole other level of joy
from kids
and you know
at first is like
your thinking is well
like i don't have enough time in the day
right if i have this passion
which is true
yes
but like if i want to solve intelligence
how is this kids situation gonna help me
but then you realize
that you know like you said the things that sparks joy
and it's very possible that kids
can provide even a greater
or deeper more meaningful joy than those bigger questions
yeah when they they enrich each other
and that that seemed like um obviously when i was younger it's probably a counter-intuitive notion
because there's only so many hours in the day
but then life is finite
and you have to pick the things that give give you joy
yeah
but you know also you understand you you can be patient too i mean it's finite
but we do have you know whatever 50 years or so it's not so long
yeah
so
so in my case
you know in my case
i had to give up on my dream of the neuroscience
because i i was a graduate student at berkeley
and they told me i couldn't do this and i couldn't get funded
and you know
and
and so i went back in
and went back in the computing industry for a number of years
i thought it would be four but it turned out to be more
but i said but i said i'll come back
you know i definitely
i'm definitely gonna come back i know i'm gonna do this computer
stuff for a while but i'm definitely
coming back everyone knows that
and it's they moved like raising
kids well yeah you still
you have to spend a lot of time with your kids it's fun enjoyable
um
but that doesn't mean you have to give up on other dreams
it just means that you
may have to wait a week or two to work on that next idea well
you talked about the
the the darker side of me disappointing sides of human nature that we're
hoping to overcome
so that we don't destroy ourselves i tend to put a lot of value in um
the broad general concept of love of the human capacity to
um of compassion
towards each other of just kindness whatever that longing of like just the human human to human connection
yeah it connects back to our initial discussion i tend to
see a lot of value in this collective intelligence
aspect i think some of the magic of human civilization
happens when there's a party is not as fun when it you're alone
yeah i totally agree with you on these issues do you think
from a neurocortex perspective
what role does love play in the human condition
well those are two separate things from a new project
i don't think it doesn't impact our thinking about human about the neocortex
from a human condition point of view i think it's core
um
i mean we get
so much pleasure out of loving people
and helping people
um
so
you know i can i'll rack
it up to old brain
stuff and maybe you can throw it under the the bust of evolution
if you want
um
that's fine
um it doesn't impact how i think about how we model the world
but from a humanity point of view i think it's essential
well i tend to give it to the new brain
and also i tend to think that some of aspects of that need to be engineered into ai systems
both in their
ability to have compassion for other humans
and their ability to maximize
love in the world between humans
so i'm more thinking about the social network
so like whenever there's a deep integration between ai systems
and humans
so specific applications
where it's ai
and humans i think that's something that
often not talked about in terms of um
metrics
over which you
try to maximize
like which metric to maximize in a system it seems like one of the most powerful
things in societies is the capacity
to work it's fascinating i think it's it's a great way of thinking about it
you know i have
i have been thinking more of these fundamental
mechanisms in the brain as opposed to the social interaction between
the interaction between humans
and ai systems in the future
which is
and i think if you think about that you're absolutely right
um
but that's that's a complex system i can have intelligent systems that don't have that component
but they're not interacting with people you know they're just running something
or building a building someplace
or something i don't know
um
but if you think about interacting with humans
yeah it's it's gonna
and then but it has to be engineered
in there i don't think it's gonna appear on its own
that's a good question i
yeah well we could
in terms of uh from a reinforcement learning perspective
whether the darker sides of human nature
or the better angels of our nature win out
yeah statistically speaking i don't know i tend to be optimistic
and hope that love wins out in the end
um you've done a lot of incredible stuff
and your book is driving towards this fourth question that you started with on the nature of intelligence
what do you hope your legacy
for people reading a hundred years from now
how do you hope they remember your work
how do you hope they remember this book
well i think as an entrepreneur
or scientist
or any human who's trying to accomplish some things
i have a view that
really all you can do is accelerate the inevitable
um
yeah it's like you know
if we didn't figure out
if we didn't study the brain
someone else would study the brain
if you know if elon just
didn't make electric cars someone else would do it eventually
and if you know if thomas anderson
didn't invent a light bulb we wouldn't be using candles today
so
what you can do as an individual is you can accelerate
something that's beneficial
and make it happen sooner than whatever that's that's really it that's all you can do
um you can't create a new reality that it wasn't gonna happen
um
so from that perspective
um i would hope that our work not just me but our work in general
um people would look back and said
hey they really helped make this better future happen sooner
um they
you know they helped us understand
the nature of false beliefs sooner than
we met up they made it now we're so happy
that we have these intelligent machines
doing these things helping us
that that maybe that solved the climate change problem
and they made it happen sooner
so i think that's the best i would hope for some would say those guys just
moved the needle forward a little bit in time
well i do it it feels like the progress of human civilization is not
is there's a lot of trajectories
and
if you have individuals that accelerate
towards one direction that helps steer human civilization
so i think in this long stretch of time all
all trajectories will be traveled
but i think it's nice for this particular civilization
on earth to travel
down one that's not yeah well i think you're right i mean look we have the
take the whole period of you know world war ii nazism
or something like that well that was a bad sidestep right
went over there for a while
but you know there is the optimistic view about life that
um that ultimately it does converge
in a positive way it progresses ultimately even if we have years of darkness
um
so
yeah
so i think you can perhaps
that's accelerating the positive it could also mean eliminating some bad missteps along the way too
um
but
but i i'm
an optimistic in that way i was like you know despite we talked about the end of civilization
you know i i think we're gonna live for a long time i hope we are
um
i think our society in the future is gonna be better we're gonna have less discord
we're gonna have less people killing
each other you know we'll solve
you know we'll make the
they'll live in some sort of way that's compatible with the carrying capacity of the earth
um i'm optimistic these things will happen
and all we can do is try to get there sooner
and at the very least if we do destroy ourselves we'll have a few satellites
i will that will tell alien civilization that we were once
or maybe our future you know future inhabitants of earth you know imagine
you know
the planet of the apes scenario you know we kill ourselves in a you know million
years from now or billion years from now there's another species
on the planet curious
creatures were once here
yeah
um jeff thank you so much for your work
and
um
thank you so much for talking to me once again
well it's great i love what you do i love your podcast
you have the most interesting people me aside
so
it's a real service i think you do for
a very broader sense for humanity i think thanks jeff all right pleasure
thanks for listening to this conversation with jeff hawkins
and thank you to codeacademy
bio optimizers expressvpn asleep
and blinkist check them out in the description to support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words from albert camus
an intellectual is someone whose mind watches itself
i like this
because i'm happy to be both haves the watcher
and the watched
can they be brought together
this is a practical question we must try to answer
thank you for listening
and hope to see you next
time
you