Today I have the honor of chatting with Jeff  Dean and Noam Shazeer. Jeff is Google's Chief
Scientist, and through his 25 years at the  company, he has worked on basically the most
transformative systems in modern computing: from  MapReduce, BigTable, Tensorflow, AlphaChip –
genuinely, the list doesn't end – Gemini now. And Noam is the single person most responsible
for the current AI revolution. He has been  the inventor or co-inventor of all the main
architectures and techniques that are used  for modern LLMs: from the Transformer itself,
to Mixture of Experts, to Mesh Tensorflow, to  many other things. And they are two of the three
co-leads of Gemini at Google DeepMind.  Awesome. Thanks so much for coming on.
Thank you. Super excited to be here. Okay, first question. Both of you
have been at Google for 25, or close to 25,  years. At some point early on in the company,
you probably understood how everything worked.  When did that stop being the case? Do you feel
like there was a clear moment that happened? I joined, this was like, end of 2000, and they
had this thing: everybody gets a mentor. I knew  nothing. I would just ask my mentor everything,
and my mentor knew everything. It  turned out my mentor was Jeff.
It was not the case that everyone at  Google knew everything. It was just the
case that Jeff knew everything because  he had basically written everything.
You're very kind. I think as companies grow, you  kind of go through these phases. When I joined,
we were 25 people, 26 people, something like that.  So you eventually you learned everyone's name,
and even though we were growing, you kept  track of all the people who were joining.
At some point, you lose track of everyone's  name in the company, but you still know everyone
working on software engineering things. Then  you lose track of all the names of people in
the software engineering group, but you at  least know all the different projects that
everyone's working on. Then at some point, the  company gets big enough that you get an email
that Project Platypus is launching on Friday, and  you're like, "What the heck is Project Platypus?"
Usually it's a very good surprise.  You're like, "Wow, Project
Platypus!" I had no idea we were doing that. But I think it is good to keep track of what's
going on in the company, even at a very high  level, even if you don't know every last detail.
And it's good to know lots of people throughout  the company so that you can go ask someone for
more details or figure out who to talk to. With  one level of indirection, you can usually find
the right person in the company if you have a good  network of people that you've built up over time.
How did Google recruit you, by the way? I kind of reached out to them, actually.
And Noam, how did you get recruited? I actually saw Google at a job fair in 1999,
and I assumed that it was already this huge  company, that there was no point in joining,
because everyone I knew used Google.  I guess that was because I was a grad
student at Berkeley at the time. I guess I've  dropped out of grad programs a few times.
It turns out that actually it wasn't really that  large. It turns out that I did not apply in 1999,
but just kind of sent them a resume on a whim in  2000, because I figured it was my favorite search
engine, and figured I should apply to multiple  places for a job. But then it turned out to be
really fun, it looked like a bunch of smart people  doing good stuff. They had this really nice crayon
chart on the wall of the daily number of search  queries that somebody had just been maintaining.
It looked very exponential. I thought, "These guys  are going to be very successful, and it looks like
they have a lot of good problems to work on." So  I was like, "Okay, maybe I'll go work there for
a little while and then have enough money to just  go work on AI for as long as I want after that."
Yeah, yeah. In a way you did that, right? Yeah, it totally worked out
exactly according to plan. You were thinking about AI in 1999?
Yeah, this was like 2000. Yeah, I remember in  grad school, a friend of mine at the time had
told me that his New Year's resolution for 2000  was to live to see the year 3000, and that he
was going to achieve this by inventing AI. I  was like, "Oh, that sounds like a good idea."
I didn't get the idea at the time that you could  go do it at a big company. But I figured, "Hey,
a bunch of people seem to be making a ton of money  at startups. Maybe I'll just make some money,
and then I'll have enough to live on and just  work on AI research for a long time." But yeah,
it actually turned out that Google  was a terrific place to work on AI.
One of the things I like about Google is our  ambition has always been sort of something
that would require pretty advanced AI. Because  I think organizing the world's information and
making it universally accessible and useful,  actually there is a really broad mandate in
there. It's not like the company was going  to do this one little thing and stay doing
that. And also you could see that what we  were doing initially was in that direction,
but you could do so much more in that direction. How has Moore's Law over the last two or three
decades changed the kinds of considerations you  have to take on board when you design new systems,
when you figure out what projects  are feasible? What are still the
limitations? What are things you can now  do that you obviously couldn't do before?
I think of it as actually changing quite a bit  in the last couple of decades. Two decades ago
to one decade ago, it was awesome because  you just wait, and like 18 months later,
you get much faster hardware, and you don't have  to do anything. And then more recently, I feel
like the general-purpose CPU-based machine scaling  has not been as good, like the fabrication process
improvements are now taking three years instead of  every two years. The architectural improvements in
multi-core processors and so on are not giving you  the same boost that we were getting 20 to 10 years
ago. But I think at the same time, we're seeing  much more specialized computational devices,
like machine learning accelerators, TPUs,  and very ML-focused GPUs, more recently,
are making it so that we can actually get really  high performance and good efficiency out of the
more modern kinds of computations we want to run  that are different than a twisty pile of C++ code
trying to run Microsoft Office or something. It feels like the algorithms are following the
hardware. Basically, what's happened is that  at this point, arithmetic is very, very cheap,
and moving data around is comparatively much  more expensive. So pretty much all of deep
learning has taken off roughly because of that.  You can build it out of matrix multiplications
that are N cubed operations and N squared  bytes of data communication basically.
Well, I would say that the pivot  to hardware oriented around that
was an important transition,  because before that, we had CPUs
and GPUs that were not especially well-suited for  deep learning. And then we started to build TPUs
at Google that were really just reduced-precision  linear algebra machines, and then once you
have that then you want to exploit it. It seems like it's all about identifying
opportunity costs. Like, okay, this is something  like Larry Page, I think, used to always say:
"Our second biggest cost is taxes, and our biggest  cost is opportunity costs." If he didn't say that,
then I've been misquoting him for years. But basically it’s like, what is the opportunity
that you have that you're missing out on? In  this case, I guess it was that you've got all
of this chip area, and you're putting a very  small number of arithmetic units on it. Fill
the thing up with arithmetic units! You could have  orders of magnitude more arithmetic getting done.
Now, what else has to change? Okay, the  algorithms and the data flow and everything else.
And, oh, by the way, the arithmetic can  be really low precision, so then you
can squeeze even more multiplier units in. Noam, I want to follow up on what you said,
that the algorithms have been following the  hardware. If you imagine a counterfactual
world where, suppose that the cost of  memory had declined more than arithmetic,
or just invert the dynamic you saw. Okay, data flow is extremely cheap,
and arithmetic is not. What would AI look like today?
You'd have a lot more lookups  into very large memories.
Yeah, it might look more like AI looked like 20  years ago but in the opposite direction. I'm not
sure. I guess I joined Google Brain in 2012. I  left Google for a few years, happened to go back
for lunch to visit my wife, and we happened to sit  down next to Jeff and the early Google Brain team.
I thought, "Wow, that's a smart group of people." I think I said, "You should think about
deep neural nets. We're making  some pretty good progress there."
"That sounds fun." Okay, so I jumped back in…  I wooed him back, it was great.
..to join Jeff, that was like 2012. I seem  to join Google every 12 years: I rejoined
Google in 2000, 2012, and 2024. What's going to happen in 2036?
I don't know. I guess we shall see. What are the trade-offs that you're
considering changing for future versions of TPU to  integrate how you're thinking about algorithms?
I think one general trend is we're getting  better at quantizing or having much more
reduced precision models. We started with TPUv1,  and we weren't even quite sure we could quantize
and model for serving with eight-bit integers.  But we sort of had some early evidence that
seemed like it might be possible. So we're like,  "Great, let's build the whole chip around that."
And then over time, I think you've seen people  able to use much lower precision for training
as well. But also the inference precision has  gone. People are now using INT4 or FP4, which
sounded like, if you said to someone like we're  going to use FP4, like a supercomputing floating
point person 20 years ago, they'd be like, "What?  That's crazy. We like 64 bits in our floats."
Or even below that, some people are quantizing  models to two bits or one bit, and I think
that's a trend that definitely – One bit? Just like a zero-or-one?
Yeah, just a 0-1. And then you have a sign  bit for a group of bits or something.
It really has to be a co-design thing because,  if the algorithm designer doesn't realize
that you can get greatly improved performance,  throughput, with the lower precision, of course,
the algorithm designer is going to say, "Of  course, I don't want low precision. That
introduces risk." And then it adds irritation. Then if you ask the chip designer, "Okay,
what do you want to build?" And then they'll ask  the person who's writing the algorithms today,
who's going to say, "No, I don't like  quantization. It's irritating." So you actually
need to basically see the whole picture and figure  out, "Oh, wait a minute, we can increase our
throughput-to-cost ratio by a lot by quantizing." Then you're like, yes, quantization is irritating,
but your model is going to be three times  faster, so you're going to have to deal.
Through your careers, at various times,  you’ve worked on things that have an
uncanny resemblance to what we're actually  using now for generative AI. In 1990, Jeff,
your senior thesis was about backpropagation.  And in 2007- this is the thing that I didn’t
realise until I was prepping for this episode  – in 2007 you guys trained a two trillion
token N-gram model for language modeling. Just walk me through when you were developing that
model. Was this kind of thing in your head? What  did you think you guys were doing at the time?
Let me start with the undergrad thesis. I got  introduced to neural nets in one section of one
class on parallel computing that I was taking  in my senior year. I needed to do a thesis to
graduate, an honors thesis. So I approached  the professor and I said, "Oh, it'd be really
fun to do something around neural nets." So, he and I decided I would implement
a couple of different ways of parallelizing  backpropagation training for neural nets in 1990.
I called them something funny in my thesis, like  "pattern partitioning" or something. But really,
I implemented a model parallelism and data  parallelism on a 32-processor Hypercube machine.
In one, you split all the examples into  different batches, and every CPU has a copy
of the model. In the other one, you pipeline  a bunch of examples along to processors that
have different parts of the model. I compared  and contrasted them, and it was interesting.
I was really excited about the abstraction  because it felt like neural nets were the right
abstraction. They could solve tiny toy problems  that no other approach could solve at the time.
I thought, naive me, that 32 processors would  be able to train really awesome neural nets.
But it turned out we needed about a million  times more compute before they really started
to work for real problems, but then starting  in the late 2008, 2009, 2010 timeframe,
we started to have enough compute, thanks  to Moore's law, to actually make neural
nets work for real things. That was kind of  when I re-entered, looking at neural nets.
But prior to that, in 2007... Sorry, actually could I ask about this?
Oh yeah, sure. First of all,
unlike other artifacts of academia, it's actually  like four pages, and you can just read it.
It was four pages and then 30 pages of C code. But it's just a well-produced artifact. Tell
me about how the 2007 paper came together. Oh yeah, so that, we had a machine translation
research team at Google led by Franz Och,  who had joined Google maybe a year before,
and a bunch of other people. Every year they  competed in a DARPA contest on translating
a couple of different languages to English, I  think, Chinese to English and Arabic to English.
The Google team had submitted an entry, and the  way this works is you get 500 sentences on Monday,
and you have to submit the answer on Friday. I  saw the results of this, and we'd won the contest
by a pretty substantial margin measured in Bleu  score, which is a measure of translation quality.
So I reached out to Franz, the head of this  winning team. I'm like, "This is great,
when are we going to launch it?" And he's like,  "Oh, well, we can't launch this. It's not really
very practical because it takes 12 hours to  translate a sentence." I'm like, "Well, that
seems like a long time. How could we fix that?" It turned out they'd not really designed it for
high throughput, obviously. It was doing  100,000 disk seeks in a large language
model that they sort of computed statistics  over – I wouldn't say "trained" really – for
each word that it wanted to translate. Obviously, doing 100,000 disk seeks is
not super speedy. But I said, "Okay, well, let's  dive into this." So I spent about two or three
months with them, designing an in-memory  compressed representation of N-gram data.
We were using- an N-gram is basically statistics  for how often every N-word sequence occurs in a
large corpus, so you basically have, in this case,  we had 2 trillion words. Most N-gram models of the
day were using two-grams or maybe three-grams,  but we decided we would use five-grams.
So, how often every five-word sequence occurs in  basically as much of the web as we could process
in that day. Then you have a data structure that  says, "Okay, 'I really like this restaurant'
occurs 17 times in the web, or something. And so I built a data structure that would let
you store all those in memory on 200 machines  and then have sort of a batched API where you
could say, "Here are the 100,000 things I need  to look up in this round for this word," and
we'd give you them all back in parallel.  That enabled us to go from taking a night
to translate a sentence to basically doing  something in 100 milliseconds or something.
There's this list of Jeff Dean facts, like Chuck  Norris facts. For example, that “for Jeff Dean,
NP equals "no problemo."” One of them, it's  funny because now that I hear you say it,
actually, it's kind of true. One of them is, "The  speed of light was 35 miles an hour until Jeff
Dean decided to optimize it over a weekend."  Just going from 12 hours to 100 milliseconds,
I got to do the orders of magnitude there. All of these are very flattering. They're
pretty funny. They're like an April  Fool's joke gone awry by my colleagues.
Obviously, in retrospect, this idea that you  can develop a latent representation of the
entire internet through just considering the  relationships between words is like: yeah,
this is large language models. This is Gemini.  At the time, was it just a translation idea,
or did you see that as being the beginning  of a different kind of paradigm?
I think once we built that for translation,  the serving of large language models started
to be used for other things, like  completion... you start to type,
and it suggests what completions make sense. So it was definitely the start of a lot of uses of
language models in Google. And Noam has worked on  a number of other things at Google, like spelling
correction systems that use language models. That was like 2000, 2001, and I think
it was all in-memory on one machine. Yeah, I think it was one machine. His spelling
correction system he built in 2001 was amazing.  He sent out this demo link to the whole company.
I just tried every butchered spelling  of every few-word query I could get,
like “scrumbled uggs Bundict"— I remember that one, yeah yeah.
—instead of “scrambled eggs benedict”,  and it just nailed it every time.
Yeah, I guess that was language modeling. But at the time, when you were developing
these systems, did you have this sense of, “look,  you make these things more and more sophisticated,
don't consider five words, consider  100 words, 1,000 words, then the
latent representation is intelligence”.  Basically when did that insight hit?
Not really. I don't think I ever felt  like, okay, N-gram models are going to–
–sweep the world– –yeah: “be” artificial intelligence.
I think at the time, a lot of people were excited  about Bayesian networks. That seemed exciting.
Definitely seeing those early neural  language models, both the magic in that,
“okay, this is doing something extremely cool”  and also, it just struck me as the best problem
in the world in that for one, it is very,  very simple to state: give me a probability
distribution over the next word. Also, there's  roughly infinite training data out there. There's
the text of the web; you have trillions of  training examples of unsupervised data.
Yeah, or self-supervised. Self-supervised, yeah.
It's nice because you then have the right  answer, and then you can train on all but
the current word and try to predict the current  word. It's this amazing ability to just learn
from observations of the world. And then it's AI complete. If you
can do a great job of that, then  you can pretty much do anything.
There's this interesting discussion in the history  of science about whether ideas are just in the
air and there's a sort of inevitability to big  ideas, or whether they're sort of plucked out of
some tangential direction. In this case, this way  in which we're laying it out very logically, does
that imply basically, how inevitable does this... It does feel like it's in the air. There were
definitely some, there was like the neural Turing  machine, a bunch of ideas around attention,
like having these key-value stores that could  be useful in neural networks to focus on things.
I think in some sense, it was in the air, and  in some sense, you need some group to go do it.
I like to think of a lot of ideas as being  partially in the air, where there are a few
different, maybe separate research ideas that  one is squinting at when you’re trying to solve
a new problem. You draw on those for some  inspiration, and then there's some aspect
that is not solved, and you need to figure  out how to solve that. The combination of
some morphing of the things that already exist  and some new things lead to some new breakthrough
or new research result that didn't exist before. Are there key moments that stand out to you where
you're looking at a research area, you come up  with this idea, and you have this feeling of,
"Holy shit, I can't believe that worked?"  One thing I remember was in the early days of
the Brain team. We were focused on “let’s see if  we could build some infrastructure that lets us
train really, really big neural nets”. At that  time, we didn't have GPUs in our data centers;
we just had CPUs. But we know how  to make lots of CPUs work together.
So we built a system that enabled us to train  pretty large neural nets through both model
and data parallelism. We had a system for  unsupervised learning on 10 million randomly
selected YouTube frames. It was a spatially local  representation, so it would build up unsupervised
representations based on trying to reconstruct  the thing from the high-level representations.
We got that working and training on 2,000  computers using 16,000 cores. After a little
while, that model was actually able to build a  representation at the highest level where one
neuron would get excited by images of cats. It  had never been told what a cat was, but it had
seen enough examples of them in the training data  of head-on facial views of cats that that neuron
would turn on for that and not for much else. Similarly, you'd have other ones for human faces
and backs of pedestrians, and this kind of  thing. That was kind of cool because it's
from unsupervised learning principles, building  up these really high-level representations. Then
we were able to get very good results on the  supervised ImageNet 20,000 category challenge
that advanced the state of the art by 60% relative  improvement, which was quite good at the time.
That neural net was probably 50x bigger than one  that had been trained previously, and it got good
results. So that sort of said to me, "Hey,  actually scaling up neural nets seems like,
I thought it would be a good idea and it seems  to be, so we should keep pushing on that."
These examples illustrate how these AI systems  fit into what you were just mentioning:
that Google is fundamentally a company that  organizes information. AI, in this context,
is finding relationships between information,  between concepts, to help get ideas to you faster,
information you want to you faster. Now we're moving with current AI models.
Obviously, you can use BERT in Google  Search and you can ask these questions.
They are still good at information retrieval,  but more fundamentally, they can write your
entire code base for you and do actual work,  which goes beyond just information retrieval.
So how are you thinking about that? Is  Google still an information retrieval
company if you're building an AGI?  An AGI can do information retrieval,
but it can do many other things as well. I think we're an "organize the world's
information" company, and that's broader  than information retrieval. Maybe:
“organizing and creating new information  from some guidance you give it”.
"Can you help me write a letter to my veterinarian  about my dog? It's got these symptoms," and it'll
draft that. Or, "Can you feed in this  video, and can you produce a summary of
what's happening in the video every few minutes?" I think our multimodal capabilities are showing
that it's more than just text. It's about  understanding the world in all the different
modalities that information exists in, both  human ones but also non-human-oriented ones,
like weird lidar sensors on autonomous vehicles,  or genomic information, or health information.
And then, how do you extract and transform that  into useful insights for people and make use
of that in helping them do all kinds of things  they want to do? Sometimes it's, "I want to be
entertained by chatting with a chatbot." Sometimes  it's, "I want answers to this really complicated
question, there is no single source to retrieve  from." You need to pull information from 100 web
pages, figure out what's going on, and make an  organized, synthesized version of that data.
Then dealing with multimodal things  or coding-related problems. I think
it's super exciting what these models are  capable of, and they're improving fast, so
I'm excited to see where we go. I am also excited to see where we go.
I think definitely organizing information  is clearly a trillion-dollar opportunity,
but a trillion dollars is not cool anymore.  What's cool is a quadrillion dollars.
Obviously the idea is not to just  pile up some giant pile of money,
but it's to create value in the world, and so much  more value can be created when these systems can
actually go and do something for you, write your  code, or figure out problems that you wouldn't
have been able to figure out yourself. To do that at scale, we're going to have
to be very, very flexible and dynamic as we  improve the capabilities of these models.
Yeah, I'm pretty excited about a lot of  fundamental research questions that come
about because you see something that we're  doing could be substantially improved if
we tried this approach or things in this rough  direction. Maybe that'll work, maybe it won't.
But I also think there's value in seeing what  we could achieve for end-users and then how
can we work backwards from that to actually build  systems that are able to do that. As one example:
organizing information, that  should mean any information
in the world should be usable by anyone,  regardless of what language they speak.
And that I think we've done some amount  of, but it's not nearly the full vision of,
"No matter what language you speak, out of  thousands of languages, we can make any piece
of content available to you and make it usable by  you. Any video could be watched in any language."
I think that would be pretty awesome. We're not  quite there yet, but that's definitely things
I see on the horizon that should be possible. Speaking of different architectures you might try,
I know one thing you're working on right now is  longer context. If you think of Google Search,
it's got the entire index of the internet in  its context, but it's a very shallow search.
And then obviously language models have limited  context right now, but they can really think.
It's like dark magic, in-context learning.  It can really think about what it’s seeing.
How do you think about what it would  be like to merge something like Google
Search and something like in-context learning? Yeah, I'll take a first stab at it because – I've
thought about this for a bit. One of the things  you see with these models is they're quite good,
but they do hallucinate and have factuality issues  sometimes. Part of that is you've trained on, say,
tens of trillions of tokens, and you've  stirred all that together in your tens
or hundreds of billions of parameters. But it's all a bit squishy because you've
churned all these tokens together. The model  has a reasonably clear view of that data,
but it sometimes gets confused and will  give the wrong date for something.
Whereas information in the context  window, in the input of the model,
is really sharp and clear because we have this  really nice attention mechanism in transformers.
The model can pay attention to things, and it  knows the exact text or the exact frames of the
video or audio or whatever that it's processing. Right now, we have models that can deal with
millions of tokens of context, which is quite a  lot. It's hundreds of pages of PDF, or 50 research
papers, or hours of video, or tens of hours  of audio, or some combination of those things,
which is pretty cool. But it would be really nice  if the model could attend to trillions of tokens.
Could it attend to the entire internet and  find the right stuff for you? Could it attend
to all your personal information for you?  I would love a model that has access to all
my emails, all my documents, and all my photos. When I ask it to do something, it can sort of make
use of that, with my permission, to help solve  what it is I'm wanting it to do. But that's going
to be a big computational challenge because the  naive attention algorithm is quadratic. You can
barely make it work on a fair bit of hardware for  millions of tokens, but there's no hope of making
that just naively go to trillions of tokens. So, we need a whole bunch of interesting
algorithmic approximations to what you  would really want: a way for the model
to attend conceptually to lots and lots  more tokens, trillions of tokens. Maybe
we can put all of the Google code base  in context for every Google developer,
all the world's source code in context for any  open-source developer. That would be amazing.
It would be incredible. The beautiful  thing about model parameters is they are
quite memory-efficient at memorizing facts.  You can probably memorize on the order of
one fact or something per model parameter. Whereas if you have some token in context,
there are lots of keys and values at  every layer. It could be a kilobyte,
a megabyte of memory per token. You take a word and you blow it up
to 10 kilobytes or something. Yes. There's actually a lot of
innovation going on around, okay, A, how  do you minimize that? And B, what words
do you need to have there? Are there better  ways of accessing bits of that information?
Jeff seems like the right person to  figure this out. Okay, what does our
memory hierarchy look like from the SRAM all  the way up to data center worldwide level?
I want to talk more about the thing you mentioned  about: look, Google is a company with lots of
code and lots of examples. If you just think  about that one use case and what that implies,
so you've got the Google monorepo. Maybe you  figure out the long context thing, you can put
the whole thing in context, or you fine-tune  on it. Why hasn't this been already done?
You can imagine the amount of code  that Google has proprietary access to,
even if you're just using it internally to make  your developers more efficient and productive.
To be clear, we have actually already done  further training on a Gemini model on our
internal code base for our internal developers.  But that's different than attending to all of
it because it sort of stirs together the  code base into a bunch of parameters, and I
think having it in context makes things clearer. But even the further trained model internally is
incredibly useful. Sundar, I think, has said that  25% of the characters that we're checking into our
code base these days are generated by our AI-based  coding models with kind of human oversight.
How do you imagine, in the next year or two, based  on the capabilities you see around the horizon,
your own personal work? What will it be like to  be a researcher at Google? You have a new idea
or something. With the way in which you're  interacting with these models in a year,
what does that look like? Well, I assume we will have
these models a lot better and hopefully  be able to be much, much more productive.
Yeah, in addition to kind of research-y context,  anytime you're seeing these models used,
I think they're able to make software  developers more productive because they
can kind of take a high-level spec or sentence  description of what you want done and give a
pretty reasonable first cut at that. From  a research perspective, maybe you can say,
"I'd really like you to explore this kind of idea  similar to the one in this paper, but maybe let's
try making it convolutional or something." If you could do that and have the system
automatically generate a bunch of experimental  code, and maybe you look at it and you're like,
"Yeah, that looks good, run that." That  seems like a nice dream direction to go in.
It seems plausible in the next year or two years  that you might make a lot of progress on that.
It seems under-hyped because you could  have literally millions of extra employees,
and you can immediately check their output,  the employees can check each other's output,
hey immediately stream tokens. Sorry, I didn't mean to underhype
it. I think it's super exciting. I just don't  like to hype things that aren't done yet.
I do want to play with this idea more because  it seems like a big deal if you have something
kind of like an autonomous software engineer,  especially from the perspective of a researcher
who's like, "I want to build the system." Okay,  so let's just play with this idea. As somebody who
has worked on developing transformative systems  through your careers, the idea that instead of
having to code something like whatever today's  equivalent of MapReduce is or Tensorflow is,
just like, "Here's how I want a distributed  AI library to look. Write it up for me."
Do you imagine you could be 10x more  productive? 100x more productive?
I was pretty impressed. I think it was on  Reddit that I saw we have a new experimental
coding model that's much better at coding and math  and so on. Someone external tried it, and they
basically prompted it and said, "I'd like you to  implement a SQL processing database system with no
external dependencies, and please do that in C." From what the person said, it actually did
a quite good job. It generated a  SQL parser and a tokenizer and a
query planning system and some storage format  for the data on disk and actually was able to
handle simple queries. From that prompt, which  is like a paragraph of text or something, to
get even an initial cut at that seems like a big  boost in productivity for software developers.
I think you might end up with other kinds of  systems that maybe don't try to do that in a
single semi-interactive, "respond in 40 seconds"  kind of thing but might go off for 10 minutes and
might interrupt you after five minutes saying,  "I've done a lot of this, but now I need to get
some input. Do you care about handling video or  just images or something?" That seems like you'll
need ways of managing the workflow if you have  a lot of these background activities happening.
Can you talk more about that? What  interface do you imagine we might need
if you could literally have millions of employees  you could spin up, hundreds of thousands of
employees you could spin up on command, who  are able to type incredibly fast, and who-
It's almost like you go from 1930s trading of  tickets or something to now modern Jane Street
or something. You need some interface to keep  track of all this that's going on, for the AIs
to integrate into this big monorepo and leverage  their own strengths, for humans to keep track of
what's happening. Basically what is it like to be  Jeff or Noam in three years working day-to-day?
It might be kind of similar to what we have now  because we already have sort of parallelization
as a major issue. We have lots and lots of really,  really brilliant machine learning researchers, and
we want them to all work together and build AI. So actually, the parallelization among people
might be similar to parallelization among  machines. I think definitely it should be good
for things that require a lot of exploration,  like, "Come up with the next breakthrough."
If you have a brilliant idea that is  just certain to work in the ML domain,
then it has a 2% chance of working if  you're brilliant. Mostly these things fail,
but if you try 100 things or 1,000 things or a  million things, then you might hit on something
amazing. We have plenty of compute. Like modern  top labs these days have probably a million times
as much compute as it took to train Transformer. Yeah, actually, so that's a really interesting
idea. Suppose in the world today there are  on the order of 10,000 AI researchers in this
community coming up with a breakthrough- Probably more than that. There were
15,000 at NeurIPS last week. Wow.
100,000, I don't know. Yeah, maybe. Sorry.
No, no, it's good to have the correct order  of magnitude. The odds that this community
every year comes up with a breakthrough on  the scale of a Transformer is, let's say,
10%. Now suppose this community is  a thousand times bigger, and it is,
in some sense, like this sort of parallel search  of better architectures, better techniques.
Do we just get like- A breakthrough a day?
-breakthroughs every year or every day? Maybe. Sounds potentially good.
But does that feel like what ML research is like?  If you are able to try all these experiments…
It's a good question, because I don't know  that folks haven't been doing that as much.
We definitely have lots of great ideas  coming along. Everyone seems to want to
run their experiment at maximum scale,  but I think that's a human problem.
It's very helpful to have a 1/1000th scale  problem and then vet 100,000 ideas on that,
and then scale up the ones that seem promising. So, one thing the world might not be taking
seriously: people are aware that it's  exponentially harder to make a model that's 100x
bigger. It's 100x more compute, right? So people  are worried that it's an exponentially harder
problem to go from Gemini 2 to 3, or so forth. But maybe people aren't aware of this other
trend where Gemini 3 is coming up with all these  different architectural ideas, trying them out,
and you see what works, and you're constantly  coming up with algorithmic progress that makes
training the next one easier and easier.  How far could you take that feedback loop?
I think one thing people should be aware  of is that the improvements from generation
to generation of these models often are  partially driven by hardware and larger scale,
but equally and perhaps even more so driven  by major algorithmic improvements and major
changes in the model architecture, the training  data mix, and so on, that really makes the model
better per flop that is applied to the model,  so I think that's a good realization. Then
I think if we have automated exploration  of ideas, we'll be able to vet a lot more
ideas and bring them into the actual production  training for next generations of these models.
That's going to be really helpful because  that's sort of what we're currently doing
with a lot of brilliant machine learning  researchers: looking at lots of ideas,
winnowing ones that seem to work well at small  scale, seeing if they work well at medium scale,
bringing them into larger scale experiments, and  then settling on adding a whole bunch of new and
interesting things to the final model recipe.  If we can do that 100 times faster through those
machine learning researchers just gently steering  a more automated search process, rather than
hand-babysitting lots of experiments themselves,  that's going to be really, really good.
The one thing that doesn't speed up is experiments  at the largest scale. You still end up doing these
N = 1 experiments. Really, you just try to  put a bunch of brilliant people in the room,
have them stare at the thing, and figure out  why this is working, why this is not working.
For that, more hardware is a good  solution. And better hardware.
Yes, we're counting on you. So, naively, there's this software,
there's this algorithmic side improvement that  future AI can make. There's also the stuff
you're working on. I'll let you describe it. But if you get into a situation where just from
a software level, you can be making better and  better chips in a matter of weeks and months,
and better AIs can presumably do that better,  how does this feedback loop not just end up in,
Gemini 3 taking two years, then Gemini 4 is-  or the equivalent level jump is now six months,
then level five is three months, then one month?  You get to superhuman intelligence much more
rapidly than you might naively think, because  of this software, both on the hardware side and
from the algorithmic side improvements. I've been pretty excited lately about how
we could dramatically speed up the chip design  process. As we were talking earlier, the current
way in which you design a chip takes you roughly  18 months to go from "we should build a chip" to
something that you then hand over to TSMC and then  TSMC takes four months to fab it, and then you get
it back and you put it in your data centers. So that's a pretty lengthy cycle, and the fab
time in there is a pretty small portion of it  today. But if you could make that the dominant
portion, so that instead of taking 12 to 18  months to design the chip with 150 people,
you could shrink that to a few people  with a much more automated search process,
exploring the whole design space of chips and  getting feedback from all aspects of the chip
design process for the kind of choices that the  system is trying to explore at the high level,
then I think you could get perhaps much more  exploration and more rapid design of something
that you actually want to give to a fab. That would be great because you can shrink
fab time, you can shrink the deployment time  by designing the hardware in the right way,
so that you just get the chips back and you  just plug them into some system. And that
will then enable a lot more specialization, it  will enable a shorter timeframe for the hardware
design so that you don't have to look out quite  as far into what kind of ML algorithms would be
interesting. Instead, it's like you're looking  at six to nine months from now, what should it
be? Rather than two, two and a half years. That would be pretty cool. I do think that
fabrication time, if that's in your inner  loop of improvement, you're going to like...
How long is it?  The leading edge nodes,
unfortunately, are taking longer and longer  because they have more metal layers than previous,
older nodes. So that tends to make it  take anywhere from three to five months.
Okay, but that's how long training runs take  anyways, right? So you could potentially do
both at the same time. Potentially.
Okay, so I guess you can't get sooner  than three to five months. But the idea
that you could get- but also, yeah, you're  rapidly developing new algorithmic ideas.
That can move fast. That can move fast, that can run on
existing chips and explore lots of cool ideas. So, isn't that a situation in which you're... I
think people sort of expect like, ah,  there's going to be a sigmoid. Again,
this is not a sure thing. But just like, is this  a possibility? The idea that you have sort of an
explosion of capabilities very rapidly towards  the tail end of human intelligence that gets
smarter and smarter at a  more and more rapid rate?
Quite possibly. Yeah. I like to think of it
like this. Right now, we have models that can take  a pretty complicated problem and can break it down
internally in the model into a bunch of steps,  can sort of puzzle together the solutions for
those steps, and can often give you a solution  to the entire problem that you're asking.
But it isn't super reliable, and it's good at  breaking things down into five to ten steps,
not 100 to 1,000 steps. So if you could go  from, yeah, 80% of the time it can give you
a perfect answer to something that's ten steps  long to something that 90% of the time can give
you a perfect answer to something that's 100 to  1,000 steps of sub-problem long, that would be
an amazing improvement in the capability of these  models. We're not there yet, but I think that's
what we're aspirationally trying to get to. We don't need new hardware for that,
but we'll take it. Never look new hardware in the mouth.
One of the big areas of improvement in  the near future is inference time compute,
applying more compute at inference time. I  guess the way I like to describe it is that
even a giant language model, even if you’re doing  a trillion operations per token, which is more
than most people are doing these days, operations  cost something like 10 to the negative $18. And
so you're getting a million tokens to the dollar. I mean compare that to a relatively cheap pastime:
you go out and buy a paper book and  read it, you're paying 10,000 tokens
to the dollar. Talking to a language model is  like 100 times cheaper than reading a paperback.
So there is a huge amount of headroom there  to say, okay, if we can make this thing more
expensive but smarter, because we're  100x cheaper than reading a paperback,
we're 10,000 times cheaper than talking  to a customer support agent, or a million
times or more cheaper than hiring a software  engineer or talking to your doctor or lawyer.
Can we add computation and make it smarter? I think a lot of the takeoff that we're going
to see in the very near future is of this form.  We've been exploiting and improving pre-training
a lot in the past, and post-training, and those  things will continue to improve. But taking
advantage of "think harder" at inference  time is just going to be an explosion.
Yeah, and an aspect of inference time is I think  you want the system to be actively exploring a
bunch of different potential solutions.  Maybe it does some searches on its own,
gets some information back, consumes that  information, and figures out, oh, now I
would really like to know more about this thing.  So now it iteratively explores how to best solve
the high-level problem you pose to this system. And I think having a dial where you can make the
model give you better answers with more inference  time compute seems like we have a bunch of
techniques now that can kind of do that. The more  you crank up the dial, the more it costs you in
terms of compute, but the better the answers get. That seems like a nice trade-off to have,
because sometimes you want to think really  hard because it's a super important problem.
Sometimes you probably don't want to spend  enormous amounts of compute to compute “what's
the answer to one plus one”. Maybe the system – Shouldn’t decide to come up with new
axioms of set theory or whatever! – should decide to use a calculator
tool instead of a very large language model. Interesting. So are there any impediments
to taking inference time, like having  some way in which you can just linearly
scale up inference time compute? Or is this  basically a problem that's sort of solved,
and we know how to throw 100x compute, 1000x  compute, and get correspondingly better results?
We're working out the algorithms as we speak. So  I believe we'll see better and better solutions to
this as these many more than 10,000 researchers  are hacking at it, many of them at Google.
I think we do see some examples in our own  experimental work of things where if you apply
more inference time compute, the answers are  better than if you just apply 10x, you can get
better answers than x amount of computed inference  time. And that seems useful and important.
But I think what we would like is when you apply  10x to get even a bigger improvement in the
quality of the answers than we're getting today.  And so that's about designing new algorithms,
trying new approaches, figuring out how best to  spend that 10x instead of x to improve things.
Does it look more like search, or does  it look more like just keeping going in
the linear direction for a longer time? I really like Rich Sutton's paper that he
wrote about the Bitter Lesson and the Bitter  Lesson effectively is this nice one-page paper
but the essence of it is you can try lots of  approaches, but the two techniques that are
incredibly effective are learning and search. You can apply and scale those algorithmically
or computationally, and you often will  then get better results than any other
kind of approach you can apply it to  a pretty broad variety of problems.
Search has got to be part of the solution to  spending more inference time. Maybe you explore
a few different ways of solving this problem,  and that one didn't work, but this one worked
better. I'm going to explore that a bit more. How does this change your plans for future data
center planning and so forth? Where can this  kind of search be done asynchronously? Does
it have to be online, offline? How  does that change how big of a campus
you need and those kinds of considerations? One general trend is it's clear that inference
time compute, you have a model that's pretty much  already trained and you want to do inference on,
it is going to be a growing and important  class of computation. Maybe you want to
specialize hardware more around that. Actually, the first TPU was specialized for
inference and wasn't really designed for training.  Then subsequent TPUs were really designed more
around training and also for inference. But it may be that when you have something
where you really want to crank up the amount of  compute you use at inference time, that even more
specialized solutions will make a lot of sense. Does that mean you can accommodate more
asynchronous training?  Training? Or inference?
Or just you can have the different data  centers don't need to talk to each other,
you can just have them do a bunch of... I like to think of it as, is the inference that
you're trying to do latency-sensitive? Like a user  is actively waiting for it, or is it a background
thing? Maybe I have some inference tasks that I'm  trying to run over a whole batch of data, but it's
not for a particular user. It's just I want to  run inference on it and extract some information.
There's probably a bunch of things that we  don't really have very much of right now,
but you're seeing inklings of it in our  deep research tool that we just released,
like a week ago. You can give it a pretty  complicated, high-level task like, "Hey,
can you go off and research the history of  renewable energy and all the trends in costs for
wind and solar and other kinds of techniques, and  put it in a table and give me a full eight-page
report?" And it will come back with an eight-page  report with like 50 entries in the bibliography.
It's pretty remarkable. But you're not  actively waiting for that for one second.
It takes like a minute or two to go do that. And I think there's going to be a fair bit of
that kind of compute, and that's the kind of thing  where you have some UI questions around. Okay,
if you're going to have a user with 20 of these  kind of asynchronous tasks in the background
happening, and maybe each one of them needs  to get more information from the user, like,
"I found your flights to Berlin, but there's no  non-stop ones. Are you okay with a non-stop one?"
How does that flow work when you kind of need a  bit more information, and then you want to put
it back in the background for it to continue  doing, you know, finding the hotels in Berlin
or whatever? I think it's going to be pretty  interesting, and inference will be useful.
Inference will be useful. There's also a compute  efficiency in inference that you don't have in
training. In general, transformers can use the  sequence length as a batch during training,
but they can't really in inference, because  when you're generating one token at a time,
so there may be different hardware and  inference algorithms that we design for the
purposes of being efficient at inference. Yeah, as a good example of an algorithmic
improvement is the use of drafter models. So you  have a really small language model that you do
one token at a time when you're decoding,  and it predicts four tokens. Then you give
that to the big model and you say, "Okay,  here are the four tokens the little model
came up with. Check which ones you agree with." If you agree with the first three, then you just
advance. Then you've basically been able to do a  four-token width parallel computation instead of
a one-token width computation in the big model.  Those are the kinds of things that people are
looking at to improve inference efficiency, so you  don't have this single-token decode bottleneck.
Right, basically the big model's  being used as a verifier.
Right, “can you verify”, yeah. [inaudible] generator
and verification you can do. Right. "Hello, how are you?" That sounds
great to me. I'm going to advance past that. So, a big discussion has been about how we're
already tapping out nuclear power plants in  terms of delivering power into one single
campus. Do we have to have just two gigawatts  in one place, five gigawatts in one place,
or can it be more distributed and still  be able to train a model? Does this new
regime of inference scaling make different  considerations there plausible? How are you
thinking about multi-data center training now? We're already doing it. We're pro multi-data
center training. I think in the Gemini  1.5 tech report, we said we used multiple
metro areas and trained with some of the  compute in each place. And then a pretty
long latency but high bandwidth connection  between those data centers, and that works fine.
Training is kind of interesting because  each step in a training process is usually,
for a large model, is usually a few  seconds or something, at least. So,
the latency of it being 50 milliseconds  away doesn't matter that much.
Just the bandwidth. Yeah, just bandwidth.
As long as you can sync all of the parameters  of the model across the different data centers
and then accumulate all the gradients, in the  time it takes to do one step, you're pretty good.
And then we have a bunch of work, even from  early Brain days, when we were using CPU
machines and they were really slow. We needed to  do asynchronous training to help scale, where each
copy of the model would do some local computation,  send gradient updates to a centralized system,
and then apply them asynchronously. Another copy  of the model would be doing the same thing.
It makes your model parameters wiggle around  a bit, and it makes people uncomfortable with
the theoretical guarantees, but it  actually seems to work in practice.
It was so pleasant to go from asynchronous  to synchronous because your experiments are
now replicable, rather than your results  depend on whether there was a web crawler
running on the same machine. So, I am  so much happier running on TPU pods.
I love asynchrony. It just  lets you scale so much more.
With these two iPhones and an Xbox or whatever. Yeah, what if we could give you asynchronous but
replicable results? Ooh.
So, one way to do that is you effectively record  the sequence of operations, like which gradient
update happened and when and on which batch of  data. You don't necessarily record the actual
gradient update in a log or something, but you  could replay that log of operations so that you
get repeatability. Then I think you'd be happy. Possibly. At least you could debug what happened,
but you wouldn't be able to necessarily compare  two training runs. Because, okay, I made one
change in the hyperparameter, but also I had a- Web crawler.
-web crawler messing up, and there were a lot of  people streaming the Super Bowl at the same time.
The thing that led us to go from asynchronous  training on CPUs to fully synchronous training
is the fact that we have these super  fast TPU hardware chips and pods,
which have incredible amounts of bandwidth between  the chips in a pod. Then, scaling beyond that,
we have really good data center networks and  even cross-metro area networks that enable
us to scale to many, many pods in multiple  metro areas for our largest training runs.
We can do that fully synchronously. As Noam said, as long as the gradient
accumulation and communication of the parameters  across metro areas happens fast enough relative
to the step time, you're golden. You don't  really care. But I think as you scale up,
there may be a push to have a bit more asynchrony  in our systems than we have now because we can
make it work, our ML researchers have been really  happy how far we've been able to push synchronous
training because it is an easier mental model to  understand. You just have your algorithm sort of
fighting you, rather than the asynchrony  and the algorithm kind of battling you.
As you scale up, there are more things  fighting you. That's the problem with scaling,
that you don't always know what it is that's  fighting you. Is it the fact that you've pushed
quantization a little too far in some  place or another? Or is it your data?
Maybe it's your adversarial machine MUQQ17 that  is setting the seventh bit of your exponent
and all your gradients or something. Right. And all of these things just make
the model slightly worse, so you don't  even know that the thing is going on.
That's actually a bit of a problem with neural  nets, is they're so tolerant of noise. You can
have things set up kind of wrong in a  lot of ways, and they just figure out
ways to work around that or learn. You could have bugs in your code. Most
of the time that does nothing. Some of the time it  makes your model worse. Some of the time it makes
your model better. Then you discover something  new because you never tried this bug at scale
before because you didn't have the budget for it. What practically does it look like to debug or
decode? You've got these things, some of which are  making the model better, some of which are making
it worse. When you go into work tomorrow, how do  you figure out what the most salient inputs are?
At small scale, you do lots of experiments.  There's one part of the research that involves,
okay, I want to invent these improvements  or breakthroughs in isolation. In which
case you want a nice simple code base that  you can fork and hack, and some baselines.
My dream is I wake up in the morning,  come up with an idea, hack it up in a day,
run some experiments, get some initial results  in a day. Like okay this looks promising, these
things worked, and these things didn't work. I think that is very achievable because-
At small scale. At small scale, as long as you
keep a nice experimental code base.  Maybe an experiment takes an hour
to run or two hours, not two weeks.  It’s great. So there's that part of the research,
and then there's some amount of scaling up. Then  you have the part which is integrating, where
you want to stack all the improvements on top of  each other and see if they work at large scale,
and see if they work all in conjunction. Right, how do they interact? Right,
you think maybe they're independent, but actually  maybe there's some funny interaction between
improving the way in which we handle video  data input and the way in which we update
the model parameters. Maybe that interacts  more for video data than some other thing.
There are all kinds of interactions that can  happen that you maybe don't anticipate. So
you want to run these experiments where you're  then putting a bunch of things together and then
periodically making sure that all the things  you think are good are good together. If not,
understanding why they're not playing nicely. Two questions. One, how often does it end up
being the case that things don't stack up  well together? Is it like a rare thing or
does it happen all the time? It happens 50% of the time.
Yeah, I mean, I think most things you don't  even try to stack because the initial experiment
didn't work that well, or it showed results  that aren't that promising relative to the
baseline. Then you sort of take those things  and you try to scale them up individually.
Then you're like, "Oh yeah, these ones seem  really promising." So I'm going to now include
them in something that I'm going to now bundle  together and try to advance and combine with
other things that seem promising. Then you  run the experiments and then you're like,
"Oh, well, they didn't really work  that well. Let's try to debug why."
And then there are trade offs, because you want to  keep your integrated system as clean as you can,
because complexity – Codebase-wise.
– yeah codebase and algorithmically.  Complexity hurts, complexity makes
things slower, introduces more risk. And then at the same time you want it
to be as good as possible. And of course, every  individual researcher wants his inventions to go
into it. So there are definitely challenges there,  but we've been working together quite well.
Okay, so then going back to the whole dynamic “you  find better and better algorithmic improvements
and the models get better and better over time”,  even if you take the hardware part out of it.
Should the world be thinking more about, and  should you guys be thinking more about this?
There's one world where AI is a thing that takes  two decades to slowly get better over time and
you can sort of refine things over. If you've kind  of messed something up, you fix it, and it's not
that big a deal, right? It's like not that much  better than the previous version you released.
There's another world where you have this big  feedback loop, which means that the two years
between Gemini 4 and Gemini 5 are the most  important years in human history. Because
you go from a pretty good ML researcher  to superhuman intelligence because of
this feedback loop. To the extent that you  think that the second world is plausible,
how does that change how you sort of approach  these greater and greater levels of intelligence?
I've stopped cleaning my garage because  I'm waiting for the robots. So probably
I'm more in the second camp of what we're  going to see, a lot of acceleration.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's super important to  understand what's going on and what the trends
are. And I think right now the trends are the  models are getting substantially better generation
over generation. I don't see that slowing  down in the next few generations probably.
So that means the models say two to three  generations from now are going to be capable
of... Let's go back to the example of breaking  down a simple task into 10 sub pieces and doing
it 80% of the time, to something that can  break down a task, a very high level task,
into 100 or 1,000 pieces and get that  right 90% of the time. That's a major,
major step up in what the models are capable of. So I think it's important for people to understand
what is happening in the progress in the field.  And then those models are going to be applied
in a bunch of different domains. I think it's  really good to make sure that we, as a society,
get the maximal benefits from what these models  can do to improve things. I'm super excited
about areas like education and healthcare,  making information accessible to all people.
But we also realize that they could be used for  misinformation, they could be used for automated
hacking of computer systems, and we want to put  as many safeguards and mitigations and understand
the capabilities of the models in place as we  can. I think Google as a whole has a really
good view to how we should approach this. Our  Responsible AI principles actually are a pretty
nice framework for how to think about trade offs  of making better and better AI systems available
in different contexts and settings, while also  sort of making sure that we're doing the right
thing in terms of making sure they're safe and  not saying toxic things and things like that.
I guess the thing that stands out to me, if  you were zooming out and looking at this period
of human history, if we're in the world where,  look, if you do post-training on Gemini 3 badly,
it can do some misinformation – but then you  fix the post training. It's a bad mistake,
but it's a fixable mistake, right? Right.
Whereas if you have this feedback loop dynamic,  which is a possibility, then the mistake of the
thing that catapults this intelligence  explosion is misaligned, is not trying to
write the code you think it's trying to write, and  [instead] optimizing for some other objective.
And on the other end of this very rapid process  that lasts a couple of years, maybe less,
you have things that are approaching Jeff Dean  or beyond level, or Noam Shazeer or beyond
level. And then you have millions of copies  of Jeff Dean level programmers, and- anyways,
that seems like a harder to recover mistake. As these systems do get more powerful,
you have to be more and more careful. One thing I would say is, there are extreme
views on either end. There's, "Oh my goodness,  these systems are going to be so much better
than humans at all things, and we're going  to be kind of overwhelmed." And then there's,
"These systems are going to be amazing, and  we don't have to worry about them at all."
I think I'm somewhere in the middle. I've been  a co-author on a paper called "Shaping AI,"
which is, you know, those two extreme views often  kind of view our role as kind of laissez-faire,
like we're just going to have the AI  develop in the path that it takes.
And I think there's actually a really good  argument to be made that what we're going to
do is try to shape and steer the way in which  AI is deployed in the world so that it is,
you know, maximally beneficial in the areas that  we want to capture and benefit from, in education,
some of the areas I mentioned, healthcare. And steer it as much as we can away- maybe
with policy-related things, maybe with technical  measures and safeguards- away from, you know,
the computer will take over and  have unlimited control of what
it can do. So I think that's an engineering  problem: how do you engineer safe systems?
I think it's kind of the modern equivalent  of what we've done in older-style software
development. Like if you look at, you know,  airplane software development, that has a pretty
good record of how do you rigorously develop safe  and secure systems for doing a pretty risky task?
The difficulty there is that there's not some  feedback loop where the 737, you put it in
a box with a bunch of compute for a couple of  years, and it comes out with the version 1000.
I think the good news is that analyzing text  seems to be easier than generating text. So
I believe that the ability of language models to  actually analyze language model output and figure
out what is problematic or dangerous will actually  be the solution to a lot of these control issues.
We are definitely working on this stuff.  We've got a bunch of brilliant folks at
Google working on this now. And I think it's  just going to be more and more important,
both from a “do something good for people”  standpoint, but also from a business standpoint,
that you are, a lot of the time, limited in what  you can deploy based on keeping things safe.
And so it becomes very, very important  to be really, really good at that.
Yeah, obviously, I know you guys take the  potential benefits and costs here seriously,
and it's truly remarkable. I know you guys get  credit for it, but not enough. I think there's
just, there are so many different applications  that you have put out for using these models to
make the different areas you talked about better. Um, but I do think that… again, if you have a
situation where plausibly there's some  feedback loop process, on the other end,
you have a model that is as good as  Noam Shazeer, as good as Jeff Dean.
If there's an evil version of you running  around, and suppose there's a million of them,
I think that's really, really bad. That could be  much, much worse than any other risk, maybe short
of nuclear war or something. Just think about  it, like a million evil Jeff Deans or something.
Where do we get the training data? But, to the extent that you think that's
a plausible output of some quick feedback  loop process, what is your plan of okay,
we've got Gemini 3 or Gemini 4, and we think  it's helping us do a better job of training
future versions, it's writing a bunch of the  training code for us. From this point forward,
we just kind of look over it, verify it. Even the verifiers you talked about of looking
at the output of these models will eventually  be trained by, or a lot of the code will be
written by the AIs you make. What do you want  to know for sure before we have the Gemini 4
help us with the AI research? We really want  to make sure, we want to run this test on it
before we let it write our AI code for us. I mean, I think having the system explore
algorithmic research ideas seems like something  where there's still a human in charge of that.
Like, it's exploring the space, and then  it's going to, like, get a bunch of results,
and we're going to make a decision, like,  are we going to incorporate this particular,
you know, learning algorithm or change to  the system into kind of the core code base?
And so I think you can put in safeguards like that  that enable us to get the benefits of the system
that can sort of improve or kind of self-improve  with human oversight, uh, without necessarily
letting the system go full-on self-improving  without any any notion of a person looking at what
it's doing, right? That's the kind of engineering  safeguards I'm talking about, where you want to
be kind of looking at the characteristics  of the systems you're deploying, not deploy
ones that are harmful by some measures and some  ways, and you have an understanding of what its
capabilities are and what it's likely to do in  certain scenarios. So, you know, I think it's
not an easy problem by any means, but I do think  it is possible to make these these systems safe.
Yeah. I mean, I think we are also going to  use these systems a lot to check themselves,
check other systems. Even as a human, it is easier  to recognize something than to generate it.
One thing I would say is if you expose the model's  capabilities through an API or through a user
interface that people interact with, I think then  you have a level of control to understand how is
it being used and put some boundaries on what it  can do. And that I think is one of the tools in
the arsenal of how do you make sure that what  it's going to do is sort of acceptable by some
set of standards you've set out in your mind? Yeah. I mean, I think the goal is to empower
people, but for the most part we should be  mostly letting people do things with these
systems that make sense and closing off as  few parts of the space as we can. But yeah,
if you let somebody take your thing and create a  million evil software engineers, then that doesn't
empower people because they're going to hurt  others with a million evil software engineers.
So I'm against that. Me too. I'll go on.
All right, let's talk about a few more fun topics.  Make it a little lighter. Over the last 25 years,
what was the most fun time? What period of  time do you have the most nostalgia over?
I think the early sort of four  or five years at Google when I
was one of a handful of people working on  search and crawling and indexing systems,
our traffic was growing tremendously fast. We  were trying to expand our index size and make
it so we updated it every minute instead of every  month, or two months if something went wrong.
Seeing the growth in usage of our systems was  really just personally satisfying. Building
something that is used by two billion  people a day is pretty incredible.
But I would also say equally exciting is working  with people on the Gemini team today. I think
the progress we've been making in what these  models can do over the last year and a half is
really fun. People are really dedicated,  really excited about what we're doing.
I think the models are getting better and  better at pretty complex tasks. Like if
you showed someone using a computer 20 years ago  what these models are capable of, they wouldn't
believe it. And even five years ago, they might  not believe it. And that's pretty satisfying.
I think we'll see a similar growth in usage  of these models and impact in the world.
Yeah, I'm with you. Early days were super fun.  Part of that is just knowing everybody and the
social aspect, and the fact that you're  just building something that millions
and millions of people are using. Same thing today. We got that whole
nice micro kitchen area where you get lots of  people hanging out. I love being in person,
working with a bunch of great people, and building  something that's helping millions to billions of
people. What could be better? What was this micro kitchen?
Oh, we have a micro kitchen area in the building  we both sit in. It's the new, so-named Gradient
Canopy. It used to be named Charleston East,  and we decided we needed a more exciting
name because it's a lot of machine learning  researchers and AI research happening in there.
There's a micro kitchen area that we've set up  with, normally it's just like an espresso machine
and a bunch of snacks, but this particular one has  a bunch of space in it. So we've set up maybe 50
desks in there, and so people are just hanging  out in there. It's a little noisy because people
are always grinding beans and brewing espresso,  but you also get a lot of face-to-face ideas of
connections, like, "Oh, I've tried that. Did  you think about trying this in your idea?" Or,
"Oh, we're going to launch this thing  next week. How's the load test looking?"
There's just lots of feedback that happens. And then we have our Gemini chat room for people
who are not in that micro kitchen. We have a team  all over the world, and there's probably 120 chat
rooms I'm in related to Gemini things. In this  particular very focused topic, we have seven
people working on this, and there are exciting  results being shared by the London colleagues.
When you wake up, you see what's happening  in there, or it's a big group of people
focused on data, and there are all kinds of  issues happening in there. It's just fun.
What I find remarkable about some  of the calls you guys have made
is you're anticipating a level of demand for  compute, which at the time wasn't obvious or
evident. TPUs being a famous example of this,  or the first TPU being an example of this.
That thinking you had in, I guess, 2013  or earlier, if you think about it that way
today and you do an estimate of, look, we're  going to have these models that are going to
be a backbone of our services, and we're going  to be doing constant inference for them. We're
going to be training future versions. And you  think about the amount of compute we'll need by
2030 to accommodate all these use cases,  where does the Fermi estimate get you?
Yeah, I mean, I think you're going to want a lot  of inference. Compute is the rough, highest-level
view of these capable models because if one of the  techniques for improving their quality is scaling
up the amount of inference compute you use, then  all of a sudden what's currently like one request
to generate some tokens now becomes 50 or 100  or 1000 times as computationally intensive, even
though it's producing the same amount of output.  And you're also going to then see tremendous
scaling up of the uses of these services as  not everyone in the world has discovered these
chat-based conversational interfaces where  you can get them to do all kinds of amazing
things. Probably 10% of the computer users in  the world have discovered that today, or 20%. As
that pushes towards 100% and people make  heavier use of it, that's going to be
another order of magnitude or two of scaling. And so you're now going to have two orders of
magnitude from that, two orders of magnitude from  that. The models are probably going to be bigger,
you'll get another order of magnitude or two  from that. And there's a lot of inference
compute you want. So you want extremely efficient  hardware for inference for models you care about.
In flops, global total global inference in 2030? I think just more is always going to be better.
If you just kind of think about, okay, what  fraction of world GDP will people decide to
spend on AI at that point? And then, like,  okay, what do the AI systems look like?
Well, maybe it's some sort of personal  assistant-like thing that is in your
glasses and can see everything around you and  has access to all your digital information
and the world's digital information.  And maybe it's like you're Joe Biden,
and you have the earpiece in the cabinet that  can advise you about anything in real-time
and solve problems for you and give you helpful  pointers. Or you could talk to it, and it wants
to analyze anything that it sees around you for  any potential useful impact that it has on you.
So I mean, I can imagine, okay, and then say  it's like your personal assistant or your
personal cabinet or something, and that every  time you spend 2x as much money on compute,
the thing gets like 5, 10 IQ points smarter or  something like that. And, okay, would you rather
spend $10 a day and have an assistant or $20 a day  and have a smarter assistant? And not only is it
an assistant in life but an assistant in getting  your job done better because now it makes you from
a 10x engineer to a 100x or 10 millionx engineer? Okay, so let's see: from first principles,
right? So people are going to want to spend  some fraction of world GDP on this thing.
The world GDP is almost certainly going to go way,  way up, two orders of magnitude higher than it is
today, due to the fact that we have all of these  artificial engineers working on improving things.
Probably we'll have solved unlimited energy and  carbon issues by that point. So we should be able
to have lots of energy. We should be able to  have millions to billions of robots building
us data centers. Let's see, the sun is what,  10 to the 26 watts or something like that?
I'm guessing that the amount of compute being used  for AI to help each person will be astronomical.
I would add on to that. I'm not sure  I agree completely, but it's a pretty
interesting thought experiment to go in that  direction. And even if you get partway there,
it's definitely going to be a lot of compute. And this is why it's super important to have as
cheap a hardware platform for using these  models and applying them to problems that
Noam described, so that you can then  make it accessible to everyone in some
form and have as low a cost for access to  these capabilities as you possibly can.
And I think that's achievable by focusing on  hardware and model co-design kinds of things,
we should be able to make these things much,  much more efficient than they are today.
Is Google's data center build-out plan over  the next few years aggressive enough given
this increase in demand you're expecting? I'm not going to comment on our future capital
spending because our CEO and CFO would prefer  I probably not. But I will say, you can look at
our past capital expenditures over the last few  years and see that we're definitely investing
in this area because we think it's important. We are continuing to build new and interesting,
innovative hardware that we think really helps us  have an edge in deploying these systems to more
and more people, both training them and also, how  do we make them usable by people for inference?
One thing I've heard you talk a  lot about is continual learning,
the idea that you could just have a model  which improves over time rather than having to
start from scratch. Is there any fundamental  impediment to that? Because theoretically,
you should just be able to keep fine-tuning a  model. What does that future look like to you?
Yeah, I've been thinking about this more and  more. I've been a big fan of models that are
sparse because I think you want different parts  of the model to be good at different things. We
have our Gemini 1.5 Pro model, and other  models are mixture-of-experts style models
where you now have parts of the model that are  activated for some token and parts that are not
activated at all because you've decided this is a  math-oriented thing, and this part's good at math,
and this part's good at understanding cat images.  So, that gives you this ability to have a much
more capable model that's still quite efficient at  inference time because it has very large capacity,
but you activate a small part of it. But I think the current problem, well,
one limitation of what we're doing today is  it's still a very regular structure where
each of the experts is the same size. The  paths merge back together very fast. They
don't go off and have lots of different  branches for mathy things that don't merge
back together with the kind of cat-image thing. I think we should probably have a more organic
structure in these things. I also would like  it if the pieces of those model of the model
could be developed a little bit independently.  Like right now, I think we have this issue where
we're going to train a model. So, we do a  bunch of preparation work on deciding the
most awesome algorithms we can come up with and  the most awesome data mix we can come up with.
But there's always trade-offs there, like we'd  love to include more multilingual data, but that
might come at the expense of including less coding  data, and so, the model's less good at coding but
better at multilingual, or vice versa. I think it  would be really great if we could have a small set
of people who care about a particular subset of  languages go off and create really good training
data, train a modular piece of a model that we  can then hook up to a larger model that improves
its capability in, say, Southeast Asian languages  or in reasoning about Haskell code or something.
Then, you also have a nice software engineering  benefit where you've decomposed the problem a
bit compared to what we do today, which is we have  this kind of a whole bunch of people working. But
then, we have this kind of monolithic process  of starting to do pre-training on this model.
If we could do that, you could have 100 teams  around Google. You could have people all around
the world working to improve languages they care  about or particular problems they care about and
all collectively work on improving the model.  And that's kind of a form of continual learning.
That would be so nice. You could just glue  models together or rip out pieces of models
and shove them into other... Upgrade this piece without
throwing out the thing... ...or you just attach a fire hose,
and you suck all the information out of this  model, shove it into another model. There is,
I mean, the countervailing interest there is sort  of science, in terms of, okay, we're still in the
period of rapid progress, so, if you want to  do sort of controlled experiments, and okay,
I want to compare this thing to that thing because  that then is helping us figure out what to build.
In that interest, it's often best to just start  from scratch so you can compare one complete
training run to another complete training run at  the practical level because it helps us figure out
what to build in the future. It's less  exciting but does lead to rapid progress.
Yeah, I think there may be ways to  get a lot of the benefits of that
with a version system of modularity.  I have a frozen version of my model,
and then I include a different variant of some  particular module, and I want to compare its
performance or train it a bit more. Then,  I compare it to the baseline of this thing
with now version N prime of this particular  module that does Haskell interpretation.
Actually, that could lead to faster research  progress, right? You've got some system, and
you do something to improve it. And if that thing  you're doing to improve it is relatively cheap
compared to training the system from scratch,  then it could actually make research much,
much cheaper and faster. Yeah, and also more
parallelizable, I think, across people. Okay, let's figure it out and do that next.
So, this idea that is sort of casually  laid out there would actually be a big
regime shift compared to how things are done  today. If you think the way things are headed,
this is a sort of very interesting prediction  about... You just have this blob where things
are getting pipelined back and forth –  and if you want to make something better,
you can do like a sort of  surgical incision almost.
Right, or grow the model, add another little bit  of it here. Yeah, I've been sort of sketching out
this vision for a while in Pathways... Yeah, you've been building the...
...and we've been building the infrastructure  for it. So, a lot of what Pathways, the system,
can support is this kind of twisty, weird  model with asynchronous updates to different
pieces. And we're using Pathways to train our  Gemini models, but we're not making use of some
of its capabilities yet. But maybe we should. Ooh maybe. There have been times, like the way the
TPU pods were set up. I don't know who did that,  but they did a pretty brilliant job. The low-level
software stack and the hardware stack, okay,  you've got your nice regular high-performance
hardware, you've got these great torus-shaped  interconnects, and then you've got the right
low-level collectives, the all-reduces, et cetera,  which I guess came from supercomputing, but it
turned out to be kind of just the right thing  to build distributed deep learning on top of.
Okay, so a couple of questions. One,  suppose Noam makes another breakthrough,
and now we've got a better architecture.  Would you just take each compartment and
distill it into this better architecture?  And that's how it keeps improving over time?
I do think distillation is a really useful  tool because it enables you to transform
a model in its current model architecture  form into a different form. Often,
you use it to take a really capable but large  and unwieldy model and distill it into a smaller
one that maybe you want to serve with really  good, fast latency inference characteristics.
But I think you can also view this as  something that's happening at the module
level. Maybe there'd be a continual process where  you have each module, and it has a few different
representations of itself. It has a really  big one. It's got a much smaller one that is
continually distilling into the small version. And then the small version, once that's finished,
you sort of delete the big one and you add a  bunch more parameter capacity. Now, start to
learn all the things that the distilled small  one doesn't know by training it on more data,
and then you kind of repeat that process. If you  have that kind of running a thousand different
places in your modular model in the background,  that seems like it would work reasonably well.
This could be a way of doing  inference scaling, like the router
decides how much do you want the big one. Yeah, you can have multiple versions. Oh,
this is an easy math problem, so I'm going  to route it to the really tiny math distilled
thing. Oh, this one's really hard, so... One, at least from public research,
it seems like it's often hard to decode what  each expert is doing in mixture of expert type
models. If you have something like this, how  would you enforce the kind of modularity that
would be visible and understandable to us? Actually, in the past, I found experts to be
relatively easy to understand. I mean,  the first Mixture of Experts paper,
you could just look at the experts. “I don’t know, I'm only the
inventor of Mixture of Experts.” Like, you could just see, okay, this expert,
like we did, you know, a thousand, two thousand  experts. Okay, and this expert, was getting words
referring to cylindrical objects. This one's super good at dates.
Yeah.  Talking about times.
Yeah, pretty easy to do. Not that you would need that
human understanding to figure out how to work the  thing at runtime because you just have some sort
of learned router that's looking at the example. One thing I would say is there is a bunch of
work on interpretability of models and what  are they doing inside. Sort of expert-level
interpretability is a sub-problem  of that broader area. I really like
some of the work that my former intern,  Chris Olah, and others did at Anthropic,
where they trained a very sparse autoencoder and  were able to deduce what characteristics some
particular neuron in a large language model has,  so they found a Golden Gate Bridge neuron that's
activated when you're talking about the Golden  Gate Bridge. And I think you could do that at
the expert level, you could do that at a variety  of different levels and get pretty interpretable
results, and it's a little unclear if you  necessarily need that. If the model is just
really good at stuff, we don't necessarily care  what every neuron in the Gemini model is doing, as
long as the collective output and characteristics  of the overall system are good. That's one of the
beauties of deep learning, is you don't need to  understand or hand-engineer every last feature.
Man, there are so many interesting implications  of this that I could just keep asking you about
this- I would regret not asking you more about  this, so I'll keep going. One implication is,
currently, if you have a model that has some  tens or hundreds of billions of parameters,
you can serve it on a handful of GPUs. In this system, where any one query might
only make its way through a small fraction of  the total parameters, but you need the whole
thing loaded into memory, the specific kind of  infrastructure that Google has invested in with
these TPUs that exist in pods of hundreds or  thousands would be immensely valuable, right?
For any sort of even existing mixtures of  experts, you want the whole thing in-memory.
I guess there's kind of this misconception  running around with Mixture of Experts that,
okay, the benefit is that you don't even have  to go through those weights in the model.
If some expert is unused, it doesn't mean that  you don't have to retrieve that memory because,
really, in order to be efficient, you're  serving at very large batch sizes.
Of independent requests. Right, of independent requests.
So it's not really the case that, okay, at  this step, you're either looking at this
expert or you're not looking at this expert. Because if that were the case, then when you did
look at the expert, you would be running it at  batch size one, which is massively inefficient.
Like you've got modern hardware, the operational  intensities are whatever, hundreds. So that's
not what's happening. It's that you are looking  at all the experts, but you only have to send a
small fraction of the batch through each one. Right, but you still have a smaller batch at
each expert that then goes through. And in  order to get kind of reasonable balance,
one of the things that the current models  typically do is they have all the experts
be roughly the same compute cost, and then you  run roughly the same size batches through them
in order to propagate the very large batch you're  doing at inference time and have good efficiency.
But I think you often in the future might  want experts that vary in computational cost
by factors of 100 or 1000. Or maybe paths  that go for many layers on one case, and
a single layer or even a skip connection in  the other case. And there, I think you're going
to want very large batches still, but you're  going to want to push things through the model
a little bit asynchronously at inference time,  which is a little easier than training time.
That's part of one of the things that pathways was  designed to support. You have these components,
and the components can be variable cost and you  kind of can say, for this particular example,
I want to go through this subset  of the model, and for this example,
I want to go through this subset of the model  and have the system kind of orchestrate that.
It also would mean that it would take companies  of a certain size and sophistication to be able
to... Right now, anybody can train a  sufficiently small enough model. But
if it ends up being the case that this  is the best way to train future models,
then you would need a company that can basically  have a data center serving a single quote, unquote
“blob” or model. So it would be an interesting  change in paradigms in that way as well.
You definitely want to have at least enough  HBM to put your whole model. So depending
on the size of your model, most likely that's  how much HBM you'd want to have at a minimum.
It also means you don't necessarily need to  grow your entire model footprint to be the
size of a data center. You might  want it to be a bit below that.
And then have potentially many replicated copies  of one particular expert that is being used a lot,
so that you get better load balancing. This one's  being used a lot because we get a lot of math
questions, and this one is an expert on Tahitian  dance, and it is called on really rarely.
That one, maybe you even page out to  DRAM rather than putting it in HBM.
But you want the system to figure all this  stuff out based on load characteristics.
Right now, language models,  obviously, you put in language,
you get language out. Obviously, it's multimodal. But the Pathways blog post talks about so many
different use cases that are not obviously  of this kind of auto-regressive nature going
through the same model. Could you imagine,  basically, Google as a company, the product
is like Google Search goes through this, Google  Images goes through this, Gmail goes through it?
Just like the entire server is just this  huge mixture of experts, specialized?
You're starting to see some of this by having a  lot of uses of Gemini models across Google that
are not necessarily fine-tuned. They're just  given instructions for this particular use
case in this feature in this product setting. So, I definitely see a lot more sharing of what
the underlying models are capable of across  more and more services. I do think that's a
pretty interesting direction to go, for sure. Yeah, I feel like people listening might not
register how interesting a prediction this is  about where AI is going. It's like sort of getting
Noam on a podcast in 2018 and being like, "Yeah,  so I think language models will be a thing."
It's like, if this is where things go,  this is actually incredibly interesting.
Yeah, and I think you might see that might  be a big base model. And then you might want
customized versions of that model with different  modules that are added onto it for different
settings that maybe have access restrictions. Maybe we have an internal one for Google use,
for Google employees, that we've trained some  modules on internal data, and we don't allow
anyone else to use those modules, but we  can make use of it. Maybe other companies,
you add on other modules that are useful for that  company setting and serve it in our cloud APIs.
What is the bottleneck to  making this sort of system
viable? Is it systems engineering? Is it ML? It's a pretty different way of operating than
our current Gemini development. So,  I think we will explore these kinds
of areas and make some progress on them. But we need to really see evidence that it's
the right way, that it has a lot of benefits.  Some of those benefits may be improved quality,
some may be less concretely measurable,  like this ability to have lots of parallel
development of different modules. But that's  still a pretty exciting improvement because
I think that would enable us to make faster  progress on improving the model's capabilities
for lots of different distinct areas. Even the data control modularity stuff
seems really cool because then you could  have the piece of the model that's just
trained for me. It knows all my private data. Like a personal module for you would be useful.
Another thing might be you can use certain data  in some settings but not in other settings.
Maybe we have some YouTube data that's only usable  in a YouTube product surface but not in other
settings. So, we could have a module that is  trained on that data for that particular purpose.
We're going to need a million automated  researchers to invent all of this stuff.
It's going to be great. Yeah, well the thing itself, you build the blob,
and it tells you how to make the blob better. Blob 2.0. Or maybe they're not even versions,
it's just like an incrementally growing blob. Yeah. Okay, Jeff, motivate for me, big picture:
why is this a good idea? Why  is this the next direction?
Yeah, this notion of an organic, not quite so  carefully mathematically constructed machine
learning model is one that's been with me for a  little while. I feel like in the development of
neural nets, the artificial neurons, inspiration  from biological neurons is a good one and has
served us well in the deep learning field. We've been able to make a lot of progress with
that. But I feel like we're not necessarily  looking at other things that real brains do
as much as we perhaps could, and that's not to  say we should exactly mimic that because silicon
and wetware have very different characteristics  and strengths. But I do think one thing we could
draw more inspiration from is this notion  of having different specialized portions,
sort of areas of a model of a brain  that are good at different things.
We have a little bit of that  in Mixture of Experts models,
but it's still very structured. I feel like  this kind of more organic growth of expertise,
and when you want more expertise of that, you  add some more capacity to the model there and
let it learn a bit more on that kind of thing. Also this notion of adapting the connectivity
of the model to the connectivity of the hardware  is a good one. I think you want incredibly dense
connections between artificial neurons in the same  chip and the same HBM because that doesn't cost
you that much. But then you want a smaller number  of connections to nearby neurons. So, like a chip
away, you should have some amount of connections  and then, like many, many chips away, you should
have a smaller number of connections where you  send over a very limited kind of bottlenecky
thing: the most important things that this part  of the model is learning for other parts of the
model to make use of. And even across multiple TPU  pods, you'd like to send even less information but
the most salient kind of representations. And then  across metro areas, you'd like to send even less.
Yeah, and then that emerges organically. Yeah, I'd like that to emerge organically. You
could hand-specify these characteristics, but  I think you don't know exactly what the right
proportions of these kinds of connections are so  you should just let the hardware dictate things
a little bit. Like if you're communicating over  here and this data always shows up really early,
you should add some more connections, then it'll  take longer and show up at just the right time.
Oh here's another interesting implication: Right  now, we think about the growth in AI use as a
sort of horizontal- so, suppose you're like,  how many AI engineers will Google have working
for it? You think about how many instances  of Gemini 3 will be working at one time.
If you have this, whatever you want to call it,  this blob, and it can sort of organically decide
how much of itself to activate, then it's more  of, if you want 10 engineers worth of output,
it just activates a different pattern or a larger  pattern. If you want 100 engineers of output, it's
not like calling more agents or more instances,  it's just calling different sub-patterns.
I think there's a notion of how much compute do  you want to spend on this particular inference,
and that should vary by factors of 10,000 for  really easy things and really hard things,
maybe even a million. It might be iterative,  you might make a pass through the model,
get some stuff, and then decide you now need  to call on some other parts of the model.
The other thing I would say is this sounds super  complicated to deploy because it's this weird,
constantly evolving thing with maybe not super  optimized ways of communicating between pieces,
but you can always distill from that. If you say,  "This is the kind of task I really care about, let
me distill from this giant kind of organic thing  into something that I know can be served really
efficiently," you could do that distillation  process whenever you want, once a day, once an
hour. That seems like it'd be kind of good. Yeah, we need better distillation.
Yeah. Anyone out there who invents amazing distillation
techniques that instantly distill from a giant  blob onto your phone, that would be wonderful.
How would you characterize what's missing  from current distillation techniques?
Well, I just want it to work faster. A related thing is I feel like we
need interesting learning techniques during  pre-training. I'm not sure we're extracting
the maximal value from every token we look at  with the current training objective. Maybe we
should think a lot harder about some tokens. When you get to "the answer is," maybe the
model should, at training time, do a lot  more work than when it gets to "the".
Right. There's got to be some way  to get more from the same data,
make it learn it forwards and backwards. And every which way. Hide some stuff this way,
hide some stuff that way, make it infer from  partial information. I think people have been
doing this in vision models for a while. You  distort the model or you hide parts of it and
try to make it guess the bird from half, like  that it's a bird from this upper corner of the
image or the lower left corner of the image. That makes the task harder, and I feel like
there's an analog for more textual or  coding-related data where you want to
force the model to work harder. You'll get  more interesting observations from it.
Yeah, the image people didn't have enough labeled  data so they had to invent all this stuff.
And they invented -- I mean, dropout was invented  on images, but we're not really using it for text
mostly. That's one way you could get a lot  more learning in a more large-scale model
without overfitting is just make like 100 epochs  over the world's text data and use dropout.
But that's pretty computationally expensive,  but it does mean we won't run it. Even though
people are saying, "Oh no, we're almost out  of textual data," I don't really believe that
because I think we can get a lot more capable  models out of the text data that does exist.
I mean, a person has seen a billion tokens. Yeah, and they're pretty good at a lot of stuff.
So obviously human data efficiency  sets a lower bound on how, or I guess,
upper bound, one of them, maybe not. It's an interesting data point.
Yes. So there's a sort of modus  ponens, modus tollens thing here.
One way to look at it is, look, LLMs have so  much further to go, therefore we project orders
of magnitude improvement in sample efficiency  just if they could match humans. Another is,
maybe they're doing something clearly different  given the orders of magnitude difference. What's
your intuition of what it would take to make  these models as sample efficient as humans are?
Yeah, I think we should consider changing the  training objective a little bit. Just predicting
the next token from the previous ones you've seen  seems like not how people learn. It's a little bit
related to how people learn, I think, but not  entirely. A person might read a whole chapter
of a book and then try to answer questions at  the back, and that's a different kind of thing.
I also think we're not learning from visual  data very much. We're training a little bit on
video data, but we're definitely not anywhere  close to thinking about training on all the
visual inputs you could get. So you have visual  data that we haven't really begun to train on.
Then I think we could extract a lot more  information from every bit of data we do see.
I think one of the ways people are so sample  efficient is they explore the world and take
actions in the world and observe what happens. You  see it with very small infants picking things up
and dropping them; they learn about gravity  from that. And that's a much harder thing to
learn when you're not initiating the action. I think having a model that can take actions as
part of its learning process would be just  a lot better than just sort of passively
observing a giant dataset. Is Gato the future, then?
Something where the model can observe  and take actions and observe the
corresponding results seems pretty useful. I mean, people can learn a lot from thought
experiments that don't even involve extra input.  Einstein learned a lot of stuff from thought
experiments, or like Newton went into quarantine  and got an apple dropped on his head or something
and invented gravity. And like mathematicians  -- math didn't have any extra input.
Chess, okay, you have the thing play chess  against itself and it gets good at chess. That
was DeepMind, but also all it needs is the rules  of chess. So there's actually probably a lot of
learning that you can do even without external  data, and then you can make it in exactly the
fields that you care about. Of course, there  is learning that will require external data,
but maybe we can just have this thing  talk to itself and make itself smarter.
So here's the question I have. What you've just  laid out over the last hour is potentially just
like the big next paradigm shift in AI.  That's a tremendously valuable insight,
potentially. Noam, in 2017 you released  the Transformer paper on which tens,
if not hundreds, of billions of dollars of  market value is based in other companies,
not to mention all this other research  that Google has released over time,
which you've been relatively generous with. In retrospect, when you think about divulging
this information that has been helpful to  your competitors, in retrospect is it like,
"Yeah, we'd still do it," or would you  be like, "Ah, we didn't realize how big
a deal Transformer was. We should have kept  it indoors." How do you think about that?
It's a good question because I think probably  we did need to see the size of the opportunity,
often reflected in what other companies  are doing. And also it's not a fixed pie.
The current state of the world is pretty  much as far from fixed pie as you can get.
I think we're going to see orders of magnitude of  improvements in GDP, health, wealth, and anything
else you can think of. So I think it's definitely  been nice that Transformer has got around.
It’s transformative.  Woo. Thank God Google's
doing well as well. So these days we do  publish a little less of what we're doing.
There's always this trade-off: should we publish  exactly what we're doing right away? Should we put
it in the next stages of research and then roll it  out into production Gemini models and not publish
it at all? Or is there some intermediate point? And for example, in our computational photography
work in Pixel cameras, we've often taken the  decision to develop interesting new techniques,
like the ability to do super good night sight  vision for low-light situations or whatever,
put that into the product and then published a  real research paper about the system that does
that after the product is released. Different techniques and developments
have different treatments. Some things we think  are super critical we might not publish. Some
things we think are really interesting  but important for improving our products;
we'll get them out into our products and then  make a decision: did we publish this or do
we give kind of a lightweight discussion  of it, but maybe not every last detail?
Other things I think we publish openly and try  to advance the field and the community because
that's how we all benefit from participating.  I think it's great to go to conferences like
NeurIPS last week with 15,000 people all sharing  lots and lots of great ideas. We publish a lot
of papers there as we have in the past, and  see the field advance is super exciting.
How would you account for... so obviously Google  had all these insights internally rather early on,
including the top researchers. And now Gemini 2 is  out. We didn't get a chance much to talk about it,
but people know it's a really great model. Such a good model. As we say around the
micro-kitchen, “such a good  model, such a good model”.
So it's top in LMSYS Chatbot Arena. And so now  Google's on top. But how would you account for
basically coming up with all the great insights  for a couple of years? Other competitors had
models that were better for a while despite that. We've been working on language models for a long
time. Noam's early work on spelling correction in  2001, the work on translation, very large-scale
language models in 2007, and seq2seq and word2vec  and more recent Transformers and then BERT.
Things like the internal Meena system that was  actually a chatbot-based system designed to kind
of engage people in interesting conversations.  We actually had an internal chatbot system that
Googlers could play with even before ChatGPT  came out. And actually, during the pandemic,
a lot of Googlers would enjoy spending,  you know, everyone was locked down at home,
and so they enjoyed spending time chatting  with Meena during lunch because it was
like a nice, you know, lunch partner. I think one of the things we were a little,
our view of things from a search perspective  was these models hallucinate a lot,
they don't get things right a lot of the time- or  some of the time- and that means that they aren't
as useful as they could be and so we’d like to  make that better. From a search perspective,
you want to get the right answer 100% of the  time, ideally and be very high on factuality.
These models were not near that bar. I think what we were a little unsure
about is that they were incredibly useful. Oh  and they also had all kinds of safety issues,
like they might say offensive things and we had to  work on that aspect and get that to a point where
we were comfortable releasing the model. But I  think what we didn’t quite appreciate was how
useful they could be for things you wouldn't ask  a search engine, right? Like, help me write a note
to my veterinarian, or like, can you take this  text and give me a quick summary of it? I think
that's the kind of thing we've seen people really  flock to in terms of using chatbots as amazing new
capabilities rather than as a pure search engine. So I think we took our time and got to the point
where we actually released quite capable chatbots  and have been improving them through Gemini models
quite a bit. I think that's actually not  a bad path to have taken. Would we like
to have released the chatbot earlier? Maybe.  But I think we have a pretty awesome chatbot
with awesome Gemini models that are getting  better all the time. And that's pretty cool.
So we've discussed some of the things you guys  have worked on over the last 25 years, and there are so many different fields, right? You start off  with search and indexing to distributed systems,
to hardware, to AI algorithms. And genuinely,  there are a thousand more, just go on either of
their Google Scholar pages or something. What  is the trick to having this level of, not only
career longevity where you're having many decades  of making breakthroughs, but also the breadth of
different fields, both of you, in either order,  what’s the trick to career longevity and breadth?
One thing that I like to do is to find out about a  new and interesting area, and one of the best ways
to do that is to pay attention to what's going  on, talk to colleagues, pay attention to research
papers that are being published, and look at the  kind of research landscape as it's evolving.
Be willing to say, "Oh, chip design. I wonder  if we could use reinforcement learning for some
aspect of that." Be able to dive into a new area,  work with people who know a lot about a different
domain or AI for healthcare or something.  I've done a bit of working with clinicians
about what are the real problems, how could AI  help? It wouldn't be that useful for this thing,
but it would be super useful for this. Getting those insights, and often working
with a set of five or six colleagues who have  different expertise than you do. It enables you to
collectively do something that none of you could  do individually. Then some of their expertise
rubs off on you and some of your expertise rubs  off on them, and now you have this bigger set of
tools in your tool belt as an engineering  researcher to go tackle the next thing.
I think that's one of the beauties of  continuing to learn on the job. It's
something I treasure. I really enjoy diving  into new things and seeing what we can do.
I'd say probably a big thing is humility, like  I’d say I’m the most humble. But seriously,
to say what I just did is nothing compared to what  I can do or what can be done. And to be able to
drop an idea as soon as you see something better,  like you or somebody with some better idea,
and you see how maybe what you're thinking  about, what they're thinking about or something
totally different can conceivably work better. I think there is a drive in some sense to say,
"Hey, the thing I just invented is awesome, give  me more chips." Particularly if there's a lot of
top-down resource assignment. But I think we also  need to incentivize people to say, "Hey, this
thing I am doing is not working at all. Let me  just drop it completely and try something else."
Which I think Google Brain did quite well.  We had the very kind of bottoms-up UBI kind
of chip allocation. You had a UBI?
Yeah, it was like basically everyone  had one credit and you could pool them.
Gemini has been mostly top-down, which  has been very good in some sense because
it has led to a lot more collaboration and  people working together. You less often have
five groups of people all building the same  thing or building interchangeable things.
But on the other hand, it does lead to some  incentive to say, "Hey, what I'm doing is working
great." And then, as a lead, you hear hundreds  of groups, and everything is, "So you should give
them more chips." There's less of an incentive to  say, "Hey, what I'm doing is not actually working
that well. Let me try something different." So I think going forward, we're going to have
some amount of top-down, some amount of bottom-up,  so as to incentivize both of these behaviors:
collaboration and flexibility. I think both  those things lead to a lot of innovation.
I think it's also good to articulate  interesting directions you think we should go.
I have an internal slide deck called "Go,  Jeff, Wacky Ideas." I think those are a
little bit more product-oriented things,  like, "Hey, I think now that we have these
capabilities, we could do these 17 things." I think that's a good thing because sometimes
people get excited about that and want to start  working with you on one or more of them. And I
think that's a good way to bootstrap where we  should go without necessarily ordering people,
"We must go here." Alright, this was great.
Yeah. Thank you, guys.
Appreciate you taking the time, it was  great chatting. That was awesome.