- The following is a conversation with Jennifer Burns,
a historian of ideas,
including the evolution of economic,
political, and social ideas
in the United States in the 20th century to today.
She wrote two biographies,
one on Milton Friedman and the other on Ayn Rand,
both of which I highly recommend.
This was a super technical
and super fascinating conversation.
At the end, I make a few comments
about my previous conversation with President Zelenskyy
for those of you who may be interested.
This is the Lex Fridman Podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors
in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Jennifer Burns.
You have written two biographies,
one on Milton Friedman and one on Ayn Rand.
So if we can, we will focus on each one separately.
But first, let's talk
about the ideas the two of them held in common.
The value of individual freedom, skepticism of collectivism,
and the ethics of capitalism.
Can you talk about the big picture ideas they converge on?
- Yeah.
So Milton Friedman and Ayn Rand, in the biggest picture,
they're both individualists,
and they're skeptical of collectivities and collectivism.
So their unit of analysis is the individual,
what's good for the individual,
what works for the individual,
and their understanding of society kind of flows from that.
They also both use this focus on individualism to justify
and to support capitalism as a social and economic system.
So we can put them in a similar category.
We can call them individualists,
we could call them libertarians of a sort.
But they're also really different
in how they approach capitalism,
how they approach thinking.
Ayn Rand developed her own moral
and philosophical system to justify individualism
and to connect the individual to capitalism
and to support capitalism as a social and economic system.
Friedman struggles a bit more with how
to justify capitalism,
and he'll ultimately come down to freedom as his core value,
his God, as he says.
And so freedom does connect back to the individual.
But he's not justifying capitalism for his own sake.
He's justifying it
for its ability to underwrite freedom in a social sense
and also in the individual sense.
- At a high level,
are there interesting differences between them?
You already mentioned a few.
Maybe in terms of who they are personally,
maybe in terms of how they approach the justification
for capitalism, maybe other ways.
- Yeah, for sure.
So beyond this idea that Milton Friedman takes a while
to come to his justification of capitalism,
whereas Ayn Rand kind of has it from the start.
She really focuses on the core quality of rationalism
and rationality.
Rationality is the defining feature of human beings,
and so she works from there.
Whereas Friedman, Milton Friedman eventually converges
on this idea of freedom.
So that's one part of it.
The other is their intellectual styles
are really, really different.
Their interpersonal styles are really different.
So, Friedman has big ideas, big principles that guide him,
but he's also deeply empirical.
He spends most of his career doing historical research,
economic research, pulling data from
how people actually make economic decisions
and live in the world,
and using them to test and refine his theories.
Where Rand, to some degree, we could say she's empirical
in that she lives through the Russian Revolution
and takes a very big lesson from that,
but her style of thinking is really first principles,
an axiomatic approach,
going from the basic idea of rationality
and then playing that out in different spheres.
And so those are
just very different intellectual approaches.
And then they lead
in some ways to really different ways of thinking
about how you get things done in the world.
Ayn Rand is a purist.
She wants to start with the pure belief.
She doesn't want it to be diluted.
You know, one of her favorite sayings was, you know,
"It's earlier than you think."
In other words,
we're still moving towards a place where we can really hold
and express these ideals purely.
Friedman, although he didn't use this terminology,
was much more half-a-loaf guy.
You know, like, I'll take what I can get,
and then I'll try to move to where I really want to be.
But he is able to compromise, especially when he moves
from being an economist
into being more of political thinker.
And so that's a really different intellectual style.
And then it also plays out
in their lives in that Ayn Rand is incredibly schismatic.
I mean, she wants her friends to believe what she believes
and support what she supports.
And she's willing
to break a relationship if it doesn't match.
Milton Friedman,
he also does tend to have friends who agree with him,
yet he's always willing to debate his opponents,
and he's willing to do so with a smile on his face.
You know, he's the happy warrior,
and he actually will win a lot of debates simply
by his emotional affect
and his cheerfulness and his confidence,
where Rand will lose debates because she gets
so angry in the face of disagreement.
So, yeah, they have a lot of similarities
and a lot of differences,
and it's been really fascinating to kind of dive deep
into both of them.
- I just re-listened to Ayn Rand's, I think, last lecture,
or at least it's called that,
and just the confrontational nature
of how she answers questions
or how she addresses critics and so on.
There is a kind of charisma to that.
So I think both of them are very effective
at winning over sort of popular support,
but in very different styles.
It seems like Ayn Rand is very cranky, but there's,
I mean, it's the most charismatic, cranky person
I think I've ever listened to.
- Yeah, I mean, people talked about her,
meeting her, and coming to believe
in her ideas in a similar way as they did with Marxism,
in that suddenly everything made sense,
and that when they came to believe in Objectivism,
they felt they had this engine
for understanding the entire world.
Now, after a while, for most people,
that then became confining.
But, yeah, that certainty,
and Friedman had some of that as well.
He clothed it differently.
He clothed it in happiness, where Rand kind of clothes it,
as you said, in crankiness or anger.
I mean, there's also an arc to Rand.
She gets kind of angrier and angrier and crankier
and crankier over the course of her life.
What I enjoyed about my research is I was able to get
into this early moment when she was different
and a little more open,
and then I kind of watched her close
and her harden over time.
- Would it be fair to say that Milton Friedman
had a bit more intellectual humility,
where he would be able to sort of evolve over time
and be convinced by the reality of the world,
to change sort of the nuances of policies,
the nuances of how he thought about economics
or about the world?
- Yeah, absolutely.
Friedman believed in being able to say, "I was wrong."
And there are some things he said he was wrong about.
We'll delve more into monetarism and monetary policy,
but he was able to talk
about the ways his ideas hadn't mapped
onto the world the way he thought they would.
He does a really interesting interview
at the end of his life where he's beginning
to voice some doubts about globalization,
which he was sort of a prophet of globalization,
a cheerleader of globalization.
He really thought it would lead to a better world
in all respects.
And towards the end of his life,
it's about two years before he dies,
there's a note of doubt about how globalization unfolded
and what it would mean,
particularly for the American worker.
And so you can see him still thinking.
And that, to me,
I had sort of assumed he became crankier
and crankier and more and more set in his ways.
And of course, there's a phase
where he does become that way,
especially as he's in the public eye
and there's not room for nuance,
but to find in the last years of his life,
him being so reflective,
that that was absolutely not something Rand could do.
- I think there's a thread throughout this conversation
where we should actually also say that you're
kind of a historian of ideas.
- I am a historian of ideas, yes.
- And so we're talking about today, in part,
about two people who kind of fought for ideas, for an idea,
like we mentioned freedom for capitalism.
And they did it in very different ways.
And it's so interesting to see
sort of the impact they both had and how their elucidation,
explanation of those ideas reverberated throughout society
and how we together, as a society,
figure out what works,
the degree to which they have influence on the public,
the degree to which they have influence
on individual administrations,
like the Reagan administration, Nixon, and so on,
and how it might return, like, fade away
and then come back in the modern times.
And it's so interesting if you just see this whole world
as a game of ideas where we're pushing and pulling
and trying to figure stuff out.
A bunch of people got real excited over a hundred years ago
about communism, and then they try stuff out,
and then the implementation broke down,
and we keep playing with ideas.
So these are the two greats of playing with ideas.
I think that's a thread that just runs through this.
- Yeah.
And of kind of pushing back
against that movement towards communism, social democracy.
But one difference that I really should emphasize,
Rand is a writer of fiction.
She's a philosopher, but she's also a writer of fiction.
So she is working almost in the mythic register,
much more in the psychological register.
She's creating characters that people identify with
and people relate to experiences they've had.
And that's one of the reasons she hits so deep.
And she's also offering people, you know,
I read all the fan letters to her.
People would say things like,
"I read 'The Fountainhead,'
and now I'm getting a divorce," you know? (chuckles)
You know, having just these incredible realizations.
- Milton Friedman didn't get such things.
- And Milton Friedman didn't get such things.
Or, you know, I'll meet someone and they'll say to me,
"You know, Ayn Rand is the reason I went to medical school."
You know, like a woman said this to me a few years back,
"It never even occurred
to me that I could be a doctor until I read Ayn Rand.
And I said, 'I'm going to go to medical school.'"
And so she has that really intense impact on people.
So she thought of herself as rational.
She thought of rationality as kind of what she was doing,
but she was actually doing
a kind of mythopoetic psychological work as well.
Whereas Friedman on the one hand was much more rational
and there's a whole set of economic thinking
and he provides a rational framework
for understanding the world,
and it's the framework of neoclassical economics.
At the same time,
he does pull on mythologies of the idea of America
in the Gilded Age, the frontier mythology,
the individual immigrant, the settler mythology.
He pulls on these, but he doesn't create them.
And he's more kind of playing a tune he already has.
Whereas I think Rand
really does something a little bit deeper
in her ability to reach into people's psyche
and then take that emotional psychological experience
and fuse it to an intellectual world and a political world.
And that's really what makes her so powerful.
And so I think she comes back in
to relevancy in a different way than Friedman does,
because I think in some ways she's tapped
into a kind of more universal human longing for independence
and autonomy and kind of self-creation and self-discovery.
- Nevertheless, there are still pragmatic ideas
that are still important today from Milton Friedman,
even just on the economics level.
So let's dig in.
Let me try.
I took some notes.
Let me try to summarize who Milton Friedman is
and then you can correct me.
Okay, so he is widely considered to be one of the greatest
and most influential economists in history,
not just the 20th century, I think ever.
He was an advocate of economic freedom, like we said,
and just individual freedom in general.
He strongly advocated for free market capitalism
and limited government intervention in the economy,
though you do give,
I've listened to basically everything you have
on the Internet.
You give some more depth
and nuance on his views on this and in your books.
He led the famed Chicago School of Economics
and he won the Nobel Prize in Economics in 1976.
He greatly influenced economic policies
during the Reagan administration and other administrations.
He was an influential public intellectual,
highly influential, not just among economists.
He lived 1912 to 2006,
so that means he lived
and worked through some major world events
where his ideas were really important,
The Great Depression with the New Deal,
World War II with the post-war Reconstruction,
the rise and fall of the Bretton Woods monetary system,
as we may talk about,
the Cold War and all the conflicts involved
in that, sort of the tensions around communism and so on,
so the fall of the Soviet Union.
And also he has some interesting relationships
to China's economic transformation since the 1970s,
the stagflation of the 1970s,
and I'm sure there's a lot more, so.
Can you maybe continue this thread
and give a big picture overview
of the ideas he is known for?
- Yeah, sure.
And that's a great summary.
You learn fast.
So let me start with the economics,
and then I can kind of transition
to how he used those economic ideas
to become a real voice
in the American conservative movement,
in the American political realm.
So I'll kind of highlight for ideas
or contributions or episodes.
One was his work with Anna Schwartz
in revising our understanding of The Great Depression.
And that's tightly related to the second,
which is the school of monetarism
that he and Schwartz really become founders of.
Then there is the prediction of stagflation
and the explanation of that in the 1970s,
which really is one of these,
these sort of career-making predictions.
And we can dig into that.
And then in terms of technical economics,
he's known for the permanent income hypothesis,
which he develops with a group
of female collaborators that I can talk about.
So those are kind of four technical pieces,
end up being really brought together
in what becomes the Chicago School of Economics.
He's undoubtedly the head
and the leader of the Chicago School of Economics.
There's an earlier generation that he learns from.
There's his generation.
There's also a Chicago School of Law
and Economics that's really profoundly influential.
And then there'll be
kind of a third generation that he's somewhat distinct from,
but that goes on to really shape economics.
But let me go back to these kind of four pieces
and let me start with Great Depression.
So Milton Friedman actually lives
through the Great Depression.
He's in college when it hits, and he is,
so he's in college, it's 1928 to 1932,
and he's aware of the Depression and he's deciding,
should I study mathematics or should I study economics?
And he's had some good economics teachers,
but it's really the context,
it's looking around at the slow, you know,
dissolving of economic prosperity.
So he decides to go to Chicago,
he decides to study economics.
And what's really interesting
is that the Great Depression is so unexpected,
it's unpredicted, it's unprecedented.
And economists are really struggling
to know how to respond to it.
And so he's going to arrive at the University
of Chicago when the field is struggling to know what to do.
So he's in this kind of really open space
where the institutional economics
of the 1920s has failed to predict,
which was focused on business cycles.
This is the irony.
Their big thing was charting
and understanding business cycles.
And then we have the biggest business cycle of all time.
And they haven't seen it coming,
and they don't have a good explanation for it.
And what he will get at Chicago is the remnants
of a monetary understanding of the economy.
And so his teachers,
they don't know exactly what's going on,
but they look first to the banking crisis.
They look first to the,
in 1933, it's bank runs,
failures of maybe it's up to a third of American banks.
It's huge, thousands of banks are failing per week.
So they're focused on that.
So that's the first kind of imprint he will have.
The Great Depression has something
to do with the banking system.
The second imprint he will have is that all
of his professors are profoundly concerned
about the social crisis.
They want relief programs, they want them now.
They want bank regulation and financial reform.
They're very active.
This is not laissez-faire by any stretch of the imagination.
So Friedman has that imprinting, and then about,
so he gets there in '32.
'36, '37, the ideas of John Maynard Keynes from Britain,
which has a different explanation,
Keynes has a different explanation of the Great Depression,
will kind of make landfall in American economics
and be very profoundly influential
on most American economists,
but Friedman already,
it's too late for Friedman.
He already has a different perspective.
So Keynesianism unfolds, I can say more about that,
but it basically leads
to more active federal government participation
in the economy.
And what underlies a lot of that,
its adaptation in America particularly,
is the idea that capitalism has failed,
Capitalism has revealed itself to have a profound flaw
in that it's cycles of boom and bust
create social instability, chaos.
It needs to be tamed, it needs to be regulated.
And so that becomes the kind of baseline of politics
in the United States.
The understanding of the New Deal,
the understanding of the Democratic Party,
even to some extent,
the understanding of the Republican Party.
And Friedman never quite,
never quite sure about that.
He has a hunch that there's something else going on.
And he does not buy that capitalism
has sort of ground to a halt,
or the other idea is that capitalism has gone through some
sort of phase transition, and it worked great,
maybe while we had a frontier.
This is a very serious argument that people are making.
The United States used to have a frontier,
a place where Europeans hadn't fully settled.
Of course, they're pushing out the native tribes.
That's another story.
But that this frontier is the engine of economic growth.
And the frontier is now over, it's closed,
and we're going to stagnate.
There's a theory of secular stagnation.
And so to deal with secular stagnation,
we're just going to have to have a more active state.
So Friedman is suspicious of all these assumptions,
and he has this idea that it's something to do with money.
Money is somehow important.
And so he joins together with Anna Schwartz,
who is an economist.
She doesn't at this time hold a PhD.
She's working for the National Bureau of Economic Research.
And they come together to do this study of money
in the US economy.
And it takes him 12 years to write the book.
And they're releasing their ideas and they're arguing.
And Friedman is writing papers, giving talks,
saying, "Money's really important,"
and nobody's really believing him.
He's a crank.
He's at Chicago, he's out,
you know, Chicago's a well-known university,
but he's sort of considered a crank.
And then in '63, he and Anna Schwartz published this book.
And it's, you know, 800 pages.
It's a reinterpretation
of the history of the United States through money.
Like the central character is money, whether it's specie,
greenback, or the US currency.
And they have a whole chapter on the Great Depression.
And what they've literally done,
Schwartz has done most of this.
They've gone, Schwartz has gone to banks and said,
"Show me your books."
And then she's added up, column by column,
how much money is in your vault,
how much money is on deposit,
how much money is circulating.
And so they literally have graphs,
you can see them in the book,
of how much money has been circulating in the US
at various different points in time.
And when they get to the Great Depression,
they find the quantity of money available
in the economy goes down by a third.
And in some ways this is completely obvious,
because so many banks have failed
and we don't have any type of bank insurance at that point.
So if your bank goes under, your savings are there,
the money essentially vanishes,
and it's fractional reserve banking, right?
So you've put in,
they can loan up to 90% off on their deposits.
And so Friedman and Schwartz present this argument
that what really made the Great Depression so bad
was this drop in the amount of money,
the 30% drop in the money,
they called the great contraction.
And then they go further and they say,
"Well, how did this happen and why?"
And they pinpoint the Federal Reserve,
which is a fairly new institution at that time.
And they say, "What did the Federal Reserve do?"
The lender of last resort,
what did it do in the face of what they're depicting
as a massive, unprecedented liquidity crisis?
And they find it's not really doing much.
And they really dig into the details,
and they find that the Federal Reserve
has gone through a sort of personnel change
and some of the key leaders in the 1920s,
Benjamin Strong is one of them, he's now deceased.
And the dominance of the New York Federal Reserve,
which in their telling is global, it's interconnected,
it's seen a lot of financial things come and go.
And they believe that the New York Fed had the understanding
to recognize this is a liquidity crisis.
We should be very generous,
we should support all the banks.
Their influence has diminished
for the kind of banks that are more,
they don't say, like the rubes and the hicks,
but it basically is.
It's like the people
in charge don't know what they're doing.
And so the Fed pursues this
kind of policy of masterly inactivity.
They don't see it as their problem.
They don't do much.
There's an enormous liquidity crisis.
And that's their version
of what the Great Depression is all about.
That it's a financial system meltdown,
it's a liquidity crisis.
And that it, in some ways,
well, in many ways, they argue,
very strong counterfactual argument,
the Federal Reserve could have prevented it,
and it did not.
And so it becomes then an institutional failure
and a political failure,
not a failure of capitalism as a system.
And so this book comes out, it's a blockbuster.
And even those economists who've been like,
"Friedman is a crank, I don't buy it,"
are like, "Friedman and Schwartz are onto something.
Milton Friedman, Anna Schwartz are onto something."
And so that really changes the game.
And this is also one
of his most influential contributions,
because Friedman and Schwartz becomes the playbook
for the Federal Reserve.
And we have lived through this, right?
In the financial crisis,
the Federal Reserve is ready to loan.
Covid, the Federal Reserve does all kinds of new things,
because no Federal Reserve chair wants to be
in Friedman and Schwartz 2.0 that somebody writes
where they're the bad guy who let the economy melt down.
So, you know, the specifics
of what they say to do have obviously evolved
as the system has changed,
but this is a playbook for how to deal with economic crisis.
It's Friedman and Schwartz.
And so it's absolutely fundamental.
And that is really going to be the place he makes his mark.
- There's a lot of things to say here.
So first, the book we're talking about
is the "A Monetary History of the United States,"
in part for which Milton Friedman won the Nobel Prize.
You've also mentioned the influence of the Great Depression,
if you could even just rewind to that.
So he went to, I guess, college in Rutgers.
- [Jennifer] That's right.
- And he was, you know, mathematical proclivities,
so he was kind of wanting to be a mathematician.
And so it's kind of a cool crossroads.
It's interesting how the right time,
the right person arrives.
So you describe this really well, that,
so he had this choice to be a mathematician or an economist.
And the economist is University of Chicago,
mathematician is Brown University, whichever.
And then this is also the beginnings, as you've described,
of mathematical economics.
So he fits in nicely into this using,
I think you said the number
of equations started going up per paper,
- [Jennifer] Yes.
- Which is a really nice way to put it.
So really the right person
at the right time to try to solve this puzzle
of the economy melting down.
It's so interesting, just one human,
it's just, from just zooming in
on a single human making a decision about life
and it's hard to know when you're in it
that the world is melting down
from an economics perspective
and that I could do something
about this to figure out what it is.
And also I'm going to reject the mainstream narrative
about why this happened.
- Yeah, so the other piece of the puzzle,
when he goes to Rutgers,
he thinks he'll be an actuary.
So Milton Friedman's family, his parents are immigrants,
Jewish immigrants from Eastern Europe.
They're pretty atypical in that they don't stay in New York,
you know, and they move to Rahway, New Jersey,
and they put together a fairly middle-class life
as kind of, they have a shop.
They do some wholesale buying and selling.
And then his father dies when he's 16.
His life becomes more precarious,
but it's never as precarious as he makes it out to be.
He's got three older sisters, they earn a good living,
incidentally, they all have better grades
in high school than he does,
but he's the one that goes to college.
But it's actually really important
that he loses his father figure,
because he's then looking for other father figures.
And he meets two at Rutgers.
One is Arthur Burns,
who will go on to have a huge influence in his career.
No relation to me, by the way,
(Lex and Jennifer chuckle)
but Arthur Burns is like him,
a fellow Jewish immigrant boy on the make.
He's older, and he's making a career as an economist.
And then there's Homer Jones,
who has gone to the University of Chicago
and is studying with Frank Knight at Chicago and says,
"You have to go to Chicago."
So he has these two mentors.
And Burns in particular suggests,
"Oh, I could be an economist.
That could be my career path."
The idea to be an actuary for an insurance company,
I'm not sure where he got that idea,
but he just thought that was something he could do
as someone who was good at math.
And so that college
really opens the perspective, opens the door.
And then I think it's really key that again,
he doesn't get an explanation that he buys
for the Great Depression.
So then he's looking for one.
And the math part
is a really interesting aspect of his career.
Now, he actually comes to Chicago to study
with a mathematical economist, Henry Schultz.
But he gets there and he thinks Schultz is kind of dumb.
(Lex laughs)
He really does.
He's incredibly arrogant,
and he just thinks this guy's not that smart.
And it seems that, I mean,
Schultz did some really important work
in the early stages of mathematical economics.
But a lot of the oral histories about him are like,
"Yeah, he wasn't that bright," you know?
So Friedman's maybe onto something.
So he falls into the set
of students who are really enthralled
with this other professor, Frank Knight.
And Frank Knight is against math in economics.
Frank Knight is like, you know, a neoclassical economist,
but not a mathematical economist.
He's an old-school liberal.
He's really concerned about liberal democracy,
economic liberalism.
And Friedman is very deeply influenced by Knight,
and he continues to pursue mathematical economics.
So he'll go, for part of his graduate career,
he goes to Columbia University,
where he actually gets his PhD from,
and he works with a mathematical economist there.
And so he comes out trained
in what will eventually be econometrics in statistics
and economics, his early publications are in statistics,
but it's not really
where his intellectual heart and soul are.
And eventually he will turn very profoundly
against mathematics and economics
and become a sort of heterodox strain
throughout 20th century economics
that says, "Simple models are better.
We need to work off empirical data,
not construct elegant models,"
and becomes really
sort of countercultural within economics in that way.
- And the test of a good model
is it should actually predict stuff that happens.
- It should predict stuff that happen.
It should tie back to what's going on.
- I'm wondering which direction to go.
So first, actually,
if we could zoom out on the different schools of economics.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- Just the basics.
You mentioned neoclassical.
We mentioned Keynesian economics.
We mentioned, what else did we mention?
Well, the Chicago School of Economics.
Where does Austrian economics fit into that pile?
And Marxian economics?
And can we just even just linger
and try to redefine Keynesian economics
and Chicago School of Economics,
neoclassical economics, and Austrian economics,
because there's some overlap and tension.
- Okay, so schools of economics.
So we could start with classical economics.
Classical economics we could think of,
Adam Smith is kind of your classic classical economist,
the founder of the discipline.
Classical economics does not really use math,
is very close to political economy.
It's concerned with, as Smith puts it,
"The wealth of nations."
It's concerned to some degree with distribution.
It's concerned to some degree
with what makes a good political system.
And what tends to really define classical economics
when you're looking from a great distance
is what's called the labor theory of value.
So where does value come from in classical economics?
It comes from the labor that a person puts into it.
So maybe this in some way comes
from Locke's notion of property that you kind of mingle,
you know, your labor with the natural world.
We can say labor theory of value.
So classical economics concerned with Smith is arguing
against mercantilism for more free trade,
often goes by the name of political economy
to show it's more capacious.
It's thinking of politics and economics.
You can still read these books today.
The sentences are long, the words are different,
but you can still follow along.
So the real big transition from classical economics
and political economy to economics
as it's understood today,
comes with the marginal revolution.
And the marginal revolution is a scientific revolution
that happens in a couple different places simultaneously.
This is one of these things that you see
in the history of science.
Like, you know, there'll be some breakthrough,
like Darwin has a breakthrough,
but like somebody else has sort of the same breakthrough
at the same time, totally, you know, differently.
So there's a version of marginalism that's continental.
You know, there's a version in the German-speaking lands,
in the French speaking lands, and in Britain.
And they all kind of come together,
and the shift is in the theory of value.
So the theory of value in marginalism is on the margin.
So say you have one apple and you want a second one.
How much is going from one apple to two apple worth for you?
Probably quite a bit.
If you had 10 apples,
maybe going to 11 apples doesn't matter that much.
The marginal value is less.
So what marginalism does, though,
most importantly is it opens the door to math in economics,
because it means you can graph this now,
you can depict this relationship graphically.
And there's some really interesting work
in the history of economics that shows a lot
of the people who developed marginalism were looking
to physics as a model,
physics, the queen of the sciences.
And so they were thinking,
they imported terms
from the natural world to describe the social world
through the lens of economics,
terms like equilibrium.
So the idea being that if you looked at a market,
a market would reach equilibrium when everybody has bought
and sold all that they want,
or the price will settle
at an equilibrium price when it's really the demand
and supply are matching up.
- And some of these ideas are things we would pick up
at a microeconomics class.
- Oh yes, this is still out there.
This is sort of the basic foundation
of microeconomics, marginal analysis.
And so in the German-speaking intellectual tradition,
this is the root of Austrian economics.
And people picking up the marginal revolution
in the German speaking lands are opposed
to the historicists,
who are thinking in a more evolutionary way
about how societies kind of grow and change.
And they have a vision of economic ideas
as applying differently to different types
of social arrangements.
Where the marginalists, remember, are inspired by physics.
And this is a set
of natural laws that applies anywhere
to any sort of human society.
So that's his first really big fissure
that we'll see again and again.
Are you historically minded?
Do certain traits of economic life inhere, adhere,
and become expressed in certain types of societies?
Or are there universal economic laws that flow
through any type of society?
So that's kind of a juncture, a break.
And so marginalism,
first people start using really geometry
to kind of graph things.
But marginalism is also opening up to the possibility
of calculus and the possibility of creating models.
But at that point in time, late 19th century,
a model is something like a physicist does,
like think of an inclined plane
and how fast does the ball roll from one to the other.
It's a physical representation of the world.
And eventually economists will start
to create mathematical representations of the world,
but we're not quite there yet.
So we're late 19th century and we have this fissure,
we have this introduction
of marginal analysis that marks the juncture
from classical economics to economics.
So let's say now we have economics,
but we still have this fissure between historical thinking
and let's call it natural law thinking,
that's not quite right,
but physical laws versus contingency.
And then in the United States this ends up mapping
onto debates about capitalism.
And so more historically-minded economists
tend to be interested in the Progressive movement
and which is invested in taming
and regulating industrial capitalism
and changing its excesses, you know,
factory safety laws, wage laws,
working conditions laws.
Yet in general,
American economists all use marginal analysis,
just in different ways.
The ones who are more drawn
to marginal analysis become known
as neoclassical economists.
They're neoclassical.
The neo is because they're using marginal analysis.
The classical is because they don't think we need
to change the way the economy operates
or the government operates.
They're not progressive,
whereas the progressives are saying things like,
"We need to use social control.
The state and the people collectively
and democratically need to control the way economics unfolds
and make sure things are fair and equal."
So that school of thought becomes known
as institutional economics in the United States
by the 20th century.
So it's part of the Progressive movement,
late 19th century.
Into the 20th century,
it really becomes institutional economics,
and it's quite dominant.
And the neoclassical economists are still there,
but they're very much a minority.
And Frank Knight, Milton Friedman's teacher,
is one of the minority neoclassical economists.
And the institutionalists are much more progressive still.
- Is it fair to say that the neoclassical folks
and even the classical folks
versus the institutional economics folks,
they have a disagreement
about how much government intervention
that should be in the economy?
So neoclassical is less intervention,
and then institutional economists,
the progressive folks,
has more intervention.
- Yes, yes, exactly right.
So this is the situation in the 1920s.
But the other piece I should mention is the first generation
of progressive economists were very radical.
They were closely allied with the socialist movement,
with labor radicalism,
and many of them lost their jobs at universities.
This is kind of connects to the early,
the dawn of academic freedom.
This is before academic freedom.
And they were chastened.
They became much more mainstream.
By the time we get to the 1920s,
we don't really have radical critiques of society
coming from economists.
Much smaller profession,
much less important than it is today,
and fairly peaceful,
because the 1920s are a fairly peaceful decade
in the United States.
So this is a situation when the Great Depression hits.
And as I mentioned before, the head,
the kind of most important institutional economist
is Wesley Mitchell,
and he has said,
he's written a whole book on business cycles,
but he doesn't see this business cycle coming.
And it hits, and he doesn't have a good explanation for it.
Now, perhaps the preeminent neoclassical economist
was Irving Fisher.
Now, Irving Fisher is big into the stock market,
and Irving Fisher says sometime in late summer 1929,
"Stocks are going ever higher
and will continue to go ever higher forever."
And so he loses his reputation after the stock market crash.
So Milton Friedman is stepping into a field
in which the greats have been discredited
and there's an enormous economic crisis all around.
- And everybody's struggling
to figure out why the crisis happened.
- Yes.
And the other thing he's stepping into is a world where
in the United States,
there's a great deal of anger at capitalism, at the system,
unemployed people on the street.
In Europe, there's rising fascist movements.
In Asia, there's rising fascist movements.
And so everyone's very concerned about this.
And Friedman is seeing a lot
of this through the lens of Frank Knight,
who feels like we are maybe reaching the end
of what he calls liberalism.
He calls himself an old-fashioned liberalism.
We're reaching the end
of representative democratic government,
because representative democratic government
cannot solve these social problems.
And capitalism, as it has developed,
Knight is very pro-capitalist,
but he says it's generating inequality
and this is putting too many strains on the system.
So Knight will become one
of the people who helps Friedman think,
how do I develop a new theory of capitalism that works
in an era of mass democracy where people can vote
and people can express
at the ballot box their unhappiness
with what's happening economically?
So this larger movement will generate,
of which F. A. Hayek is a part,
Friedman is a part, that becomes the very early stirrings
of trying to think about a new sort
of liberalism which will eventually be called neoliberalism.
- Okay, so if we can just linger
on the definitions of things.
So we mentioned what neoclassical is,
and the institutional economics is.
What's Keynesian economics?
And the Chicago School of Economics, I guess,
is a branch of neoclassical
that's a little bit more empirical
versus maybe model-based. - [Jennifer] Yeah.
- And Keynesian is very model-heavy,
more intervention of government.
- [Jennifer] Yes.
- So the real battle is Keynesian versus everybody else.
- That is what eventually comes to pass in the United States
and in the kind of overall
developed profession of economics.
The other piece of the puzzle here
is the introduction of mathematics.
And it's been around the edges,
but it will pick up speed in the 1930s,
like the Econometrics Society is founded.
They start publishing,
people start using more statistical
and mathematical tools to think about economics,
and they're given a boost,
sort of inadvertently by the rise of Keynesian economics.
So Keynes is trained in the neoclassical tradition.
He's an absolutely fascinating figure.
He's been there in the peace negotiations at Versailles.
He basically calls World War II.
He's like, "Hey,
we're gonna have another war here caused by Germany,
because this peace Treaty has been done
in such a vindictive way,
and people have made such bad decisions."
He's there, he sees it happening.
And so when the Great Depression unfolds,
he basically comes up with a new theory
for explaining what's going on.
And the previous neoclassical understanding
is sort of things go up and things go down,
and when they go down,
there's a natural mechanism to bring them back up.
So when the economy's going down,
prices are going down,
wages are going down, everybody's losing money,
but eventually firms are going to realize,
hey, I can hire people cheap.
Hey, I can buy stuff cheap.
I don't have a lot of competition.
Maybe I should get in the game here.
And then others will start to get in,
and then you regenerate prosperity in that way.
And so Keynes says, "Sure, that's one theory,
but something different is happening right now.
Part of why it's happening
is because the working class is more empowered now.
They're not simply going to just take low wages
and ride them down to the floor.
We might not hit the floor."
But also, he says,
"People might become too anxious to spend.
They might not want to invest."
And, you know, Keynes has these discussions
of animal spirits, right?
He's still enough of a political economist to think not just
in terms of human rationality,
but what are some other things going on in human beings?
And people might decide to sit on their money,
they might not invest it.
And so what happens then is you could get stuck
in a bad equilibrium.
So in the neoclassical model,
the equilibrium kind of restarts and resets itself.
And he says, "No, we could get stuck here.
We could get stuck in the depression."
"And in that case, what has to happen," he says,
"The government stimulates investment
and the government itself invests."
And then he argues that, you know, this is a student of his,
Richard Kahn says, you know,
"As the government invests a dollar,
it has like a multiplier effect."
A dollar spent by the government
kind of ramifies out throughout the economy.
So it takes the government and puts it in the center,
as opposed to, say,
the banking system or the financial system,
which would be the more Friedman analysis.
And for many economists of Friedman's generation,
and he's a weird generation,
because the generation that becomes dominant
is just like four years older,
the men who become Keynesian economics,
but that four years is really important,
because they come in to graduate school in economics
and they get exposed to the new ideas
of John Maynard Keynes, and they, you know,
I think it's Paul Samuelson calls it,
like it was like a South Sea virus (chuckles)
that attacked all of the younger,
all of the younger economists immediately succumbed.
And like no one under 50 ever got the disease, right,
because their thinking's already set.
And so Keynesianism,
Keynes himself is very suspicious of math in economics.
And he and Friedman, it's fascinating.
One of the first books by Jan Tinbergen, a Dutch economist,
to use math in economics,
these huge volumes.
Volume one, Keynes pans it.
Volume two, Friedman pans it.
So they're in the same page,
but what happens is
as Keynesianism arrives in the United States,
Franklin Roosevelt is not really a Keynesian.
He's kind of an accidental or experimental Keynesian.
And there's a bunch of different ideas
in the United States that are very similar to Keynesianism.
They're not theorized,
but they're similar ideas
that the government has to do something.
So this all comes together,
and American economists realize
that you can construct models in the Keynesian perspective.
And if you can use numbers in these models,
you can go to Washington D.C. with numbers,
and you seem like you have a lot more authority.
And so math becomes really twinned into Keynesian economics.
- So numbers are used as a kind of a symbol of expertise.
We really know what the hell's going on
because we have some numbers, right?
- Right, and we can create a model.
And so we can say,
"Okay, in the model, the interest rate is here.
Taxes are here.
So let's play with government spending.
Let's make it up, let's make it down,
and then we can get an estimation.
It'll spit out here's predicted GDP."
So the other piece of the Keynesian revolution
is it really gets people thinking kind of holistically
about the economy as one conceptual unit.
And you then have what Paul Samuelson
will end up calling the neoclassical synthesis.
And this was still in economics today.
If you take Micro, you're going to get supply and demand,
scarcity, marginal analysis.
If you take Macro,
you're going to get a very different approach.
And that's more Keynesian-based.
And so the idea is that,
and this makes sense, I mean,
you can think of this from statistics, right?
The way things act individually
versus when they're all added together
can be very different.
So there's this kind of uneasy piece
where economists are using
kind of neoclassical tools to analyze individual behavior
and individual market behavior.
And they're shifting to a different paradigm when they think
about the economy as a whole.
And in this paradigm of the economy as a whole,
the federal budget,
the taxing and spending power of the federal government,
become paramount.
And that is called the fiscal revolution.
And that's really the essence of Keynesianism.
But the key thing to remember is that Keynesianism
and Keynes are different.
And there's this famous episode
where John Maynard Keynes comes to D.C.
and he goes to dinner,
and he comes back
and he says to one of his friends in London, he says,
"Oh, yeah, it was really interesting.
I was the only non-Keynesian there."
(Lex laughing)
- [Lex] Yeah.
- You know?
- So Keynesianism
is more government intervention, fiscal policy,
so put the government
at the center of influencing the economy.
And then the different flavors
of whether it's Austrian economics
or Chicago School of Economics is saying,
"No, we have to put less government intervention
and trust the market more."
And the formulation of that
from Milton Friedman is trust the money more,
not trust, but the money supply is the thing
that should be focused on.
- Yes.
So the Austrians
and the Chicago schools see economic prosperity
and growth comes from individual initiative,
individual entrepreneurship,
kind of private sources.
The private market is what drives economic growth,
not the public sector.
And so for Friedman, then the question is,
what is the government's role?
And because he's lived through the Great Depression,
he's not laissez-faire,
and he won't ever be laissez-faire.
Now, interestingly, Hayek,
living through the Great Depression,
at first is laissez-faire.
And he's like, "Sure, let it rip."
And things get so bad that Hayek's like,
"Okay, that's not gonna work.
- Can we actually define laissez-faire?
So what do we mean?
Like, what's the free market?
What's laissez-faire?
What's the extreme version here?
- So, yeah, laissez-faire means leave it be.
In France, it's more often used
as an insult than as an actual.
Very few people are completely and totally laissez-faire.
That would be, like the pure laissez-faire
would be the sort of pure, maybe pure anarchist position,
like the state does nothing,
or the state isn't even there,
but it tends to,
if I could maybe make it more precise,
it would be focused on freedom
of contract would be essential.
And that means,
like the buyer of labor and the seller of labor
must have absolute freedom to contract.
So that means no minimum wage law,
no working hours law,
no employment law, things like that.
And this is all pre-Progressive movement.
A lot of things are that way.
You know, imagine you're in 19th century America
and you have a farm,
and you hire someone to help you on the farm.
You offer the money, they take it.
If they fall off a ladder and break their back,
maybe you help them out, maybe you don't,
but there's not a whole apparatus of legal liability
and safety and things like that.
So that would be one piece.
Another piece of laissez-faire
would be free trade amongst nations.
So no regulation of who can invest in a nation
or who can take money out of a nation.
So Nippon Steel could come and invest in US Steel,
and there would be no grounds in which to reject that.
Or you could, as a billionaire in the United States,
relocate you and all your money to another country,
and the United States couldn't try to keep you
and nobody else could stop you from coming in.
And then in the context of economic crisis,
laissez-faire would not encompass centrally provided relief
because in the pure theory, again,
very seldom applied purely,
but in the pure theory,
the wages need to come down far enough
and people need to be desperate enough to start taking work
and to start the machine again.
So the theory would be if you give people relief,
they might not go back to work.
Now, almost nobody says that in the Great Depression,
because the situation is so bad,
and it's, you know,
people are starving on the street
and people feel for humanitarian and ethical reasons,
it's not okay to say that.
The Austrians, though,
at first Hayek and Lionel Robbins are like,
"This is a business cycle and it needs to run its course
and it will be detrimental if we intervene."
And then pretty soon Hayek has to change his tune.
- So the Austrians are the most hardcore
in terms of laissez-faire?
- Absolutely.
And so Hayek will make the turn towards accepting more
of a state, and then will come to talk
about how the state needs
to support what he calls a competitive order.
But his mentor, Ludwig von Mises,
still remains very hardcore
and is not really open to things like unemployment insurance
or other state-based interventions.
- What does von Mises say about human suffering
that's witnessed in the Great Depression, for example?
Like, what are we supposed to, as economists,
as humans that define policy,
what are we supposed to see
when people are suffering at scale?
- Yeah, I wish I knew an answer to that question.
I don't know enough about von Mises
and his reaction in the Great Depression.
I think I would hazard that he would look more down the road
and say, "Well, if you start here,
you're gonna go places that are bad."
But I don't factually know what he said in response.
I do know that Hayek's position doesn't last very long.
It's not a position you can hold to,
maybe you could hold to it in other cycles.
The other thing that was interesting
is I found very few Americans saying this.
Most who were, were kind of small town electeds
or the most famous is Andrew Mellon,
quoted by Herbert Hoover.
So not directly, we don't have him on record saying this,
but apparently Hoover records
in his memoirs that Mellon said something
like, "Liquidate real estate, liquidate stocks,
you know, purge the rottenness out of the system,
people will live a healthier life."
And certainly there were members
of the Federal Reserve who felt like it would create,
they didn't say moral hazard, but it would create
what we now call moral hazard, bad habits,
were we to intervene and to save failing banks,
because failing banks need to be taught a lesson.
They need to be taught discipline.
And so a lot of people, I think,
saw it in the context of discipline.
This is discipline.
And if you remove the discipline,
you'll be taking away something fundamental in society.
- So Milton Friedman never quite went all the way
to laissez-faire.
- No, no, he didn't see that.
And what's really interesting is the number
of incredibly radical proposals
that he and his teachers were floating.
So I've mentioned Frank Knight.
Another really important influence
on Friedman was Henry Simons,
who was a junior professor at Chicago.
And Simons had this idea for what he called 100% money,
which would be a law that says banks have to hold 100%
of the deposits they receive.
They can't loan them out on the margin.
So this would completely
and totally have overhauled the US banking system.
And he would have said, "There's a category
of things called banks where you get deposits.
And then there's going to be a category of sort of,"
he didn't say investment banks,
but investment vehicles that will invest.
So similar to what did happen
in some ways in the banking reforms
in that in the 1930s the investment banks were split
from the deposit banks,
and the banks that took deposits
were much more highly regulated
and they were supported by the FDIC.
But the point being the Chicago School
had these very radical proposals for reform.
Go off the gold standard, restrict the currency,
change the banks, immediately relieve payments now.
What is important to note though
is that they thought of all of those
as emergency measures to get through the emergency,
not as permanent alterations in the state of what had to be,
and not permanent alterations between state and market.
Where the Keynesian assumption is things have changed,
times have changed,
we're in a new dispensation,
and we need a new relationship.
So Milton Friedman is very open to doing things differently
in a state of emergency.
He will have different ideas
during World War II than any other time.
And that's why I argue,
I think he would have been supportive
of at least the first rounds of coronavirus relief,
because I think he
would have put his emergency thinking hat on.
So in that way he was definitely more flexible.
- You mentioned Hayek.
Who is this guy?
What's his relationship to Milton Friedman
in the space of ideas
and in the context of the Great Depression?
Can we talk about that a little bit?
- Sure.
So F.A. Hayek is an Austrian economist
who takes up a posting in London,
and, you know, he's a mentor,
a mentee rather, of Ludwig von Mises.
He's writing about business cycles,
Austrian capital theory, and the Depression hits.
And he's one of the few economists who in the beginning,
really is not calling for much intervention.
Although as he realizes how politically unpalatable that is,
he will develop a more softened version
of Austrian economics that has room
for a whole range of social services.
What's significant about Hayek
is that he is also watching what's happening
in Austria, what's happening in Germany,
and he's really worried the same thing is going
to happen to the Western democracies.
And he sees the root cause of this is socialism.
This shift towards an expanded role
for government which we've been talking about,
is happening in the United States.
It's also happening in Britain.
And so he writes this book that becomes incredibly famous,
"The Road to Serfdom,"
basically saying, taking these steps
towards a planned economy
or an economy that's a modified form
of capitalism is going to, could,
he's very clear that this is not an inevitability.
But if the same steps are taken
and people follow the same line of thinking,
we may end up in a sort of coercive totalitarian state.
So this becomes enormously popular in the United States.
First of all, he's in good touch
with Friedman's teachers,
even before this book comes out.
They see them as kindred spirits.
Frank Knight is in touch with him.
Henry Simons is in touch with him.
They all see themselves as liberals.
They call themselves old-fashioned,
unreconstructed liberals.
And so even before he becomes famous,
Hayek will be trying to kind of organize thinkers
and intellectuals who he believes shares his values
of what we would call today classical liberalism,
and to kind of create a counter-consensus
to the one that's gathering.
Now, Hayek also chooses not to argue against Keynes,
and he feels that this is a huge missed opportunity,
that he should have staked out the case against Keynes
and that because he did not,
people come to believe there is no case against Keynes.
Keynes is literally unanswerable.
So Hayek will have this great regret.
He will channel some of his regrets
into sort of community building,
specifically developing the Mont Pelerin Society
And it will fall to Friedman
to really make that case against Keynes.
But Hayek will end up at Chicago.
And Hayek really influences Friedman to think
about what Hayek calls the competitive order
and how the state can and must maintain a competitive order,
that is the system of laws, of norms,
of practices that makes it possible for markets to function.
And this is one of these key differentiators
between the older philosophy of laissez-faire
and the newer reconceptualization of liberalism, which says,
"Yes, we need a state.
We need a state that's not intervening
in markets under social democratic auspices,
but is structuring and supporting markets
so that they can function with maximum freedom,
keeping in mind that
if there aren't basic social supports needed,
the market is apt to generate the type of either inequality
or social instability
that will call the whole system into question."
So Hayek is really key
in promoting this modified liberalism.
But from being a very prominent economist in the 1920s
and 1930s, as mathematics becomes the language of economics,
Hayek is completely left out in the cold.
Now, Friedman to some degree, is left out in the cold.
But Friedman at least has proved the mathematical economists
that he knows what they're up to, and he's rejecting it
from a position of expertise and knowledge.
And he literally drives
the mathematical economists out of Chicago.
They're clustered in a group called the Cowles Commission,
and he makes their life hell.
They flee.
They flee the Friedman onslaught.
(Lex chuckles)
But then when Hayek arrives at the University of Chicago,
he would like to be considered
for a position in the economics department.
And Friedman, Milton Friedman, says, "No way.
You're not really an economist because you're not empirical,
because you just develop these theories."
So he has an appreciation for Hayek as a social thinker,
but not as an economist.
So what Friedman decides to do,
his answer to Keynes will be deeply empirical,
but it will also be theoretical.
And it will create an alternative intellectual world
and approach for economists who aren't satisfied
with Keynesianism.
And almost single handedly,
Friedman will introduce sort of political
and ideological diversity into the field of economics,
because from his beachhead in Chicago,
he will develop the theory of monetarism.
So what is monetarism?
The easy way to summarize it is this famous dictum
of Milton Friedman's,
"Inflation is always and everywhere a monetary phenomena."
And it's fascinating that he becomes an expert in inflation
because the first research,
and the first major research product
of monetarism is that theory of the Great Depression
in "A Monetary History of the United States."
And that is a theory of a deflation, all prices going down.
And he will go back
to an idea that Irving Fisher had popularized,
but a very old idea, almost a truism,
the quantity theory of money,
which says, "The level of the price level
is related to the amount
of money circulating in an economy."
So if you have more money, prices go up.
If you have less money, prices go down.
Now this seems like very basic
and almost too basic to bear repeating,
but Friedman is saying this very basic relationship
holds true even in an advanced industrial economy.
And that is what people have started to doubt.
And if you think about money,
you think about banks,
you don't think necessarily about the federal budget,
spending, and taxation.
And what you see happens in American economics,
the textbooks previous to the Keynesian revolution,
they spent a lot of time on money,
they spent a lot of time on interest rates.
You can do word counts.
And other scholars have done the word counts.
And then word count
for money after World War II just plummets
and you start seeing things like taxation, budget,
those things go up.
So what happens
is the economics profession shifts its attention.
It just looks away from money to other things.
And Friedman is one of the few who's saying,
"No, money still matters, money still counts."
And it's a very counterintuitive argument to make.
It's a very historical argument to make.
And this is absolutely fascinating to me.
With Anna Schwartz, he develops this 150-year timeframe.
He also has students working on episodes of hyperinflation
in different periods of time.
He's also looking back to ancient history,
inflationary episodes there.
And he's saying, "This is a law of economics.
This is something that recurs throughout time.
It's not historical, it's not contingent,
it's a law of economics."
And you know, his Keynesian counterpoints are saying,
"No, that's not relevant any longer.
Maybe once it was relevant, but it's not relevant today."
Now, in some ways they have a point,
because in order to pay for World War II,
the federal government sells a lot of bonds,
it issues a lot of debt,
and it wants to pay this debt back at a low interest rate.
And it wants people to keep buying it.
It wants the low interest rate
to be competitive with other interest rates.
So it wants, in general,
low interest rates throughout the economy.
And the Federal Reserve has been
so discredited by the Great Depression
that the treasury basically runs the Federal Reserve
and says, "Keep interest rates low."
And so that's what it's doing.
And so the Federal Reserve
has stopped being an independent entity.
It's just a sub sort of Department of the Treasury.
But in 1951, they negotiate
what's called the Treasury-Fed Accord.
And the Federal Reserve gets its independence,
but it doesn't really use it,
but statutorily it now has it.
And so most economists are just observing a regime
in which the Federal Reserve has no power,
a regime in which there is really little inflation,
the inflation that is seen is post,
there's a little burst of inflation in the Korean War.
And they're saying,
"Inflation's not really important,
it's not really relevant,
and money's not really relevant and important."
And so to break through and to make the argument,
that's why Friedman and Schwartz go to history,
and they're able to make that argument for history.
So then Friedman is coming out with a variety
of papers that are saying,
"When I look at economic fluctuations,"
he maps them side by side
to fluctuations in the money supply
and says, "Look, they fit."
And other economists,
remember they're building complicated mathematical models
and Friedman's doing extremely simple stuff,
and they just think it's dumb, it's not interesting,
it's not true, they don't buy it at all.
But after a monetary history of the United States,
they have to pay attention.
So it's really in those years,
Friedman is hammering this idea of monetarism,
and it starts to become something respectable,
bordering on respectable,
for other economists to look to and think about.
And that's really the beginning
of the kind of Keynesian-monetarist split,
where if you start to give Friedman any credence,
you're heading towards a monetarist position.
Now, at the same time,
Friedman comes out very publicly in 1964
as a supporter of Barry Goldwater.
And Keynesian economics has found a home
in the Democratic Party.
Its probably brightest moment
in the sun is the administration of John F. Kennedy,
who brings in a lot of Harvard
and Yale professors to the Council of Economic Advisors.
He proposes a series
of spending programs that are really guided
by the Keynesian philosophy.
And Barry Goldwater is tremendously controversial,
part for his votes against civil rights,
which Friedman really supports,
part because he's a hardcore libertarian
in an age when that's not in the political mainstream
or not discussed in the political mainstream.
And, I mean, he's just tremendously unpopular,
particularly in all the educated precincts
where Friedman lives.
So Friedman is like an outcast
and a pariah for his support of Goldwater.
And so that actually really affects monetarism,
because people feel
that this is now becoming a package deal.
And so there's a great reluctance
to embrace Friedman's ideas,
because it seems like he would then have
to embrace his politics.
- Ah.
So it's associated with conservatism.
- So this is the years when conservatism.
There is a movement that calls itself conservatism.
And Friedman is very tightly allied with this movement
from the beginning,
partly through his friendship with William F. Buckley.
And a lot of people say to me,
"Yeah, but Friedman's not conservative."
And this is like a bigger.
We could have a whole separate podcast on this.
But for now, I'll just say that conservative
in the United States becomes a political brand
that contains elements of conservatism that are recognizable
across time and space,
embrace of tradition,
more comfort with hierarchy, et cetera.
And it also has something new and different,
which is Friedman's ideas
about Milton Friedman's advocacy of more free markets,
less government regulation,
and the benefits of capitalism and the benefits of freedom.
And that gets folded into American conservatism,
in part because Milton Friedman
is such a powerful intellectual figure.
And after his advocacy of Goldwater,
the media realizes, this guy's really smart.
He has really interesting things to say.
He makes great copy, he makes a great guest,
and he starts writing a column for "Newsweek" magazine,
which is very big deal
in a much more consolidated media environment.
And he's quoted in all the newspapers.
And so his public profile really starts to rise
right as he's pushing monetarism
as an alternative to the Keynesian synthesis.
- Can we just linger on,
what is monetarism?
- [Jennifer] Yes, okay, I didn't go into it.
- So, like, what? (chuckles)
Okay, the money supply.
- [Jennifer] Yes.
- So money is this thing that you can think
of it like a notion where people buy and sell stuff,
and there's this fascinating, complex dynamical system
of people contracting with each other in this beautiful way.
I mean, there's so many pothead questions I want to ask
about the nature of money.
I mean, money is fascinating in that way.
And I think for Milton Friedman,
trusting the flow of money is really important,
and the signals that pricing
and money in general provides is really important.
- So, yeah, and some of this,
I could take some of this back again to Frank Knight.
So one thing Frank Knight said
to all his students was,
"The market is the best allocation mechanism we have.
The market is what allocates resources.
In a situation of scarcity,
the market allocates them the best."
And Hayek will add to that
by saying, "Prices are information signals,
and a price sends information to buyers
and sellers about how they should act."
And these are two of the strongest arguments
for why the government should not intervene
in the price system,
because it will blur information
or because it will allocate less efficiently
than market allocation will.
And so what Friedman is really going to add to that
is maybe going up a level
and thinking in the macro about the whole economy
and how money circulates through that economy as a whole.
And so what he and Anna Schwartz do
is they construct what are called monetary aggregates.
This is adding together, say,
all the money that's on deposit in banks
and all the money that's believed to be circulating
in people's wallets.
And you also have to really go back in time.
We don't have credit cards.
There is a stock market,
but it's tiny in terms of the number of people who invest.
There aren't mutual funds.
Like, when traveler's check are introduced,
this is like a big deal.
So we have a very simple monetary system.
And so Schwartz and Milton Friedman start measuring
what they call the monetary aggregates.
They focus on M1 and M2,
and their favorite aggregate is M2,
which I believe is encompassing sort of deposits
and circulating medium.
The other thing to recall,
there's some fine distinctions
between money in savings accounts
and money in checking accounts.
And money in savings accounts can earn interest
and is generally believed not to circulate,
or money in checking accounts does not
at that time bear interest and cannot legally bear interest,
and so is thought of as circulating.
And then there's different institutional architectures
of postal savings banks and credit unions.
But Friedman is, one,
taking the focus to these aggregate amounts of money
and saying, "These really have a lot
to do with economic booms and busts.
When we have an expansion in the amount of available money,
we see an expansion in economic activity.
When we have a contraction in available money,
we have a contraction."
And so he says, "At this stage, the government,
through the mechanism of the Federal Reserve
and its influence on interest rates,
can either make money more cheaply available
and more freely available in the economy,
or can make money more expensive and slow things down."
But the central core idea
of monetarism is this is potentially very bad.
If the government can hit the gas and then hit the brake,
and hit the gas and hit the brake based on, say,
what a politician wants
or what somebody at the Federal Reserve wants,
you have a lot of instability in the system.
And so one of the core policy proposals
of monetarism is let's grow the money supply
at a steady rate.
And in the beginning, Friedman just says K percent.
He doesn't even put a number on it,
because he says, "The number doesn't matter.
What matters is the steadiness in the growth rate,
because if it's a steady growth rate, it will fade away.
And then people will make economic decisions
based on the fundamentals,
not based on what they think is going to happen,
not based on hedging against inflation
or hedging against deflation.
They'll just be able to function."
So this is sort of the paradox of monetary policy.
When it's happening right, you don't see it,
you don't notice it.
When it's happening wrong, Friedman argues,
it can just fundamentally destabilize everything.
It can cause a Great Depression,
it can cause an artificial boom.
And so he's taking monetary policy at a time
when most economists think it's completely irrelevant,
and saying, "This is the central game of the economy."
Now, we live in a world where we believe this
and the Federal Reserve chair can't open their mouth
without headlines being generated.
But Friedman is saying this
at a time when the Federal Reserve is like a mysterious
and secretive organization.
It's not well known.
It's not deeply appreciated.
Some of the only people who appreciate the Fed's power
are like hardcore rural populace
who have constituents who think the banks
and money power are the problem,
who are like throwbacks from the frontier days.
So Friedman in the beginning has no constituency
for this policy.
He has no constituency for this analysis.
And so just going back to summarize monetarism,
it's using the quantity theory of money
to analyze the macro economy.
It's proposing a policy of slow
and steady growth in the money supply.
And then it is arguing that inflationary episodes,
when they emerge,
are profoundly driven by changes in the money supply,
not by anything else.
- I mean, and going even up a level as we started,
how epic is it to develop this idea,
to hold this idea,
and then to convince the United States
of this idea that money matters,
that today we believe is mostly correct for now.
And so just this idea that goes against the experts
and then eventually wins out
and drives so much of the economy, the biggest,
the most powerful economy in the world.
So fascinating.
- Yeah, so, I mean, that's a fascinating story.
And so what happens
is Friedman has advanced all these ideas.
He's roiled the economics profession,
he's built a political profile,
and then he becomes the head
of the American Economics Association.
And he is asked in that role to give a presidential address.
And so he gives his presidential address, December 1967,
and he says, "I'm going to talk about inflation,
and I'm going to talk about the trade off
between inflation and unemployment."
And this is what's generally known as the Phillips Curve.
And the Phillips Curve
in its original form is derived of post World War II data.
So it's derived of about 12 years of data.
And it shows that when inflation goes up,
unemployment goes down.
And the idea would make sense
that as the economy is heating up
and lots of things are happening,
more and more people are getting hired.
And so this relationship has led policymakers
to think that sometimes inflation is good.
And if you want to lower unemployment,
you could let inflation kind of go a little bit.
And in the crude forms,
it becomes to seem like a menu.
You could take your model and you could plug in,
I want this much unemployment.
And then it would say, "Well, great,
this is how much inflation you should do."
And so then you would target that inflation rate.
So Friedman gets up and he says, "This is wrong."
This might work in the short term,
but it's not going to work in the long term,
because in the long term, inflation has, first of all,
it has a momentum of its own.
Once it gets going, it tends to build on itself.
The accelerationist thesis, it accelerates.
And once inflation gets going,
and the reason it gets going is
because workers go to the store
and they see the price level has gone up,
things have cost more,
they ask for the wages to go up.
Then people, eventually the wages will go up too high
and they will no longer be hireable,
or companies will decide,
at these high wages, I can't hire as many workers.
I'd better lay off.
So if inflation keeps going, eventually over the long term,
it will result in high unemployment.
So he says, "Theoretically you could end up
in a situation where you have high inflation
and high unemployment."
This hasn't been seen.
But he says, "Theoretically this could happen."
And then he goes and he says,
"And the government has started expanding the money supply.
It started expanding the money supply in 1966.
So we're going to get a bunch of inflation,
and then we're going to get a bunch of unemployment."
And he estimates about how long it will take.
And then he says, "Once this all happens,
it will take about 20 years to get back to normal."
- And he predicts the stagflation of the 1970s.
- [Jennifer] Stagflation of the,
- How gangster is that for an economist to do that?
Again, against the mainstream belief represented
by the Phillips Curve?
- Yeah, and what really makes it happen is that many
of the economists who most deeply dislike Friedman
and most deeply dislike his politics in the 1970s,
as they're running their models,
they start to say, "Friedman's right."
They start to see in the data that he's right.
And a very parallel process happens in Britain.
Britain is going through a very similar burst of spending,
burst of inflation.
And so Friedman is vindicated in a very profound way,
in the way that he himself said
would be the ultimate vindication,
which is my theory should predict.
So that prediction of stagflation is really
the sort of final breakthrough of his ideas
and also their importance to policy
and to thinking about how we should intervene
or not in the economy
and what the role of the Federal Reserve is,
because he's saying the Federal Reserve
is incredibly powerful.
And finally people start to believe him.
- And I don't know if we said, but to make clear,
stagflation means high unemployment and high inflation,
which is a thing like you mentioned,
was not seen before, and he predicted accurately.
And it also disproves the sort of the relationship,
the inverse relationship between unemployment and inflation.
- Yeah, now I should say the Phillips Curve
is still out there.
It's been expectations augmented,
and it is relevant in the short term.
But Friedman's warning is still very much apt,
that if you get too focused on unemployment,
you can let inflation out of the bag.
And so until very recently,
the Federal Reserve's tradition has been focusing
on inflation, believing that's fundamental
and that will keep unemployment low,
rather than trying to lower unemployment
at the cost of raising inflation.
- Can we go back to Frank Knight
and the big picture thing we started with,
which is the justification of capitalism?
- Yes.
- So as you mentioned, Milton Friedman searched
for a moral justification of capitalism.
Frank Knight was a big influence on Milton Friedman
and including on this topic
of understanding the moral justification of capitalism.
I think you spoke about Knight's case
for capitalism was grounded
in the idea that the ability to act
in the face of uncertainty creates profit,
and it should, because taking risks should be rewarded.
So, like this idea that taking risks
in the face of uncertainty should create profit,
and that becomes a justification,
the ethics of capitalism.
Can you just speak to that?
- Yeah.
So Knight is talking about, where does profit come from?
And to his mind,
it comes from the entrepreneurial function
and the risk-taking function.
And so he kind of weaves that into why, you know,
capitalism works best
and why it's the most effective allocation machine
and why it assigns responsibility
in a way he believes that a socialist system never could.
Now Knight, though, is not a booster of capitalism.
It could be in part
because he's just a darkly pessimistic
kind of depressive guy.
And so he's afraid capitalism is going to collapse
and socialism or fascism is going to take over or communism.
And so he kind of descends into darkness there.
Friedman, as the more optimist, believes with Hayek
that you can develop a different approach
to capitalism that would preserve the price system,
preserve allocation, but build in social supports,
build in a social minimum, things like this.
But there's a moment
in his career when he's really struggling
to figure out like, how do I make this case for capitalism?
And basically the whole sort of conservative movement,
or people who we later call the conservative movement,
are struggling to make this case.
And he starts thinking about what makes capitalism work
is that if you put forth effort, you get a reward.
So then you could say, "Well,
people get what they deserve under capitalism."
But then he kind of stops and he says,
"That's not really true,
because we're born with such different endowments
and there's a huge quotient of luck, right?
So some people are just in the right position
and some people aren't.
So if I say capitalism is moral
because people get what they deserve,
that's not really true."
And he also kind of has an ethical reaction,
which he ends up calling an aesthetic reaction.
He's kind of like, "It just doesn't feel right to say that."
And so he struggles for a while with like, "What do I say?"
And then he basically says, "Capitalism,
it can't be the core,
discipline of the market
can't be the core to your ethics.
It has to be something else."
So that's when he will decide it's freedom,
it's individual freedom
that's really the ethical core.
And capitalism makes individual freedom possible
because capitalism is dedicated to maximizing that.
And so the defense of capitalism comes through freedom.
And at his stage in history,
he's able to set aside Knight's worry about inequality
and say, "When I look at the data,"
and this is true for the macro data at mid-century,
"incomes are actually converging."
And also if you look historically, if a country goes
from say a more feudal agrarian society
to a more market-based society, incomes will converge.
Now, then they might start to diverge.
But Friedman's in the moment
when he's seeing the convergence.
And so that's what he's really focused on.
So he believes he can justify capitalism
through the ethic of freedom.
And he also believes
that inequality is a problem that can be addressed
through specific policies,
and it's not a fundamental feature of capitalism.
In other words, he doesn't see capitalism
as an engine of inequality the way that Frank Knight did
and the way that, you know,
maybe some critics on the left would.
- How did he conceive of freedom?
So individual freedom,
economic freedom, political freedom, civil freedom?
What was the tension,
the dynamic between those different freedoms for him?
- So he really begins focusing on economic freedom,
and he says, "It's really important to focus
on economic freedom, because in the United States,
we don't value it enough."
So by economic freedom,
he means the ability to keep what you've earned,
the ability to make decisions about your business,
the ability to make decisions about the work that you do.
So this will translate into things like,
there shouldn't be a minimum wage.
He believes the minimum wage has bad social effects.
But he also believes you should be free to accept a job
at a wage that you yourself have determined
is acceptable to you.
And there should be very minimal regulation,
questions around safety and other things,
because the market will ultimately,
if you create an unsafe product, it won't sell,
and that's sort of your incentive.
So he really centers economic freedom
because he thinks especially, and he's really speaking
from his vantage point in the universities
and speaking to the kind of liberal consensus of the 50s
and 60s, he thinks economic freedom has been undervalued
in the American context.
So he really wants to push that forward.
He's really kind of taking political freedom for granted.
Now, later in his career, when he becomes famous,
he's traveling the world, he spends time in Chile.
And this country is now being ruled by a dictator,
Gustav Pinochet, who starts introducing economic freedom,
but there's no political freedom.
And Milton Friedman believes eventually these two things
are going to go together and tells Pinochet,
"You've got economic freedom,
and eventually it's going to bring,
it's going to mean political freedom."
Pinochet is like, "Okay, fine,
not really interested in that.
I want to know what I should do about inflation."
(Lex and Jennifer laughing)
But then when Milton Friedman leaves Chile,
he is attacked and vilified for having been a supporter.
He's interpreted that he's a supporter
of the regime, which he's not.
But he realizes he has talked too much
about economic freedom,
and he hasn't talked enough about political freedom.
He's kind of assumed political freedom,
because he's come from the American context.
So then he starts recalibrating them and saying,
"You know what, if you don't have political freedom,
you're never going to be able
to hold on to economic freedom."
So he sees that they need to go together
and they don't naturally go together.
And so he starts to become more clear in talking
about political freedom.
Now let's fast forward to the end of his life
and he's witnessing the emergence
of what we call the Asian Tigers.
So capitalist economies that are doing very well,
but they don't have political freedom,
but then he observes, they don't have political freedom
and that you can't vote in a free and fair election,
but they also don't have a Stasi, they don't have a KGB,
they're not hauling people off for their wrong opinions.
So then he says they have something called civic freedom.
And so he kind of defines this third sphere,
civic freedom of, you know, debate, discussion,
interpersonal relations,
but you can't be political.
So this is a late in life addition.
I don't think it's fully theorized.
I think what it shows is that during the Cold War,
he very much believed economic and political freedom,
you know, capitalism and freedom, democracy,
the United States, capitalism.
This all went together.
And he starts to see
at the end of his life the emergence
of different social systems that are using market trading
and allocation but aren't giving people similar freedoms.
And he's kind of puzzling over that.
Now, he always believes that China will democratize,
and he thinks China's on the path to democratization,
in part because Chile does democratize.
Eventually Pinochet has voted out
and it's become a democratic,
capitalist, and very prosperous country.
And he thinks that's exactly what's happening in China.
He sees Tiananmen, and he hasn't lived long enough
to get to where we are now
in which doesn't look like political
or civic freedom is coming to China anytime soon.
- And he did oppose the dual-track system of China,
meaning like the market is bottom-up,
the government in China is top-down,
and you can't have both.
- He thought you couldn't have both.
He thought eventually the market would triumph.
- Well, that's a really powerful idea.
Say, okay, maybe there's not political freedom,
but just hold on to the economic freedom
and eventually that's going to give political freedom.
Is that correct to say, like,
start to work on the economic freedom
and the political freedom piece will take care of itself?
- That's what he believed.
That's what he believed, yeah.
I think it's it's more complicated than that.
The people who gain
out of a system of economic freedom could decide to collude
in a system where there isn't political freedom.
That's certainly a scenario.
But again, that's that core idea of freedom.
And that core belief that people want freedom
and that people are drawn to freedom.
- Just to go back to Frank Knight a little bit,
he wrote an essay called "The Ethics of Competition."
The metaphor that economic life is a game,
and then maybe that extends to society as a whole.
The entirety of it is a competitive game.
And Milton Friedman, I think, adapted some of this,
appreciated some of this.
Can you speak to this metaphor?
- Yeah, I think what the metaphor
of the game does is it asks you, okay, well,
what are the rules, then?
And let's focus on the rules that keep the game going.
So he didn't use the concept of an infinite game,
but I think that's an interesting one.
A game that all the players are in
and keep going again and again and again.
And so that helped Knight, along with Hayek,
shift from the allocation question,
who's getting what, are things allocated fairly,
to the more structural question of,
what are the rules of the game
that we need to keep this system going?
And so for a while, that led to the discussion of Monopoly.
Well, we need rules against concentration,
or we need the rule of law.
Everyone needs to be treated equally.
People need to know what they're up against.
And then going back to monetarism,
the core of monetarism is a rule.
Friedman called it a monetary growth rule.
And so, again, what keeps the economic game going is a rule
about how much the money grows that everybody knows,
nobody's guessing,
nobody's changing the rules to help their side
or to help the people they're friendly with.
We all know it's there, it's clear, it's easy.
And so that emphasis on rules, I think,
really has a through line.
It goes into Hayek's competitive order,
and then it goes into the monetary growth rule.
And then today,
monetary policy makes use of monetary policy rules.
We have not abandoned discretionary,
but rules are used as a heuristic or a check.
And those come out of Friedman's thinking.
And so it's really profound.
And it was always counterposed to discretion,
which Friedman worried would be subject to capture
or political corruption.
If you had discretion in policymaking,
or if you had discretion in these very big areas,
then people would stop competing
against each other in a market,
and they would turn their attention
to getting control of the rules
or the rule makers.
- So if there's clear, transparent rules,
then you're free to play the game.
- Yes, exactly.
- But then depending on the rules, the game can turn out,
the equilibrium that it arrives at might be different.
So that speaks to the mechanism, design,
the design of the rules.
- Yeah.
And that was, again,
to go back to the idea separating new liberalism
or neoliberalism from classical liberalism was more
of a focus on what are the rules that are needed,
what is the competitive order that we want to set out,
how do we design in social safeguards,
how do we think about it?
And so that shift towards monetary policy
and focusing on stable monetary growth,
that becomes really important in the post-70s era
as one of the basic rules
of how capitalist economy should function.
And it becomes really important
because they see the example of, say, countries,
most notably in Latin America,
where monetary rules weren't followed
and different governments played politics
with their currencies.
And that created just huge upheaval and huge social loss,
economic loss, just economic disaster.
- So my friend, she's a poker player,
philosopher of sorts,
great human being, she has a podcast called "Win-Win"
that everybody should listen to.
And the whole purpose of the podcast
and her whole way of being
in spirit is to find win-win solutions.
So do you think of economic life
as having such win-win solutions?
So being able to find rules where everybody wins,
or is it always going to be zero sum?
- I definitely believe in win-win,
but with a big asterisk.
You can have win-win,
but it can feel like win-lose, which is,
it's not just are people getting more,
it has a lot to do with do people feel they're getting more
and do people feel they're getting what's fair and equal?
So you could have a situation, for instance,
if you look at the history of going back to Chile,
it has steady growth, steady income growth,
steady diminution of inequality,
and a high level of discontent within the society
and a high level of belief that the society is corrupt
and unfair, and that's what matters.
How people feel about it, how people perceive it matters.
And you can't, you know, we saw this recently,
you can't just come out with a bunch of statistics
and tell people, "You're winning in this game,"
if they feel like they're losing.
So that goes to all the non-rational factors
and all the comparative factors that people have
when they think
about where they are vis-a-vis other people in society.
So we're just incredibly social creatures.
We're incredibly attuned to our status,
to rising and falling, to where we sit vis-a-vis others.
And so that absolutely has to be attended to.
It can't just be an economic analysis.
- That's so interesting that the experience
of the economy is different than the reality of the economy.
On the topic of corruption, I think the reality
of corruption versus the perception of corruption
is really important in a lot of these nations.
You take Ukraine for example,
the perception of corruption has a big impact
on the economy.
You don't want to invest,
you're very cautious as a business person.
The reality of corruption could be way different
than the actual perception.
But if narratives take hold,
it's a self-fulfilling prophecy that it has a big effect
on the psychology of the people involved.
It's interesting.
- Yeah, I mean, this goes back to Keynes' analysis
of the Great Depression, right?
If people won't invest, if they're spooked,
if the investing classes are spooked,
you could be in real trouble.
And in some ways this simple analysis of the problem
and proposal of a solution was enough
to restore eventually the path to economic prosperity.
That's Franklin Roosevelt,
"Nothing to fear, but fear itself."
You know, the sense of, we know we have a future,
we have optimism, then you believe in it.
And to go back to like thinking about money, right?
Money works because we all believe in it.
You know, it's a form of social trust,
and it's a form of belief
and faith in our society and in the other people in it.
And when that breaks down,
the money system will break down as well.
- Is there something that Milton Friedman said
and thought about, you know,
how to control the psychology of humans at scale?
- No.
I mean, what's interesting is he does talk,
especially in his later work,
he says, "We have fiat currency and this is an experiment,"
you know, "And we don't know how it's going to turn out.
And it's turning out okay right now.
But we've always had a commodity-based
or backed currency of some form or another.
And this is the first time.
And so who really knows?
So far so good."
And he also is very attuned.
It's interesting in his later writings when he's thinking
about this too, "Sure,
I could design a monetary system that would be different,
but when I look at history,
I see that monetary systems have always, say,
incorporated the role of a state,
because it's so important to people.
And so therefore my theoretical designs
really have to be tempered
by what I've actually seen happen in history."
- So maybe you could speak to this tension
between how much government intervention is okay
for Milton Friedman.
So he was against minimum wage,
but he was for guaranteed minimum income.
Can you explain actually the difference between the two?
- Yeah, so this was one of the discoveries
I made in my research.
I found a paper from 1938 he wrote advocating
what we would call today a universal basic income,
a minimum income.
And he basically sees this
as part of the effort to create a new liberalism.
And he basically says,
"We have advanced societies,
we have prosperous societies.
We have decided in keeping with our morals
and our ethics that people should not be starving
in an advanced society like this.
The question is, how are we going to make that happen?"
And he ended up believing the best thing
to do was to put a floor under everybody.
And he said, you can get that based on your income.
If you have a lot of income, you don't get it.
If you have a little income,
you might get a little bit of it.
If you have no income, you get enough of it.
And he believed in the beginning you should base that
on what was required to buy food.
That that would be kind of an objective.
You could objectively determine the nutrition
and the price of food.
And so that for him, it's important,
he says, "It's keeping with a liberal polity,
because it's not intervening in the price system,
it's not intervening in economic relations."
And it does not, in his view,
require a bureaucracy to administer.
It is not, in his view,
require that you qualify for it
by virtue of being in a protected class.
You just get it as kind of part of your membership
in this general citizenship body.
And so that to him was really different than a minimum wage,
because it did not interfere with the work bargain.
His belief about minimum wages was specifically
that it priced out unskilled labor.
That what an unskilled laborer had
to offer was a willingness to work for a very low wage.
And if you set the minimum wage too high, businesses,
instead of hiring that higher priced labor
would not hire or like we could think of today, right?
They put in an electronic checkout, you know,
or something like this,
where you don't actually need the labor.
So he really believed the minimum wage
had that perverse incentive.
Now, this is a live debate on what minimum wages do.
And there seems to be a level at which you can set them
that they cannot have that perverse effect
and in fact can kind of create people
with more spending money that then powers the economy.
So he had a very sort of clinical analysis of that,
rather than an empirical one,
or a really abstract analysis,
but the minimum income is fascinating
because it seems very leftist to us,
but what it is is it's purely individualistic.
And it never really happened,
because it was so purely individualistic,
because American social policy typically identifies
like this group of people is deserving
and will give them benefits.
So the classic example is soldiers, veterans.
Another example is mothers raising dependent children.
These people deserve money.
The rest of you, you better go out and work.
And so Friedman's proposal, it really caught on in the 60s.
It ultimately went nowhere, but it was no litmus test,
no income analysis,
just, we're gonna give you this much.
Everyone's gonna get this much.
And he decided once mass taxation had come in,
you could do it through taxes,
and you could just rebate people
who didn't pay income taxes got a rebate.
That actually came to pass.
It's the earned income tax credit,
and it's considered extremely successful by policy analysts.
It does what it's supposed to do.
It's not that expensive.
And so I see that as a kind of paradigm of his thinking
in that instead
of creating a bureaucracy that does some form
of redistribution,
or instead of trying to intervene in the market for labor
or the market for something else,
the market for housing,
you provide a cash grant that people spend for themselves.
And so, interestingly, that's what happened
in the emergency situation of Covid.
That's exactly what people did.
They followed that model.
We just get money out quick.
And there's a lot of discussion still about UBI,
is this something that should be done?
And I think it's always going to be hard to pull off,
because I think Americans
and their elected representatives don't want
to provide a universal benefit.
They want to provide a targeted benefit
because they believe there's a moral component here.
And Friedman advanced a policy that was really abstract
and really just, you know, kind of,
it was devoid of judgment.
It was pure and beautiful in that way,
but utterly impractical.
- And it really focused on not interfering with the market
and the signals that the market provides.
Like, it was really against price controls
for the same kind of reason.
- Yeah, exactly.
You could say, "Okay,
but how does this not interfere with the market?
If you provide people with a minimum income,
won't that change their incentives to work, et cetera?"
I mean, there's a big, big body of research on this.
Most of it seems to show, one,
it's way better than the current benefits cliff,
where you have to not work to get your benefits,
and any incentive impact
on working seems to be much lower than would be expected.
But I'll let the economists
and the social scientists fight that one out
and figure it out empirically.
Hopefully we should be able to.
- Yeah, there's been a bunch of studies.
It's interesting, even just how you conduct studies
like this, how you do these kinds of experiments,
especially if you're empirically minded, you know,
because a lot of the studies I saw
is they're pretty small.
- Right.
- So how do you make big conclusions
about how to run the world,
how to run the economies from such small studies?
It's all a fascinating experiment of ideas.
And it's also inspiring to see individuals
and maybe small groups
of individuals like the Chicago School of Economics,
to sort of shake up what we believe
and how we run the world.
Inspiring.
You call Milton Friedman
the last great conservative, (chuckles)
maybe to be a little bit sort of controversial
and make bold statements that get everybody excited.
But what do you mean by that
and what makes a great conservative?
- So I was really thinking of that
in terms of kind of American political identities
and particularly the 20th century conservative movement,
which, you know, people are always saying,
"This isn't conservatism."
And I was like,
"Yes, in America, conservatism is different."
It looks different, it feels different.
Conservatism in America builds in a big component
of what we could call libertarianism,
pro-capitalism, anti-government ideas.
And critics will say,
"But conservatism is about conserving institutions
and practices and it has a role for the state
and an organic community."
But in the United States, it's always had,
since the 20th century, also this anti-statist,
let's let the market rip.
Let's not worry
about what the market does to establish traditions.
The market is our tradition.
Capitalism is our tradition.
So that was really synthesized.
You know, many people were there,
but Friedman and the importance of his books,
"Free to Choose," "Capitalism and Freedom,"
the television series he did,
all of these were like core components
of this American conservative synthesis as it evolved.
And I really see that as having broken down.
It is scattered into different pieces
and we don't know
where they're gonna come back together again.
But Friedman's push for open global markets,
unfettered free trade,
that's getting pushback on both the left and the right.
That I think is just a major sign
that both parties have turned away from this division.
I don't know what they've turned to,
but the way that Friedman brought these pieces together,
I think that political moment has passed.
So that's what I was trying to talk about
with the book title.
There's another way, though,
in which I think of him also as a conservative,
which is that within the field of economics,
he went back to this older idea,
the quantity theory of money, and said,
"This still has value.
This can be applied in the modern day.
It is something to teach us."
And he pushed back
against this trend towards mathematization.
So he kept writing books.
You can still pick up a Friedman book and read it,
whereas lots of economics articles and output,
it's like unreadable unless you're in the field.
And so I think in that way,
he was trying to conserve methodologically
and intellectually the traditions of the field.
The work that he and particularly Anna Schwartz did,
that literal counting of things
and deep analysis of data from the field,
that was completely unfashionable in his time.
Now we've sort of gone back to it with big data
and with computers.
But he helped bring that forward
and preserve that tradition.
So I think of him kind of intellectually as a conservative,
if you think of the mode of his thought.
And so, I mean, what makes a great conservative
is one who takes those older ideas
and makes them fresh for a new time period.
I think that's exactly what he did.
- You've also spoken
about the fact that the times when he was sort of out
in public, there was more of an open battle
of ideas where conservatism often had,
William F. Buckley, he had a more vibrant,
deep debate over ideas where it seems less deep now.
- I mean, that is the thing that it's hard,
especially for the students I teach today, to be like,
"You know, there were arguments about ideas,
and conservatives want a bunch of them."
You know, and that happened in the 70s
and late 1960s to 1970s when they, you know,
one set of arguments was about economics.
Like, okay, this idea of stimulating the economy
by spending more, it has a downside.
The downside is called inflation,
and the downside's called too much regulation.
And you've gone too far
in kind of bottling up the actual sources
of economic growth and dynamism,
and we have to let those free.
In social policy, there was also a critique.
The Great Society had all these ways
of ideas of ending poverty.
And people came and analyzed them and said,
"The programs aren't helping.
In some ways,
you've actually created engines to trap people in poverty,
because you've given them a benefit
and said if they actually start to work,
they lose the benefit.
You've created all these perverse incentives."
And these ideas were fought out.
They were empirical, they were controversial,
and they were based on really deep research
and really deep argumentation.
And so it seems that era has passed.
It seems like we're driven much more quickly
by moods rather than thought through ideas.
Right now, it seems like the ideas come after.
They follow the political mood
and try to put together the underpinning of it,
where it really was the opposite
for much of the 20th century.
- It does seem like we lead with emotional turmoil.
- Right.
- And the ideas follow, versus lead with the ideas,
and the sort of the emotion of the masses respond.
- Right, exactly.
So if we think of the evolution of conservatism,
it was a whole set of ideas that was crafted, refined.
The 1950s, 1960s, 1970s,
sort of really found their emotional standard bearer,
translator, salesperson in Ronald Reagan,
who, incidentally,
had been following these ideas as they developed
and had been honing his ability to express them
and apply them politically.
It's a very opposite,
if we look at Trump as the political definer of the era,
there's a set of ideas,
but it was more attitudes, impulses, vibes,
and the ideas are coming after that,
trying to figure out how they patch on.
So it's interesting to watch, to see that difference.
And I hazard that a lot
of it just has to do with the immediacy
of the media environment we're in,
and it's just power
of the media messages to get out so fast.
- What do you think Milton Friedman would say
about Donald Trump,
about him winning in 2024,
and just in general,
this political moment?
- I think he would love Doge.
I think that's, you know,
(Lex and Jennifer laugh)
it goes without saying. - He would focus on that part?
- I think he would focus on that part,
because I think he would really love it.
He would be very alarmed by the idea of tariffs
and very alarmed by the return to protectionism.
I mean, I think he believed that part
of what made the world peaceful
in the second half of the 20th century,
as opposed to during World War II,
was the world was knit together more by trade.
And that was the great hope that if people traded
with each other, they wouldn't fight.
He was also, you know,
a proponent of the free movement of capital.
You know, he would absolutely oppose this idea that,
you know, Nippon Steel wasn't allowed to invest
in the United States.
I think he would struggle,
and he wholeheartedly embraced Reagan,
and he worked to minimize the parts
of the Reagan legacy he didn't like.
I think he would find it harder to embrace Trump,
because he's not of that style.
He just had a different style.
But I'm guessing he would have come around through,
I think he would just say, "Okay,
we have a chance to reduce the size of government."
At the same time, the spending plans
of the Trump administration
are not fiscally conservative in any way.
And that was his concern,
was not so much with debt,
but with the feeling that there's no mechanism
to stop the growth of government,
that it just grows and grows and grows.
And so he ended up believing,
like even deficits aren't so bad,
because they make politicians cautious,
he thought, about continuing to spend,
but I have to believe he would be concerned
about the potential threats to the US currency's position
as the world's reserve currency
with increased levels of debt and spending.
He was concerned about low interest rates in the,
he died, I think it's 2004, 2006,
but it was in the beginning,
he didn't see the zero low bound,
but he saw low interest rates.
And he said, "This isn't necessarily good."
Everyone's talking
about low interest rates as if they're good,
but there should be a price on capital,
there should be a price on this.
It shouldn't be so low.
And so he had some of still the kind of macro insights
that I think are important.
- You wrote "The Wall Street Journal" essay titled
"How Inflation Ended Neoliberalism and Re-Elected Trump."
So can we weave that into this discussion
in terms of inflation and Trump,
what's the main idea of the essay?
- So the main idea is kind of looking back and saying,
so today we have been living
in a world where people have been focused
on monetary policy, steady monetary policy,
free trade, reducing regulation.
This is all called the neoliberal era.
And my argument was a lot of that arose,
was driven by inflation.
So we have Milton Friedman predict inflation in 1967.
It starts breaking out in the 1970s,
Britain and the United States,
and every institution was designed around stable prices.
And once inflation broke out,
prices were no longer stable.
So, for example, tax rates weren't inflation adjusted.
So if your income went up because of inflation,
you might bump from a low tax rate
to an extremely high tax rate,
but you don't actually have more money.
On paper, you have more money,
but everything costs more,
so you don't actually have more money
and your taxes have gone up.
That kicks off the taxpayer revolt.
There's a whole shift
of American corporations towards focusing
on financial investments,
because the tax breaks they used to get for depreciation,
for building new factories, are not inflation adjusted.
So they no longer pay off in an inflationary environment.
And then when Paul Volcker comes in
in 1980s, early 1980s,
and starts fighting inflation,
really pushes up interest rates to bring down inflation.
And that completely reorders the banking sector,
because banks had statutory legal limits
on the interest they could charge.
And once general market interest rates exceeded that,
this proliferation of new financial forms
to take advantage of that.
So my point was,
the era we live in was ushered in by inflation.
And then everyone turned against all the formulations we had
and said, "Well,
these have hollowed out our industrial base.
We've got too much immigration.
We've got too much economic openness.
We need to reshore.
We need to focus.
We need to turn against all these things.
We need to spend more.
We've disinvested."
And the net result of that turning away, I argued,
is people forgot about inflation.
They really forgot it could ever exist.
And you had a whole set of theories on the left,
modern monetary theory, that basically said,
"We don't really need to worry about inflation,
we can spend what we want."
And lo and behold, inflation came back.
And so my argument is that has now opened the door
to the presidency of Donald Trump,
which is potentially a deeply transformative moment
that will change the size and shape of government,
that may change our foreign policy profoundly,
that may change our immigration policy, I mean,
change the demographics of our country, all of that.
And my thesis
is that has all been made possible by inflation.
And so the great mistake of the past years
was to forget how fundamental inflation was to the rise
of the last political order
and to profoundly underestimate how much inflation
would change the current political order.
So I just think it's one of these things.
This is why I think you should study history,
because I think if you had studied history,
you would be aware of this.
And it's so easy for people to forget,
just like the banks forgot
that interest rates could ever go up.
They got so used to it,
and it's only a 10, 15-year thing,
but to them that seems like forever.
So I really do believe what history teaches you to do
is just have a much vaster scope in your vision
and then take into account the possibilities
of so many things happening that are different
than what's happening today.
And so I just hope we don't forget about inflation entirely.
But here's the thing, it is quite a strong chance
that Trump's policies will initiate even worse inflation,
and then they will prove to be his undoing.
So the ironies of inflation could be continuing.
- Like you said, Milton Friedman would be a big fan of Doge,
so if he was still here today
and rolled with Elon Musk and Vivek,
what advice would he give?
What do you think he would focus on
in terms of where to cut, how to cut,
how to think about cutting?
- You know, his signature policy move,
I talk about this,
is taking the price mechanism
and trying to make that into the policy.
And that seems sort of obvious to us today.
But in the era that he came in,
so there would be rent controls.
Let's take away rent controls,
let's let housing prices set themselves.
Or, he was very against national parks.
I actually think the national parks are good,
so I hope the Doge people don't take this up, but,
(Lex and Jennifer laugh)
that rather than an allocation to fund the national parks,
they should be funded
by the revenue that they bring in when people visit them.
And so I think he was always looking
to let's let prices make the decisions here.
So I think that would be one of the key pieces.
The other thing I think he'd really be thinking about,
he wrote about this a lot about occupational licensure
and barriers to entry.
And he felt like one
of the worst things that government does,
and sometimes it's private entities that do this,
is create barriers
to entry to protect industries and markets.
So he talked about this
in the case of the medical profession,
which I think is actually not a good example,
because I think we all have a collective investment
in having medical doctors be highly trained.
But so, for instance,
you could look at nail technicians or haircutting.
There's often these licensing requirements
or there's a sort of big kerfuffle.
I think it's D.C. passed a law
that to run a childcare center,
you have to have a college degree.
Well, what does that do?
I mean, that disenfranchises a whole bunch
of would-be entrepreneurs
who don't happen to have a college degree,
but probably could be really good
at this particular business.
So I think he would be saying,
"Look out for where private interests have used the state
to protect themselves,
and clear away those types of barriers
and let competition through prices guide outcomes."
- Yeah, so open up for more competition
and allow for more signals
from the market to drive decisions and so on.
- Yes, yeah.
- Which would actually naturally lead to cutting a lot
of the bureaucracy of government.
- I think the other thing he would probably be arguing for
is, again, going back to the design
of the minimum income or the negative income tax,
that there's a way,
he ultimately decided to run it
through the tax system.
The government's already collecting this data.
They already have your information,
and they can just send the money out through the system,
rather than having a social bureaucracy
where you have to come in in person,
you have to fill out forms,
you have to document,
do you own a car, what's your income,
who lives in the household.
So I think he would say,
and his analysis of that was,
who that really benefited was the bureaucracy
that processed that paper,
that implemented those norms.
And then if you could pull that away,
you could get help out where it was needed much quicker
without having this drag of people doing
sort of unproductive work of administering these systems.
So I think trying to cut administrative overhead.
And what he didn't have then, which we have now,
is the technology that we have
and the ability to send benefits out via smartphone
or just to move so much faster
and to handle information on a mass scale so much faster.
- It's painful,
but I think one of the big things you can do is just that,
which is digitalize, I don't know if that's a word,
but just convert everything to where the speed
of signal can be instantaneous,
so there's no paperwork.
It goes immediately.
And then that means that the pricing signals
and all these kinds of things
are just immediately available to people.
- That seems to be the low-hanging fruit.
Government, you know,
IT systems could be vastly improved upon.
- But that would result again with a lot
of people getting fired.
And I think somebody submitted a question
for me saying like,
"What are your thoughts,
as a person who cares about compassion,
what are your thoughts about government employees,
which there's a lot of,
that are going to be hurt by Doge?
And it's always a really difficult question.
A lot of people get fired to make room for a new system.
That's going to lead to a lot of pain.
- There is going to be a lot of pain.
I don't know what the solution is.
I think that's also part
of why Friedman favored a minimum income.
He talked about it being sort of countercyclical.
In other words, when things were really bad,
the spending level on it would naturally go up.
This is what economists today call an automatic stabilizer.
And then when it's not needed,
the cost of it goes down.
I mean, maybe there's a way to make it sweeten it with honey
and have people take buyouts or things like that.
That would certainly be a way better way to go.
- I did a podcast with Javier Milei.
He has consistently praised Milton Friedman
and cited him as one of his inspirations,
so what do you think Milton Friedman would say
about what's going on in Argentina
and what Javier Milei is trying to do in Argentina?
- Yeah, I think he would appreciate it.
I mean, I think Milei is much more
of an Austrian-inspired thinker,
but I think he definitely appreciates Friedman.
And on the macro level,
Friedman always understood it's really painful
to treat inflation, but the more you put it off,
the harder it is.
So I think he would be trying to get him, as he's doing,
to just message that short-term pain, long-term gain.
I think he'd be very supportive.
I think he'd be thrilled to see also that Milei is very good
at explaining these abstract ideas
and putting his policies
in a framework of the bigger picture.
That was really meaningful to Friedman.
I don't know how politically persuasive it is overall.
You know, Milei is very intense.
He doesn't have the same sort of gifts of salesmanship
and setting people at ease
that say someone like Ronald Reagan had,
but it seems to be
that's what his country was calling for right now, so.
- Yeah, he is more chainsaw, less like warm blanket.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
(Lex chuckles)
Javier recollects this line from Milton Friedman.
I don't know if this is accurate, but,
"If you strive for equality over freedom,
you often get neither,
but if you strive for freedom, you often get both."
Do you think there's truth to this?
- You know, I think on the big picture, definitely.
I mean we've seen focusing too much on equality can be,
because equality is such an alluring word,
it can lead you to downgrade all kinds
of other things that are really important.
But I really think it depends
on how you're defining freedom.
I mean the statement is too big and too broad, right?
So if you're talking about freedom,
if by freedom you mean not having
to pay taxes if you're successful,
I think that can have all kinds of knock on effects.
The idea that people are able
to prosper when they're educated,
where is education going to come from?
How is that going to be paid for and supported?
And again to go back to Knight,
if you're generating too much inequality
or people are feeling
that you're generating too much inequality,
sometimes they value that more than they value freedom.
And so I think the balance,
I think there has to be more of a balance.
And it's hard to make such global statements.
You have to break them down into what actually do you mean.
But again, Milei is coming from a very different context,
a very different country that has seen so much upheaval,
so much government intervention, so much inflation,
so much political turmoil.
He's probably thinking
about it differently than Friedman was thinking about it.
- Yeah, I mean, there was,
there probably still is a real threat of hyperinflation.
There seems to be a very high level of corruption
or the capacity for corruption,
so it's a really messy situation.
So Javier Milei likes to recollect this great line
from Milton Friedman,
that if you strive for equality over freedom,
you often get neither,
but if you strive for freedom, you often get both.
Do you think there's truth to this?
- Yeah, I think in the macro, for sure.
I mean, we've seen if you really put equality as your goal,
it's such a seductive ideal
and people believe in it so much
that they can carry out horrible crimes
in the name of equality.
But then focusing on freedom,
these words are too big.
They're so hard to define.
And so I think you have to ask sort of like,
what is the freedom you're talking about?
If you're talking
about the freedom of ordinary people to be entrepreneurial,
to make their own way, to start new things,
to continue what they're doing,
to keep what they've earned,
for sure, I think that can increase the equality overall.
If you're talking about lower taxes,
if freedom is just a code for lower taxes,
there has to be,
I mean, lower taxes in general, great.
But if you're one of the top generators of wealth,
there has to be some way to ensure that, say, education.
People prosper when they're well educated.
That's when economies do better.
Education is generally state funded,
and you need some way to support that
and provide for those institutions that structure society,
that make competition possible.
So I think it's just a really broad statement.
Again, Milei is coming from a really different context.
He's coming from the South American context,
from such upheaval, such economic devastation
in pursuit of the goal of equality that I think trying
to rebalance with that emphasis on freedom,
I definitely see where he's coming from.
- If we can pivot a little bit.
We've talked about Reagan.
What are some interesting stories
about how Milton Friedman navigated the Reagan
and maybe even the Nixon administrations
and how he was able to gain influence?
- Well, the Nixon administration
is an interesting case, because,
so I've been talking about inflation
and the different consequences it had.
One consequence it had is that it began
to undermine the Bretton Woods currency system
that was established in the wake of World War II.
Now, Bretton Woods, what it did,
basically it ended up inadvertently putting the US dollar
at the center of the world economic system.
But under Bretton woods,
countries of the industrialized West agreed
to trade their currency in set ratios that government set.
So a franc was worth so many dollars,
or a German mark was worth so many francs.
And then also under this system,
countries could come to the United States
and they could trade the dollars that they held for gold,
because the US was on a sort of modified gold standard.
There was a ratio of gold to paper money.
And so this system was set up
and very quickly most countries were,
the dollar was at the heart of it
in that the converting into
and out of dollars was really the mechanism of trade
for many of these countries.
So Friedman said, you know,
what we should have is floating exchange rates.
This is an idea, again,
of instead of having a top-down design of policy,
an administered policy, we will have policy set by prices.
And you should be able to trade currencies
on an open market.
They should trade and they should fluctuate,
and that would be fine.
Totally outlandish idea.
But he was pinpointing the fact
that Bretton Woods had an instability.
And that instability began to emerge
in the time of inflation.
So you have more and more dollars being printed.
They're worth less and less.
If European nations keep trading their currency for dollars,
they're going to be importing inflation
into their own economies.
So they say, "We don't want these dollars.
We'd like some gold instead."
And they have the right to go to the Treasury,
send in an order, and get gold out.
And so they start doing this more and more,
and it becomes, it's called the gold drain.
And the United States starts running out of gold.
They're aware this is happening through the 60s.
They're trying various things to fix it.
And when Nixon comes into office in '68,
Friedman sends him a memo and it says,
"This is going to be a real problem."
He says something like,
"This is a running sore,
and you have to lance it right away."
You know, some very graphic metaphor.
- [Lex] Very nice.
- Otherwise it's going to, you know,
it's going to explode.
And Nixon just, you know, files the memo away.
Nixon loved people to think he was influenced by
and following the wisdom of Milton Friedman.
But he didn't actually want to do that.
He just wanted the political benefit that came from it.
So then comes the moment
where the US Treasury Department realizes,
we are going to run out of gold.
What should we do?
And everybody decamps to Camp David, and Nixon decides,
we're just going to stop redeeming currency for gold.
It's called slamming the gold window shut.
Done.
And he also, at that same meeting,
decides to institute price controls.
He does a whole bunch of stuff.
It's an emergency.
He calls it the New Economic Plan,
which is an unconscious echo
of the Soviet New Economic Plan,
so a problematic name, a problematic policy.
And Friedman is livid at the price controls, but he's like,
"Actually, it's great that you close the gold window.
Let's go all the way to floating exchange rates."
And this idea was heresy within the Treasury Department.
Everyone's very committed to the idea
of the gold standard convertibility possibility,
the United States at the core of the financial system,
kind of hem and ha.
But at this point,
Friedman has a very close relationship with George Shultz.
And George Shultz is a high-level appointee
who will eventually,
over the course of Nixon administrations,
become the Treasury Secretary.
And so Friedman is feeding Schultz all his ideas
about how we should move to floating exchange rates,
how we shouldn't try to reconstruct Bretton Woods.
And the people in Treasury,
it's funny because I've read some of their accounts
and actually Paul Volcker is in the Treasury Department
at this time, and he can kind of sense
that Friedman is in here somewhere,
like feeding his boss ideas.
He doesn't quite know.
And in the oral history,
Schulz talks about this quite a bit.
So at any rate,
Friedman exerts this behind-the-scenes influence.
And what Schultz does is just
kind of lets Bretton Woods fade away.
He doesn't make grand pronouncements.
It just slowly the world shifts to a regime of,
for a while it was like a regime of steady prices.
Then they call it a steady regime of changing prices,
or whatever, the language changes,
the reality changes,
and they kind of end up where they are.
So that's a real measure of Friedman's influence.
If there had been another economist
in Schultz's ear that said,
"No, catastrophe is imminent,
we have to go back to Bretton Woods,"
he probably would have worked harder.
The US government would have worked harder.
And so that becomes one of these pieces of globalization.
And what people don't realize is there used to be,
in addition to these floating set capital ratios,
you couldn't bring capital in
and out of different countries.
You had to register, you couldn't invest,
all these rules and strictures,
and the falling of Bretton Woods really blows that all open.
It's a precursor to globalization.
So Friedman is right there.
Now, he's very ambivalent about Nixon.
I mean, he sees that Nixon is not an honest person.
He thinks he's very intelligent.
And Nixon's dream is to create a new centrist majority.
So he does many things to go back
on his supposed economic principles and ideals.
So Friedman does not like this.
He doesn't like the price controls.
He's in communication with his old mentor, Arthur Burns,
who's now the chair of the Federal Reserve.
And Burns is basically doing everything wrong
in monetary policy.
And I describe this in the book in some detail,
these anguished letters back and forth.
And basically, as I see it,
Burns doesn't have a solid theory of inflation.
And the more Friedman pushes him,
it's almost like Burns is willfully ignoring Friedman
and kind of doing the opposite of what Friedman says.
So Burns is running a very loose monetary policy.
Inflation is quite considerable over the 70s.
I mean, we were all spooked by what, did it get to?
6%, something like that,
recently, for a very short time.
This is inflation going over 10%,
hovering in 8% for basically the whole decade of the 70s,
going up and down with extremely elevated rates.
And so the Carter presidency largely falls.
Foreign policy is a big part of it,
but the failure to tame inflation is part of it.
And then Reagan comes in, and now Reagan loves Friedman,
and Friedman loves Reagan.
Very mutual feeling.
The Reagan administration creates
like an advisory economic board.
Friedman's on it.
He's retired now.
He's entering his kind of golden years.
But he really has Reagan's ear.
And here what he does is he convinces Reagan
of his theory of inflation,
which is inflation has been caused.
It's a monetary phenomenon that has been caused
by bad monetary policy.
Inflation has an accelerating dynamic.
The only way to end inflation is by really showing
and signaling that government policy has changed.
And when you do that, it's very painful
for a short amount of time, people will suffer,
but then you will come out on the other side
into stable prices,
and this is what you need for economic prosperity.
So the man who implements this policy, Paul Volcker,
is definitely influenced by Friedman,
buys the big picture of Friedman.
He even buys Friedman's specific technique
of the monetary growth rule
and of the focus on monetary aggregates,
which Friedman has said, right, "Money matters,
aggregates matter, and that's what money is."
Pretty quickly, Volcker finds that because of inflation
and the financial deregulation in response to it,
the aggregates don't work the way Friedman said they would.
And so the specific policy Friedman recommends,
Volcker tries it for a year or so,
doesn't work super well.
But what does work is letting interest rates go high,
go above inflation
to a point where both the general citizenry
and the financial markets Believe, like,
"Oh, they're actually serious about inflation."
And because we've had a decade
of inflation with all these presidents saying,
"Forward, we're going to whip inflation now,"
that monetary policy has lost credibility.
This is why people focus so much on credibility today,
because once it's lost, it's really hard to get it back.
And one way Volcker gets it back is interest rates over 20%,
unemployment very high,
as high as 25% in construction sectors.
And as this is happening,
Milton Friedman is whispering in Reagan's ear,
"This is the right thing.
Stay the course.
This is going to work."
Now, interestingly, he hates Volcker, Volcker hates him.
And Friedman will never give Volcker credit for this policy,
but he will give Reagan credit for this policy.
But he owes credit himself
for keeping Reagan from wobbling on this policy
and just pushing it through.
And he also tells Reagan very pragmatically,
"You better do this now.
You've got a four-year term.
Do this in the first two years of your term.
Things will have turned around by 1984
when you run for reelection,
and you'll benefit from it."
And that's absolutely what happens.
- If we could take a small tangent,
sort of a question I have to ask about, (chuckles)
since we mentioned Bretton Woods
and maybe the gold standard,
maybe just have a general discussion
about this whole space of ideas.
There's a lot of people today
that care about cryptocurrency.
What do you think that Milton Friedman would say
about cryptocurrency
and what role crypto might play in the economy?
Whether he would be for this idea, against this idea,
and if we could look at it for today,
and also just 10, 100 years from now.
- There's a clip,
I think it's in 1992, where people say,
"Oh, Friedman predicted cryptocurrencies,"
because he's talking (Lex chuckles)
about how payments will eventually be electronic.
So in some ways he definitely,
as he was looking at the computer and money,
he knew these would come together in some way.
I think he probably would see a use case for crypto.
He definitely would not buy the stronger forms, I think,
of crypto ideology
in which we could be heading towards a future
in which there's many different currencies that compete
or that are distributed or there's a stateless currency.
And he addresses this very, very clearly,
because Hayek's "Denationalization of Money,"
it's a paper in the late 70s, you know,
Hayek argues for this
kind of competing currency model or regime.
And so he's responding to that.
He's responding to people writing about free banking.
And he basically says, "Look,
even if you developed a variety of competing currencies,
eventually society would converge on one."
And that's because people just want one currency.
They know they don't want a bunch of different options.
Even in places where there have been options to do that,
they've been used very minimally.
And then he says secondly, "The state always steps in."
He says, "Technically, theoretically it doesn't have to.
I could draw you a model,
I could tell you about how it could work without the state.
But in actual reality,
all human societies through time and space,
the state eventually becomes involved
in the provision of money,
because it has so many knock-on effects to so many people."
So sure, I think he would, again,
find a use case for crypto, think it's interesting,
but I don't think he would see it
as this is going to displace state money
and we're going to have a variety of distributed currencies.
The other thing he really stresses is that a change
in a monetary system,
it only happens amid great, great crisis.
So again, you see in countries
where the state is not controlling the money well,
right, that's when people are more turning to crypto.
But he says, "Because money is so fundamental,
there are going to be so much political pressure
on any country that gets the currency profoundly wrong
that the government will fall
and another one will replace it."
So if you look at episodes of hyperinflation,
they don't go on very long,
because they're so upsetting to people.
- If we can go back in time,
we've talked about it a bunch,
but it's still a fascinating time,
the Great Depression, University of Chicago.
There's these folks
like Jacob Viner, Frank Knight, Henry Simons.
All of these influence the thinking of Milton Friedman.
There's this Room 7 situation, University of Chicago,
just going back there,
even just speaking almost philosophically,
what does it take to explore ideas together?
Sort of like deliberate argue in that space.
And maybe there might be interesting stories
about that time.
It would just be interesting
to understand how somebody like Milton Friedman forms.
(chuckles) The seed is planted and the flower blooms.
- Yeah, yeah.
So he gets to University of Chicago,
he makes fast friends,
and in his third and fourth year,
they become what I call them, the Room 7 Gang.
So Room 7 is they find an old storeroom in the basement,
they take it over,
and that's where they have their jam sessions.
And what made this world come together was Frank Knight.
There was a charismatic leader,
and there were a bunch of acolytes who clustered around him.
That I think was a key piece of the ingredient.
And then there was a sense
that they were onto something
that the rest of the economics field had forgotten
or was rejecting.
So there was like that sense of mission.
So that seems to have been,
there was a formal education piece,
and then there was a parallel education piece
rooted in admiration for a thinker,
a shared admiration,
and then what that led Friedman to do,
I found syllabi that he had from non-economics courses,
lists of books, and he'd written the prices
of different ones he wanted to read.
So he had John Stuart Mill, "On Liberty,"
like "50 cents" written in the margin.
So he began to educate himself.
He gave himself a parallel curriculum
alongside this very formal economics curriculum.
He started reading the traditions of political liberalism,
and then talking them through with friends,
and then developing a shared sense of mission.
And the incredible thing is of those friends in the group,
they scattered for like 10 years
and then they all came back together.
George Stigler, his great friend, was hired at Chicago.
Aaron Director, who was his wife's brother,
was at Chicago.
So many of these people continued.
He became Frank Knight's colleague.
So that was the base.
That was what really grew him,
that really profound peer group.
Now the other piece I talk about a lot
is Friedman was a collaborator,
an open-minded collaborator,
and he had incredible connections
with economists who were women.
And he basically found first in the figure of Anna Schwartz,
later in the figure
of this group of women who were his wife's friends,
this kind of untapped pool of talent.
And so he immersed himself
in this whole other world of consumption economics.
And that resulted in his more technical work on a theory
of the consumption function,
which is the theory of permanent income.
So for Friedman, intellectual work
and intellectual production was always done
in this very social context,
in a context that blended friendship
and intellectual partnership.
And he only had a handful of friends
who were not also economists
interested in the same questions he was.
So he just lived and breathed ideas all day long.
- Can you speak to the jam sessions?
Like what do we know about the jam sessions?
What are we talking about here?
You're sitting in a room, are they analyzing,
are they reading papers
and discussing papers, or are they arguing
more like over beers kind of situation?
- Yeah, more arguing over beers.
And in this case,
there's several people who say,
"It was all about Frank Knight."
What did he say?
What did he mean when he said it?
Is he right?
And so Knight was very,
he would say one thing and then say another.
If you read him,
it's very hard to follow what he's actually saying,
because he's full of qualifications and irony as it blends.
And so he would throw out these pieces,
and then the students would kind of clutch at them,
and then they would come back together
and try to assemble this sort of worldview.
And then Frank Knight fell into this terrible depression,
and to cheer him up, they planned a big party,
and they went back through all of his previous writings,
and they assembled them into a book that was published.
This is "The Ethics of Competition."
And you can read the introduction written in part
by Milton Friedman.
So not only were they talking about Knight and what he said,
but then they started pouring over his work.
And one of them described it
as like a general equilibrium system where you had
to know all the parts, and then all of a sudden,
it all fit together in a whole.
So if we step back,
what they were doing was getting
inside the mind of a great thinker
and understanding the ways it all fit together,
and then kind of testing their ideas against Knight's.
And what's fascinating is one
of the first papers that Friedman publishes in statistics
is a rebuttal of Frank Knight.
He publishes a rebuttal of Frank Knight's ideas
about risk and uncertainty.
And Frank Knight,
he kind of took a black swan argument.
He said, "Risk, you can calculate.
Uncertainty, you can't existentially, philosophically,
you can't get your hands around it.
It is the black swan."
And Friedman publishes this statistical paper, and he says,
"I can put uncertainty on a graph."
And so there's that sort of Freudian killing
of the father element when he comes back.
And he will, in some ways,
turn his back on Knight's approach and Knight's pessimism,
even while it's like a foundation of his thinking.
- Fascinating.
Is there something you could say
about the thinking process that Milton Friedman followed,
like how he developed his ideas?
You mentioned there's a strong collaborative component.
But there's another story I saw
about that I think his son recalled
about the argument number system you mentioned.
- [Jennifer] Yes.
- Which I, by the way,
if you can explain that as a tangent of a tangent,
that's really awesome.
I think it's like, number one,
if the other person is right.
- Number two means you were right and I was wrong.
And the number system evolved in some ways to be quick
and efficient, but in other ways,
they also were really clear about it.
So, you know something like there's
kind of like three reasons behind it.
First is if you use a number,
it reminds the listener that it's really hard
to say the words, "I was wrong."
So you're kind of calling on their sympathy
by using the number,
reminding them that you're doing a hard thing.
And then it's also reminding them
that you're in this family with this code.
And so you're signaling your membership
and your closeness and your love, really.
And so it's supposed to be an easy way
to disagree without like breaking the relationship.
- Yeah, so admitting you're wrong now comes
with this warm fuzzy feeling.
- [Jennifer] Yeah, yeah.
- And that's really, I mean, that's so powerful.
I think so much of the friction
of human interaction could be boiled down
to just not being able to admit they are wrong efficiently
and quickly and regularly and just often.
And to be able to do that, that's really powerful.
- Yeah, I think it's a really neat aspect
of their family life, for sure. (chuckles)
- That's a fun story.
But can we just generalize to how he engaged
in collaboration, how he developed his ideas?
Is there a thinking process?
- So he taught at the University of Chicago
and he tended to teach for six months
and then have six months off.
And he spent the summers in New Hampshire or Vermont.
He had, right near that border,
they had two different houses.
And that to him was the deep thinking time.
And so when he's at Chicago,
he's teaching, he's arguing.
Some people loved his teaching style.
Very much in charge,
very much keeping students on their toes, confrontational.
Others found it too much, overwhelming,
kind of shut them down intellectually,
and they couldn't cope with it.
And so I think it was kind of go time when he was teaching.
In that case, that was a lot of social time,
interacting, talking other professors,
going out and giving papers,
arguing with the people at Yale or Harvard.
Then he would go
and do these very deep dives over the summer.
He would also regularly do these trips
to New York to see Anna Schwartz,
so his a 12-year collaborator.
Phone calls were really expensive.
They did have quite an extensive correspondence.
But then they would do these meetings.
So he would basically come in
at the beginning of this summer,
going to Rahway, stop in New York, see Schwartz,
and then again on the way back to Chicago.
So you'd have these deep check-ins at that point.
The other thing that happened is people would come visit him
in New Hampshire, and so he would have these,
he had a studio separate from the house.
He would go and he would work,
and then at night his friends would come.
His friends are all economists.
There's a whole like cluster of economists.
They all clustered within driving distance
of the Dartmouth Library,
so that they could get their hands on books.
And so they would come over
and then they would argue and talk into the night.
So I think he did need that deep focus time,
but it was not,
like he also lived a very engaged,
very embedded social life.
- A part of which was his marriage.
Is there something you could say about love, about marriage,
about relationship that made the whole thing work?
Because it was vibrant.
And they wrote a biography together.
- They did.
I mean, they were very complimentary.
They were kind of the yin and the yang.
She was very introverted,
somewhat suspicious of others, skeptical,
and he was extremely extroverted, optimistic, high energy.
And they also were at a time when it was really clear, like,
for broader society, these are the roles of a man,
these are the roles of a woman.
And they pretty much adopted those.
Now, Rose Friedman did some very important economic work.
She's part of the early stages
of the theory of the consumption function.
She didn't complete her degree,
because she really knew there wasn't,
if she wanted to be married
and have children in the world she lived in,
there wasn't a real pathway to also being an economist.
I do think that a lot of that,
although it feels very gendered,
like he's the man out in the world and she's in private.
It's interesting because her brother, Aaron Director,
was the same way.
He was very private man, very shy, very introverted.
And he exerted this quiet intellectual influence
on all of his friends.
So I think that was just
kind of a family trait of being more quiet,
preferring to be behind the scenes.
It wouldn't have worked any other way,
because Friedman was so out there,
so, you know, so extroverted.
And there's a bit of a sad thing she said.
She said, "When I married Milton,
I lost half of my conversations.
When David came along, I lost the other half."
So this is a household that was just dominated
by male voices in which she didn't have a lot of room.
What was tricky
for me in my research is she didn't leave much of a trace.
She put together Milton Friedman's archive
and she took herself out of it.
So I really had trouble finding her actual voice
in the historical documents.
And she didn't want to leave that behind.
So absolutely essential piece of his success,
because she's the one who pushed him
to do the "Newsweek" column, to do "Free to Choose,"
and she really wrote "Capitalism and Freedom."
She took all his random notes,
and she put them together into a book.
And that became this kind of testimony of his ideas.
But she shared many of his ideas.
And she, you know, without,
when I think of Friedman, if you take away Anna Schwartz,
if you take away Rose Friedman,
if you take away the other woman who collaborated with him,
you have a much thinner resume than the one he actually has.
- Yeah, it's always sad,
and it always makes me wonder about the private,
secret conversations between partners,
because they might not show up in the record,
but they probably influence the person
more than almost anything else,
those quiet little conversations.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- If we can switch our path to another great mind
of the 20th century, Ayn Rand.
We talked about some of the similarities here,
about them being fighters for freedom
and fighters for capitalism.
What is Ayn Rand's philosophy?
If you can give a big 10,000-word summary of Objectivism.
- Yes, so she called it Objectivism.
She used to do this thing,
like I can stand on one foot and say it.
So it goes something like,
"Epistemology, reason, ethics,
selfishness, politics, capitalism."
That was kind of how she summarized it.
So what she did.
There's a couple things she did with Objectivism.
First of all, she says the key defining element
of humanity is rationalism, the rational faculty.
So that's what defines what humanity is.
Therefore, there is an objective reality that we can access
and know with our reason.
That's the objective epistemology.
And the one social
and economic system that lets rationality flower
and is based upon rationality is capitalism.
And then rationality only works in her view,
as an individual capacity.
And that rationality teaches
that what you should do is pursue your interests.
And so she ends up calling that selfishness.
Now, it's tricky because selfishness has so many strong
and negative connotations.
And she meant, I think,
something closer to like self-actualization,
because she really tried to create this idea
and express the idea that
to be truly selfish did not mean trampling on others.
It meant just being motivated
by your own kind of internal measures and metrics.
And so in her fiction, she tries to show this
by showing the false selfishness of some of Peter Keating,
who's an architect who kind of steps over everybody
to advance his career.
And she says, "That's not true selfishness,
because true selfishness would recognize it's false
to take others work and pass it off as your own."
Now, the other big piece
of Objectivism is a very approach that's really inspired
and related to Friedrich Nietzsche's idea
of revaluing values or a genealogy of morals.
And so she says, "What's happened here
is Western culture has converged
on this idea of altruism as good,
being selfless and altruistic is good.
And this has led us to communism,
and has led us to devalue the individual
in favor of the Collective.
So what we need is a new moral code
which elevates selfishness,
which elevates the individual,
and which takes all the things
that we have been told are bad
and actually says their values."
This is what she's trying to do with Objectivism.
I mean, it is about
as ambitious of an intellectual project as there can be,
and that's what really draws people in.
Yet at the same time,
she's flying in the face of the way human morals
and ethics in societies have evolved,
and she's not able to single handedly recreate them
the way she wants them to be.
- Yeah, I mean, she's not doing herself any favors
by like taking on the words
and trying to rebrand them completely,
like writing "The Virtue of Selfishness."
It's like, can we just call it self-actualization?
- Yeah.
- There's a negative connotation to selfishness
and a positive connotation to altruism.
So she sometimes, it seems,
takes on the hardest possible form of argument.
- Yeah, I mean, she had a student,
who ended up being very close to her, Nathaniel Branden,
and he was the reverend advisor, and he said,
"Can you please not use selfishness?
Like just come up with another word."
But part of her liked it.
Part of her wanted to provoke and unsettle.
She didn't want to give that up.
- I mean, people should listen to her public talks.
Her whole aura, way of being is provocative,
and she's a real powerhouse of an intellectual.
So like she loves the challenge,
and that just listening to her in itself is just inspiring
because you could see the individualism radiate from her.
- Yeah, I mean, that was one of the things I found
in researching and writing about her.
Like, she's an incredibly unusual human being, you know?
(Lex chuckles)
And so that was like her strength,
because she's so unusual,
but it was also her downfall
because she looked to herself as a model
or to get insight about humanity,
and she never quite processed how different she was
from other people.
- So just because we talked about Milton Friedman so much,
can we just return to what to you,
given everything we've said,
is the interesting differences about Ayn Rand,
her ideas, related to Milton Friedman?
- Yeah, I mean, broadly, we could put Milton Friedman
and Ayn Rand in some sort of category together,
but she has this focus on ethics and rationality
and this desire to be revolutionary
that's much stronger than Friedman.
Friedman wanted to overthrow the economic consensus.
He didn't want to overturn the moral basis
of Western society.
Also so she does something.
So in one of Frank Knight's essays,
he talks about "The Ethics of Competition."
And he says, "You basically cannot build an ethics
out of competition,
because it would be monstrous to do so,
because it would say,
'The winner of this competition is ethically right.'
And that would open the door to sort of might makes right."
And this is what Friedman struggles with.
And he says, "I can't take capitalist outcomes
as ethical unto themselves.
I can't do it.
Doesn't feel right."
And there's this line where Frank Knight says,
"No one would ever do this."
And I was like, "Oh, Frank Knight,
you haven't read Ayn Rand yet."
(Lex and Jennifer chuckle)
- Hold my beer, yeah.
- You're a little too early.
Because that's what she does.
She takes the outcomes of capitalism
and of market competition and says,
"These have ethical meaning,
and this is where ethical meaning inheres,
and it is ethical to try to succeed
and to succeed in a capitalist society."
Now, what she's able to do is create a fictional world
in which people succeed
in her fictional capitalist world through ethical behavior.
And so she doesn't really have
to wrestle with a capitalist world
in which people succeed through fraud and corruption
and all the other things that might go
into someone's success.
She creates the best possible take
on success under capitalism.
And then she holds that up as an ideal.
And I think what's important is that
so few people have done that.
And she comes at a time
when everybody is emphasizing the downsides of capitalism.
And she says, "There's another way to look at it.
Here are the good sides of capitalism."
- And like you said, "She was operating,"
which I really loved the phrasing of that,
"in the mythic register."
- Yeah.
- So she was constructing these characters,
these capitalists that are like the highest form,
these great heroic figures,
almost romanticizing them.
- [Jennifer] Yeah, yeah.
- You mentioned "We the Living"
is one of the books that you like of hers the most.
But can we stay in the mythic register
with "The Fountainhead" and "Atlas Shrugged?"
What to you are some sort of memorable, inspiring moments,
insightful moments from those books that may be scenes
or ideas that you take away from them
that are important for people to understand?
- Yeah.
So "The Fountainhead" is this story
of a struggling architect, Howard Roark,
and she kind of follows his life and his career.
And the message is really,
it's a version of to thine own self be true.
And Roark's designs are too avant garde.
Nobody appreciates him,
and he just keeps doing what he wants to do
and is just focused on his own visions, his own genius.
I think that's been really inspiring
to kind of creators of all types.
I think it's fairly unrealistic
as a portrait of human achievement,
but it's an aspirational idea.
I mean, one phrase that comes
to mind is there's a character, I forget which one,
who is in some sort
of adversarial relationship with Howard Roark
and says something to him like,
"Well, Mr. Roark, what do you think of me?"
And Roark says, "I don't think of you."
And that, to Rand, was the ideal.
You're not thinking of other people.
You're an island unto yourself.
You know, you're focused on your own goals,
your own capacities.
And you're not doing it to impress other people
or to be better than other people
or to dominate other people.
You're doing it
because you're sort of expressing your inner soul in a way.
So that has been very captivating to so many.
And "The Fountainhead" is one of those books we talked
about that causes, you know,
people read it and they make changes in their life
or they feel called to their higher self.
- And I think there's also the scene where Roark
with the dean of architecture school that's speaking
to what you're saying,
I think, to me is inspiring.
So this is the dean of architecture that expels Roark,
and it brings him into a meeting,
thinking Roark will plead for a second chance.
And the dean says that Roark's work, "Is contrary
to every principle we have tried to teach you,
contrary to all established precedents
and traditions of art.
Do you mean to tell me that you're thinking seriously
of building that way when and if you are an architect?"
And then in a gangster-like way,
Roark says, "Yes."
And then Dean asks,
"My dear fellow, who will let you?"
And Roark replies, "That's not the point.
The point is, who will stop me?"
- Yes, I mean, you know,
Rand is coming from Communist Russia,
but it has a bit of the don't-mess-with-Texas flavor.
You know, I might say that really resonates with this idea
of anyone who's felt
like they're fighting the powers that be.
Yeah, it's interesting.
I thought you might be going
to the quote where he says something like,
"I inherit no tradition.
I stand at the beginning of one."
And I really think Rand's thinking
about herself when she says that she inherits nothing.
She stands at the start.
But "The Fountainhead" comes out
in the middle of World War II,
and it's not expected.
Rand is an unknown writer.
This is kind of a strange book.
It's, you know, classic story.
It's turned down by 12 publishers
before one takes a chance on it.
And Rand really loved this story.
The editor who read it said, "This book is great."
And his boss said, "No."
And he said,
"If you don't take this book, I'm quitting," you know?
And so she idolized him for doing that.
So they print it,
and it becomes a bestseller just through word of mouth.
So it's not advertised.
It gets one good book review,
but people tell each other how much they like this book.
And it keeps printing and selling out printings.
It's made into a movie.
And so it lands in this time when Americans are engaged
in this great collective endeavor of World War II.
They're making all kinds of sacrifices for the Collective.
And I think paradoxically, as they do that,
they're drawn to this vision
of someone who doesn't have to compromise at all,
who is leading their life exactly as they want to.
You know, meanwhile,
they might be sleeping on an ocean liner
because they've been drafted to fight in this war.
And they're reading "The Fountainhead"
and they're feeling better about themselves.
And so it's also really interesting.
"The Fountainhead" is hugely popular in India,
which is fascinating.
And I've talk to people about this,
and they basically say,
"This book comes like a breath of fresh air
into a very traditional and conformist culture,
and people just latch onto it and they love it.
And it gives them that feeling of freedom
and possibility that they're hoping for."
- Yeah, I mean, it really is a book,
"Atlas Shrugged" can be a bit of that too,
but it's more the philosophy of Objectivism
and the details and the nuance of that
seeps into "Atlas Shrugged."
"The Fountainhead" is very much like a thing
that makes you change the path of your life.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- And that, I mean,
that's beautiful to see that books can have that power.
- And, you know, Rand knew that she was doing that
and she knew what she was doing.
This wasn't an accident.
And people say, "Oh, she's a bad writer.
Oh, her characters are so heavy-handed."
You know, she started as a screenwriter.
She started as someone who analyzed films for movie studios.
She knew exactly how to manipulate plot
and character and drama.
And she also knew that she was writing,
people say, "Oh, Rand is for adolescents,
adolescent teenagers love Rand."
And that's kind of who she was writing for.
And she said, you know,
"I'm writing for people as they start out on their life
and they're thinking about who they want to be."
So she's not writing for the weary middle age.
She's writing for the young who are looking for inspiration.
- You know, people say that to me sometimes
about certain books like Rand,
but also about "The Alchemist."
I know a lot of people for whom "The Alchemist,"
and they're adults and they're brilliant people,
"The Alchemist" changed their life.
And the same can be said about "The Fountainhead."
I sometimes get criticized
for using words that are too simple. (chuckles)
I think simple words can have power.
And the cliche thing sometimes needs to be said.
And sometimes, if effectively,
needs to be said in an over the top way
in the mythic register,
because that's the thing that resonates with us.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- Because we are like heroes of our own story.
We need to hear that message sometimes
to take the bold step,
to take the risk, to take the leap.
- Yeah, and I mean, the other thing,
she knew she was doing kind of propaganda in a way.
She was like, "I'm doing pro-capitalist propaganda."
She has a degree from the University of Leningrad.
You know, she's raised up in Soviet Russia.
She said, "We need to present the case
for the other side in the same way."
And that's what she did.
- Why do you think she's so divisive?
People either love her or hate her.
- I mean, I think it's because of that purity,
that I'm willing to say
sort of you get what you deserve,
and that kind of lack of charity.
And part of that in her work is
because she creates this fictional world
where she can set everything up just so,
and so you don't have contingency
or accident or bad luck,
or you don't really have a lot of children,
you don't have handicapped people.
You know, you just have this idealized world.
And I think it's really infuriating
for people who feel that's so inaccurate.
How can you be deriving a social theory
and philosophy around this?
And how can you be missing what seems
to many people she's missing the kind of ethical instinct
or the altruistic or charitable instinct.
And so they just become enraged at that,
and they don't want to see anyone go that far.
And they're outraged that someone went that far,
did the thing that Frank Knight said no one would do.
Yeah, it's very unsettling.
- Would you say that's her main blind spot?
The main flaw of Objectivism is just how black
and white it paints the world?
Or if not, what would you say are the flaws of Objectivism?
- So I mean, the big flaw is that it's justified
through a fictional world.
It's not justified through reference to the real world.
It's not empirical.
And Rand herself would say that.
She's not writing about things how they are,
but how they should be.
And so that idealism just really undermines it
as a mechanism to understand where we're actually living.
- And that is a big contrast with Milton Friedman,
who would focus on how things are
versus how things should be.
- And then I think it's the problem
of elevating rationality over any other mode
of insight or thinking.
And so what happens in Rand's life,
I describe this in some detail in the book,
is she essentially creates a cult of reason around her
and people who are drawn into this cult,
it's called the Collective.
It's a group of young people
in New York City who are drawn to her work.
And she's already famous,
but she's writing "Atlas Shrugged"
and so she's sharing drafts of "Atlas Shrugged"
as she goes along.
And one of the members of the Collective,
to bring all of this together, is Alan Greenspan,
who will later be head of the Federal Reserve.
And he's incredibly taken with her.
He's one of these people who says,
"I was a narrow, technical thinker.
I never thought about ethics
or politics or anything bigger until I met Ayn Rand.
And she really opened my mind."
He's part of this tight knit group.
But over time, in this tight knit group,
they think of themselves,
we are all individualists.
We're dedicated to individualism and capitalism.
We're different than everybody else.
Over time, they all come to share Ayn Rand's views
and opinions on everything from music to art to clothes.
You know, she gets a dining room table
and a bunch of them get the same dining room table.
And it becomes incredibly conformist,
because they've all believed they're acting rationally.
And they believe that to act rationally
is to agree with Ayn Rand.
And they believe there's no other way
to make decisions than rationality.
And so to disagree with her is to be irrational.
They don't want to be irrational.
So people get really caught up
in this very damaging cult-like circle around her.
- Plus, for a cult of reason,
they get awfully emotional
when there's any disagreement with Ayn Rand. (chuckles)
I mean, it's kind of hilarious.
It's absurd, but it's,
I mean, it's also beautiful to watch this singular figure.
We've talked about several singular figures,
like Frank Wright,
that shakes up the world with her ideas.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- And of course it would form a cult.
And of course that cult would be full of contradictions
and hypocrisies.
- Yeah, I mean, it's amazing.
So Murray Rothbard, who's a famous anarchist,
falls into the Ayn Rand cult,
and then he disagrees,
and there's some type of show trial
where he's told he's wrong about everything.
And then he has a little sort of pseudo cult of his own,
and two of his cult members switch over to Ayn Rand,
and then one of them, to show,
to gesture their breaking of their relationship,
mails him a dollar bill that's been torn in half.
I mean, this is high theatrics, right? (laughs)
- Okay, sticking on the drama and the theatrics,
who was Nathaniel Branden?
- Oh, yes.
- Can you take me through the arc
of Ayn Rand's relationship with Nathaniel Branden
to their dramatic falling out in 1968?
- Yes.
So after "The Fountainhead,"
"The Fountainhead" is auctioned,
is sold to be a film.
So Ayn Rand moves to Hollywood,
where she's going to help in the writing the film.
She wants a lot of creative control.
And then she's also still working in screenwriting
and things like this.
And so she gets a letter from,
there's a Canadian student who's written
to her several times, and then he writes again,
and he says, "I'm at UCLA."
And she's like, "Young man, you're so full of error.
Why don't you come visit me,
and I'll straighten you out?"
So he comes, and they have this real meeting of the minds.
They talk all night.
He comes again.
He brings his girlfriend.
She loves him.
And they start this very intense relationship
of spending every weekend at her house,
basically, staying up all night talking about ideas.
He becomes completely converted
to the Objectivist worldview.
Rand begins counseling him
and his girlfriend about their relationship.
You know, very intense thing.
Then eventually they graduate from college
and they both enroll in a graduate program in Columbia,
and they leave.
And after they've left, Ayn Rand is just bereft.
And within a few months,
she packs up her home and she moves to New York.
Here I am, I like New York better.
And so that becomes the seedbed of the Collective.
And the Brandens, they get married.
They change their name to Branden.
They've never publicly spoken on this,
but many people have pointed out it has the word Rand
in the name, so it's some type
of acknowledgment of how important she is to them.
And time goes on,
and romantic feelings develop between Ayn Rand
and Nathaniel Branden,
who's some 20 years her junior.
And they discuss them,
and they realize that rationality has led them
to the conclusion that they should be lovers.
- [Lex] Right.
- Right, they've rationally decided this,
but because they're rational,
they need the consent,
or at least to inform their partners.
- They're both married.
So they call a meeting and they obtain the consent,
or maybe simply inform the others
of the rationality of the choice.
And then they say,
"But this is only going to be an intellectual relationship,
but we'd like a few hours alone each week,
and we don't want to be deceptive,
so we want you to know and approve of this."
So the spouses bought into rationality,
know and approve.
One thing leads to another.
It becomes a full romantic and sexual relationship.
And although it's open within these four people,
it is not open more broadly.
And so in all these meetings of the Collective,
got Alan Greenspan and all these other people coming up,
you know, drinking coffee all night, talking, talking.
They all know that Nathaniel Branden
is Objectivist number one.
They don't know that there's a romantic
and sexual relationship happening.
It's kept a secret.
And then when "Atlas Shrugged" comes out,
it's panned by reviewers.
People absolutely hate this book.
And Rand is not Howard Roark.
She falls into a deep depression,
because her masterpiece has been rejected.
And so then, the romantic relationship ends,
but the close personal relationship continues.
And then over time, Branden,
who's still married to his wife,
begins an affair with another young woman.
And at this point,
he has started the Nathaniel Branden Institute
to teach Objectivism.
And he's making good money.
He's becoming quite famous.
- She supported the institute.
- She supported it,
and at first it was to help her in her depression
because he said, "The world needs to recognize your genius.
They missed 'Atlas Shrugged,' but I'm going to teach them.
I will bring the message."
And it's very successful.
It becomes its own business.
It has a newsletter.
It's a whole world.
So that small cult
around Ayn Rand expands to this whole social network.
And it's very much a piece
with this burgeoning conservative movement.
Objectivists are involved in criticizing the draft.
There it's kind of a libertarian Objectivist world going on.
All of this is happening.
In the meantime,
Nathaniel Branden has found a new partner.
But he doesn't tell Ayn Rand this,
because he knows she'll be upset.
And so it goes on for years.
And Ayn Rand knows something is going on,
but she can't quite figure it out.
And then finally Barbara Branden says to Nathaniel Branden,
you know, "You have to tell her.
This has just gone on too long."
So she finds out, and the whole thing blows up,
and she exiles him,
and she breaks off contact with him,
and nobody is ever told what happens.
It's called the Objectivist schism.
You know, Objectivism breaks in two,
because some people say,
"How could Ayn Rand do anything wrong?"
And other people say,
"What is this letter all about?
And what did Nathaniel Branden do?
And I'm not just going to take her word for it.
I need more information."
And then a bunch of people,
I've read all the accounts of this.
A bunch of people are like,
"Okay, they were having an affair."
And a bunch of other people are like,
"No, that couldn't possibly be happening."
You know, and so, (chuckles)
the whole thing breaks up.
But what I argue in my book
is actually this is to the benefit
of Rand's ideas, because Rand herself was
so controlling over her ideas.
And now that she steps back from a public role, you know,
Objectivism flows into the student libertarian movement.
Some Objectivists become conservatives.
It just kind of spreads out more generally.
And you don't have to drink the Kool Aid,
you don't have to take the official course.
Nathaniel Branden goes on to be part
of the self-esteem movement, you know,
human potential movement, California.
And Ayn Rand lives another 10 years or so,
but she doesn't do major work after that.
- So since we were talking about some of the,
although rationalized,
some strange sexual partnerships
that they were engaging in,
I have to ask about "The Fountainhead"
and the, quote unquote, "rape scene"
in "The Fountainhead."
Was she intending to add that there to be controversial?
How are we supposed to read into it?
Is it a glimpse into Ayn Rand's sexuality?
And maybe broadly we can say,
what was her view on this,
on sexuality, on sex, on power dynamics and relationships?
- Yeah, I mean, there's also an Objectivist theory
of sexuality that probably the least convincing
of all the parts of Objectivism.
And it goes something like,
your sexual desires express your highest values,
and they are related in some ways to your rationality,
which is also related to your highest value.
So for her, that explained her attraction
to Nathaniel Branden,
and Nathaniel Branden's attraction to her was a function
of their highest values.
And in fact, Branden imbibed this
so deeply that the fact that he was later drawn sexually
to a woman who was not particularly accomplished,
but was beautiful caused him deep anguish
and guilt for being non-Objectivist.
So this is the Objectivist theory.
Then, the gender politics are just crazy,
and we have to kind of back up and think,
okay, so who is Ayn Rand?
She's born Alisa Rosenbaum in Russia.
She is someone who stands out
from the crowd from the beginning.
She never really fits in.
She's not conventionally beautiful
by any stretch of the imagination.
She struggles with her weight,
and she doesn't consider herself to have a beautiful face.
She's very independent.
She meets none of the metrics
of traditional femininity at all.
She finds love with a man who is very handsome
but very passive.
Yet she writes in all her fiction
about strong, manly heroes.
So this seems to be like a projection.
The man she's actually with is not a strong, manly hero.
The hero she writes about,
she probably wouldn't be able to be
in the same room with them for more than one minute
before they got in a raging argument, right?
(Lex chuckles)
And then she develops this theory about women
and men in that a woman should worship her man,
and a woman finds her true expression
in worshiping the man she's with.
So, again, this is not at all how Ayn Rand lives her life.
This is like this,
I would say, compensatory theory
for her lack of ability
to conform to the gender norms of her day.
She then articulates them in a very strong
and almost distorted and exaggerated way to compensate
for the fact that she doesn't actually meet them,
can't actually enact them.
The rape scene, to some degree,
embodies that idea that, to some degree,
that the woman should worship the man.
I tend to read it more in terms of literary genre.
So Rand is a screenwriter,
you know, a consumer of movies.
And that rape scene is paradigmatic
for the romance genre.
In other words, these like pulpy romance novels,
- Mhm, (chuckles) yeah.
- The hero rapes the heroine,
and then they fall in love.
That's just the trope of how it works.
So it's crazy when you read it,
but if you were reading a bunch of novels in this genre,
you would find this is very standard.
And so that is a huge part of its appeal at the time.
There's this feminist who hates Rand, Susan Brownmiller,
and she wants to write an angry denunciation
of the rape scene.
So she goes to get "The Fountainhead."
And she's wondering how is she ever gonna find the scene
in this, you know, 800-page book?
It's a library copy, because she doesn't wanna buy it.
And it just falls open to the rape scene,
because everybody's gone and read it,
because it's very racy
and explicit for that time.
So I'm almost positive she also knew that.
Like if I put in this kind of taboo-breaking sex scene,
that's also gonna probably be
why people tell their friends about it.
So I just, I think it's a mess.
I think all of the gender
and sexuality stuff she states
is just a total mess.
- I think it also reminds me of another guy related,
Friedrich Nietzsche,
who had very strong opinions on women
and wrote about what women's role in society should be
and different power dynamics
and relationships and all that kind of stuff,
when he himself really had trouble getting laid.
- Yeah.
- (chuckles) And so he has to sort of always maybe chuckle
or take with a grain of salt the analysis of power dynamics
in relationship from these figures,
which failed in many regards in their own private life.
You mentioned feminists.
Would you consider Ayn Rand a feminist?
- I mean, she's almost an anti-feminist,
because she then goes on,
and someone writes her a letter about like,
should there be a female president or something.
This is like the beginning of feminism.
And she says, "No.
No woman should ever be president,
because if she's president,
she wouldn't be able to look up to any man,
because she would be so powerful,
and therefore she would be like corrupt
and rotten in the soul
and unfit to be a leader."
And it just makes no sense.
- But that said, she's a woman,
and she's one of the most powerful intellects
in the 20th century.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- And so it's the contradictions.
I mean, Nietzsche is full of contradictions of this sort.
That the very fact that she's one of the most powerful minds
in history to me means that she is a feminist in her,
in the spirit she embodies, right?
In what she represents.
- I mean, she lived the ideals of individualism in her life
and set aside gender norms in her own life,
but she did not see herself as part of any,
she did not see herself as doing this
for the benefit of other women
or to change society's views about women.
There was no collective essence to it.
So if feminism has some sort of collective aspect to it,
or at least some identification,
one needs to identify with a broader category of women
and feel they're acting on behalf of that,
she's definitely not doing that.
And she did, you know,
she was fair to women in her life,
promoted them in her life, but did not,
I mean, she was very negative about feminism.
And then, because they dress terribly, you know?
And then the other thing, it's really interesting,
there's all these kind of homoerotic themes in her writing.
And for that reason, many gay men were drawn to her writing.
And then she would say, like,
"Homosexuals are dirty, terrible people."
You know, she would denounce people for being homosexual.
So there's a whole actual literature
of gay men wrestling with Rand
and what she says about gay people.
So, yeah, it's hard to make sense of.
And I just think of the enormous pressures.
I want to be charitable,
I just think of the enormous pressures she was under
in the culture she was raised in,
the expectations that were placed upon her,
and her just utter inability to meet any of them.
And it came out in this very tortured set of ideals
that she tried to promote,
and this kind of lack of ability to introspect in herself
was probably too painful to introspect
and to think about that,
so she just tried to rationalize her way through it,
and it came out in these very strange theories.
- Why do you think that Ayn Rand is,
maybe you can correct me, but as far as I can see,
never mentioned in the list of great thinkers in history,
or even the great thinkers of the 20th century,
or even the great female thinkers of the 20th century?
So you have somebody like Simone de Beauvoir, Hannah Arendt.
I almost never see her in the list.
If you Google those silly lists, top whatever. (chuckles)
Top thinkers of the 20th century, she's not mentioned.
Why is that?
- A lot of people just deeply dislike Rand.
They deeply dislike her ideas.
They don't think they're profound,
because they're disconnection from other ideas
and other understandings of human society.
I think where you could look at them and say,
"These ideas are very provocative,
and they're very deep,
because she's not taking anything for granted,
and she's flipping everything around
and forcing you to really think."
To a lot of other readers, to her critics,
they just look absurd.
Like, how could you even make these contentions?
And I think that because she's not without precedence
and she's not without followers,
but she doesn't knit herself
into an intellectual community
the way that these other thinkers do very naturally.
You can see who they influence.
You can see who they're in dialogue with.
I think my book was one of the first to really take Rand
and say, "She's a figure in American history.
Here's who she's connected to.
Here's who she's influenced."
And I got a lot of pushback for that.
You know, I think now people are more open to it.
But I think the people
who compile these lists really dislike her work,
and they think it's shallow
because they find her fiction overdrawn.
They find her work in the mythic register simple.
And she's also a grand systematic thinker
in an age that's over systems, you know?
She's almost, she's creating an inverse Marxism.
Marx was writing in 1848, you know,
he's not a thinker of the mid-20th century.
So I think that's part of it.
The lack of a legacy
and the dislike of what she had to say
and the feeling that she's too detached.
Her insights are not insights because they're too idealized,
rather than being rooted
in a theory of human nature that people find plausible.
- You study and write about history of ideas
in the United States
over the past hundred years, 100 plus years.
Well, how do you think ideas evolve
and gain power over the populace,
over our government, over culture?
Just looking at evolution of ideas as they dance
and challenge each other and play in public discourse,
what do you think is the mechanism by which they take hold
and have influence?
- Yeah, I mean,
there's a couple different ways I think it happens.
I really am interested in the relationship
between the thinker and then the reader
and the interpreter of the ideas,
and then the conditions
on the ground that make that idea resonate or not resonate.
And so I think a lot,
so as an intellectual historian, I'm studying ideas.
I'm always putting them in their historical context,
like what is happening
that is making these things resonate,
that is making people seek them out.
So for Rand's case, she has this credibility
because of her experience of communism,
which is one of these defining moments of the time.
And then I think the idea comes out in a sort of pure form,
and then other people rework it
and reshape it as they read it.
And I'm really interested in how people form communities
around these ideas.
So a bunch of people started calling themselves Objectivists
and getting together to read Rand's work.
That was spontaneous and ground up,
and wasn't supported by any money.
Nobody planned it.
It just happened.
Friedman's a different case
in that he joins an established tradition
of thought that's been institutionalized in universities.
So people are signing up and paying money
and getting credential to learn these ideas.
So to my mind, these are two different ways,
but really emblematic ways of how ideas spread.
So Rand, I think of as more bottom-up.
Like people encounter the idea in a book,
they're kind of blown away by it, or they imbibe it
without even realizing they're imbibing it.
And then they're like,
"Well, maybe I don't like Franklin Roosevelt so much,
or maybe I'll look another time at Barry Goldwater."
Whereas Friedman, you get the idea more top-down.
I know I'm getting the idea.
I know I'm being positioned
within a sort of elite discourse of economics.
And so I think they kind of go top-down
and bottom-up, and then they hit the events.
Friedman's ideas wouldn't have gone anywhere
without that episode of stagflation
that really made people think they proved out.
And I think Rand's ideas really caught fire
in Cold War America that's looking for a statement
of, what does it mean to be an individual?
What does it mean to live in this mass society?
Because it's also a time of great social conformity
and where people are suddenly,
they're working for large corporations,
they've been served in a large military.
The United States is stepping out onto the world stage.
Everything is bigger.
What does it mean to be an individual in that world?
And that's where Rand's ideas catch fire.
So I think a lot about that,
about how they trickle through different levels of society
and then how ideas collide with experience,
I think is critical.
- What do you think about, like,
when they actually take power in government?
So I think about ideas like Marxism
and how that evolves into the Bolshevik Revolution,
how that takes hold in its implementations.
Or you can think about Nazism and with Hitler,
where it goes from a small number
of people that get real excited about a thing,
and then like somehow just becomes viral
and takes hold in power.
And then that has its consequences.
- When I think about this
sort of historical path of communism
and the kind of logics and dynamics of communism, I mean,
in many ways it has some echoes with Rand
in that the ideology in its purest form is almost,
it's a rationalist ideology of some ways.
It's an analysis of history
and how things are supposed to be.
And I think you mentioned Hannah Arendt.
I think she has one of the most
kind of penetrating analyses
of communism which she really puts in the category of like,
it's a logical ideology.
Logic leads inexorably to its conclusions.
And then experience crops up and experience is different.
And what does a sort of cult of rationality do
when it hits experience?
Well, it tries to bend experience to its will.
And that, I think,
is really the story of communism writ large.
So the question though is, why does it catch fire?
Why does it draw people into political allegiance?
I think in the case of communism,
it's this dream of a more ethical world,
dream of equality,
dream of the powerless rising up against the powerful.
I mean, that's drawn in so many.
And then you had the whole addition of Leninism,
which gave a kind of international cast to that
and helped people think
about what are the relations between poorer
and richer countries,
and what can we expect out of them,
and what might happen,
gave a sort of a framework for thinking about that
in a time when the world was becoming more interconnected
and those differences were becoming more obvious.
Fascism, to me is unleashing more something primal,
something sort of dark and primal within people.
And it's more a permission structure to indulge in that
that is normally not there.
Those impulses are normally channeled or held down.
And it seems that when the fascist regimes come into power,
they give people permission to let those forces out.
- I think on communism,
going back to that lecture that Ayn Rand gave,
I think what rings true to me a little bit is that,
what fuels it is a kind of, maybe not resentment,
but envy towards the people that have,
the have-nots versus the haves.
And there is some degree to which Nazism has the same
of envy towards some group,
resentment towards some group.
So it's given the environment of hard times,
hard economic times,
combined with the more primal just envy
of not having and seeing somebody who has it
and just constructing a narrative around that.
That can become a real viral idea.
- Yeah, it seems like communism is more animated
by this idea of injustice.
You know, the world is unjust, it should be different.
And fascism seems like the process of scapegoating.
We've identified the source of the problem,
and it's this group,
and they need to be punished
for what they've done to the rest of us.
- There is a primal thing,
this is going back to literature,
in "1984," the Two Minutes Hate
where you can get everybody real,
like excited about like hating a thing.
And there's something primal about us humans where you,
once you're in that state of hate,
anyone can direct that hate towards anything.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- Yeah, towards any group,
towards any idea, towards anything,
because we could get caught up
in the mass hysteria of the hatred.
It's a dangerous thing.
- Yeah.
- You floated the idea, I forget where,
of pivoting for your next book
towards maybe writing about postmodernism,
which is a set of ideas almost the opposite
of Ayn Rand's philosophy.
So can you maybe explain your curiosity about,
first of all, spaces of ideas,
but maybe postmodernism?
- Yeah, I mean, I think in the broadest sense,
what I'm interested in,
kind of two dimensions that guide me
in doing intellectual history.
One is what I talked about,
like how does an idea go from a book,
an elite space, out to more popular dimensions?
Like, how does that happen?
What happens to the idea along the way?
How is it distorted or changed?
And the other is just search
for meaning in a post-Christian era or a secular era.
Like what are people coming up with?
And I think to replace that void in their religious
or spiritual lives.
I think both Rand and Friedman
offered these sort of alternatives, right?
Objectivism, this quasi-rationalist religion.
People take economics as a theory of the world that almost,
you can almost believe in it, right?
It can almost take that place.
And in both cases, how do those ideas travel?
When I think about postmodernism, you know,
it first struck me,
if you read the original postmodern thinkers,
it's really tough going.
I mean, I make my students do it and they suffer.
I think they see it's worthwhile,
but it's no fun to read Derrida, you know?
But somehow it's trickled down
into how do we go from Derrida to Tumblr?
And I sort of realized, like,
oh, this has happened with postmodernism.
It's followed the same path
that, say, from Milton Friedman's economic theory
to free to choose on YouTube.
We've had a similar path (Lex chuckles)
of high French theory down to Tumblr,
and, you know, I sexually identify as an attack helicopter
or whatever it may be.
And so that was really interesting.
And then I also thought,
"Well, at the same time,
this is clearly a structure of meaning."
And I actually think it's followed the same path
of Objectivism, which is turning into its opposite,
like distilled down and then turning into its opposite.
So if Objectivism was a group
of people who considered themselves individualists
who ended up deeply conforming to the dictates
of a charismatic leader, you know,
postmodernism started about disrupting binaries.
That was, we're going to be fluid,
we're going to go beyond the border,
we're going to disrupt the binary.
And it's devolved
in its popular forms to the reinscribing
of many different binaries, oppressor and oppressed.
You know, it's become this paradigmatic set
of glasses you put on to understand the world.
So I think it is the dynamics are very, very similar.
So I think it's something in the traffic of the idea
from its pure form to its popular form,
and then how it gets politicized
or mobilized in different ways.
And behind it all, I think,
is this human longing for meaning
and the inadequacy of the traditional ways
that need was met at this point in time.
- By the way,
that going from pure form to popular form.
I remember, this might be before the Internet,
but when I was in college reading Derrida, Foucault,
and not knowing context at all,
it was just interesting.
All right, this is,
like I'm able to read pure encapsulations of an idea
and just kind of like,
all right, well, that person believes that,
and you just kind of hold it.
But then you realize
if you actually take the pure form of that idea
and then it creates a community around it,
you realize what that actually becomes.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- And you're like, "Oh, yeah, no, I don't." (laughs)
Although I do consider myself sexually an attack helicopter.
That's it, identify sexually, yes, beautiful.
Okay.
Your process of researching for, let's say,
the biographies of Milton Friedman, Ayn Rand,
seems like an insane amount of work.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- You did incredible work there,
going to the original sources.
Can you maybe speak to that?
What is required to persevere
and to go for so many years to go so deep to the sources?
- Yeah, so, I mean, I go to the archive.
That's where I feel like I'm communing with the dead
in some ways,
you know, I'm seeing what they saw in some ways
and reading what they felt.
And I tell my doctoral students,
it's gotta be something that gets you out of bed
in the morning, because there comes a point
in your doctoral career when there's nowhere to go,
there's nowhere to be.
You gotta be getting up
because you're interested in what you want to study.
And so with Rand, it was this real sense of discovery,
like I am discovering.
I want to know about this woman.
I want to know where she fits.
And the only way to find out
is to do the research, you know?
And so, yeah, I like to go deep.
It's really interesting to me.
And I should say, in both of these cases,
I've done it in an institutional structure.
I don't know that I would do it independently.
So the first was a graduate program in history,
was at UC Berkeley.
And so I had coursework,
and then I had structures,
and I did have people to check in with and read,
but I had a great deal of latitude I'm very grateful for.
People are like,
"You wrote a dissertation on Ayn Rand at Berkeley?"
I'm like, "Yeah, hell, I did."
You know, Berkeley's like, it's a great place.
At the time I was there,
there was absolute room for free inquiry.
- Oh, can you just linger on that?
So when you said that you're doing that
and doing a dissertation on Ayn Rand,
did people get upset?
- No, I did have a friendly critic
who took it upon himself to throw at me
everything he thought the outside world would throw at me.
I think maybe 5 or 10 years earlier,
it wouldn't have been possible.
But the most important thing I had to,
the person I really had
to convince this was worth doing was myself, you know,
because I knew it was an unconventional choice for the field
and for a dissertation.
But once I convinced myself, I just said,
"Well, we're going to do this and see."
And because it was unconventional,
it ended up standing out.
But it really was the time.
I started it during Second Bush Administration,
George W. Bush, second term.
People were interested in just conservatism in general
and felt no matter where they stood
on the political spectrum, felt like, objectively,
we don't know enough about this, and this is a problem.
And so they were open to learning more,
so I really kind of caught that wave in scholarship
and caught that wave
in American culture where people wanted to know more.
- We should probably say that,
I mean, Ayn Rand is, at the very least,
as you've mentioned,
a kind of gateway to conservatism.
- Yes, I called her the gateway drug
in that people start with Rand.
They're taken by her.
In some ways, she takes the worldview of Milton Friedman
in terms of what capitalism can accomplish economically,
and then she puts it in this mythopoetic register
and she fictionalizes it.
So once people have absorbed that, they want more.
They go on to learning more of the ideas behind that vision,
or they have become true believers, they've converted,
and so then they head off to work for a politician,
to work for a think tank, to work for a party,
so absolute traffic.
Now, not everyone.
There's plenty of people who read
on Rand who don't take the politics.
It's a nice story, it's interesting,
just an episode in their life.
But for others, it's really foundational.
It really, really changes them.
So those were the people I wanted
to track very deliberately.
I wasn't trying to do in the round
everything about Ayn Rand.
I was like, Ayn Rand and the American Right, you know,
"Goddess of the Market:
Ayn Rand and the American Right" is the title.
So where did they take her,
those who took her in this political direction?
What difference did she make?
- If we return to the actual, your process.
- [Jennifer] Yeah.
- So you're showing up and reading sources,
- [Jennifer] Mhm.
- And you're like,
is it kind of like the process of discovery?
You're just kind of like taking it all in
and seeing what unifying ideas emerge
or maybe special moments that illustrate an idea emerge?
- Yeah, I mean, I know with the biography of a person,
I am already given a start and an end date
and a rough narrative of what happens.
So I have a kind of structure.
And then both with Rand and Friedman,
I started by reading their major books,
before I really read anything about them,
because I wanted my own experience
of the material to be fresh.
And I had read some Ayn Rand, but not a lot.
Similarly, I had read some Friedman, but not a lot.
So first is like, let me read the major stuff, get oriented,
and then just dive into the archive and see what's there.
Who are they talking to?
What's going on?
In Rand's case,
I was interested in her in the United States,
not her in Russia.
I didn't have the language skills to do that.
So I start her in the United States,
and I start when she publishes her first book,
and she starts getting letters,
and who is she writing to?
Who's writing to her?
And then I start to uncover this world
of kind of nascent conservatism.
And I'm kind of putting that together.
And once I have enough, I say,
"Well, that's a chapter.
I'm gonna cover that chapter,
and then there's gonna be, you know,
the book has come out,
and so now I need to start a different chapter.
What's her life like after the book has been published?"
You know, and then I look for that.
But I'm really,
although I have this very high level structure,
it's coming out of the archive,
the material I'm finding.
And if I'm not finding the material there,
I won't cover it in great detail.
Or if I've decided it's outside my ambit,
I'm not gonna go into great depth on it.
- And your trying to understand the relationships
is so fascinating.
Like reconstruct, in a dark room,
trying to reconstruct,
shine a light on relationships through reading letters.
It's interesting.
- Yeah, yeah.
I mean, correspondence is really, really helpful.
Drafts, correspondence.
And someone this famous, they have oral histories.
Other people write about them.
So you're reading all these different things
and kind of triangulating
and trying to sort of put them together,
and then think about,
how do I present this in a compelling story
and what do I need to explain?
And then also for me,
what was really helpful was that because I teach
and I am explaining the kind of broad sweep
of 20th century history,
so I know that Rand's involved in a labor action
at Warner Brothers,
but through my teaching, I realized,
oh, yes, this is a moment of labor strikes
across the country.
And so then that really changes the origin story
of "Atlas Shrugged," because she's looking at labor actions,
and she originally thinking of the book
as being called "The Strike."
So she's really responding in real time
and being inspired
by what's happening in the mid-1940s in the United States.
So then I can kind of take that,
and run with that, and figure out where to go.
- So you're super passionate about teaching.
You mentioned Milton Friedman
had a very interesting way of teaching.
So how do you think of teaching?
Teaching history, teaching history of ideas,
teaching bright young minds about the past?
- Yeah, I mean, it's great.
It's really inspiring.
The ways, the old-school kind of dominating way
in which Friedman taught would not fly
in today's university, wouldn't be permitted,
and also the students wouldn't respond to it, you know,
so I try to share my enthusiasm.
I think that's like almost the number one thing I bring
is my enthusiasm.
Like, look how neat and interesting these ideas are.
I try to keep my own views out pretty much.
I try to give the fairest possible rendition I can
of each thinker.
If I find someone really disturbing,
I might sidebar at the end of the lecture
and say this kind of, you know, I find this unsettling,
and this tells me something about myself.
But most of the time,
I'm bringing people into the biography of a great thinker,
the context of them.
And then in the lecture,
we'll literally read the work together
and we'll talk about it, and I'll ask the students,
"What are you keep finding here?
What's jumping out at you?"
Kind of breaking down the language
and really teaching them how to do deep reading.
So I feel like that is my contribution right now.
We're having trouble reading collectively.
We're having trouble paying attention collectively.
And I'm trying to cultivate their skills to doing that
and showing them how I do it.
And also modeling, like this is how I would read a text.
This is what jumps out to me when I look at, you know,
Thomas Kuhn or something like this,
and just show them that studying a history
of ideas is really fun.
I feel incredibly privileged to do it, you know,
and the other thing is, I think this is the time
for students in college figuring out who they are.
Their minds are developing and growing.
They can really handle complicated, hard ideas.
They don't always have the context behind them.
So I need to give them the hard ideas
and then show them this is kind of the context,
what's happening in the world.
But really I'm just,
I'm showing them the landscape.
I don't have time to go deep.
We have a 10-week quarter, you know,
I'm giving them a flyover,
and then I want them to know how to go deep
and know where they want to go deep.
- Do the thing that Milton Friedman did,
which is, in parallel, have a list of books.
- Yes, do their own parallel curriculum.
Exactly, exactly.
- What advice would you give in terms of reading
about ideas you agree with
and reading ideas you disagree with?
- I mean, even though I think the passion is important
for the teaching of the ideas,
like dispassion is more important for the reading
and understanding of them.
So a lot of people have said to me, like,
"I could never write about Ayn Rand.
She makes me so angry."
And I've never become,
I don't get angry reading her.
I'm like, "Oh, there you go again," you know?
Or like, "Well, that's gonna cause trouble," you know?
And so, I guess I'm approaching it with a sort of charity,
but also with this, I don't have huge expectations.
I'm not expecting to have the light shine on me.
I'm not expecting to agree.
I can be very clinical about it.
So that's what's worked for me.
It might not work for others.
And then I just try to find the humor in it.
Like, how funny is it?
These different aspects of them, you know,
like when teaching my students about Oliver Wendell Holmes,
his dad wrote a poem about him,
he called him, "The Astronaut,"
about how he came from outer space.
He seemed like he came from outer space.
I'm like, "This is his dad's view of his son.
That's how weird of a guy he was," you know?
- [Lex] (chuckles) Yeah.
- And so I try to find that,
keep alert for those funny kind of human touches,
that these are ultimately just people,
people with ideas that they spent enough time polishing up
and developing that we still want to read
about them 100 years later.
- What about the dramatic formulation of that same question?
Do you think there's some ideas that are good
and some of that are evil?
Do you think we can draw such lines
or is it more complicated,
like the old Solzhenitsyn line between good and evil
that runs through the heart of every person?
- I mean, I philosophically agree
with Solzhenitsyn for sure.
I do think some ideas pull on the good side
and some ideas pull on the bad side, like, absolutely.
And I think that's probably why people dislike Rand so much,
is they feel like she's giving license to the bad side
and she's saying, "It's okay to be selfish."
You know, they feel like she's unloosing the dark forces.
And, you know, in some cases, that may be true,
but she's also unloosing some of the light forces
in terms of reflecting on yourself and trying to be true.
But definitely there are ideas that are dangerous
to play with, and there are ideas that I think give license
to the darker sides of human nature.
But I think you can see that in the historical record.
So I think that it's possible to show that.
And obviously, there's some places, like Germany,
they think the ideas are
so dangerous they can't be allowed to circulate.
And in some contexts, that may absolutely be true.
- And then still,
even that we should take with a grain of salt,
because perhaps censorship
of an idea is more dangerous than the idea.
So all of that, that's the beautiful thing about us humans,
we are always at tension,
trying to figure out what ideas are the ones
that are going to help humanity flourish.
Pothead question.
- [Jennifer] Yeah. (chuckles)
- (chuckles) Do humans have ideas, or do ideas have us?
So where do ideas come from?
You have Milton Friedman sitting there
after Rutgers trying to figure out what he can do
about the Great Depression.
Do you ever think about this?
I sometimes think that ideas are,
aliens are actually ideas.
They're just kind of like travel through human brains
and captivate us, and we get all real excited.
Like with the monolith in "2001: A Space Odyssey,"
a monolith lands, and everybody gets excited,
and somehow this idea just gets everybody
to be on the same page,
and it reverberates through the community,
and then that results
in an implementation of some action that results
in us figuring out that that idea was actually bad
and we learn new ideas.
But it feels like the idea is running the show.
- Yeah, I mean, I think in a lot of cases,
I think it's true.
You know, Keynes has this famous quote like, you know,
"Most men are slaves of some defunct economist," you know?
- (chuckles) That's funny, that's funny.
- So I do think that it's really hard
to have an original thought.
You know, we are social creatures.
We encounter the same situations again and again.
And so it's really hard.
You're born into these traditions of thinking
and being and knowing,
and most people are never going to question them,
and most people are never going to become aware of them.
So again, that's some of the work of what I do
as an intellectual historian is like, let's become aware.
Let's realize that you're carrying a map
that's orienting you to the world in a certain way.
And so I think you have to work really,
really hard to have an original idea.
And even then, it's not a completely original idea.
It's a reworking
and a reassembling of ideas others have had.
So I definitely think it's possible to create autonomy
in the realm of ideas
and to be an autonomous consumer of ideas.
But I think on balance, most people are not,
and that's fine.
They want to have experiences,
they want to do other things with their life, you know.
- Well, Jennifer,
thank you so much for this journey through ideas today.
And thank you so much for your incredible work.
It was really fun and fascinating to talk with you today.
Thank you.
- Thank you.
- Thank you for listening
to this conversation with Jennifer Burns.
And now let me try to reflect on
and articulate some things I've been thinking about.
If you'd like to submit questions
or topics that I can comment on in this way here
at the end of episodes, go to lexfridman.com/ama
or contact me for whatever other reason
at lexfridman.com/contact.
Please allow me to say a few words
about my interview with the President of Ukraine,
Volodymyr Zelenskyy.
Now that a few days have passed
and I've had the chance to think
about the conversation itself, the response,
future upcoming conversations,
and what it all means for the war in Ukraine,
for global geopolitics,
and for us humans in general,
I've gotten a lot of heartfelt,
positive words from all sides,
including, at least so far,
literally everybody who knows me personally inside Ukraine,
which includes a lot of soldiers
and many high-profile figures,
some who are supportive of the president,
and some who are critical of him.
Literally all private communication
has been positive and supportive.
This is usually not the case with me.
Friends usually will write to me to criticize
and to disagree.
That's the whole point of friendship,
to argue and have fun doing it.
There was none of that here, at least so far.
So thank you for your support and kind words.
It means the world.
The most common message was please keep pushing for peace.
I will.
But online, on the interwebs,
I saw a lot of attacks,
sometimes from swarms of online accounts,
which of course makes me suspicious
about the origin of those attacks.
One of my friends in Ukraine,
who by the way thinks the attacks are all propped up
by Ukrainian bot farms, said,
"There's no need to say anything extra.
Let the interview stand on its own.
Just keep focused on the mission of pushing for peace."
Basically, he's a Ukrainian version of my other friend,
Joe Rogan, who to this day says,
"Don't read the comments."
This is generally good advice,
and I try to follow it,
but I'm also a human being.
I wear my heart on my sleeve.
And this interview, this war for me is deeply personal,
and the level of vitriol, misrepresentation,
and lies about the conversation
and about me personally was particularly intense
and disingenuous.
So I thought I would use this opportunity
to say a few words, just speak a bit more
about how I approach this conversation
with President Zelenskyy and conversations in general.
This interview is something I poured my heart
and soul into, preparing a lot.
I've described parts of the preparation process I follow
in the outro to the Zelenskyy conversation.
But in general, let me say that I've read a lot,
listened to a lot,
and had a lot of private conversations
with people on the ground.
I have many flaws, but being unprepared
for this conversation is not one of them.
Two low-effort attacks got to me a bit,
if I'm being honest,
though I am learning to take it all in stride.
First attack is that I'm unprepared, uninformed, or naive.
I don't give a damn about the trolls,
but I want people who listen to me, who support me,
who care about my words,
to know that this is not the case.
It never will be the case for future conversations,
especially ones of this importance.
I work extremely hard to prepare.
Second, low-effort attack that got to me a bit
is that I'm a shill for Zelenskyy
or a shill for Putin.
Both accusations were hurled readily
and freely by the online mob of all persuasions,
by the left and the right in the United States and Europe,
by the pro and the anti-Zelenskyy people in Ukraine
or of Ukrainian origins,
and by the pro and anti-Putin people in Russia
or of Russian origins.
As I've said over and over,
this is not the case,
and will never be the case.
I'm a shill for no one.
More than that, I just simply refuse to be caught
in any one single echo chamber.
It's an ongoing battle, of course,
because social media algorithms
and the various dogmatic groups
and tribes out there want to pull you in
to their warm embrace of belonging,
and humans want to belong.
But the cost of the path I have chosen
is that I will never belong to any one group.
In the end, like many of us must,
I walk alone.
And I try to do my best to do what is right
to my independent heart and mind,
not what is popular with any one group.
My goals for this conversation were two-fold.
First, give a large platform
to President Zelenskyy to explain his perspective on the war
and to do so in a way that brings out the best in who he is
as a leader and human being.
Second goal was to push for peace
and to give him every opportunity possible
to signal that he is ready to make peace
and to provide his vision for what that might look like.
And just to be clear,
by peace I mean long-lasting peace
that minimizes suffering of people in the region
and maximizes the flourishing of humanity
in the coming decades.
The war in Ukraine has led to over 1 million casualties
and growing every single day.
For some people torn apart by loss,
tormented and forced into a state of anger and hate,
peace is a dirty word.
To them, nothing less than justice must be accepted.
I hear this pain.
I've seen the bodies and the suffering.
It's true, peace will not bring back your loved ones,
but it will prevent further slaughter of more people,
each of whom are someone else's loved ones.
So again, the second goal of this conversation
was to push for this kind of peace.
So how did I approach it?
Every conversation is its own puzzle,
so let me try to explain my approach for this one.
As I've said, I read and listened to a lot of material
since February 24, 2022.
There would be many weeks
over the past three years where I would spend every day,
over eight hours a day of focused reading and research.
There were several rabbit holes
that I consistently returned to and researched,
but the most important line of inquiry
was always peace talks,
not just in this war,
but in other wars in modern history.
For this specific war,
as part of the background prep,
I would take notes
on every single perspective I could find
on every single major diplomatic meeting
and negotiation that happened
in Ukraine-Russia relations since 1991.
There is a lot of material to go through,
and there are a lot of perspectives
even on the very 2019 meeting
that President Zelenskyy spoke about in this podcast.
Just as a small but important example,
Andriy Bohdan was interviewed twice by Dmytro Gordon
and gave a deep inside look
of the administration of President Zelenskyy,
including that very 2019 meeting.
The two interviews are seven and a half hours by the way,
and from my interviewer perspective
are a masterclass of interviewing.
Andriy Bohdan worked directly with President Zelenskyy
as the head of the Office of the President of Ukraine.
He was there for the 2019 face-to-face meeting
between Volodymyr Zelenskyy
and Vladimir Putin at the Paris summit,
along with French President Emmanuel Macron
and German Chancellor Angela Merkel.
This was part of the Normandy format peace talks.
In those two interviews,
Andriy Bohdan gave a very different perspective
on that 2019 meeting than did President Zelenskyy
to me in our conversation,
the perspective being that the failure
to negotiate a ceasefire
and peace was not a simple one-sided story.
I don't think this is the right time
for me to dive into that data point and be critical.
I'm not interested in being critical
for the sake of criticism.
I am interested once again in productive conversations,
critical or otherwise, that push towards peace,
the kind I described earlier.
This is merely an example
of a data point I was collecting in my brain.
There are many, many others,
but all of it taken together made it clear to me,
and I still believe this,
that it is indeed very difficult
but possible to negotiate long-lasting peace
with Vladimir Putin.
It is certainly true that Ukraine is best positioned
to negotiate from a place of strength.
After the invasion of February 24th, 2022,
I believe there were three chances
where peace was most achievable.
First chance was March and April of 2022
with a successful defense of the North.
Second chance was the fall of 2022
with the successful counteroffensive
in Kherson and Kharkiv.
The third chance is now.
As he has stated multiple times publicly,
Donald Trump is very interested in making peace.
It is likely that the US financial support
for this war will continue to dwindle.
So the leverage and the timing for peace negotiation is now.
There is unlikely to be another chance like this
for a long time.
Just to zoom out on the conversation piece of this,
I interviewed Donald Trump and may do so again.
I interviewed Volodymyr Zelenskyy and may do so again.
And it seems likely that I will interview Vladimir Putin
in Russia, in the Kremlin.
I understand the risks, and I accept them.
The risks for me are not important.
I'm not important.
I merely want to do my small part in pushing for peace
in a moment in history when there's a real chance
for that peace to actually be achieved.
I may be speaking too long, I'm sorry,
but I can probably speak for many more hours,
so this is in fact me trying to be brief.
So again, my two goals were to bring out the best
in President Zelenskyy as a leader and a human being,
and to give him every opportunity possible
to signal that he is ready to make peace
and to lay out his vision
for what that peace might look like.
Like I said, step one through ten is prepare well.
I did, but step eleven is the actual conversation.
There the specific psychological and personality quirks
and qualities of the guest matter a lot.
My job is to try to cut through the bullshit walls
we put up as human beings
and reveal, directly or indirectly,
who the person truly is and how they think.
With Zelenskyy, he is a deeply empathic
and emotional human being who personally feels the suffering
of the people of Ukraine in this war.
This is a strength and perhaps also a weakness.
But it is an important part
of the reason why I said many times
that he is a truly historic figure.
Very few leaders in recent history
would be able to pull off what he did
to stay in Kyiv, to unite the country,
to convince the West
to join the war effort to the degree they did.
He is also a showman,
to borrow the title of the biography I recommended,
a man with many layers of humor and wit,
but also ego and temper,
sometimes fully self-aware
and sometimes losing himself
in the emotional rollercoaster of a painful memory
or a turn of phrase that he can use as a springboard
for an angry soliloquy.
Add to this the fact that we didn't agree to anything,
what we will talk about,
or how long we will talk about it.
The interview could have easily been five minutes
or three hours.
So I had to quickly gain his trust enough to open up
and stay for a long form conversation,
but push him enough to reveal the complexities
of his thought process and his situation.
This is where humor and camaraderie was essential,
and I would return to it often,
though it was very difficult given the stakes,
the heaviness, the seriousness of the topic of the war.
So in this case, the approach I followed
for this conversation is constant nudges
and questions about peace,
often using almost childlike statements or questions.
I generally like these kinds of questions.
On the surface, they may seem naive, but they're not.
They are often profound in their simplicity,
like a lot of questions that children ask.
Remember, it was a child who pointed out
that the emperor was not wearing any clothes.
I like the simplicity, the purity,
the boldness of such questions
to cut through the bullshit to the truth.
And that truth is that hundreds of thousands of people
died in this war and are dying every day.
And all the other problems,
from corruption to suspended elections to censorship,
cannot be solved until peace is made.
I give the president every single chance
to signal willingness to negotiate,
knowing that both Trump
and Putin will listen to this conversation.
I don't think he took it,
and instead chose to speak very crude words
towards Vladimir Putin.
This is fully understandable,
but not directly productive to negotiation.
To clarify, I have hosted many conversations
that were intensely critical of Vladimir Putin,
from Serhii Plokhy to Stephen Kotkin,
but this conversation is with a world leader
speaking about another world leader
during a historic opportunity for peace.
Crude words of disrespect, while powerful,
may harm negotiations.
Peacemaking in this situation requires compromise
in order to avoid further death and suffering.
And I believe it requires treating the other leader
with the seriousness you expect him to treat you with.
This is what I was pushing for.
All that, while also putting my ego aside
and letting the president shine,
which is necessary to accomplish both goals one
and two that I mentioned previously.
This is also why I wanted the president
to speak about Elon and Trump,
to extend the olive branch
for further avenues of peacemaking.
This is not about politics.
It is once again simply about peace.
Now, all of this, my words, my attempts,
were taken out of context
and used to attack me by some online mobs.
As an example, President Zelenskyy said in a mocking tone
that he thinks that Vladimir Putin is simply irritated
by people who are alive in Ukraine.
And I answered, quote,
"If you believe this,
it will be very difficult to negotiate.
If you think that the president
of a country is completely crazy,
it is really hard to come to an agreement with him.
You have to look at him
as a serious person who loves his country
and loves the people in his country,
and he conducts, yes,
destructive military actions."
The president interrupted me at this point and said,
"Who are you talking about now?
Who loves this country?"
And I said, "Putin.
Do you think he doesn't love his country?"
And the president answered, "No."
Again, this is not a podcast conversation
with a historian or activist,
and I somehow out of nowhere, just for fun,
waxed poetic about Putin's,
or Zelenskyy's, or Trump's love of nation.
It is a conversation with a world leader
discussing the opportunity
to negotiate peace when a large number
of people are dying every single day.
Even if the heart boils over with hate,
leadership now requires sitting at the negotiation table
and compromising.
This may be painful, but it is necessary.
There are a few other places
in the conversation
where some online mobs took my words out of context
and used them to call me naive
and to call for more war,
saying peace is impossible with a man
who they claim is the second coming of Hitler.
My friends, if you make such attacks on this conversation,
it is in fact you who are naive
and ignorant of the facts of history and geopolitics.
Peace must be made now in order for death
and suffering to stop,
in order for Ukraine to have a chance to flourish,
and in order for the drums of a global war to stop beating,
a global war that would cripple humanity.
This was my goal, once again,
to push for peace,
and I will continue this effort to the best of my ability.
Thank you.
I love you all.