the following is a conversation with jim keller his second time in the podcast
jim is a legendary microprocessor
architect and is widely seen as one of the greatest engineering minds of the computing age
in a peculiar twist of space-time in our simulation
jim is also a brother-in-law of jordan peterson
we talk about this and about computing artificial intelligence
consciousness
and life
quick mention of our sponsors athletic greens all-in-one nutrition drink brooklyn and sheetz expressvpn
and belcampo
grass-fed meat click the sponsor links to get a discount and to support this podcast
as a side note let me say that jim is someone who on a personal level
inspired me to be myself
there was something in his words on and off the mic
or perhaps that he even paid attention to me at all that almost told me
you're all right kid
a kind of pat on the back that can
make the difference
between a mind that flourishes
and a mind that is broken down by the cynicism of the world
so i guess that's just my brief few words of thank you to jim
and in general
gratitude for the people who have given me a chance on this podcast
in my work and in life
if you enjoy this thing subscribe on youtube review on apple podcast follow on spotify
support on patreon or connect with me on twitter alex friedman
and now here's my conversation
with jim keller
what's the value and effectiveness of theory versus engineering this dichotomy in building
good software or hardware systems
well it's good designs both
i guess that's pretty obvious
but engineering do you mean you know reduction of practice of known methods
and then science is the pursuit of discovering things that people don't understand
or solving unknown problems
definitions are interesting here but i was thinking more in theory constructing models
that kind of generalize about how things work
and engineering is
like actually
building stuff the pragmatic like okay we have these nice models
but how do we actually get things to work maybe
economics
is a nice example
like economists have all these models of how the economy works and how different
policies will have an effect
but then there's the actual
okay let's call it engineering of like actually deploying the policies
so computer design is almost all engineering
and reduction of practice is known message now
because of the complexity of the computers we built
you know you could think you're well we'll just go write some code
and then we'll verify
it and we'll put it together
and then you find out that the combination of all that stuff is complicated
and then you have to be inventive to figure out how to do it
right so that's that's definitely happens a lot
and then
every so often some big idea happens
but it might be one person
and that idea is in what in the space of engineering or is it
in the space
well i'll give you an example
so one of the limits
of computer
performance
is branch predictions
so
and there's there's a whole bunch of ideas about how good you could predict the branch
and people said there's a limit to it it's an asthmatic
curve
and somebody came up with a better way to do branch prediction
it was a lot better
and he published a paper on it and every computer in the world now uses it
and it was one idea
so the the engineers who build branch prediction hardware
were happy to drop the one kind of training array and put it in another one
so it was it was a real idea
and branch prediction is is one of the key problems underlying
all of sort of the lowest level of software it boils down to branch prediction
boils down to uncertainty
computers
are limited by you know single thread computers limited by two things
the
predictability of the path of the branches and the predictability of the locality
of data
so we have predictors that now predict both of those pretty well
yeah so memory is you know a couple hundred cycles away
local cache is couple cycles away
when you're executing fast virtually all the data has to be in the local cache
so a simple program says
you know add one to every element in array
it's really easy to see what the stream of data will be
but you might have a more complicated
program that you know says get a get an element of this array look at something
make a decision
go get another element it's kind of random
and you can think that's really unpredictable
and then you make this big predictor
that looks at this kind of pattern and you realize
well if you get this data in this data then you probably want that one
and if you get this one and this one and this one you probably
want that one and is that theory or is that engineering
like the paper that was written was it well it was asymptotic
kind of kind of discussion or is it more like here's a hack that works well
um it's a little bit of both
like there's information theory in it i think somewhere okay
so
that's actually trying to prove yeah but once once you know the method
implementing it is an engineering problem
now there's a flip side of this which is
in a big design team what percentage of people think their
their their
their their plan or their life's work is engineering versus design inventing things
so lots of companies will reward you for filing patents
yes
some many big companies
get stuck because to get promoted
you have to come up with something
new
and then what happens is everybody's trying to do some random new thing 99
which doesn't matter
and the basics get neglected
and or
they get to there's a dichotomy
they think like the cell library
and the basic cad tools
you know or basic
you know software validation
methods
that's simple stuff you know they want to work on the exciting stuff
and then they they spend lots of time trying to figure out how to patent something
and that's mostly useless but the breakthroughs are on the simple stuff
no no you no you have to do the simple stuff really well
if you're brilliant building a building out of bricks
you want great bricks
so you go to two places to sell bricks so one guy says
yeah they're over there in an ugly pile and the other guy is like
lovingly
tells you about the 50
kinds
of bricks
and how hard
they are and how beautiful
they are and
how square they are and you know which one you can buy bricks from
which is going to make a better house
so you're talking about the craftsman the person who understands
bricks who loves bricks who loves their varieties that's a good word
you know good engineering
is great craftsmanship
and when you start
thinking engineering is about invention
and set up a system that rewards invention the craftsmanship gets neglected
okay so maybe one perspective is the theory the science
over emphasizes invention
and engineering emphasizes craftsmanship and therefore
like
so if you it doesn't matter what you do in theory well everybody
knows like read the tech rags they're always talking about some breakthrough
or intervention
innovation and everybody thinks that's the most important thing
but the number of innovative ideas is actually relatively low
we need them right and innovation creates a whole new opportunity
like when when some guy invented the internet
right
like that was a big thing
the million people that wrote software against that were mostly doing engineering software writing
so the elaboration of that idea was huge
i don't know if you know brendan ike he wrote javascript
in 10 days and that's an interesting story it makes me wonder
and it was you know famously
for many years considered to be a pretty crappy programming language
still is perhaps it's been improving sort of consistently
but the interesting thing about that guy is
you know he doesn't get any awards
you don't get a nobel prize or a field medal or
a crappy
piece of you know that software code
that is currently the number one programming language in the world that runs
now is cons
increasingly running the backhand of the internet what does he end up does he know why
everybody uses it
like that would be an interesting thing was it
the right thing at the right time because like when stuff like javascript
came out like there's a move from you know writing c programs and c plus plus
to let's call what they call managed code frameworks
where
you write simple code it might be interpreted it has lots of libraries
productivity is high and you don't have to be an expert
so you know java was supposed to solve all the world's problems it was complicated
javascript came out you know after a bunch of other scripting languages
i'm not an expert on it but
yeah but was it the right thing at the right time
or was there something
you know clever because he wasn't the only one
there's a few elements
maybe if he figured out what it was
no then he'd get a prize
like that destructive theory yeah
you know babies probably he hasn't defined this or he this needs a good promoter
well i think there was a bunch of blog posts written about it which is like
wrong is right which is
like doing the crappy thing fast
just like hacking together the thing that answers some of the needs
and then iterating
over time listening to developers
like listening to people who actually use the thing
this is something you can do more in software
but the right time like you have to sense you have to have a good instinct
of when is the right time for the right tool
and make it super simple
and just
get it out there the problem is this is true with hardware
this is less true with software is this backward compatibility
that just drags behind you as
you know
as you try to fix all the mistakes of the past but the the timing
was good there's something about that it wasn't accidental
you have to like
give yourself over to the
you have to have this like broad sense of what's needed now
and both scientifically and like the community and just like this it was obvious that
there was no the interesting thing about javascript
is everything that ran in the browser at the time like java and
and i think other like scheme other programming languages
they were all
in a separate external container
and then javascript
was literally just injected
into the web page it was the dumbest possible thing
running in the same thread as everything else
and like
it was inserted as a comment so javascript code is inserted as a comment
in the html code and it was i mean it's there's
it's either genius or super dumb but it's like right so it has no apparatus
for like a virtual machine and container
it just executed
in the framework the program is already running and it was that's cool and then
because something about that accessibility
the ease of its use
resulted in then developers
innovating on how to actually use it i mean i don't even know what to
make of that but
it does seem to echo across different software
like stories of different software php has the same story really crappy language
they just took over the world
i always have a joke that the random length instructions
that variable length instructions that's always one
even though they're obviously worse
like nobody knows why x86 is arguably the worst architecture
you know on the planet is one of the most popular ones
well i mean isn't isn't that also the story of risk versus
i mean is that simplicity
there's something about simplicity that
us in this evolutionary process
is valued
if it's simple
it's
gets it spreads faster it seems like
yeah or is that not always true that's always true
yeah it could be simple is good but too simple is bad
so why did risk win you think so far did risk win
in the long arc of history
maybe
we don't know
so who who's going to win
what what's risk what's cisco who's going to win in that space
in these instruction
sets
a ice offers going to win but
they'll be little computers that run little programs like normal all over the place
but but we're we're going through another transformation
so
but you think instruction sets underneath it all will change
yeah they evolve slowly
they don't matter very much
they don't matter very much okay i mean the limits of performance
are
you know predictability of instructions and data i mean that's the big thing
and then
the usability of it is some you know
quality of design quality of tools
availability
like right now
x86 is proprietary
with intel and amd but they can change it any way they want independently
right arm is proprietary
to arm and they won't let anybody else change it so it's like a sole point
and risk 5 is open source so anybody can change it which is super cool
but that also
might mean
it gets changed in too many random
ways
that there's no common
sub subset of it that people can use
do you like open
or do you like clothes
like if you were to bet all your money
on one or the other risk
five versus
no idea
it's case dependent well x86
oddly enough when intel first started developing it they licensed
like seven people
so it was the open architecture
and then they move faster than others and also bought one or two of them
but there were seven different people making x86
because at the time there was
and z80s and you know 8086
and you could argue everybody thought z80 was the better instruction set but that was propriety
proprietary to one place oh and the 6800
so there's like five or four or five different microprocessors
intel went open
got the market
share because people felt like they had multiple
sources
from it and then over time it narrowed down the two
players
so why you as a historian
well why did intel win for so long
with the
with their processors
i mean they were great
their process development was great
oh so it's
just looking back to javascript and brand nike is
microsoft
and netscape and all these internet browsers
microsoft won the browser game because they aggressively stole other people's ideas
like right after they did it you know i i don't know
if intel
was stealing
other people's ideas they started making a
just good way they started making rams
random access memories
and then
at the time when the japanese manufacturers came up
you know they were getting out competed on that and they pivoted the microprocessors
and they made the first you know integrated microprocessor
programs
or something who was behind that pivot that's a hell of a pivot andy grove
and he was great
that's a hell of a pivot and then they led
semiconductor
industry
like they were just a little company ibm
all kinds of big companies had both loads of money
and they out innovated everybody
auto innovated okay yeah yeah so it's not like marketing it's not yeah
their processor designs were pretty good
um i think the
you know core 2 was probably the first one i thought was great
it was a really fast processor and then haswell was great
what makes a great processor
in that delay oh if you just look at it's performance
versus
everybody
else
it's you know the size of it the you know usability
of it so it's not specific
some kind of element that makes it beautiful it's just like literally just raw performance
is that how you think about processors it's just like raw performance
of course
it's like a horse race the fastest one wins now you don't care how [laughter]
just as long as it was well there's the fastest in the environment
like
right you know for years you made the fastest
one you could and then people started to have power limits
so then you made the fastest at the right power point
and then and then when we started doing multiprocessors
like
if you could scale your processors
more than the other guy you could be 10
faster on like a single thread but you have more threads
so there's lots of variability
and then
arm
really explored
like you know they have the a series and the r series and the m series
like a family of processors for all these different design points from like unbelievably
small and simple
and so then when you're doing the design
it's sort of like this big palette of cpus
like they're the only ones with a credible you know top to bottom palette and
what do you mean incredible
top to bottom well there's people who make microcontrollers
that are small but they don't have a fast one there's people make fast processors
but don't have a little a medium one or a small one
is it hard to do
that full palette
that's that seems like a it's a lot of different
so what's the difference in
the arm folks and intel
in terms of the way they're approaching this problem well intel
almost all their processor designs were you know very custom
high end you know for the last 15 20 years the fastest force possible yeah
in one horseshoe
yeah and then architecture they're really good but the company itself was
fairly insular
to what's going on in the industry with cad tools and stuff
and there's this debate about custom design versus synthesis
and how do you approach that
i'd say intel was slow on the getting to synthesize
processors
arm
came in from the bottom and they generated ip which went to all kinds of customers
so they had very little say how the customer implemented their ip
so arm is super friendly to the synthesis ip environment
whereas intel said we're going to make this great
client chip server chip with our own cad tools with our own process
with our own
you know other supporting
ip and everything only works with our stuff
so is that
is arm winning the mobile platform space in terms of processors and so
in that and
what you're describing
is why they're winning well they had lots of people doing lots of different experiments
so they controlled the processor architecture and ip
but they let people put in lots of different chips
and there was a lot of variability
in what happened there
whereas
intel when they made their mobile
their foray
into mobile they had one team doing one
part
right so it wasn't 10 experiments and then their mindset was pc mindset microsoft software mindset
and that brought a whole bunch of things along that
the mobile world embedded world don't do do you think it was possible for intel
to pivot hard and win the mobile
market
that's a hell of a difficult thing to do right for a huge company
to just pivot
i mean it's so interesting to because we'll talk about your current work it's like
it's clear that pcs were dominating for several decades like desktop computers and then mobile
it's unclear
it's a leadership question
like like apple under steve jobs when he came back they pivoted multiple times
you know they built ipads and itunes
and phones and tablets
and great macs like like who knew computers should be made out of aluminum
nobody knew that
that they're great it's
super fun that was steve
yeah steve jobs like they pivoted
multiple
times
and you know the old intel they they did that multiple times
they made drams and processors and processes and
i got to ask this what was it like working with steve
jobs
i didn't work with him
did you interact with him twice
i said hi to him twice in the cafeteria
what did he say hi he said hey fellas
he was friendly
he was wandering around and with somebody he couldn't find the table because the cafeteria was
was packed
and i gave my table
but i worked for mike colbert who talked to
like mike was the unofficial
cto of apple
and a brilliant guy and he worked for steve for 25 years maybe more
and he talked to steve multiple times a day
and
he was one of the people who could
put up with steve's let's say brilliance
and intensity
and and steve really liked him and steve trusted mike to translate
the he thought up
into engineering
products at work and then mike ran a group called platform architecture
and i was in that group
so many times i'd be sitting with mike and the phone would ring
it'd be steve
and mike would hold the phone like this because steve
would be yelling about something
or other
yeah
and he would translate it and he translated
and then he would say
steve wants us to do this
so
was steve a good engineer or no i don't know
he was a great idea guy idea person he's a really good selector for talent
yeah so that seems to be one of the key elements of leadership right
and then he was a really good first principals
guy like
like somebody say something couldn't be done and he would just think
that's obviously wrong
right but you know
maybe it's hard to do maybe it's expensive
to do maybe we need different people
you know there's like a whole bunch of you know if you want to do something
hard
you know maybe it takes time maybe you have to iterate
there's a whole bunch of things you could think about
but saying it can't be done is stupid
how would you compare
so it seems like elon musk is more engineering
centric
but it's also i think he considers himself a designer
too he has a design mind
steve jobs
feels like he is much more idea space design space versus engineering
yeah just make it happen
like the world should be this way
just figure it out but but he used computers
you know he had computer people talk to him all the time
like mike was a really good computer guy he knew what computers
could do computer meaning computer hardware like
hardware software
all of pieces the whole thing and then he would
you know have an idea about what could we do with this next
that was grounded in reality it wasn't like he was you know just
finger painting on the wall and wishing somebody would interpret
it like
so he had this interesting
connection
because
no he wasn't a computer architect or a designer
but he had an intuition from the computers we had to what could happen
and
essentially you say intuition because it seems like he was pissing off a lot of engineers
in his intuition about what canada can't be done those like the
what is all these stories
about like floppy
disks
and all that kind of stuff like yeah so
in in steve the first round like he'd go into a lab
and look at what's going on and hate it and and
fire people or or ask somebody in the elevator what they're doing for apple
and you know not be happy
when he came back my impression was
is he surrounded himself with this relatively
small group of people yes and didn't really interact
outside of that as much
and then the joke was you'd see like somebody moving a prototype
through the
quad with a with a black blanket over it
and that was because it was secret
you know partly
from steve
because they didn't want
steve
to see it until it was ready
yeah the dynamic with johnny ive and steve
is interesting it's like you don't wanna
he ruins as many ideas as he generates yeah
yeah it's a dangerous kind of
line to walk
if you have a lot of ideas like
like gordon bell was famous for ideas
right and it wasn't that the percentage of good ideas was way higher than anybody else
it was he had so many ideas
and and he was also good at talking people about it and and getting the filters
right
and you know seeing through stuff
whereas elon was like hey i want to build rockets so
steve would hire a bunch of rocket guys and elon would go read rocket manuals
so ian is a better engineer a sense like or like more
like a love and passion for the manuals yeah and the details the details
the craftsmanship too right well i guess you had craftsmanship too but of a different kind
what do you make of the
just the standard
for just a little longer
what do you make of like the anger
and the passion
and all that the the firing
and the
mood swings
and
the madness the
um you know being emotional
and all that that's
steve and i i guess elon
too so what is that a
is that a bugger feature
it's a feature
so there's a graph which is
y-axis productivity yeah x-axis at zero it's chaos
yeah and infinity is complete order yeah right so as you go from
the you know the origin
as you improve order you improve productivity
yeah and at some point productivity peaks
and then it goes back down again yeah too much order nothing can happen yes
but the question is is
how close to the chaos
is that no no no here's the thing
is once you start moving the directional
order the force vector to drive you towards order
is unstoppable
oh this is the same every organization
will
move to the place where their productivity is stymied by order so you need
so the question is who's the counter force
like because it also feels really good as you get more organized
then productivity goes up the organization
feels it they orient it towards it right to hire more people
they get more guys who can run process you get bigger
right and then inevitably inevitably
the organization gets captured by the bureaucracy that manages all the processes
right and then humans really like that and so if you just walk into a room
and say guys
love what you're doing
but i need you to have less order
if you don't have some force behind that nothing will happen
i i can't tell you on how many levels that's profound so
so that's why i'd say it's a feature
now
could you be nicer about it
i don't know i don't know any good examples of being nicer about it
well
the funny
thing is to get stuff
done you need people who can manage
stuff
and manage
people because humans
are complicated
they need lots of care and feeding
and you need to tell them
they look nice and they're doing good stuff and pat them on the back
right
i don't know
do you tell me is that is that needed
humans need that i had a friend he started to manage the group and he said
i figured it out you have to praise them before they do anything
i was waiting until they were done
and they're always mad at me now i tell them what a great job they're doing
while they're doing it
but then you get stuck
in that trap
because then when they're not doing something how do you confront
these people
i think a lot of people that had trauma in their childhood who disagree
with you successful
people that you just first do the rough stuff and then be nice later
i don't know
okay but
you know nice engineering
companies
are full of adults
who had all kinds of range of childhoods
you know most people had okay childhoods
well i don't know if and lots of people only work for praise
which is weird you mean like everybody
i'm not that interested in this but well you you're you're probably looking for somebody's approval
um
even still
yeah maybe i should think about that
maybe somebody who's no longer with this kind of thing
i don't know
i used to call it my dad
and tell him what i was doing
he was he was
very excited
about engineering
and stuff
you got his approval
yeah a lot
i was lucky
like he he decided i was
smart and unusual as a kid and that was okay when i was really young
so when i like did poorly in school i was dyslexic
i didn't read until i was third or fourth grade and
they didn't care my parents were like
oh he'll be fine
so that was funny that was cool is he still with us you miss him
sure yeah he had parkinson's and then cancer his last 10 years were tough
and i killed him killing a man like that's hard the mind well it's pretty good
um parkinson's causes slow dementia and the chemotherapy i think accelerated it
but it was like hallucinogenic dementia so he was clever and funny and interesting and
was it was pretty unusual
do you remember conversations
of course from that time like where do you have fond memories
of the guy yeah oh yeah anything come to mind
a friend
told me one time i could draw
a computer
on the whiteboard
faster
than anybody
you'd ever met
and i said you should meet my dad
like when i was a kid he'd come home and say
i was driving
by this bridge
and i was thinking
about it and he pulled out a piece of paper
and he'd draw
the whole
bridge
he was a mechanical engineer
yeah
and he would just draw
the whole thing
and then he would
tell me about
it and
tell me how
you would have changed
it
and he had this you know idea that he could understand and conceive anything
and i i just grew up with that so that was natural
so if
you know
like
when i interview
people i ask them to draw a picture of something
they did on a whiteboard
and it's really interesting like some people draw a little box
you know and then they'll say and then this talks to this and
yeah i'd be like this is frustrating
and i had this other guy come in one time he says
well
i designed
a floating
point in this chip
but i'd really
like to tell you how the whole thing
works
and then tell you how the floating
point works inside of it do you mind if i do that he covered
two whiteboards
yeah like 30 minutes
and i hired him like yeah he was great
this is craftsman i mean that's the craftsmanship to that yeah but also
the the mental agility to understand the whole thing
right put the pieces in contacts
like you know real view of the balance of how the design worked
because
if you don't understand
it properly
when you start to draw it you'll
fill up half the white board with like a little piece of it and you know
like
your ability to lay it out in an understandable
way it takes a lot of understanding
so
and be able to zoom into the detail and then zoom out to the zoom
really fast
what about the impossible thing you see your dad
believed that you could do anything
that's a weird feature for a craftsman
yeah it seems that that
echoes in your own behavior
like that's that's the well it's not that anybody can do anything right now
right it's
that if you work
at it you can get better
at it
and there might not be a limit
and they did funny things like
like he always wanted to play
piano
so at the end of his life he started playing the piano
when he had parkinson's
and he was terrible
but he thought if he really worked
out in this life maybe
the next life he'd be better at it
he might be onto something yeah
he enjoyed doing it yeah so that's pretty funny
do you think the perfect is the enemy of the good in hardware and software engineering
it's like we were talking about javascript a little bit and the messiness of the 10-day
building process
yeah it's you know creative tension right
the creative tension is you have two different ideas that you can't do both
right right and then but the fact that you want to do both
causes you to go try to solve that problem that's the creative part
so if you're building computers
like some people say we have the schedule
and anything that doesn't fit in the schedule we can't do
right so they throw out the perfect because they have a schedule
i hate that
then there's other people who say we need to get this perfectly right
and no matter what you know more people more money right
and there's a really clear idea about what you want some people are going to articulate
in it right
so let's call that the perfect yeah yeah
all right but that's also terrible because they never ship anything you never hit any goals
so now you have that now you have your framework
yes you can't
throw
out stuff because you can't get it done today because maybe you get it done tomorrow
or the next project
right you can't
so you have to
i work with a guy that i really like working with
but he over filters
his ideas
over filters
he'd start thinking about something
and as soon as he figure out what's wrong with it you'd throw it out
and then
i start thinking about it like you know you come up with an idea
and then you find out what's wrong with it
and then you give it a little time to set because sometimes
you know you figure out how to tweak it or maybe that idea helps some other
idea
so idea generation is really funny
so you have to give your ideas space like spaciousness of mind is key
but you also have to execute programs and get  done
and then it turns
out
computer
engineering
is fun because it takes you know 100
people to build a computer
200 to 300 whatever the number is and people are so variable about
you know temperament and you know skill sets and stuff
that you know in a big organization
you find that
the people who love the perfect ideas
and the people that want to get stuff done yesterday
and
people like to come up with ideas and people like to
let's say shoot down ideas and it takes the whole
it takes a large group of people
some are good at generating ideas some are good at filtering ideas and then all
in that giant mess you somehow
i guess the goal is for that giant mess of people to
find the perfect path through the attention the creative tension
but like how do you know when
you said there's some people good at articulating
what perfect looks like what a good design is like if you're sitting in a
in a room
and you have a set of ideas about like how to design
a better processor how do you know
this is this is something
special here this is a good idea
let's try this
so have you ever brainstormed
idea with a couple people that were really smart
and you kind of go into it and you you don't quite understand
it and you're working on it
and then you start you know talking about it putting it on the whiteboard
maybe it takes days or weeks
and then your brain start to kind of synchronize it's really weird
and like you start to see what each other is thinking
and yeah and it starts to work
like you can see work like my talent in computer design is i can
i can see how computers work in my head
like really well and i know other people can do that too
and when you're working with people that can do that
like it is kind of a an amazing experience
and then
and every once in a while
you get to that place and then you find the flaw
which is kind of funny because you you can you can fool yourself in
but the two of you kind of drifted along
yeah into the direction that was useless
yeah that happens too like you have to
because you know
well the nice thing about computer design there's always reduction in practice
like you come up with your good ideas
and i know some architects who really love ideas
and then they work
on them and they
put it on the shelf
they go work on the next
idea
and put on the shelf
they never
reduce
the practice
so they find out what's good and bad because most
every time i've done something really new by the time it's done
like the good parts are good but i know all the flaws like
yeah would you say your career
just your own experience is your career defined by mostly by flaws or by successes
like if again there's great tension between those
if you haven't
tried hard yeah right and done something new
right
then you're not going to be facing
the challenges
when you build it then you find out all the problems with it
and but when you look back you see problems
okay oh when i look back
um what do you think earlier in my career
yeah like eb5
was the second alpha chip
i was so embarrassed about the mistake so i could barely talk about it
and it was in the guinness book of worlds records and it was the fastest processor
on the planet
yeah
so it was and at some point i realized that was really a bad
mental framework
to deal with like doing something new we did a bunch of new things
and some worked
out great and some were bad
and we learned a lot from it and then
the next one we learned a lot that also ev6 also had some
really cool things in it i think the proportion of good stuff went up but
it had a couple of fatal flaws in it that were
painful
and then
yeah you learn to channel the pain into like pride not pride really you know just
realization
about how the world works okay or how
that kind of ideas that works life is suffering that's the reality
what no it's not
well i know the buddha said that and a couple other people
are stuck on it no
it's you know there's this kind of weird combination
of good and bad
you know light and darkness that you have to tolerate and you know deal with
yeah there's definitely lots of suffering in the world
depends on the perspective it seems like there's way more darkness but
that makes the light part really nice
what computing
hardware
or just any kind of even software design are you
do you find beautiful from your own work from
other people's work that you're just
we were just talking about the
the battleground of flaws and mistakes and errors but things that were just
beautifully done is there something that pops to mind well when things are beautifully done
usually
there's a well thought out set of abstraction layers
so the whole thing works in unison nicely yes
and and when i say abstraction layer that means two different components when they work together
they work independently they don't have to know what the other one is doing
so that decoupling
yeah so the famous one was the the network stack like there's a seven layer network
you know data transport and protocol and all the layers
and the innovation was is when they really wrote got that right
because networks before that didn't define those very well the layers could innovate independently
and occasionally the layer boundary would you know the interface would be upgraded
and that that let you know the the design space breathe and
you could
do something
new in layer
seven
without
having to worry about how layer
four
worked
right and
so good design does that and you see it in processor designs
when we did the zen design at amd
we made several components very modular
and you know my insistence
at the top was i wanted all the interfaces
to find before we wrote the rtl for the pieces
one of the verification
leads said if we do this right i can test the pieces
so well independently when we put it together
we won't find all these interaction bugs because the floating point knows how the cache works
and i was a little skeptical but he was mostly right
that the modularity design greatly improved the quality
is that universally true in general would you say about good designs the modularity
is
like usually
talked about this before humans are only so smart like
and we're not getting any smarter
right but the complexity of things is going up yeah so
you know a beautiful design can't be bigger than the person doing it
it's just
you know their piece of it
like
the odds of you doing a really beautiful
design of something that's way too hard for you is slow
right
if it's way too simple for you it's not that interesting
it's like well anybody could do that but when you get the right match of
your
your expertise and you know mental power
to the right design size
that's cool but that's not big enough to make a meaningful
impact in the world
so now you have to have
some framework to design the pieces
so that the whole thing is big and harmonious but
you know when you put it together it's you know sufficiently
sufficiently
interesting to to be used
and you know so that's like a beautiful design is
matching the limits of that human cognitive capacity
to to the module you can create and creating a nice interface between those modules
and thereby do you think there's a limit to the kind of
beautiful complex systems we can build with this kind of modular
design it's like
you know if we build increasingly more complicated you can think of like the internet
okay let's scale it up you can think of like social network like twitter as one
computing system
and but those are little modules yeah right
but it's built on it's built on so many components nobody at twitter even understands
right so
so so if an alien showed up and looked at twitter
he wouldn't just see twitter as a beautiful
simple thing that everybody
uses
which is really big
you would see
the network
it runs on the fiber optics the data is transported
the computers the whole thing is so bloody complicated
nobody twitter understands it and so i think that's what the alienware
sees so yeah if an alien showed up and looked at twitter
or looked at the various different
networked systems that you can see on earth
so imagine they were really smart they could comprehend the whole thing
and then they sort of
you know evaluated
the human and thought this is really interesting no human on this planet comprehends
the system they built
no individual
or well would they even see individual
humans that's the interest
like we humans
are very human-centric
entity-centric
and so we think
of us as the organ as the central organism and the networks
as just the connection of organisms
but from a perspective of
an alien from an outside perspective it seems like yeah
yeah i get it where the ants and they'd see the ant colony
the ant colony yeah
or the result the production of the ant colony which is like cities and
it's it's
yeah in that sense humans are pretty impressive the modularity that we're able to
and the
and how robust we are to noise and mutation
all that kind of stuff well that's because it's stress tested all the time yeah
you know you build all these cities with buildings and you get earthquakes occasionally and
you know some you know wars earthquakes
viruses every once in a while
you know changes in business plans for you know like shipping or something like
like
as long as it's all stress tested then
it keeps adapting to the the situation so the
that's that's a curious phenomena
well let's go let's talk about moore's law a little bit
at the broad view of moore's law was just exponential improvement of
computing capability like openai for example recently published this kind of
papers looking at the exponential improvement in the training efficiency of neural networks
for like image net and all that kind of stuff we just got better on
this is purely software aside
just figuring out better tricks and algorithms for training neural networks
and that seems to be improving
significantly faster than the moore's law prediction
you know
so that's in the software space like what do you think
if moore's law continues or if the general
version of moore's law continues
do you think that comes mostly
from the hardware from the software some mix of the two
some interesting totally
so not the reduction of the size of the transistor
kind of thing but more in the
in the totally interesting kinds of innovations in the hardware space all that kind of stuff
well
there's like a half a dozen things going on in that graph
so one is
there's initial innovations that had a lot of had room to be exploited
so you know the efficiency of the networks has improved dramatically
and then
the decomposability
of those and the use go you know they started running on one computer
then multiple computers
and multiple gpus
and then arrays of gpus
and
they're up to thousands
and at some point
so
so it's sort of like they were consumed
they were going from like a single computer application
to a thousand
computer application
so that's not really a moore's law thing that's an independent
vector how many computers can i put on this problem
because the computers themselves are getting better on like a moore's law rate
but their ability to go from one to ten to a hundred to a thousand
yeah you know was something and then multiplied
by
you know the amount of computes
it took to resolve like alex
net to resnet
the transformers
it's it's been quite
you know steady improvements
but those are like s cars
aren't they yeah that's the exactly
kind of
s-curves
that are underlying
moore's law from the very beginning
so so what what's the biggest what's the most
productive
rich source of s-curves
in in the future do you think
is it hardware
is it software
or is it so hardware
is going to move along
relatively slowly
like you know double performance every two years there are there's still
i like how you call that slow yeah that's the slow version
the snail's pace of moore's law maybe we should we should
we should trademark that one
whereas the scaling by number of computers
you know can go much faster
you know i'm sure at some point google had a
you know their initial search engine was running on a laptop you know like
yeah and at some point they really worked on scaling that and then they factored
the indexer
from
you know this piece and this piece and this piece and they spread the data
on more
things and
you know they did a dozen innovations
but as they scaled up the number of computers on that it kept breaking
finding new bottlenecks in their software and their schedulers and and made them rethink
like it seems insane to do a scheduler
across a thousand computers
to schedule parts of it and then send the results to one computer
but if you want to schedule a million searches
that makes perfect sense
so so there's the the scaling by just quantity is probably the richest thing but then
as you scale quantity
like a network that was great on 100 computers
may be completely the wrong one you may pick a network that's 10 times slower
on 10 000 computers like per computer
but if you go from a hundred to ten thousand that's a hundred times
so that's one of the things that happened when we did internet scaling is the efficiency
went down
not up the future of computing is inefficiency
not efficiency
but scales
in efficient scale it's it's scaling faster than inefficiency
bites you
and as long as there's you know dollar value there like scaling costs lots of money
yeah but google showed
facebook showed everybody
showed that
the scale was where the money was at
it was and so it was
worth it financially do you think
is it possible that like basically the entirety of earth will be like a computing surface
like this table will be doing computing
this hedgehog will be doing computing like everything
really inefficient dumb computing would be fiction books they call it computronium
computing we turn everything into computing
well most of the elements aren't very good for anything
like you're not going to make a computer out of iron like you know silicon and
carbon have like nice structures
you know we'll we'll see what what you can do with the rest of it
people talk about well maybe we can turn the sun into computer but it's it's hydrogen
and a little bit of helium so
what i mean is more like actually just adding computers to everything
oh okay so you're just converting all the mass of the universe into a computer
no no so not using to be ironic from the simulation point of view is like
the simulator build mass to simulate
like
yeah i mean yeah so
i mean ultimately
this is all heading towards the simulation yeah well
i i think i might have told you the story a tesla they were deciding
so they want to measure the current coming out of the battery
and they decide between putting the resistor
in there
and putting a computer
with a sensor in there
and the computer was faster than the computer i worked on in 1982.
and we chose the computer because it was cheaper than the resistor
so so sure this hedgehog you know it costs 13
and we can put a you know
an ai that's the smartest you in there for five bucks it'll have
one
you know so computers will be you know he'd be everywhere
i was hoping it wouldn't be smarter than me because
well everything's going to be smarter than you
but you were saying it's inefficient
i thought it was better to have a lot of doubt well
well moore's law will slowly compact
that stuff
so even the dump things will be smarter
than us
the dump things are going to be smart or they're going to be smart
enough to talk to something
that's really
smart
you know it's like
well just remember
like a big computer
chip
yeah
you know it's like an inch by an inch
and you know
40 microns thick
it doesn't take very much very many atoms to make a high power computer
yeah and 10 000 of them can fit in the shoe box
but you know you have the the cooling
and power problems
but you know
people are working on that
but they still can't write
compelling poetry or music or
understand what love is or have a fear of mortality
so so we're still winning neither can most of humanity so
well they can write books about it so [laughter]
but but speaking about this
you know this walk along the path of innovation towards
the dumb things being smarter than humans you are now the cto
of tens torrent as of two months ago they build hardware for deep learning
how do you build scalable
and efficient deep learning this is such a fascinating
space yeah yeah so it's interesting
so um
up until recently i thought there was two kinds of computers there are serial computers
that run like c programs and then there's parallel computers
so the way i think about it is you know parallel computers you have given parallelism
like gpus are great because you have a million pixels
and modern gpus run a program on every pixel they call the shader program right so
or
like finite
element analysis
you
you build something
you know you make this into little tiny
chunks
you give each chunk to a computer
so you're giving all these chunks a parallel something like that
but most c programs you write this linear narrative
and you have to make it go fast
to make it go fast you predict all the branches
all the data fetches and you run that more in parallel
but that's found parallelism
ai is
i'm still trying to decide how fundamental this is it's a given parallelism problem
but the way people describe the neural networks
and then how they write them in pi torch it makes graphs
yeah that might be fundamentally different than the gpu
kind of parallelism yeah it might be because the
when you run the gpu program on all the pixels you're running
like you know depends you know this group of pixels
say it's background blue and that runs a really simple program this pixel
is
you know some patch of your face so you have some
really interesting shader program to give you impression of translucency
but the pixels themselves don't talk to each other there's no graph
right
so you you do the image
and then you do the next image and you do the next image
and you run
8 million pixels 8 million programs every time and modern gpus have like 6 000
thread engines in them
so you know
to get 8 million pixels each one runs a program on you know 10 or 20
pixels
and that's how that's how they work but there's no graph
but you think graph might be a totally
new
way to think about hardware so raja gadori and i've been having this good conversation
about giving versus found parallelism
and then
the kind of walk cause we got more transistors
like you know computers way back when did stuff on scalar data
then we did it on vector data famous vector machines
now we're making computers that operate on matrices
right and then the the category we we said that was next was spatial
like imagine you have so much data that
you know you want to do the compute on this data and then when it's done
it says
send the result to this pile of data run some software on that
and it's better to
to think about it spatially than
to move all the data to a central processor and do all the work
so especially
i mean moving in the space of data as opposed to moving the data
yeah you have a you have a petabyte data space
spread across some huge array of computers
and when you do a computation
somewhere you send the result of that computation
or maybe a pointer to the next program some other piece of data and do it
but i think a better word might be graph
and all the ai neural networks are graphs
do some computations
send the result here do another computation
do a data transformation
do a merging do a pooling
do another computation
is it possible to compress and say how we make this thing
efficient
this whole process efficient that's different
so first
the fundamental elements in the graphs are things like matrix multiplies convolutions data manipulations
and data movements
so gpus
emulate those things with their little singles you know basically running a single threaded program
and then
there's a you know nvidia calls it a work where they group a bunch of programs
that are similar together
so for efficiency and instruction use
and then at a higher level you kind of
you take this graph and you say this part of the graph is a matrix multiplier
which runs on these 32
threads
but the model at the bottom was built for
running programs on pixels not executing graphs so it's emulation
yes so is it possible to build something that natively runs graphs
yes so that's what ten storm did
so
where are we on that
how like in the history of that effort
are we in the early days yeah i think so tense torrance
started by a friend of mine labisha bajak and i
i was his first investor so i've been you know kind of
following him and talking to him about it for years and
in the fall when i was considering things to do
i decided you know the
we we
held a conference last year with a friend organized it and
and we we wanted to bring in thinkers and two of the people were andre carpassi
and chris lattner and
andre gave this talk on youtube called software 2.0
which i think is great
which is we went from programmed computers where you write programs to data program computers
you know like the futures you know of software as data programs the the networks
and i think that's true
and then
chris has been work he worked on llvm
the low-level virtual machine which became the intermediate representation
for all compilers
and now he's working on another project called mlir which is mid-level intermediate representation which is
essentially under the graph
about how do you represent that kind of computation
and then coordinate large numbers of potentially heterogeneous
computers
and and i would say technically tense torrents
you know two pillars are those those those two ideas software 2.0 and mid-level representation
but it's in service of executing graph programs
the hardware is designed to do that so it's including the hardware piece yeah
and then the other cool thing is
for a relatively small amount of money they did a test chip and two production chips
so it's like a super effective teams and
and unlike some ai startups where if you don't build the hardware
to run the software that they really want to do
then you have to fix it by writing lots more software
so the hardware naturally does matrix multiply convolution the data manipulations
and the data movement between processing elements that that you can see in the graph
which i think is all pretty clever and
that's that's what i'm i'm working on now so
the i think it's called the grace call processor
introduced last year it's
you know there's a bunch of measures of performance we're talking about horses
it seems to outperform
trillion operations per second seems to outperform nvidia's tesla t4 system
so these are just numbers
what do they actually mean in real world perform like what are the
metrics
for you that you're chasing
in in your horse race like what do you care about
well first so the the native language of
you know people who write ai network programs
is pie torch now by torch tensorflow
there's a couple others
the pi torch is one over tensor flows it's just i'm not an expert on that
i i know many people have switched from tensorflow to pi torch
yeah and there's technical reasons for it and
i use both both are still awesome both are still awesome
but the deepest
love is for pytorch
currently
yeah
there's more love for that and that that may change
so the first thing is
when they write their programs
can the hardware execute it pretty much as it was written
right so pi torch turns into a graph
we have a graph compiler
that makes that graph
then
it fractions
the graph down so if you have a big matrix
multiply
we turn it into right-sized
chunks that run on the processing
elements
it hooks all the graph up it lays out all the data
there's a couple mid-level representations of it that are also simulatable
so that
if you're writing the code you can see how it's going to go through the machine
which is pretty cool and then at the bottom it schedules kernels like
math data manipulation data movement kernels which do this stuff so
we don't have to run write a little program to do matrix
multiply
because we have a big matrix multiplier
like there's no cmd program for that
but there is scheduling for that
right so the the one of the goals is if you write
a piece of pytorch
code that looks pretty reasonable
you should be able to compile
it run it on the hardware
without having to tweak it and and do all kinds of crazy things to get performance
there's not a lot of intermediate
steps
right it's running directly as right like on a gpu
if you write a large matrix
multiply
naively
you'll get five to ten percent of the peak performance of the gpu
right and then there's a bunch there's a bunch of people publish papers
on this and i read them about
what steps do you have to do and it goes from
pretty reasonable
well transpose one of the matrices so you wrote or not column ordered
you know
block it so that you can put a block of the matrix on different
sms you know groups of threads
but some of it gets into little details
like you have to schedule it just so so you don't have registered
conflicts
so the the the they call them cuda ninjas
i love it to get to the optimal point you either write a pre use a
pre-written
library
which is a good strategy
for some things or you have to be an expert
in micro architecture
to program it
right so the optimization
step is way more complicated with the gpa so our our goal is
if you write pi torch that's good pi torch you can do it now there's
as the networks are evolving you know they've changed from convolutional to matrix multiply
people are talking about conditional graphs you're talking about very large matrices they're talking about sparsity
you're talking about problems that scale across many many chips so the the native
you know data item is a as a packet
like so you send a packet to a processor it gets processed
it does a bunch of work and then it may send packets to other processors
and and they execute like a data flow graph kind of methodology
got it we have a big network on chip and then 16
the next second chip has 16 ethernet ports they hook lots of them together
and it's the same graph compiler across multiple chips
so that's where the scale comes in so it's built to scale naturally
now
my experience with scaling is as you scale you run into lots of interesting problems
so scaling is the mountain to climb
yeah so the hardware is built to do this and then
we're in the process of
is there a software part to this with ethernet and all that
well the
you know the protocol at the bottom you know we send you know it's an ethernet
phi
but the protocol basically says
send a packet from here to there it's all point to point
the header bit says which processor to send it to and we basically
take a packet off our on-chip network
put an ethernet header on it send it to the other end
to strip the header off and send it to the local thing it's pretty straightforward
human human interaction is pretty straightforward
too but when you get a million of us we could do some crazy stuff together
it could be fun
so is that the goal is scale
so like for example i've been recently
doing a bunch of robots at home for my own personal pleasure
am i going to ever use 10 story or is this more for
there's all kinds of problems
like they're small inference problems or small training problems there's big training problems
what's the big goal is it the big difference
training problems or the small training problems
well one of the goals is to scale from 100 milliwatts to a to a megawatt
you know so
like really have some range on the problems
and
the same kind of ai programs work at all different levels
so that's cool
the natural since the natural
data item is a packet that we can move around
it's built to scale
but so many people have you know small problems
right right but but
you know like inside that phone is a small problem to solve so
do you see that storm potentially being inside a phone well
the power efficiency of local memory local computation
and the way we built it is pretty good
and then there's a lot of efficiency on being able to do conditional graphs and sparsity
i think it
for complicated networks i want to go in a small factor it's been quite good
um but we have to prove that that's a
that's a fun problem and that's the early days of the company right it's a couple
years you said
but you think you invested you think they're legit yeah as you join yeah well that's
well it's also it's a really interesting place to be
like the ai world is exploding you know and
i looked at some other opportunities like build a faster processor which people want
yes but that's more on incremental path than
what's going to happen in ai in the next 10 years
so this is kind of
you know an exciting place to be part of
the revolutions
will be happening in the very space
and then lots of people are working on it but there's lots of technical
reasons
why some of them you know aren't going to work out that well and
and you know that's that's interesting and there's also the same
problem about getting the basics right like we've talked to customers about exciting features
and at some point we realized that each unit was realizing
they want to hear first about memory bandwidth local bandwidth compute intensity programmability
they want to know the basics power management
how the network ports work what are the basics do all the basics work
because it's easy to say we got this great idea that you know the crack gbt3
but
the the people we talked to want to say
if i buy that so we have a pc express card
with our chip on it if you buy the card
you plug it in your machine you download the driver
how long does it take me to get my network to run
right right you know that's a real question it's a very basic question
so
yeah
is there an answer to that yet or is it trying to our goal is like
an hour
okay when can i buy a tesla
pretty soon for my for the small case training yeah pretty soon
months good i love the idea of you inside the room with the
carpathi andre kapathi and chris ladner
very
um
very interesting
very brilliant
people very out of the box thinkers but also like first principles thinkers
well they both
get stuff done
they only get stuff done to get their own projects
done they
they
talk about it clearly
they educate
large numbers of people and they've created
platforms
for other people to go do their stuff on
yeah the the clear
thinking
that's able to be communicated
is kind of impressive
it's kind of remarkable to
yeah i'm a fan
well let me ask because i talked to chris actually a lot these days he's been
one of the cool just to give him a shout out and he's been so
supportive as a human being so everybody's
quite different like great engineers are different but he's been like sensitive to the human element
in a way that's been fascinating like he was one of the early people on this
stupid podcast that i do to say like
don't quit this thing and also
talk to whoever the hell you want to talk to
that kind of from a legit engineer
to get like
props and be like you can do this
that was i mean that's what a good leader does right they just kind of
let a little kid
do his thing
like go
go do it let's see
let's see
see what turns
out
that that's a that's a pretty powerful thing but what do you
um
what's your sense about he used to be
he no i think stepped away from google
right
he said sci-fi i think
what
what's really impressive
to you about
the things that chris has worked on because it's that we mentioned
the optimization
the compiled design stuff the llvm
then there's he's also a google work that the tpu stuff
he's obviously worked on swift
so the programming language side
talking about people that work in the entirety of the stack yeah
what
from your time interacting with chris
and knowing the guy
what's really impressive to you it just inspires you well
well
like llvm became
you know the platform the de facto platform for you know compilers like it's it's amazing
and you know it was good code quality good design
choices
he hit the right level of abstraction
there's a little bit of the right time in the right place
and then he built a new programming language called swift
which you know after you know let's say some adoption resistance became very successful
i don't know that much about his work at google although i know that
you know that was the typical
they started
tensorflow
stuff and they you know it was new is you know
they wrote a lot of code
and then at some point it needed to be refactored
to be
you know because it its development slowed down why
pytorch
started a little later and then passed it
so he did a lot of work on that and then his idea about mlir
which is
what people started to realize is the complexity
of the software stack above
the low level
ir
was getting so high that forcing
the features
of that into a level
was was putting too much of a burden on it so he's splitting that into multiple
pieces
and that was one of the inspirations for our software stack where we have
several intermediate representations
that are all executable
and you can look at them and do transformations on them before you lower the level
so that was i think we started before moir
really got you know far enough along to use
but we're interested in that he's really excited about that malaya
he's that's that's his like little baby so he you know and
there seems to be some profound
ideas on that that are really useful so so each one of those things has been
as the world of software gets more and more complicated
how do we create the right abstraction
levels to simplify it in a way that people can now work independently
on different levels of it
so i would say all all three of those projects allovm
swift and mlir
did that successfully
so i'm interested
what's
what he's going to do next
in the same kind of way
yes
so on either the tpu or maybe the nvidia gpu side
how does 10 story you think or the ideas underlying it doesn't have to be testosterone
just this kind of graph focused
graph centric hardware
deep learning-centric hardware beat nvidia's
do you think it's possible for it to basically overtake nvidia sure
what's what's that process look like what's that
a journey look like you think well
gpus were built around shader programs on millions of pixels
not to run graphs
yes so there's a hypothesis
that says
the way the graphs you know are built
is going to be really interesting to be inefficient
on computing this and then the the primitives
is not a cmd program it's matrix multiply convolution
and then the data manipulations
are fairly extensive about
like how do you do a fast transpose
with a program
i don't know if you've ever written the transpose program
they're ugly and slow but in hardware you can do really well
like i'll give you an example so
when gpu accelerators first started doing triangles
like so you have a triangle which maps on the set of pixels
so you build it's very easy straightforward
to build a hardware engine that will find all those pixels
and it's kind of weird because you walk along the triangle to get to the edge
and then you have to go back down to the next
row
and walk along
and then you have to decide
on the edge
if the line of the triangle is like half on the pixel
what's
the pixel
color
because it's half of this pixel
and half the next one that's called rasterization
because you're saying that could be done in
in hardware now that's an example of
that operation
as a software program is really bad i've written a program that did rasterization
the hardware that does it has actually less code than
the software program that does it and it's way faster
right so there are certain times when the abstraction you have rasterize a triangle
you know execute a graph you know components of a graph
the right thing to do in the hardware software boundary is for the hardware to naturally
do it and so the gpu
is really optimized
for the rasterization
of triangles
well no that's just well like in a modern you know
that's a small piece of modern gpus
what they did is
that they still rasterize
triangles
when you're running the game but for the most part
most of the computation in the area the gpu is running shader programs
but they're single threaded programs
on pixels not graphs
let's be honest to say i don't actually know the the math behind shader
shading and lighting and all that kind of stuff i don't know what
they look like little simple floating point programs or complicated
ones you can have 8 000 instructions in a shader program
but i i don't have a good intuition why it could be parallelized
so easily
no it's because you have 8 million pixels in every single
so when you have a light
right yeah that comes down
the angle you know the amount of light
like like say this is a line of pixels across this table
right the amount of light on each pixel is subtly different
and each pixel is responsible
for figuring
out what figure it out so that pixel
says
on this pixel
i know the angle
of the light
i know the occlusion
i know the color i am
like every single
pixel
here is a different color
every single
pixel
gets a different
amount of light
every single pixel has a subtly different translucency
so to make it look realistic
the solution
was you run a separate program
on every pixel
see but i thought there's a reflection
from all over the place
is
every picture
yeah but there is
so
so you build a reflection
map which also
has some pixelated
thing
and then when the pixel is looking at the reflection
map it has to calculate
what the normal of the surface is
and it does it per pixel
by the way there's both loads of hacks
on that you're like you may have a lower resolution
light map reflection map there's all these you know attacks they do
but at the end of the day it's per pixel computation
and it so happened that you can map
graph like computation
onto the this pixel essentially you could do floating point programs on convolutions
and matrices
and nvidia invested for years in cuda
first for hpc and then they got lucky with the ai
trend
but do you think they're going to essentially
not be able to hardcore pivot out of their we'll see
that's always interesting how often do big companies hardcore pivot occasionally
how much do you know about nvidia folks
so
some yeah
well i'm i'm curious as well who's ultimately
as a
well
they've
innovated
several
times
but they've also
worked really hard on mobile
they worked really hard on radios
you know you know they're fundamentally a gpu company
well they tried to pivot it's an interesting little
game and play
in autonomous vehicles right with
or semi-autonomous
like playing with tesla and so on and seeing that's a
dipping a toe into that kind of pivot
they came out with this platform which is interesting technically
yeah but it was like a three thousand watt
you know you know thousand watt three three thousand dollar you know gpu platform
i don't know if it's interesting technically it's interesting philosophically
i i
technically i don't know if it's the execution that craftsmanship was there i'm not sure
but that i didn't get a sense they were
repurposing
gpus for an automotive solution
right it's not a real pivot they didn't they didn't build a ground-up solution
right
like the
like the chips inside tesla are pretty cheap like mobile eye has been doing this
they're they're doing the classic work from the simplest thing
yeah you know they were building 40 mil square millimeter
chips
and nvidia their solution had two 800 millimeter chips and two 200 millimeter chips and
you know like boatloads are really expensive drams and
and you know it's a really different approach
the mobilelite fit the let's say automotive cost and form factor
and then they added features as it was economically
viable and nvidia said take the biggest thing and we're gonna go make it work
you know and and that's also influenced like waymo
there's a whole bunch of autonomous
startups where they have a 5000 watt server in their trunk
right and but that's
that's because they think well 5000 watts and you know 10 000
is okay because it's replacing the driver
elon's approach was that port has to be cheap enough
to put it in every single tesla whether they turn on it autonomous driving or not
which
and mobileye was like
we need to fit in the bomb and you know cost structure
that
car companies
do so they may sell you a gps for 1500
bucks
but the bond for that's like 25
well and
for mobile eye it seems like neural networks
were not first-class citizens
like the computation
they didn't start out as a yeah it was a cv problem yeah
and did classic
cv
and found stop
lights
and lines
and they were really good at it
yeah and they never
i mean i don't know what's happening now but they never
fully pivoted
i mean it's like it's the nvidia
thing
and then
as opposed to so if you look at the new tesla work
it's like neural networks from the ground up yeah right
yeah and even tesla started with a lot of cv stuff in it and andre's
basically been eliminating
it
move it move everything into the network
so
without
this isn't like confidential stuff but you sitting on a porch looking over the world
looking at the work that andre is doing that elon's doing with tesla autopilot
do you like the trajectory
of where things are going on the floor they're making serious progress
i like the videos of people
driving the beta stuff
like it's taking some pretty complicated
intersections and all that but it's it's still an intervention for drive
i mean i i have autopilot the current autopilot
my my tesla i use it every day do you have full self-driving
beta or no no
so you you like where this is going
we're making progress it's taking longer than anybody thought
you know my wonder was
is you know hardware three is it enough computing
off by two off by five off by ten off by a hundred yeah
and
and i i thought it probably wasn't enough
but they're doing pretty well with it now yeah and one thing is
the data set gets bigger the training gets better
and then there's this interesting thing is
you sort of train and build an arbitrary size network that solves the problem
and then you refactor the network down to the thing that you can afford
to ship
right so the
the goal isn't to build the network that fits in the phone it's to build
something that actually works
and then then how do you make that most effective on the hardware you have
and they seem to be doing that much better than a couple years ago
well
the one really important thing is also
what they're doing well is how to iterate that quickly
which means like it's not just about one time deployment
one building is constantly entering the network
and trying to automate as many steps as possible right
and that's actually the
principles of the software 2.0 like you mentioned with andre
is
it's not just
i mean i don't know what the actual his description of software 2.0
is
if it's just high-level philosophical or their specifics but the interesting thing about
what that actually looks in the real world is it's that
what i think andre calls the data engine it's like
it's the iterative improvement of the thing you have a neural network that
does stuff
fails on a bunch of things
and learns from it over and over and over so you're constantly discovering
edge cases
so it's very much about
like data engineering
like figuring out
it's it's kind of what you were talking about with testosterone
is you have the data landscape
they have to walk along that data landscape in a way that
that's constantly improving the
the
the neural network and that that feels like that's the central
piece of it yeah itself
and there's two pieces
of it like
you you find
edge cases
that don't work and then you define
something
that goes get your data for that
but then the other constraint
is whether you have to label it or not
like the
the amazing
thing about like the gpt3
stuff is it's unsupervised
so there's essentially infinite amount of data now there's obviously infinite amount of data
available from cars of people successfully driving
but you know the
the current pipelines are mostly running on labeled data which is human limited
so when that becomes
unsupervised
right it it'll create
unlimited amount of data which then they'll scale
now the networks that may use that data might be way too big for cars
but then there'll be the transformation
from now we have unlimited data i know exactly what i want
now can i turn that into something that fits in the car
and that pro that process is going to happen all over the place
every time you get to the place where you have unlimited data
and that's what software 2.0 is about unlimited data training networks to do stuff
without humans writing code to do it
and ultimately also trying to discover like you're saying the self-supervised
formulation of the problem so the unsupervised
formulation of the problem like
you know in driving there's this really interesting
thing which is
you look at a scene that's before you and you have data about what a successful
human driver did
in that scene you know one second later
it's a little piece of data that you can use just like with gpt-3
as training
currently even even though tesla says they're using that it's an open question to me
how much how far can you can you sell all of the driving
with just
that
self-supervised
piece of data
and
like i i think that's what comedy is doing
that's what common ai is doing but the question is how
how much data so what comedy ai doesn't have
is
as
good of a data engine for example
as tesla does that's where the
like the organization
of the data
i mean as far as i know i haven't talked to george
but they do have the data
the question is how much data is needed
because we say infinite very loosely here
it's it's and then the other question which you said
i don't know if you think it's still an open question is
are we in the right order of magnitude for the compute necessary
that
is is this is it like what elon said this
chip that's in there now is enough to do full self-driving
or do we need another order of magnitude
i think nobody actually knows the answer to that question
i like the confidence that elon has but
yeah we'll see
and there's another funny thing is you don't learn to drive with infinite amounts of data
you learn to drive with an intellectual framework that understands physics and color and horizontal surfaces
and laws and roads and you know all your
your experience from manipulating your environment
like look there's so many factors go into that so then when you learn to drive
like driving is a subset of this conceptual framework that you have
right and so with self-driving cars right now we're teaching them to drive with driving data
you never teach a human to do that
you teach a human all kinds of interesting things like
language
like don't do that you know watch
out
you know there's all kinds of stuff going on
well this is where you i think previous
time with we talked
about
where you poetically
disagreed with my naive notion about humans i just think that
humans will will make this whole driving thing really difficult
yeah all right
like i said humans don't move that slow
it's a ballistics problem
it's a ballistic
human zero ballistics
problem which is like poetry
to me
it's very
it's very possible
that in driving
they're indeed
purely a ballistics
problem i
and i think that's probably the right way to think about it but
i still
they still continue to surprise me those and damn pedestrians the cyclists
other humans and other cars
and yeah but it's going to be one of these compensating things so
like when you're driving
you have an intuition
about what humans are going to do but you don't have 360
cameras
and radars
and you have an attention problem so yeah
so so the self-driving
car comes in with no attention problems 360
cameras right you know
a bunch of other features
yeah so they'll wipe out a whole class of accidents
right and you know
you know emergency
braking with radar and especially as it gets you know ai enhanced will eliminate
collisions
right
but then you have the other problems of these unexpected
things where you know you think your human intuition
is helping but then the cars also have
you know a set of hardware features that you're not even close to
and the key thing of course is
if you wipe out
a huge number of kind of accidents
then it might be just way safer than the human driver even though
even if humans are still a problem that's hard to figure out
yeah
that's probably what happens
autonomous
cars will have
a small number of accidents humans would have avoided
but they'll wipe
they'll get rid of
the bulk of them
what do you think about
like tesla's dojo efforts
or it can be bigger than tesla in general
it's kind of like the tense torrent
trying to innovate like this is the dichotomy like
should a company try to from scratch build its own neural network training
hardware
well first i think it's great so we need lots of experiments
right and there's lots of startups working on this and they're pursuing different things
you know i was there when we started dojo
and it was sort of like what's the unconstrained
computer solution to go do very large training problems
and then there's fun stuff like
you know we said
well we have this 10 000 watt board to cool
well you go talk to guys at spacex
and they think 10 000 watts is a really small number not a big number yeah
and
and there's brilliant people working on it i'm curious to see how it'll come out i
i couldn't tell you
you know
i know it pivoted a few times since i left so so the
cooling does seem to be a big problem i do like what
elon said about it which is like we don't want to do
the thing
unless
it's way better than the alternative
whatever the alternative
is so it has to be way better than like
racks of gpus
yeah and the other thing is just like you know
you know the tesla autonomous driving hardware
it was only serving one software stack
and the hardware team and the software team were tightly coupled
you know if you're building
a general purpose ai solution
then you know there's so many different customers
with so many different needs
now something andre said is i think this is amazing 10 years ago like vision recommendation
language were completely different disciplines
we said the people literally couldn't talk to each other and three years ago
it was all neural networks
but the very different neural networks
and recently it's converging on one set of networks
they vary a lot in size obviously they vary in data varying outputs
but the technology
has converged a good bit
yeah these transformers behind gbt3
it seems like they could be applied
to video they could be applied to a lot of yeah
and it's like and they're all really
it was like to literally replace letters with pixels
yeah it does vision it's amazing
so and then size actually improves the thing
so the bigger it gets the more compute you throw at it the better it gets
the more data you have the better it gets
so
so so then you start to wonder well is that a fundamental
thing or is is this
just another step to some fundamental understanding about this kind of computation
which is really interesting
us humans don't want to believe that that kind of thing will achieve conceptual
understandings you were saying like you'll figure out physics but maybe it will
maybe probably will
well it's worse than that
it'll understand physics in ways that we can't understand
i like to hear stephen will from
talk where he said you know there's three generations of physics there was
physics by reasoning well big things should false faster than small things right that's reasoning
and then there's
physics by equations
like you know
but the number of programs in the world that are solved with the single equations relatively
low almost all programs have you know
more than one line of code maybe 100 million lines of code
so you said that now we're going to
physics by equation which is his project which is cool
i might point out that there was there was two two generations of physics before reasoning
habit
like all animals you know know things fall and you know birds fly and
you know predators know how to you know solve a differential equation to cut off a
accelerating you know
curving animal path yep and then there was you know the gods did it
right
so yeah right so you know there's five generations now
software 2.0 says programming things is not the last step
data so there's going to be a physics past stephen's wolfram's com that's not explainable
and and actually
there's no reason that i can see while that even that's the limit
like there's something beyond that
i mean they're usually like usually when you have this hierarchy
it's not like
well if you have this step in this step in this step and they're all qualitatively
different
and conceptually
it's not obvious
why
you know six
is the right hand number of hierarchy
steps
in not seven
or eight or
well then it's
probably impossible
for us to
to comprehend
something that's beyond the thing that's not explainable
yeah because i think but the thing that you know understands the thing that's unexplainable
to us
we'll conceive the next one and
like i'm not sure why there's a limit to it
your brain hurts that's the sad story
if if we look at our own brain which is an interesting illustrative example
in your work with testor and trying to design deep learning architectures
do you do you think about the brain at all maybe from a
hardware designer perspective
if you could
change something about the brain what would you change or do funny question
like how would you so your brain is really weird
like you know your cereal cortex where we think we do most of our thinking
is what like six or seven neurons thick
yeah like that's weird like all the big networks are way bigger than that
like way deeper so that seems odd
and then
you know when you're thinking if it's if
if the input
generates
a result you can lose it goes really fast but if it can't
that generates an output that's interesting which turns into an input and then your brain
to the point where you mold things
over for days
and how many
trips
through your brain
is that
right
like it's you know
300 milliseconds or something to get through seven levels of neurons i forget the number exactly
but then it does it over and over and over as it searches
and the brain clearly
is looks like some kind of graph because you have a neuron
with you know connections and it talks to other ones and
it's locally very computationally
intense but it's also
does sparse computations across a pretty big area
there's a lot of messy biological type of things and it's it's
meaning like
first of all there's mechanical chemical and electrical signals that's all that's going on
then the there's a the asynchronicity
of signals
and there's like there's just a lot of variability that seems continuous
and messy and just a mess of biology
and it's unclear whether that's a good thing yeah or it's a bad thing because if
if it's a good thing that we need to run the entirety of the evolution
well we're going to have to start with basic bacteria to create some imaging we could
you could build a brain with 10 layers would that be better or worse
or more more connections or less connections
or you know we don't know to what level our brains are optimized
but if i was changing
things like
yeah like you know you can only hold like seven numbers
in your head
yeah like why not 100 or a million
never thought of that
like and why can't like why can't we have like a floating point processor
that can compute anything we want
like and see it all properly like that would be kind of fun
and why can't we we see in four or eight dimensions
like because you know 3d is kind of a drag
like all the hard mass transforms are up in multiple dimensions
so there's that you know you could imagine a brain architecture that
you know you could
enhance with a whole bunch of features that would be
you know really useful for thinking about things it's possible that the limitations
you're describing are actually
essential
for like the constraints are essential for creating
like the depth of intelligence like that
the ability to reason
you know it's hard to say because like your brain is clearly a parallel processor
you know you know
10 billion neurons talking to each other at a relatively
low clock rate
but
it produces
something that looks like a serial
thought process
it's a serial narrative in your head
that's true right but then there are people famously who are visual thinkers
like
i think i'm a relatively visual thinker
i can imagine any object and rotate it in my head and look at it
and there are people who say they don't think that way at all
and recently i read an article about people
people who say they don't have a they don't have a voice in their heads
they can talk
but when they you know it's like well what are you thinking
they'll they'll describe something that's visual
so that's curious
now
if if you're saying
if we dedicated
more hardware to holding information
like you know 10 numbers or a million numbers
like would that
just distract us from our ability to form this kind of singular
identity like it dissipates
somehow right
but but maybe
you know future humans will have many identities
that
have some higher level organization but can actually do lots more things in parallel
yeah there's no reason if we're thinking modularly there's no reason we can't have multiple consciousnesses
in one brain yeah and maybe there's some way to make it faster so that the
you know the the area the computation could
could still have a unified
feel to it
but while still having way more ability
to do parallel stuff at the same time
could definitely be improved
it could be improved
okay well
it's it's
pretty good right now actually
people don't give it enough credit the thing is pretty nice the
the you know the the fact that the right ends seem to be
on give a nice like spark
of
beauty to the whole experience
i don't know i don't know if it can be improved easily
it could be more beautiful
i don't know how yeah what do you mean
what do you mean how
all the ways you can't imagine
no but that's the whole point
i wouldn't be able to i'm at
the fact that i can imagine
ways
in
in which it could be more beautiful
means so do you know you know ian banks his stories so the the super smart
ais there live mostly live in the world of what they call infinite fun
because they can create arbitrary worlds
so they interact
and you know the story
has it they interact
in the normal
world and they're very smart
and they can do all kinds of stuff
and
you know a given
mind can
you know talk to a million
humans
at the same time because we're very
slow
and
for reasons you know artificial the story
they're interested in people and doing stuff but they mostly live in this
this other land of thinking my
inclination is to think that the ability to create infinite fun will
um will not be so fun
that's sad
there are so many things to do imagine be able to make a star
move planets around
yeah
yeah but because we can imagine that as wildlife
is fun
if we can if we actually were able to do it it'd be a slippery slope
where fun wouldn't even have a meaning because we just consistently
desensitize ourselves by the infinite amounts of fun we're having
and the sadness the the dark stuff is what makes it fun i think i
mean that could be the russian
it could be the could be the fun makes it fun and the sadnesses
makes it bittersweet
yeah that's true fun could be the thing that makes it fun
so what do you think about the expansion
not through the biology side but through the bci the brain computer interfaces
yeah you got a chance to check out the neural link stuff it's super interesting
like like humans like
like our thoughts to manifest as action
you know like
like as a kid you know like shooting a rifle was super fun
driving a mini bike
doing things
and then computer games i think for a lot of kids became the thing where they
you know they can do what they want they can fly
a plane
they can do this they can do this
right
but you have to have this physical interaction now imagine
you know you could just imagine stuff and it happens
right
like really richly
and interestingly
like we kind of do that when we dream like dream dreams are funny because
like if you have some control or awareness in your dreams
like it's very realistic looking
or not realistic
it depends on the dream
but you can also manipulate that
and you know what what's possible there is
is is odd and the fact that nobody understands it's hilarious but
um do you think it's possible to expand that capability through computing sure
is there some interesting so from a hardware designer perspective is there
do you think you'll present totally new challenges and the kind of hardware that required
that like so this hardware isn't
standalone
computing well this just knows
today computer games are rendered by gpus
right right so but you've seen the gans stuff yep right where
trained neural networks
render realistic images but there's no pixels no triangles
no shaders no light maps no nothing
so the future of graphics is probably ai
right yes now that ai is heavily trained by lots of real data
right so if you have an interface with a aai renderer
right so if you say render a cat
it won't
say
well
how
tall is the cat and how big it you know it'll render
a cat
and you might say well a little bigger a little smaller
you know
make it a tabby
shorter hair you know like you could tweak it
like the the amount of data you'll have to
send to interact with a very powerful ai renderer could be low but the question is
for brain computer interfaces would need to
render not onto a screen but render onto the brain
and
like directly
so that there's a bandwidth
you could do it both ways
i mean our eyes are really good sensors
it could render onto a screen
and we could feel like we're participating
in it you know they're gonna
they're gonna have you know like the oculus
kind of stuff
it's gonna be so good when a projection
to your eyes you think it's real
you know they're slowly solving those problems
and i suspect
when the renderer of that information into your head is also ai mediated
you know they'll be able to give you
the cues
that
you know you really want for depth and all kinds of stuff
like
your your brain is probably faking
your your visual field right
like your eyes are twitching around but you don't notice that occasionally
they blank you don't notice that
you know there's all kinds of things
like you think you see over here but you don't really
see there
yeah
it's all fabricated
yeah so yeah peripheral vision is fascinating
so if you have an ai renderer that's trained to understand exactly how you see
and the kind of things that enhance the realism of the experience
it could be super real actually
so i don't know what the limits that are
but obviously
if if we have a brain interface that goes in
inside
your
you know visual cortex in a better way than your eyes do which is possible
it's a lot neurons
yeah
um
maybe that will be even cooler
well the really cool thing is it has to do with the
the infinite
fun that you're referring
to
which is
our brains seem to be very limited
and like you said computational
so very plastic
very plastic yeah yeah so it's a it's a com interesting combination
now the the interesting open question is the limits of that neuroplasticity like how
how flexible
is that thing because we don't we haven't really tested it
we know about that experiments where they they put like a pressure pad on somebody's head
and had a visual transducer
pressurize it and somebody slowly learned to see yep that's like it's
especially
at a young age
if you throw
a lot at it
like
what
what can it
can it completely so can you like arbitrarily expand it with computing power so
connected to the internet directly somehow yeah the answer's probably yes
so the problem with biology
and ethics is like there's a mess there like us humans are
perhaps unwilling to take
risks in
into directions that are full of uncertainty
so that's like 90
of the population is unwilling to take risks the other 10
is rushing into the risks
unaided by any infrastructure whatsoever
and
you know and that that's where all the fun happens in you know society
there's been huge transformations
yeah in the last you know a couple thousand years
yeah it's funny i mean i got a chance to interact with
this is matthew johnson from johns hopkins he's doing this large-scale study of psychedelics
it's it's becoming
more and more
i've gotten a chance to interact
with that community
of scientists
working on psychedelics
but because of that that opened the door to me to
all these
what are they called psychonauts
the people who like you said the ten percent who like
i don't care i don't know if there's a science behind this i'm taking the spaceship
to
if i'm being the first on mars i'll be
the you know you know psychedelic's interesting in the sense that
in another dimension
like you said it's a way to explore the
with the limits of the human mind like
what is this thing capable of doing
because you kind of like when you dream
you detach it i don't know exactly in your science of it but you detach your
like reality from
what your mind
the images
your mind is able to conjure
up and your mind goes into weird
places
and like entities appear
freudian type of
like trauma is probably connected in there somehow but you start to have like these
weird vivid worlds that like so do you actively dream
do you why not
i had like six six hours of dreams and i it's like really useful time
i know i do i haven't
i don't for some reason i just knock out and
i have sometimes like anxiety inducing kind of like very pragmatic
like nightmare type of dreams but not nothing fun nothing nothing fun nothing fun
i i try i unfortunately have mostly have fun
in the waking world which is very limited in the amount of fun you can have
it's not that limited either yeah that's what we'll have to talk
yeah i need instructions yeah there's like a manual for that you might wanna
i looked it up i'll ask elon what what did you dream
you know years ago and i i read about you know
like you know a book about how to have
you know become aware of your dreams
i worked on it for a while like there's this trick about
you know imagine you can see your hands and look out and
and i got somewhat good at it like
but my mostly
when i'm thinking about things or working on problems i i
i prep myself before i go to sleep it's like i i pull into my
mind all the things i want to work on or think about
and then
that let's say greatly improves the chances that i'll i'll work on that while i'm sleeping
and then and then i also you know basically asked to remember it
and i often remember
very detailed
within the dream yeah or outside the dream well
to bring it up in in my dreaming
and then remember it when i wake up
it's just it's more of a meditative practice you say
you know to prepare yourself to
do that
like if you go to you know the sleep still
gnashing your teeth about some random thing that happened
that you're not that really interested in you'll dream about it
that's really interesting maybe but but you can direct your dreams
somewhat by prepping
you know i'm going to try that it's really interesting
like the most important the interesting not like
what what did this guy send
in an email kind of like stupid
worry stuff but like fundamental
problems you're actually concerned about
prepping and interesting things you're worried about or just
you're reading or you know some great conversation
you had or something
some adventure you want to have like there's there's a lot of
space there
and
and it seems to work
that
you know my percentage of interesting dreams and memories went up
is there
is that the source of
if you were able to deconstruct like where some of your best ideas came from
do is there a process
that's at the core of that yeah like so some people you know
walk and think some people like in the shower the best ideas hit them
if you talk about like newton
apple hitting them on the head
no i i found that a long time ago i'm i process things somewhat slowly
so like in college
i had friends that could study at the last minute get an a next day
i can't do that at all
so i always front loaded all the work like i do all the problems
early you know for finals like the last three days i wouldn't look at a book
because i want you know because
like a new fact the day before finals may screw up my understanding
of what i thought i knew so my
my goal was to always get it in
and and give it time to soak
and
i used to you know
i remember we were doing like 3d calculus
i would have these amazing dreams of 3d
surfaces
with normal
you know calculating the gradient and this is like all come up so it was
really fun
like very visual
and and if i got cycles of that that was useful
um and the other is don't over filter your ideas like i like that process of
brainstorming
where lots of ideas can happen i like people who have lots of ideas
and things but that's what's up
then there's a yeah let them sit and let it breathe a little bit
and then reduce it to practice like at some point you really have to
does it really work like you know is this real or not
right but you but you have to do both there's creative
tension there like how do you be both open
and
you know precise
if you had ideas that you just
that sit in your mind for like years
before the
sure
it's an interesting way to
is generate ideas and just let them sit let them sit there for a while
i think i have a few of those ideas you know that was so funny
yeah i think that's
you know creativity this one or something
for the slow thinkers in the in the room i suppose
as i some people like you said are just like
like the yeah it's really interesting like there's so much diversity in how people think
you know how fast or slow they are how well they remember don't
like you know i'm not super good at remembering facts but processes and methods
like in our engineering i went to penn state and almost all our engineering
tests were open book i could remember the page and not the formula
but as soon as i saw the formula i could remember the whole method
if i if i'd learned it
yeah you know so it's just a funny
or some people could
you know i i
swatched
friends
like flipping
through the book trying to find the formula
even knowing that they'd done just as much work
and i would just open the book i was on page 27
about half i could see the whole thing visually
yeah
and you know
and you have to learn that about
yourself
and figure out what to do with the
function
optimally
i had a friend who he was always concerned
he didn't know how he came up with ideas
he had lots of ideas but he said they just sort of popped up
like you'd be working on something having this idea like where does it come from
but you can have more awareness of it like like
like
like how you
how your brain works is a little murky
as you go down
from the voice
in your head or the obvious
visualizations
like when you visualize something how does that happen
yes you know if i say you know visualize volcano
it's easy to do right
and what does it actually look like when you visualize
it i can visualize
to the point where i don't see
very much out of my eyes and i see the colors
of the thing i'm
visualizing
yeah but there's like a
there's a shape there's a texture
there's a color but there's also conceptual
visualization
like
what are you actually visualizing
when you're visualizing volcano
just like with peripheral vision you think you see the whole thing yeah yeah
that's a good way to say it you know you have this kind of
almost peripheral vision of your visualizations
they're like these ghosts
but if you know if you
if you work
on it you can get a pretty high
level
of detail
and somehow you can walk along those visualizations to come up with an idea which is
but weird but when you're thinking about solving problems
like you're you're putting information and you're exercising the stuff you do know
you're sort of teasing the area that's you don't understand and don't know
but you can almost you know feel
you know that process happening you know that's that's how i like
like like i know sometimes when i'm working really hard on something like
like i get really hot when i'm sleeping and you know it's like
we got the blank throw i wake up all the blankets are on the floor
and you know every time it's while i wake up and think wow that was great
you know are you able to
to reverse engineer what the hell happened there oh sometimes it's vivid dreams and sometimes
it's this kind of like you say like shadow
thinking that you you sort of have this feeling
you're
you're going through this stuff but it's it's not that obvious
isn't that so amazing that the mind just does all these little
experiments
i never
you know i thought i always thought
it's like a river that you can't you're just there for the ride
but you're right if you prep it
no it's all understandable
meditation
really helps
you you got to start figuring out you need to learn language of your own mind
and there's multiple levels of it
but the abstractions again right it's somewhat comprehensible
and observable and
feelable or whatever the right word is no it's
you know you're not long for the ride you are the ride
i have to ask you hardware engineer working on neural networks now
what's consciousness what the hell is that thing is that
is that just some little weird quirk of our particular
computing device
or is it something fundamental
that we really need to crack open if we're to
to build like good computers
do you ever think about consciousness
like why it feels like something to be i know it's it's it's really weird
so yeah
i mean everything about it is weird first it's a half a second behind reality
right it's a post-hoc narrative about what happened you've already done stuff
by the time you're conscious of it
and your consciousness
generally is a single threaded thing but we know your brain is 10 billion neurons
running some crazy
parallel thing
and there's a really big sorting
thing going on there it also seems to be really reflective
in the sense that
you create a space in your head right like we don't really see anything right like
photons hit your eyes it gets turned into signals it goes through multiple layers the neurons
you know like
i'm so curious that you know that looks glassy
and that looks not glassy
like like how the resolution
of your vision is so high you have to go through all this processing
yeah where for most of it it looks nothing like vision
okay like like there's no theater in your mind
right so we we have a world in our heads
we're literally just isolated
behind our sensors but we can look at it speculate about it speculate about alternatives
problem solve what if you know there's so many things going on
and that process is lagging reality
and it's single threaded
even though the underlying thing is like massively parallel so it's so
curious
so imagine you're building an ai computer if you wanted to replicate
humans well you'd have huge arrays of neural networks and
apparently only six or seven deep which
clarious
they only remember seven numbers but i think we can upgrade that a lot
right and then
somewhere in there
you would train the network to create basically
the world that you live in
right so like tell stories to itself about the world that it's perceiving
well create this create the world tell stories in the world
and then have many dimensions
of
you know
like sideshows to it like we have an emotional structure like we have a biological
structure
and that seems hierarchical too like
like if you're hungry it dominates your thinking if you're mad it dominates your thinking
like
and we don't know if that's important to consciousness or not but it certainly
disrupts
you know in truths in the consciousness
like so there's lots of structure to that
and
we like to dwell
on the past
we like to think about the future
we like to imagine
we'd like to fantasize
right and the somewhat circular observation of that is the thing we call consciousness
now if you created
a computer
system
it did all things create
world views
created
future
alternate
histories
you know dwelled on past events you know accurately or semi-accurately
you know it's it's
consciousness just bring up like natural well would that feel look and feel conscious to you
like do you think
do you think the thing that looks conscious is conscious like do you
again this is like an engineering kind of question i think because
like
if we want to engineer consciousness is it okay to engineer something that just looks conscious
or is it is there a difference between well we have all consciousness
because it's a super effective way to manage our affairs
yeah it's right the social development yeah well it gives us the planning system
you know we have a huge amount of stuff
like when we're talking
like the reason we can talk really fast is we're modeling
each other a really
high level of detail and consciousness
is required for that right and well
all those components together manifest consciousness
right so if we make intelligent
beings that we want to interact with that we're like
you know wondering what they're thinking you know you know looking forward to seeing them
you know when they interact with them they they're interesting surprising
you know fascinating
you know
they will probably
feel conscious like we do and we'll we'll perceive them as conscious
i don't know why not but you never know another fun question on this because
in in from a computing perspective we're trying to create something that's human-like or superhuman-like
let me ask you about aliens aliens
do you think there's intelligent alien civilizations out there and do you think their
technology their computing their ai bots
their their chips are of the same nature as ours
yeah i got i have no idea
i mean
if there's lots of aliens out there they've been awfully quiet
you know there's there's speculation about why
there seems to be more than enough planets out there there's a lot yeah
um
there's intelligent life on this planet that seems quite different you know like
you know dolphins seem like plausibly understandable octopuses don't seem understandable at all
if they live longer than a year maybe they would be running the planet
they seem really smart and their neural architecture is completely different than ours
now who knows how they perceive things
i mean that's the question is for us intelligent
beings who might not be able to perceive other kinds of intelligence
if they become sufficiently different than us so yeah
we live in the current constrained world that you know it's three-dimensional geometry
and the geometry defines a certain amount of physics
and you know you know there's like how time works seems to work
like there's so many things that
seem like a whole bunch of the input parameters
to the you know another conscious being are the same
yes like if it's biological biological things seem to be in a relatively narrow temperature range
right because you know organic stones aren't stable too cold or too hot
you know so so there's if you specified the list of things that
input to that but as soon as we make really smart
you know beings
and they go solve
about how to think about a billion
numbers
at the same time
and
and how to think in n
there's a funny science fiction book where the all the society had uploaded into this matrix
and at some point some some of the beans in the matrix thought
i wonder if there's intelligent life out there
so they had to do a whole bunch of work to figure
out
like how to make a physical
thing
because their matrix was self-sustaining
and they made a little spaceship
and they traveled to another planet when they got there there was like life running around
but there was no intelligent life
and then they figured out that there was these huge
you know organic matrix all over the planet inside there where intelligent beings had uploaded themselves
into that matrix
so everywhere intelligent life was as soon as it got smart
it up leveled itself into something way more interesting than 3d geometry and yeah it escaped
whatever this is not escaped
better yeah the the essence of what we think of as an intelligent being
i tend to like the
thought experiment of
the organism like humans aren't the organisms
i like the notion of like richard dawkins and memes that
ideas themselves are the organisms
like that are just using our minds to evolve so like we're just like meat receptacles
for ideas to breed and multiply and so on and maybe those are the aliens yes
so
jordan peterson
has a line says
you know you think you have ideas but ideas have you
yeah right good line which
and and then we know about the phenomena of groupthink
and there's so many things that constrain us
but i think you can examine all that and not be
completely owned by the ideas and completely sucked into groupthink
and part of your responsibility as a as a human
is to escape that kind of phenomena
which isn't
you know it's you know it's it's one of the creative tension things again you're constructed
by it
but you can still observe
it and you can think about it and you can make choices
about
to some level
how constrained you are by it
and you know it's useful to do that
and
but but at the same time
and it could be by doing that
that you know
the
the the group and society
you're
you're part of becomes collectively even more interesting
so you know so the outside observer will think wow
you know all these lexus running around with all these really independent
ideas have created
something even more interesting
and aggregate
so
so i so i don't know i'm
those are lenses to look at the situation
but i'll give you some inspiration but i don't think they're constrained
right you know as a small little quirk of history it seems like you're
related to jordan peterson like you mentioned he's going through some rough stuff now
is there some comment you can make about the the roughness of the human journey
the ups and downs
well
i i became an expert in benzo withdrawal
like which is you took benzodiazepines and at some point they interact with gaba circuits
you know to reduce anxiety and do 100 other things like there's actually
no known list of everything
they do because they interact with so many parts of your body
and then once you're on them you habituate
to them and you're you're
you have a dependency
it's not like you're a drug dependency we're trying to get high it's a
it's a
metabolic dependency
and then if you discontinue them
there's a funny thing called kindling
which is if you stop
them and then go you know you'll have a horrible it's for all symptoms
if you go back on them at the same level you won't be stable
and
that unfortunately happened to him
because it's so deeply
integrated
into all the kinds of systems
in the body it literally
changes
the size and numbers
of
neurotransmitter
sites in your brain yeah
so there's a there's a
process called the ashton protocol where you taper it down slowly over two years
to people go through that goes through unbelievable
hell
and what jordan went through seemed to be worse because
the on advice of doctors you know we'll stop taking these and take this
it was the disaster
and
he got some yeah it was pretty tough
um
he seems to be doing quite a bit better intellectually
you can see his brain clicking back together
i spent a lot of time with i've never seen anybody suffer so much
well his brain is also like this powerhouse right so i wonder
does a brain
that's able to think deeply about the world suffer more through these kinds of withdrawals like
i don't know i've watched videos of people going through withdrawal
they they all seem to suffer
unbelievably
and you know my work goes out to everybody
and there's some funny math about this some doctors said as best you can tell
you know there's the standard recommendations
don't take them for more than a month and then taper over a couple of weeks
many doctors prescribe them endlessly which is against the protocol but it's common
right and then
something like 75 percent of people when they taper it's you know
half the people have difficulty but 75
get off okay
20 have severe difficulty and 5 have life-threatening difficulty
and if you're one of those it's really bad
and the stories that people have on this is
heartbreaking
and
tough
so you put some of the fault that the doctors
that just not know what the hell they're doing oh no
it's hard to say it's
it's one of those commonly prescribed things like one doctor said what happens is
if you're prescribed them for a reason and then you have a hard time getting off
the protocol basically says you're either crazy or dependent
and you get kind of pushed into
a different treatment regime you're a drug drug addict or a psychiatric patient
and so
like one doctor
said you know i prescribed
me for 10 years thinking i was helping my patients
and i realized
i was really
harming
them
and you know the awareness of that is slowly coming up
the fact that they're casually prescribed to people is horrible
and it's bloody scary
and some people are stable on them but they're on them for life
like once you know it's another one of those drugs
that
but benzo's long range have real impacts on your personality
people talk about the benzo bubble where you get disassociated
from reality and your friends a little bit
it's it's it's it's really terrible the mind is terrifying we were talking about how
how the infinite possibility of fun
but like
it's the infinite possibility of suffering too which is one of the dangers of
like expansion of the human mind it's like
i wonder if all the possible huma experiences that a intelligent computer can have
is it mostly fun or is it mostly
suffering
so like if you if you brute force expand
the set of possibilities like are you going to run into some trouble
in terms of like torture and suffering and so on
maybe our human brain is just protecting
us from
much more possible pain and suffering
maybe the space of pain
is like much larger than we could possibly imagine and that the world's in the balance
you know all the all the literature
on religion and stuff is you know the struggle between
good and evil is
is balanced versus
very finely tuned for reasons that are complicated
but that's a that's a long philosophical conversation
speaking of balance that's complicated
i i wonder because we're living through one of the more important
moments in human history with this particular virus
it seems like pandemics
have at least the ability to
kill off most of the human population
at their worst
and they're just fascinating because there's so many viruses
in this world there's so many i mean viruses
basically around the world in the sense that
they've been around very long time they're everywhere
they seem to be extremely powerful and they're just in a distributed
kind of way but at the same time they're not intelligent
and they're not even living
do you have like high level thoughts about this virus that
like in terms of you being fascinated about terrified or not somewhere in between
so i believe in frameworks right so
like one of them is the evolution
like we're evolved creatures right yes
and one of the things about evolution is it's hyper competitive
and it's not competitive
out of a sense of evil it's competitive in the sense of there's endless variation
in variations that work better when
and then over time there's so many levels of that competition
you know like multi-cellular life partly exists because of
you know the the competition between you know different kinds of life forms
and we know sex partly exists to scramble our genes so that we have
you know genetic variation against
the invasion of the bacteria and the viruses and it's endless
like
i read some funny statistic
like the density
of viruses
and bacteria in the ocean is really high
and one third of the bacteria die every day because the virus is invading them
like one-third of them
wow
like like i don't know if that number is true but it was like it's
like there's like the amount of competition
and what's going on is stunning
and there's a theory as we age we slowly accumulate
bacterias
and viruses
and as our immune system kind of
goes down you know that's what slowly kills us and
it just feels so peaceful from a human perspective
when we sit back and they're able to have a relaxed conversation
and there's wars going on out there like right now
you're you're harboring how many bacteria and you know the ones
many of them are parasites
on you and some of them are helpful and some of them are modifying
your behavior and some of them are
you know it's just really it's really wild
but you know this particular manifestation is unusual
you know in the demographic
how it hit and the political
you know response that it engendered
and you know the health care response it engendered
and the technology
it's gendered it's kind of wild
yeah the communication
on twitter that it
every level all that kind of stuff at every single level yeah but but
what usually kills life the big extinctions
are caused by
meteors and volcanoes
that's the one you're worried about as opposed to human-created bombs
solar flares are another good one
you know occasionally solar flares hit the planet
so it's nature
oh yes yeah it's all pretty wild
on another historic moment this is perhaps outside but perhaps within your
space of frameworks that you think about that just happened
i guess a couple weeks ago is um
i don't know if you're paying attention at all it's the
the game stop and
wall street bets
so it's really fascinating
there's kind of a theme to this conversation
today because it's like you know that works the
it's cool how there's a large number of people in a distributed way
almost having a kind of fun we're able to take on the powerful elites
elite hedge funds centralized powers and overpower them
do you have thoughts i mean saga
i don't know enough about finance but it was like the elon
you know robin hood guy when they talked yeah what do you think about that
well the robin guy didn't know how the finance system worked
that was clear
right he was treating like the the people who settled the transactions
as a black box
and suddenly somebody called him up and said hey black box calling you
your transaction
volume
means you need to put up three billion
dollars
right now and he's like i don't have three billion dollars
like i don't even make any money on these trades
why do i owe three billion
dollars while you're sponsoring
the trade
so so there was a set of abstractions
that
you know i don't think either like like now he understands
it like this happens in chip design like
you buy wafers from tsmc
or samsung or intel
and
you know they say it works
like this and you do your design
based on that and then chip comes back and doesn't work
and then suddenly you start having to open the black boxes
like the transistors
really work like they said you know what's the real issue
so
so the
there's a whole set of things that created this opportunity and somebody spotted it now
people spot these kinds of opportunities all the times there's been flash crashes there's been
you know there's always short squeezes are fairly regular
every ceo i know hates the shorts
because they're they're manipulating
they're trying to manipulate their stock in a way that they make money
and you know deprive value from both this you know the company and the investors
so the fact that
you know some of these stocks were so short it's hilarious
that this hasn't happened before i don't know why and i don't actually know why
some serious hedge funds didn't do it to other hedge funds
and some of the hedge funds actually made a lot of money on this yes
so
my my guess is we know five percent of what really happened
and that a lot of the players don't know what happened and
the people who probably made the most money aren't the people that they're talking about
yeah that's
do you think there was something
i mean this is the this is the cool kind of
elon
you're the same kind of conversationalist
which is like first principles questions of like what the hell happened
just very basic questions of like was there something shady going on
what
you know who are the parties
involved
it's the basic
questions
that everybody
wants to know about
yeah so like we're in a very hyper competitive
world right but transactions like buying and selling stock is a trust event
you know i trust the company representing themselves properly
you know i bought the stock because i think it's going to go up
i trust that the regulations are solid
now inside of that there's all kinds of places where you know humans over trust and
you know this this expose let's say some weak points in the system
i don't know
if it's going to get corrected i don't know if the
i don't know if we have close to the real story
yeah my suspicion is we don't
yeah and listen to that guy he was like a little wide-eyed
about and then he did this and then they did that and it was like
i think you should know more about that your business than that
but again there's many businesses when like this layer is really stable
you stop paying attention to it
you pay attention to the stuff that's bugging you or new
you don't pay attention
to the stuff that just seems to work all the time you just
you know the sky's blue every day california
and where once a while the continued rains there was like what do we do
somebody go bring in the lawn furniture
you know like
it's getting
wet
we don't know it's getting wet
yeah it doesn't it was blue for like 100
days and now it's
you know so
but
part of the problem here with vlad this the ceo of robin hood is the scaling
is that what we've been talking about is
there's a lot of
unexpected things that happen with the scaling and you have to be
i think the scaling forces you to then return to the fundamentals
well it's interesting because when you buy and sell stocks the scaling
is you know the stocks
only move in a certain
range
and if you buy a stock you can only lose that amount of money
on the short short market you can lose a lot more than you can benefit
like it has a it has a weird
cost you know cost function or whatever the right word for that is
so he was trading in a market where he wasn't actually capitalized
for the downside
if it got outside a certain range
now whether something the various has happened i have no idea but at some point the
financial risk to both him and his customers was way outside of his financial capacity
and his understanding how the system work was clearly
weak or or he didn't represent himself i you know i don't know the person
when i listened to him nick
yeah it could have been the surprise question was like and then these guys called and
you know it sounded like
he was treating stuff as a black box
maybe he shouldn't have
but maybe his whole pilot
expert somewhere
else and it was going on i don't i don't know
yep
i mean this is
this is one of the qualities
of
a good leader is under fire you have to perform
and that means to think clearly and to speak clearly
and he dropped the ball on those things because
and understand the problem quickly learn and understand the problem like at this like
basic level like what the hell happened
and my guess is
you know at some level it was amateurs trading against
you know expert slash insiders slash people with you know special information
outsiders is insiders
yeah and the insiders
you know my guess is the next time this happens we'll make money on it
the insiders always win
well they have more tools and more incentive i mean this always happens like the outsiders
are doing this for fun the insiders are doing this 24 7.
but there's numbers in the outsiders
this is the interesting thing well there's numbers on the insiders too
like different kind of numbers different kind of numbers
but this could be a new era
because
i don't know at least i didn't
expect
that
a bunch of redditors
could you know there's
you know millions of people who can get together
the next one won't be a surprise
but don't you think the the the crowd the people are planning the next attack
we'll see but it has to be a surprise can't be the same game
as to the end
it could be there's
a very large number of games to play and they can be
agile
about it i don't know i'm not an expert
right that's a good question how the space of games how how restricted is it
yeah and the system is so complicated it could be relatively unrestricted
and also like you know during the last couple financial crashes
you know what set it off was you know sets of derivative events where
you know the you know nasim talibs
you know thing is they're they're they're trying to lower
volatility
in the short run but creating tail events
and systems always evolve towards that and then they always crash like
the gas curve is the
you know
star low
ramp
plateau
crash
it's 100 effective
in the long run let me ask you some advice to put on your profound hat
what
there's a bunch of young folks to listen to this
thing for no good reason whatsoever
undergraduate students maybe high school students maybe just young folks a young at heart looking for
the next steps to taking
life what advice
would you give to a young person
today
about
life
maybe career but also life in general
get good at some stuff
well get to know yourself right
get good at something that you're actually interested
in you have to love what you're doing to get good at it
you really got to find that don't waste all your time
doing stuff that's just
boring
or bland
or numbing
right don't let old people screw you
well people get talked into doing all kinds of and wrapping up huge student
you know student debts and
like there's so much crap going on
you know and then it drains your time
and drains
yeah the eric weinstein
you know thesis that you know the older generation
will let go
yeah and they're trapping all the young people
i think there's some truth to that yeah sure
just because you're old doesn't mean you stop thinking i know lots of really original
yeah old people
i'm an old person
so
um
but you have to be conscious about it you can fall into the ruts and then
do that you know when i hear
young people spouting opinions that sounds like they come from fox news or cnn
i think they've been captured by
groupthink
and memes and
supposed to think on their own you know so
if you find yourself repeating what everybody else is saying
you're not going to have a good life
like like that's not how the world works it may be
it seems safe but it puts you at great jeopardy for
well being boring
or unhappy
or how long did it take you to find the thing that
you have fun with
well i don't know
i've been a fun person since i was pretty little
so everything
i've gone through a couple periods of depression
in my life
for a good reason or for the reason that doesn't make any sense
yeah
like some some things are hard like you go through mental transitions in high school
i was really depressed for a year and
i think i had my first midlife crisis at 26.
i kind of thought is this all there is like i was
working at a job that i loved
and but i was going to work and all my time is consumed
what's what's the escape out of that depression what's the answer to is is
this all there is well
a
friend of mine
i
asked him because he was working
his ass
off i said what's your
work-life
balance
like
like there's
you know work friends family personal time
are you bouncing in that and he said work 80 family 20 and i try to
i try to find some time to sleep
like there's no personal time there's no passion at a time
because you know young people are often passionate about work
so and i was certainly like that
but you need to you need to have some space in your life for different things
and that's that creates
that makes you resistant to the whole
the the the dip
the the deep dips into depression
kind of thing yeah well you have to get to know yourself too meditation
helps
some physical
something physically intense helps
like the weird
places your mind goes kind of thing like and why does it happen
why do you do what you do like triggers
like
the things that cause your mind to go to different places
kind of thing or
events
like
you're upbringing
for better or worse whether your parents are great people or not
you
you come into
you know adulthood with all kinds of emotional burdens
yeah and you can see some people are so bloody stiff and restrained
and they think you know the world's fundamentally
negative
like you maybe
you have unexplored territory yeah or you're afraid of something
definitely afraid of quite a few things then you gotta go face them
like like what's the worst thing that happened you're going to die right
like that's inevitable you might as well get over that like a 100 death rate
like people were worried about the virus but you know the human condition is pretty deadly
there's something about embarrassment
let's see i've competed a lot in my life and
i think the
if i'm too introspected
the thing i'm most afraid of is
being like humiliated
i think nobody cares about that look you're the only
person on the planet zack cares about you being humiliated
exactly
it's like a really useless
thought
it is
it's like
you're all humiliating
something
happened
in a room full of people
and they walk
out and they didn't think
about
it one
more
second
or maybe
somebody
told a funny
story to somebody
else and then it just
hates
it throughout
yeah
yeah now i know it too i mean
i've been really embarrassed about that nobody cared about myself
yeah it's a funny thing so the worst thing ultimately is just
yeah but that's the cage
and then you have to get out of it yeah
like once you here's the thing once you find something like that
you have to be determined to break it
because otherwise you'll just you know slowly accumulate
that kind of junk and then you die as a
you know a mess
so
the goal i guess it's so
it's like a cage with
a cage i guess the goal is to die in the biggest
possible
cage
well ideally you have no cage
people do get enlightened i've got a few it's great
you found a few there's a few out there i don't know of course
um
either that or they have you know it's a great sales
pitch there's like enlightened
people
writing books and doing all kinds of stuff
it's a good way to sell a book
i'll
give you that you've never met somebody
you just thought
they just killed me like this
like like mental clarity humor
no 100
but i just feel like they're living in a bigger cage they have their own
they don't think there's a cage they're still okay you secretly
suspect
there's always the case
ah there's no there's nothing outside the the unit there's nothing outside the cage [laughter]
you were you worked in a bunch of companies you led a lot of amazing teams
um i don't
i'm not sure if you've ever been like at the early stages of a startup
but do you have advice for
somebody that wants to do a startup or build a company
like build a strong team of engineers that are passionate just want to
solve a big problem like is there more specifically on that point
well you have to be really good at stuff
if you're going to lead and build a team
you better be really interested in how people work and think
the people
or the solution
to the problems
there's two things
right
one is how people
work
and the other is
actually
there's there's quite a few successful
startups it's pretty clear the founders don't know anything about people
like the idea was so powerful that it propelled them but i suspect somewhere
early they they hired some people who understood people
because people really need a lot of care and feeding to collaborate
and work together and feel engaged and work hard
you know like startups are all about out producing other people
like you're nimble because you don't have any legacy
you don't have
you know a bunch of people who are depressed about life you know just showing up
you know so startups have a lot of advantages that way
you know do you like the the steve jobs talked about this idea of
a players and b players i don't know if you
know this formulation yeah no
um organizations that get taken over by pb player leaders
often really underperform their rc players that said in big organizations
there's
so much work to do
like
and there's so many people who are happy
to do what you know like the leadership
or the big idea people who can see it consider menial jobs
and you know you need a place for them but you need an organization that
both values and rewards them but doesn't let them take over the leadership of it
got it but so so you need to have an organization that's resistant to that but
in the early days
the the notion with with steve was that
like one b player in a room
of a players will be like destructive
to the whole i've seen that happen i i don't know if it's like always true
like
you know you you run into people who are clearly
b players but they think they're very
players
and so they have a loud voice
at the table
and they make lots of demands
for that
but there's other people are like i know who i am
i just want to work with you know cool people and cool
and just tell me what to do and i'll go get it done
yeah you know so you have to again this is like people skills like
what kind of person is it you know i've met some really great
people i love working with
that weren't the biggest id people the most productive
ever but they show up they get it done
you know they create connection and community that people value it's it's
it's pretty diverse so i don't think there's a recipe for that
i gotta ask you about love
i heard you're into this now
into this love thing yeah
is this is you think this is your solution to your depression
no i'm just trying to like you said the enlightened
people on occasion
trying to sell a book i'm writing a book about
love you're writing a book about me no
i'm not
a
friend of mine he's gonna
somebody said you should really write a book about your you know your management philosophy
he said it'd be a short book [laughter]
well that one was all pretty well
what role do you think love family friendship all that kind of
human stuff play in a successful life you've been exceptionally successful in the space of
like running teams building cool in this world creating some amazing things
what did love get in the way did love help
the family get in the way to family help friendship you want the engineer's answer
please so but first love is functional right
it's functional in what way so we habituate ourselves to the environment
and actually jordan told me jordan peterson told me this line
so
you go through life and you just get used to everything
except
for the things you love
they they remain new
like this is really useful for you know
like like other people's children and dogs and you know trees
you just don't pay that much attention to your own kids you monitor them really closely
like and if they go off a little bit because you love them if you're smart
if you're going to be a successful parent you notice it right away you don't habituate
to
just things you love
and if you want to be successful at work if you don't love it
you're not going to put the time in somebody else
it's somebody else that loves it like
because it's new and interesting
and that lets you go to the next level
so it's the thing it's just a function that generates newness and novelty
and surprises you know those kind of things
it's really interesting
but and there's people
figured out lots of you know frameworks
for this you know like
like humans
seem to go in partnership
go through you know interest like somebody suddenly somebody's interesting
and then you're infatuated with them and then you're in love with them
and then you you know
different people have
ideas
about parental
love
or mature
like you go through a cycle
of that
which keeps us together and it's you know super functional for creating families and
and creating communities
and making you support somebody despite the fact that you don't love them
like and
and
it can be really enriching
you know now in the work life balance scheme if all you do is work
you think you may be optimizing
your work potential
but if you don't love your work or you don't have
family and friends and things you care about
your brain isn't well balanced
like everybody
knows the experience
of you works on something
all week you went home and took two days
off and you came back
in
the odds of you working on the thing you
picking up right where you left off is zero
your brain refactored it
but being in blood is great
it's like changes the color of the light in the room
it creates a spaciousness that's that's different it helps you think
it makes you strong
buckowski
had this line about love being a fog that dissipates with the first light of reality
in the morning it's that's depressing i think it's the other way around
it lasts
well you like you said it's a function
it's a thing that just be the light that actually
enlivens
your world and creates the interest and the power and the strength and the
to go do something
well it's like
like that sounds like
you know there's like physical love emotional of intellectual
love spiritually yeah right isn't it all the same thing kind of nope
you should differentiate that maybe that's your problem
in your book you should you should refine that a little bit different chapters
yeah there's different
chapters
what's that what's
these
are there aren't these
are just different
layers
of the same thing
the stack
no physical people people
some people are addicted to physical love and they have no idea about emotional or intellectual
love
i don't know if they're the same thing so i think they're different
that's
true they could be different
it'd
be
it
i
guess the ultimate
goal is for it to be the same well if you want something
to be bigger and interesting
you should find all its components
and differentiate
them not climb it together
people do this all the time they yeah and the modularity
get your abstraction layers right and then you can you have room to breathe
well maybe you can write the forward to my book about love
yeah or the afterwards
and the after you really tried
i feel like lex has made a lot of progress in this book but
well you have things in your life that you love yeah
yeah you know so and they are you're right they're modular it's
and you can have multiple
things with the same person or the same thing and yeah but
yeah depending on the moment of the day yeah there's
like what bukowski
described
as that moment you go from being in love to having
a different kind of love yeah
right and that's the transition
but when it happens
if you read the owner's manual and you believed it you would have said
oh this happened
it doesn't mean it's not love it's a different kind of love
but
but maybe there's something better about that as you grow old if
all you do is regret
how you used to be it's sad
right you should have learned a lot of things because
like who you can be in your future self is
is actually more interesting and possibly delightful than
you know being a mad kid in love with the the next person like
that's super fun when it happens but
that's that's you know five percent of the possibility
yeah that's right that there's a lot more fun to be had
in the long lasting stuff
yeah or meaning you know if that's me
which is a kind of fun
it's a deeper kind of fun and it's surprising you know that's
like like the thing i like is surprises
you know and you just never know what's gonna happen
yeah
but you have to look carefully
and you have to work at it you have to think about
it and
you know it's
yeah you have to see the surprises
when they happen right you have to be looking for it
from the branching perspective
you mentioned regrets
do you have regrets about your own trajectory oh yeah of course
yeah some of it's painful but you want to hear the painful stuff
i'd say like in terms of working with people
when people did say stuff i didn't like especially if it was a bit nefarious
i took it personally and i also
felt it was personal about them
but a lot of times like humans are you know most humans are a mess
right and then they act out and they do stuff
and i this psychologist
i heard a long time ago said
you tend to think somebody does something to you
but
really what they're doing is they're doing
what they're doing
while they're in front of you
it's not that much about you
yeah right and as i got more interested in
you know when i work with people i think about them and probably analyze them
and understand them a little bit and then when they do stuff i'm way less surprised
and i'm wait you know and if it's bad i'm way less hurt
and i react way less
like i sort of expect everybody's got their
yeah and it's not about you it's not about me that much
it's like you know
you know you do something and you think you're embarrassed
but nobody cares
like and somebody's really mad at you at the odds of it being about
you
yeah no they're getting mad the way they're doing that because of some pattern they learned
and you know and maybe you can help them
if you care enough about
it but
or you could step you could see it coming
and step
out of the way
like
like i wish i was way better at that i'm i'm a bit of a hothead
and and
you said with steve that was a feature not a bug
yeah well he was using it as the counter force the orderliness
that would crush his work well you were doing the same
yeah
maybe i don't think i don't think my
my vision was big enough
it was more like i just got pissed off
and did stuff
i'm sure that's just yeah yeah you're telling me i don't know if it had the
it didn't have the amazing
effect
of creating
the trillion dollar
company
it was more like i just got pissed
off and left
and or
made enemies that he shouldn't have been
yeah it's hard
like i didn't really understand politics until i worked at apple
where you know steve was a master player of politics
and his staff had to be or they wouldn't survive them and
it was definitely part of the culture
and then i've been in companies where they say it's political but it's all
you know fun and games compared to apple and it's not that
the people apple are bad people it's just they operated politically at a higher level
you know it's not like oh somebody said something bad about somebody
somebody else which is most politics
it's you know they they had strategies about accomplishing their goals
sometimes you know
over the dead bodies of their enemies
you know
with some communication
yeah more game of thrones and sophistication
and like a big time factor rather than a
you know well that requires a lot of control over your emotions i think
to do to have a bigger strategy in the way you behave
yeah and it's it's it's
effective
in the sense that coordinating
thousands of people to do really hard things
where many of the people in there don't understand themselves much less how they're participating
yeah creates all kinds of
you know drama and problems
that you know our solution is political in nature
like how do you convince
people how do you leverage them how do you motivate
them how do you get rid of them how you know like there's
there's so many layers
of that that are interesting
and even though some some of it let's say may be tough
it's not
evil
unless you know you use that skill to evil purposes which some people obviously do but
but it's a skill set that operates you know and i wish i'd
you know i was interested
in it but i you know it was sort of like i'm an engineer
i do my thing
and you know there's there's times when i could have way bigger impact
if i you know knew how to
if i paid more attention and knew more about that
about the human layer of the stack yeah that human political
power you know expression layer of the stack which is complicated
and there's lots
to know about
it
i mean people
are good at it are just
amazing
and when they're good at it and let's say
relatively
kind and oriented in a good direction you can really feel
it can get lots of stuff done and coordinate things you never thought possible
but all people like that also have some pretty hard edges because
you know it's it's a heavy lift
and i wish i'd spent more time with that when i was younger but
but maybe i wasn't ready you know i was a wide-eyed kid for 30 years
it's a little bit of a kid i know what do you hope
your legacy is when there's a
when there's a book like a hitchhiker's
guide to the galaxy and this is like a one sentence entry ball jim caller
from like that guy lived at some point
there's not many you know not many people be remembered
you're one of the sparkling little
human creatures
that had a big impact on the world
how do you hold you'll be remembered my daughter was trying to get
she added my wikipedia page to say that i was a legend and a guru
but they took it out so she put it back in she's 15.
i think i think that was probably the best part of my legacy [laughter]
she got her sister they were all excited
they were like trying to put it in the references
because there's articles
in that and they're telling you that
so the eyes of your kids your
legend
well they're pretty skeptical because they'll be better than that they're like dad
so yeah that's
that's stupid that kind of stuff is super fun
in terms of the big legends stuff anchor
okay legacy i don't really care you're just an engineer
no they've been thinking about building a big pyramid
so i had a debate with a friend about whether pyramids or craters are cooler
and you realize that
there's craters
everywhere but you know they built a couple of pyramids
five thousand years ago in there and they remember you
think that would be foreign
those aren't easy to build oh i know
and they don't actually know how they built them which is great
it's either agi or aliens could be involved so i think
i think you're gonna have to figure out quite a few more things than just
the basics of civil engineering
so i guess you hope your legacy is pyramids
that would that would be cool
and my wikipedia page you know getting updated by my daughter periodically
like those two things would pretty much make it
jim it's a huge
honor talking
to you again
i hope we talk many more times
in the future
i can't wait to see
what you do with tennis torrent i can't wait to use it
i can't wait for you to revolutionize
yet another space in computing
it's a huge honor to talk to you thanks for talking today this was fun
thanks for listening to this conversation with jim keller and thank you to our sponsors
athletic greens all-in-one nutrition drink
brooklyn and sheetz
expressvpn
and bel campbell grass-fed meat
click the sponsor links to get a discount and to support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words from alan turing
those who can imagine anything can create the impossible
thank you for listening and hope to see you next
time
you