the following is a conversation with jim keller legendary
microprocessor engineer who has worked at amd apple tesla
and now intel he's known for his work on amd k 7 k 8 k 12
and xen microarchitectures apple a4 and a5 processors
and co-author of the specification for the x86 64 instruction
set and hyper transport interconnect he's
a brilliant first principles engineer
and out-of-the-box thinker
and just an interesting
and fun human being to talk to this is the artificial intelligence podcast
if you enjoy it subscribe
on youtube give it five stars an apple podcast follow
on spotify supported on patreon
or simply connect with me on twitter alex
friedman spelled fri d ma a.m. i recently
started doing ads at the end of the introduction
i'll do one or two minutes
after introducing the episode
and never any ads in the middle that can break the flow of the conversation i
hope that works for you and doesn't hurt the listening experience
this show is presented by cash app the number one finance
i up in the app store i personally
use cash app to send money to friends but you can also use it to buy sell
and deposit bitcoin in just seconds cash
app also has a new investing feature you
can buy fractions of a stock say $1 worth no
matter what the stock price is brokers
services are provided by cash app investing a subsidiary of square
and member si pc i'm
excited to be working with cash app to support one of my favorite organizations called first best
known for their first robotics
and lego competitions they educate
and inspire hundreds of thousands of students in over 110
countries and have a perfect rating a charity navigator which
means that donated money is used to maximum effectiveness when
you get cash app from the app store google play
and use code lex podcast you'll
get ten dollars and cash app will also donate ten dollars to the first which
again is an organization
that i've personally seen inspire girls
and boys the dream of engineering a better world
and
now here's my with jim keller
what are the differences in similarities
between the human brain and a computer with
the microprocessors core let's
start with a philosophical question perhaps well
since people don't actually understand
how human brains work i think
that's true i think that's true so
it's hard to compare them computers are
you know there's really two things there's memory and there's computation right
and to date almost all computer architectures are global memory which is a thing right
and then computation
where you pull data and you do relatively simple operations on it and write data back
so it's decoupled in modern in modern computers
and you think in the human brain everything's
a mesh a mess that's combined together what
people observe is there's you know some number of layers of neurons
which have local
and global connections
and information is stored in some distributed fashion
and people build things called neural networks in computers
where the information is distributed in some kind of fashion you know there's a mathematics behind it i
don't know that the understandings that is super deep the computations we run on those are straightforward computations
i don't believe anybody has said a neuron does this computation
so
to date it's hard to compare them i
would say so let's get into the basics before we zoom back out
how do you build a computer from scratch
what is a microprocessor
what is it microarchitecture
what's an instruction set architecture maybe
even as far back as what is a transistor
so
the special charm of computer engineering is there's a relatively good understanding of abstraction layers
so down to bottom you have atoms
and atoms get put together in materials like silicon
or dope silicon
or metal
and we build transistors on top of that we build logic gates
right and in functional units like an adder or subtractor or an instruction parsing unit
and we assemble those into you know processing elements modern computers are built out of you
know probably 10 to 20 locally
you know organic processing elements
or coherent processing elements
and then that runs computer programs right
so there's abstraction layers and then software
you know there's an instruction set you run and then there's assembly language c c++ java javascript
you know there's abstraction layers you
know essentially from the atom to the data center right
so when you when you build a computer
you know first there's a target like what's it for look
how fast does it have to be which you
know today there's a whole bunch of metrics about what that is and then
in an organization of you know a thousand people who build a computer there's
lots of different disciplines that
you have to operate on does that make sense and so
so
there's a bunch of levels abstraction of in in organizational
i can tell and in your own vision there's
a lot of brilliance that comes in it every one of those layers some
of it is science some was engineering some of his art what's the most
if you could pick favorites what's the most important your favorite layer on
these layers of abstractions
where does the magic enter this hierarchy i
don't really care that's
the fun you know i'm somewhat agnostic to that so i would say for
relatively long periods of time instruction sets are stable
so the x86 instruction said the arm instruction set what's
an instruction set so it says how do you encode the basic operations load store multiply add subtract conditional
branch you know there
aren't that many interesting instructions look
if you look at a program
and it runs you
know 90% of the execution is on 25 opcodes you know 25 instructions
on those are stable right
what does it mean stable until architecture has been around for twenty-five years it
works it works and that's because the basics you
know or defined a long time ago right
now the way an old computer ran is you fetched instructions and you executed them in order to
the load do the ad do the compare the
way a modern computer works is you fetch large numbers of instructions say 500
and then you find the dependency graph between the instructions
and then you you execute in independent units those little micro graphs
so a modern computer like people like to say computers should be simple
and clean
but it turns out the market for a simple complete clean slow computers is zero right
we don't sell any simple clean computers
now you can there's
how you build it can be clean
but the computer people want to buy that's say you know phone or data center
such as
a large number of instructions computes the dependency graph and then
executes it in a way that gets the right answers
and optimizes that graph somehow
yeah they run deeply out of order
and then there's
semantics around how memory ordering
works and other things work so the the computer sort of has a bunch of bookkeeping
tables it says what order cds operations finishing
or appear to finish him but to go fast you have to fetch a lot of instructions
and find all the parallelism
now there's a second kind of computer
which we call gpus today
and i called the difference there's
found parallelism like you have a program with a lot of dependent instructions you
fetch a bunch and then you go figure out the dependency graph and you issues instructions out order that's
because you have one serial narrative to execute
which
in fact is and can be done out of order you call a narrative
yeah well
so
yeah so humans think of serial narrative
so read read a book right
there's a you know there's the sends after sentence after sentence
and there's paragraphs
now you could diagram that imagine you diagrammed it properly
and you said
which sentences could be read in anti order any order without changing the meaning right
but that's a fascinating question to ask of a book yeah
yeah you could do that right
so some paragraphs could be reordered some sentences can be reordered you could say he is tall
and smart
and x right
and it doesn't matter the order of tall and smart
but
if you say is that tall man who's
wearing a red shirt what
colors you know like
you can create dependencies right right
and so
gpus on the other hand run simple programs on pixels
but you're given a million of them and the first order the screen
you're looking at it doesn't care which order you do it in so
i call that given parallelism simple
narratives around the large numbers of things
where you can just say it's parallel
because you told me it was so found parallelism
where the narrative is it's sequential
but you discover like
little pockets of parallelism of versus turns out large pockets of parallelism large
so
how hard is it to discuss well how hard is it that's just transistor count right
so once you crack the problem you say here's
how you fetch ten instructions at a time here's
how you calculated the dependencies between them here's
how you describe the dependencies here's you know these are pieces right
so once
you describe the dependencies then it's just a graph sort of it's an algorithm that finds
what is that i'm sure there's a graph there is the theoretical answer here that's solved
well in general programs
modern programs like human beings right
how much found
parallelism is there and on that i max what is 10 next mean oh well
you execute it in order vs.
yeah you would get what's called cycles per instruction and it would be about
you know three instructions three cycles per instruction
because of the latency of the operations
and stuff
and in a modern computer excuse it but like point to 0.25
cycles per instruction so it's about with today fine 10x
and there
and there's two things one is the found parallelism in the narrative right
and the other is to predictability of the narrative right
so certain operations
they do a bunch of calculations and if greater than one do this else do that that
that decision is predicted in modern computers to high 90% accuracy
so branches
happen a lot so imagine you have you have a decision to make every six instructions
which is about the average right
but you want to fetch five under instructions
figure out the graph and execute them all in parallel that means you
have let's say if you effect 600 instructions it's every six you
have to fetch you have to predict ninety-nine out of a hundred branches correctly for
that window to be effective
okay
so parallelism you can't paralyze branches
or you can looking pretty you can what is predict a branch mean
or
what open take so imagine you do a computation over
and over you're in a loop so wow
and it's greater than one do
and you
go through that loop a million times so
every time you look at the branch you say it's
probably still greater than one he's
saying you could do that accurately very accurately monitoring
comes my mind is blown how
the heck did you that wait a minute well
you want to know this is really sad 20 years ago
yes you simply recorded
which way the branch went last time and predicted the same thing right
okay what's the accuracy of that 85%
so then somebody said
hey let's keep a couple of bits and have a little counter
so and it predicts one way we count up and then pins
so say you have a three bit counter so you count up and then
count down and if it's you know you can
use the top bit as the sign bit so you have a sign to bit number
so if it's greater than one you predict taken and lesson one you predict not-taken right
or less than zero or whatever the thing is
and that got us to 92%
oh
okay
i know is this better this branch depends on how you got there
so
if you came down the code one way you're talking about bob and jane right
and then said is just bob
like jane enoch went one way but if you're talking about
bob and jill this bob like changes
you go a different way right
so that's called history
so you take the history and a counter that's
cool but that's not how anything works today they
use something that looks a little like a neural network
so
modern you take all the execution flows and then
you do basically deep pattern recognition of how the program is executing
and
you do that multiple different ways and you have something that chooses
what the best result is there's a little supercomputer
inside the computer that's trying to project that calculates
which way branches go so
the effective window that it's worth finding grassing gets bigger
why was that gonna make me sad that's
amazing it's amazingly complicated
oh well here's the funny thing so to get to 85% took a thousand bits
to get to 99% takes
tens of megabits
so
this is one of those to
get the result you want you know to get from a window of say 50
instructions to 500 it took three orders of magnitudes
or four orders of magnitude toward bits
now
if you get the prediction of a branch wrong
what happens then what is the pipe you flush the pipes is just the performance cost
but it gets even better yeah
so we're starting to look at stuff that says
so executed down this path and then
you had two ways to go but far far
away there's something that doesn't matter which path you went
so you miss you took the wrong path you executed a bunch of stuff then
you had to miss predicting
too backed it up but you remembered
all the results you already calculated
some of those are just fine look
if you read a book and you misunderstand the paragraph your understanding is the next paragraph
sometimes is invariance i don't understand you sometimes it depends on it
and you can kind of anticipate that invariance
yeah well you can keep track of whether that data changed
and so
when you come back to a piece of code should you calculate
it again or do the same thing
okay
how much does this is art and how much of it is science
because it sounds pretty complicated so well
how do you describe a situation so
imagine you come to a point in the road we have to make a decision right
and you have a bunch of knowledge about which way to go maybe you have a map
so
you want to go is the shortest way or
do you want to go the fastest
way or you want to take the nicest road so it's just
some set of data so imagine
you're doing something complicated like a building a computer
and there's hundreds of decision points all with hundreds of possible ways to go and the
ways you pick interacts in a complicated way right
and then you have to pick the right spot right
so those are there so i don't know yeah avoided the question you just described
do the robert frost poem road
less taken i describe
the robin truss problem
which we do as computer designers it's all poetry ok great
yeah
i don't know how to describe that because some
people are very good at making those intuitive leaps it seems like the combinations of things some
people are less good at it but they're really good at evaluating your alternatives right
and everybody has a different way to do it and some people can't make those sleeps
but they're really good at analyzing it
so
when you see computers are designed by teams of people who have very different skill sets and a
good team has lots of different kinds of people
and i suspect you would describe some of them as artistic right
but not very many unfortunately
or fortunately fortunately well you know computer science hard it's 99% perspiration
and the 1% inspiration is really important
but
i need the 99
yeah you got to do a lot of work and then there's there
are interesting things to do at every level that stack
so at
the end of the day if you're on the same program multiple times does
it always produce the same result is is there some room for fuzziness there that's a math problem
so
if you run a correct c program the definition is every
time you run it you get the same answer yeah that well that's a math statement
but that's a that's a language definitional statement
so
yes for years when people did when we first did 3d acceleration of graphics
you could run the same scene multiple times and get different answers right right
and then some
people thought that was okay and some people thought it was a bad idea and then when
the hpc world used gpus for calculations
they thought it's a really bad idea okay
now in modern ai stuff people are looking at
networks
where the precision of the data is low enough that the date has somewhat noisy
and the observation as the input data is unbelievably noisy
so why should the calculation be not noisy
and people
have experimented with algorithms that say
can get faster answers by being noisy like
as the network starts to converge
if you look at the computation graph it starts out really wide and it gets narrower
and you can say is that last little bit that important
or should i start to graph on the next rap rev before
we would live all the way down to the answer right
so you can create algorithms that are noisy
now if you're developing something
and every time you run it you get a different answer it's really annoying and
so
most people think even
today every time you run the program you get the same answer
now
i know but the question is that's the formal
definition of a programming language there is a definition of languages that don't get the same answer
but people who use those you always want something because you get a bad answer
and then you're wondering is it because right
something in your brother
because of this and
so everybody wants a little swish that says no matter what ya do it deterministically
and it's really weird because almost everything going into monetary calculations is noisy
so why the answers have to be so clear it's right so
where do you stand by design computers for people who run programs
so
somebody says i want in deterministic answer like
most people want that can you deliver a deterministic answer i guess is the question like
when you hopefully sure that's
what people don't realize is you get a deterministic
answer even though the execution flow is very own deterministic
so
if you run this program a hundred times it never runs the same way twice ever
and the answer it arises
the same in but it gets the same answer every time it's just just
them is just amazing
okay you've achieved in eyes of
many people
legend status as a cheap art architect
what design creation are you most proud of perhaps
because it was challenging
because of its impact
or
because of the set of brilliant ideas that that were
involved in well i find that description odd
and i has two small children
and i promise you
they think it's hilarious this question
yeah
so i dude
so i i'm
i'm really interested in building computers
and i've worked with really really smart people i'm not unbelievably smart i'm fascinated by
how they go together both as a as
a thing to do and is endeavor that people do
how people in computers go together yeah like
how people think
and build a computer
and i find sometimes that the best computer architects aren't that interested in people
or the best people managers aren't that good at designing computers
so the whole stack of human beings is fascinating
so the managers individual engineers
yeah i just i said i realized
after a lot of years of building computers
where you sort of build them out of the transistors logic gates functional units come computational elements that
you could think of people the same way so people are functional units
yes
and then you can think of organizational design it's a computer architectural problem
and then
it's like oh that's super
cool because the people are all different just like the computation
elephants are all different and they
like to do different things and
and
so i had a lot of fun like reframing
how i think about organizations just like with with
computers we were saying execution
paths you can have a lot of different paths that end up at a at
at the same good destination
so
what have you learned about the human
abstractions from individual functional human units to the broader organization
what does it take to create something special well
most people don't think simple enough
all right so do you know the difference between a recipe
and understanding
there's
probably a philosophical description of this so imagine you can make a loaf of bread yeah
the recipe says get some flour add some water add some yeast mix it up let it rise put
it in a pan put it in the oven it's
a recipe right understanding bread you
can understand biology supply chains you
know grain grinders yeast physics
you know thermodynamics like there's
so many levels of understanding there and then when people build
and design things they frequently are executing some stack of recipes right
and the problem with that is the recipes all have a limited scope look
if you have a really good recipe
book for making bread it won't tell you anything about how to make an omelet right right but
if you have a deep understanding of cooking
right then bread
omelets you know sandwich you know there's there's a different you know way of viewing everything
and most
people when you get to be an expert at something you
know you're you're hoping to achieve deeper understanding
not just a large set of recipes to go execute
and it's interesting the walk groups of people because xqt
reps apiece is unbelievably efficient if it's
what you want to do if it's not what you want to do you're really stuck
and
and that difference is crucial
and ever
and everybody has a balance of let's say deeper understanding recipes
and some people are really good at recognizing when
the problem is to understand something dp deeply that
make sense it totally makes sense does
it every stage of development deep on understanding on the team needed
oh this goes back to the art versus science question sure
if you constantly unpacked everything for deeper understanding you never get anything done right
and
if you don't unpack understanding when you need to you'll do the wrong thing
and then at every juncture like human beings are these really weird things
because everything
you tell them has a million possible outputs all
right and then they all interact in a hilarious way
and then having
some intuition about what you tell them what you do when do you intervene
when do you not it's it's complicated all right
so it's you know essentially computationally unsolvable
yeah it's an intractable problem sure
humans are a mess but
with deep understanding do you mean also sort of fundamental questions of things like
what is a computer
or
why like think the why question is why are we even building this like of purpose
or do you mean more
like going towards the fundamental limits of physics sort of really getting
into the core of the sighs well in terms of building the computer thinks
simple think a little simpler
so common practice is you build a computer
and then when somebody says i want to make it 10% faster you'll
go in and say alright
i need to make this buffer bigger and maybe i'll add an ad unit or you
know i have this thing that's three instructions wide i'm going to make it four instructions wide and
what you see is each piece gets incrementally more complicated right
and then at some point you hit this limit like adding another feature
or a buffer doesn't seem to make it any faster and
then people say well that's because it's a fundamental limit
and then
somebody else to look at it and say well actually the way you divided
the problem up and the way that different features are interacting is limiting
you and it has to be rethought rewritten right
so then you refactor it and rewrite it and what people commonly find is
the rewrite is not only faster
but half is complicated from scratch
yes
so
how often in your career
but just have you seen as needed
maybe more generally to just throw the whole out thing
out this is where i'm on one end of it every
three to five years
which end are you on like rewrite more often right
and three
or five years is if you want to really make a lot of progress on computer architecture every
five years you should do one from scratch
so
where does the x86 64 standard come in or
what how often do you i wrote
the i was the co-author that's back in 98 that's 20 years ago
yeah
so that's still around the instruction set it stuff has been extended quite a few times yes
and instruction sets are less interesting
and implementation underneath there's
been on x86 architecture
intel's designed a few eames is designed a few very different architectures
and i
don't want to go into too much of the detail about how often
but it's
there's a tendency to rewrite it every you know 10 years and it really should be every five
so
you're saying you're an outlier in that sense in really
more often we write more often well in here isn't that scary
yeah of course well scary - who - everybody involved
because like you said repeating
the recipe is efficient companies
want to make money well
no in the individual juniors want to succeed so you want to incrementally
improve increase the buffer from three to four well we get
into the diminishing return curves i think
steve jobs said this right so every you have a project
and you start here and it goes up and they have domitian return
and to get to the next level you have to do a new one in the initial
starting point will
be lower than the old optimization
point but it'll get higher
so
now you have two kinds of fear short-term disaster
and long-term disaster
and you're you're wrong
right like
you know people with a quarter by quarter business objective are terrified about changing everything yeah
and people who are trying to run a business
or build a computer for a long term objective know that the short-term limitations block
them from the long term success
so
if you look at leaders of companies
that had really good long-term success every
time they saw that they had to redo something they did and
so somebody has to speak up or you
do multiple projects in parallel like you optimize
the old one while you build a new one and
but the marketing guys they're always like make promise
me that the new computer is faster on every single thing
and the computer architect says well the new computer will be faster on the average
but there's a distribution
or results in performance
and you'll have some outliers that are slower
and that's very hard because they have one customer cares about that one so speaking
of the long-term for over 50 years now moore's law has served a for
me and millions of others as an inspiring beacon
what kind of amazing future brilliant engineers can build no i'm
just making your kids laugh all of today it was great
so
first in your eyes what is moore's law if you could define for people who don't know
well the simple
statement was from gordon moore was double the number of transistors every two years something
like that and then my operational model is we
increased the performance of computers by 2x
every 2 or 3 years and it's wiggled around substantially
over time and also in
how we deliver performance has changed
but the foundational
idea was to x two transistors every two years the
current cadence is something like they call it a shrink factor like
point six every two years which is not 0.5
but that that's referring strictly again to the original definition of transistor count a shrink
factors just getting them smaller small as well as you use for a constant chip area
if you
make the transistor smaller by 0.6 then you get 1 over 0.6 more transistors
so can you linger a little longer what's what's
a broader what do you think should be the broader definition of moore's law we mentioned before how
you think of performance just
broadly what's a good way to think about moore's law well
first of all so
i i've been aware of moore's law for 30 years in
what sense well i've been designing computers for 40 just watching
it before your eyes kind of slow and somewhere
where i became aware of it i was also informed that
moore's law was gonna die in 10 to 15 years
and i thought that was true at first
but then after 10 years it was gonna die in 10 to 15 years and then
at one point it was gonna die in 5 years
and then it went back up to ten years and at some point i decided
not to worry about that particular
product mastication for the rest of my life
which is which is fun
and then i joined intel
and everybody said moore's law is dead and i thought that's sad because it's the moore's law company
and it's not dead and it's always been gonna die and you
know humans you like these apocryphal
kind of statements like we'll
run out of food or run out of air or
you know something right
but it's still incredible this lived for as long as it has
and
yes
there's many people who believe now that moore's law instead you know they
can join the last 50 years of people had the thing yeah there's a long tradition
but why do you think if you can in touch try
to understand it why do you think it's not dead well
for hartley let's just think people
think moore's law is one thing transistors get smaller
but actually under the sheets ours literally thousands of innovations
and almost all those innovations have their own diminishing return curves
so
if you graph it it looks like a cascade of diminishing return curves i don't
know what to call that but the result is an exponential curve at
least it has been so
and we
keep inventing new things so if you're an expert in one of the things on a diminishing return curve
right
and you can see it's plateau you will
probably tell people well this is this is done meanwhile
some other pile of people are doing something different
so that's that's just normal
so then there's the observation of how small could a switching device be
so a modern transistor is something like a thousand by a thousand by thousand atoms right
and you get quantum effects down around two to two to ten atoms
so you can imagine the transistor as small as 10 by 10 by 10
so that's a million times smaller
and then the quantum computational people are working away at how to use quantum effects
so a
thousand by thousand five thousand atoms
it's a really clean way of putting it well fin like a modern transistor
if you look at the fan it's like a hundred
and twenty atoms wide but
we can make that thinner and then there's there's a gate wrapped around it
and under spacing there's a whole bunch of geometry
and you know a competent transistor designer could count both atoms in every single direction
like there's techniques now to already put down atoms in a single atomic layer
and you can place atoms
if you want to it's
just you know from
a manufacturing process if placing an atom takes ten minutes and you need to put
you know 10 to the 23rd atoms together to make a computer it would take a long time
so the the methods are you know both shrinking things
and then coming up with effective ways to control what's happening
manufacture stabling cheaply
yeah
so the innovation stocks
pretty broad you know there there's
equipment there's optics there's chemistry there's physics there's material science there's metallurgy there's
lots of ideas about when you put their four materials together
how they interact are they stable is i stable
or temperature you
know like are they repeatable you know there's look there's like
literally thousands of technologies involved
but just for the shrinking you don't think we're quite yet close to the fundamental
limit in physics i did
a talk on moore's law and i asked for a road
map to a path of 100
and after two weeks they
said we only got to fifty a hundred what's
a 100 extra hundred shrink we
only got 15 i said once you go to another two weeks
well here's the thing about moore's law right
so i believe that
the next 10 or 20 years of shrinking is going to happen right
now as a computer designer there's
you have two stances you think it's going to shrink in which case you're designing
and thinking about architecture in a way that you'll use more transistors
or
conversely not be swamped by the complexity of all the transistors you get right
you have to have a strategy
you know so you're open to the possibility
and waiting for the possibility of a whole new army of transistors
ready to work i'm expecting
expecting more transistors every two or three years by a number large enough that
how you think about design
how you think about architecture has to change like
imagine you're you build built brick buildings out of bricks and every
year the bricks are half the size
or every two years well
if you kept building bricks the same way you know
so many bricks per person per day the
amount of time to build a building would go up exponentially right right but
if you said i know that's coming
so
now i'm going to design equipment
and moves bricks faster uses them better because
maybe you're getting something out of the smaller bricks more strengths inner walls you
know less material efficiency out of that so
once you have a roadmap with what's going to happen transistors
they're gonna get we're gonna get more of them then you design
was collateral rounded to take advantage of it and also to cope with it like
that's the thing people to understand
it's like if i didn't
believe in moore's law and moore's
law transistors showed up my design teams were all drowned
so what's the what's the hardest part of this in flood of new transistors
i mean even
if you just look historically throughout your career what's
what's the thing you what
fundamentally changes when you add more transistors in in the task of designing an architecture no
there's there's two constants right one is people don't get smarter i
think by the way there's some size shown that we do get smarter
because nutrition whatever sorry
bring that what effect yes nobody understands
it nobody knows if it's still going on so that's all or whether
it's real or not but yeah that's a i sort of amen
but not if i believe for the most part people aren't getting much smarter the
evidence doesn't support it that's right and then teams can't grow that much right
all right so human beings understand
you know we're really good in teams of ten you
know up two teams of a hundred they can know each other beyond
that you have to have organizational boundaries so
you're kind of you have those are pretty hard constraints all
right so then you have to divide
and conquer
like as the designs get bigger you have to divide it into pieces you know
that the power of abstraction layers is really high we used to build computers out of transistors
now we have a team that turns transistors
and logic
cells and our team that turns them into functional
you know it's another one it turns in computers right
so we have abstraction layers in there and
you
have to think about when do you shift gears on that we
also use faster computers to build faster computers so
some algorithms run twice as fast on new computers
but a lot about rhythms are n squared
so you know a computer with twice as many transistors
and it might take four tom's times as long to run so
you have to refactor at the software like
simply using faster computers to build bigger computers doesn't work
so
so you have to think about all these things so in terms of computing performance
and the exciting possibility that more powerful computers bring is shrinking
the thing we've been talking about
one of the for you one of the biggest exciting possibilities of advancement in performance
or is there are other directions that you're interested in like like
in the direction of sort of enforcing given parallelism
or like doing
massive parallelism in terms of many many cpus you
know stacking cpus on top of each other that kind of that kind of parallelism
or you kind of well think about it a different way
so old
computers you know slow computers you said a equal b plus c times d pretty simple right
and then we made faster computers with vector units
and you can do proper equations
and matrices right
and then modern like ai computations
or like convolutional neural networks we you convolve one large data set against another and
so there's
sort of this hierarchy of mathematics
you know from simple
equation to linear equations to matrix equations to it's a deeper kind of computation
and the data sets are getting
so big that people are thinking of data as a topology
problem you know data is organized in some immense shape
and then the computation
which sort of wants to be get
data from immense shape and do some computation
on it so the with
computers of a lot of people to do is how about rhythms go much much further
so
that that paper you you reference the sutton paper they
talked about you know like in a i started
it was a ploy rule sets to something that's
a very simple computational situation
and then when they did first chess thing they solved deep searches
so have a huge database of moves
and results deep search but it's still just a search right
now we we take large numbers of images
and we use it to train these weight sets that
we convolve across it's a completely different kind of phenomena we
call that ai now they're doing the next generation
and if you look at it they're going up this mathema graph right
and then computations the both computation
and data sets support going up that graph
yeah
the kind of computation
of my i mean i would argue that all of it is still a search right just
like you said a topology problems data says he's searching the data sets for valuable
data and also the actual optimization of your networks is a kind of search for
the i don't know if you looked at the inner layers of finding a cat
it's not a search it's it's a set of endless projection
so you know projection
and here's a shadow of this phone
yeah right then
you can have a shadow of that onto something a shadow on that or something
if you look in the layers you'll see this layer actually describes pointy ears and round eyeness
and fuzziness
and
but the computation to tease out the attributes is not search right
ain't like the inference part might be searched
but the trainings not search
okay well 10 then in deep networks
they look at layers and they don't even know it's represented
and yet
if you take the layers out it doesn't work ok
so if i don't think it's search all
right well but you have to talk to my mathematician about what that actually is
oh you disagree
but the the it's just semantics
i think it's not but it's certainly not i would say it's absolutely not semantics
but okay
all right well
if you want to go there
so optimization to me is search
and we're trying to optimize
the ability of a neural network to detect cat ears
and this difference between chess
and the space the incredibly
multi-dimensional hundred thousand
dimensional space that you know networks are trying to optimize over is nothing like the chessboard database
so it's a totally different kind of thing and okay in that sense you can say
yeah yeah you
know i could see how you you might say if if you the
funny thing is it's the difference between given search space
and found search space exactly
yeah maybe that's a different way beautiful
but okay but you're saying what's your sense in terms of the basic mathematical operations
and the architectures
can be hardwired that enables
those operations do you see the cpus of today still being a really core part of executing
those mathematical operations
yes well the operations you know continue to be add subtract loads
or compare
and branch it's it's remarkable
so it's it's interesting that the building blocks of you know computers
or transistors
and you know under that atoms
so you got atoms transistors logic gates computers right
you know functional units and computers the building blocks of mathematics at some level are things like adds
and subtracts and multiplies
but that's the space mathematics can describe is i think
essentially infinite
but the computers that run the algorithms are still doing the same things
now a given algorithm may say i need sparse data or
i need 32-bit data
or
i need you know like
a convolution operation that naturally takes 8-bit data multiplies
it and sums it up a certain way so the like the data types in tensorflow
imply an optimization set
but when you go write down a look at the computers it's an inorganic salt applies like
like that hasn't changed much
now the quantum researchers think they're going to change that radically
and then there's people who think about analog computing
because you look in the brain and it seems to be more analog ish you
know that maybe there's a way to do that more efficiently
but we have a million acts on computation
and i don't know the reference the relationship between computational let's say intensity
and ability to hit match mathematical abstractions i don't know anyway subscribe dad
but
but just like you saw an ai you went from rule
sets the simple search to complex search does a found search like
those are you know orders of magnitude more computation to do
and
as we get the next two orders of magnitude
your friend roger godori said like every order magnitude changed the computation
fundamentally changes
what the computation is doing here oh you
know the expression the difference in quantity is the difference in kind
you know the difference between ant
and ant hill right
or neuron
and brain you know there's there's there's just indefinable place
where the the quantity changed the quality right
now we've seen that happen in mathematics multiple times and you
know my my guess is it's gonna keep happening so your senses
yeah
if you focus head down and shrinking a transistor let's
not just head down and we're aware about
the software stacks that are running in the computational loads and we're kind of pondering
what do you do with a petabyte
of memory that wants to be accessed in a sparse way and
have you know the kind of calculations ai programmers want
so there's that there's a dialog interaction
but when you go in the computer chip you know you find adders
and subtractors and multipliers
and
so
if you zoom out then with as you mentioned
which sutton the idea
that most of the development in the last many decades in the ai research came from just leveraging computation
and just the simple algorithms
waiting for the computation to improve well suffer guys have a thing that they called the
the problem of early optimization right
so
if you write a big software stack
and
if you start optimizing like
the first thing you write the odds of that being the performance limiter is low but
when you get the whole thing working can you make it to x faster by optimizing
the right things sure while
you're optimizing that could you've written a new software stack
which would have been a better choice maybe
now you have creative tension
so
but the whole time as you're doing the writing the
that's the software we're talking about the hardware underneath gets faster
which goes back to the moore's laws moore's law is going to continue then your ai research
should expect
that to show up and then you make a slightly different set of choices then we've
hit the wall nothing's
gonna happen and from here it's just us rewriting algorithms like
that seems like a failed strategy for the last 30 years of moore's laws death
so
so can you just linger on it i think you've answered it
but it just asked the same dumb question over and over so
what why do you think moore's law is not going to die
which is the most promising exciting
possibility of why it won't done that's five 10 years so is it that continues shrinking the transistor
or is it another s-curve that steps in and it totally
so dope shrinking the transistor is literally thousands of innovations right
so there's so this they're all answers
and it's there's a whole bunch of s-curves just kind of running their course
and being reinvented
and new things you know the the semiconductor
fabricators
and technologists have all announced what's called nano wires
so they they took a fan
which had a gate around it and turned that into a little wire
so you have better control that
and they're smaller
and then from there there's some obvious steps about how to shrink that
so the metallurgy around wire stocks
and stuff has very obvious abilities to shrink and you
know there's a whole combination of things there to do your
sense is that we're gonna get a lot
yes this innovation from just that shrinking
yeah like a factor of a hundred salade
yeah i would say that's incredible
and it's totally it's only 10 or 15 years
now you're smarter you might know but to me it's totally unpredictable of
what that hundred x would bring in terms of the nature of the computation
and people be yeah you familiar with bell's law
so for a long time those mainframes
mini's workstation pc mobile moore's law drove faster smaller computers right
and then we
were thinking about moore's law rajae godori said every 10x generates a new computation
so scalar vector made erichs topological computation right
and
if you go look at the industry trans there was no mainframes
and mini-computers and pcs
and then the internet took off and then we got mobile devices
and
now we're building 5g wireless with one millisecond latency and
people are starting to think about the smart world where everything knows
you recognizes you like
like like the transformations are going to be like unpredictable
how does it make you feel that you're one of the key
architects of this kind of futures you're not we're not talking about the architects of the high-level
people who build the angry bird apps
and flapping
angry bird of who knows we're gonna be that's the whole point of the universe
let's take a stand at that and the attention
distracting nature of mobile
phones i'll take a stand but anyway in terms of that matters much
the the side effects of smartphones
or the attention distraction
which part well who knows you know where this is all leading it's changing
so fast wax my parents
do steal my sister's
for hiding in the closet with
a wired phone with a dial on it stop
talking your friends all day right
now
my wife feels with my kids for talking to their friends all day on text looks
the same to me it's always it's echoes of the same thing okay but you are the one
of the key people architecting
the hardware of this future
how does that make you feel do you feel responsible
do you feel excited
so we're we're in a social context
so there's billions of people on this planet there
are literally millions of people working on technology i feel lucky to be
you know what doing
what i do and getting paid for it and there's an interest in it but
there's so many things going on in parallel it's like
the actions are so unpredictable if i wasn't here somebody else are doing the
the vectors of all these different things are happening all the time
you know there's a i'm sure some philosopher
or meta philosophers you know wondering about how we transform our world
so you can't deny the fact that these tools whether
that
these tools are changing our world that's
right do you think it's
changing for the better so
some of these i read this thing recently it said the peat the two disciplines with
the highest gre scores in college are physics in philosophy right
and they're both sort of trying to answer the question why is there anything right
and the philosopher's you know are on the kind of theological side
and the physicists are obviously on the you know the material side and there's a hundred billion galaxies
with a hundred billion stars it seems well repetitive at best
so i you know there's on our way to ten billion people
i mean it's hard to say what it's all for is that's what you're asking
yeah i guess i guess i do tend to are significantly increases in complexity
and i'm curious about
how
computation like like our world our physical world inherently generates mathematics it's kind of obvious right
so we have x y z coordinates you
take a sphere you make it bigger you get a surface that falls
you know grows by r-squared like
it generally generates mathematics
and the mathematicians
and the physicists
have been having a lot of fun talking to each other for years and computation has been let's
say relatively pedestrian like computation
in terms of mathematics has been doing binary binary algebra while those guys have been gallivanting
through the other realms of possibility right
now recently the computation
lets you do math m'q mathematical computations that are sophisticated enough that nobody understands
how the answers came out right
machine learning machine lying yeah it used to be you get data set you
guess at a function the function is considered physics if it's predictive of new functions
data sets modern
you
can take a large data set with no intuition
about what it is and use machine learning to find a pattern that has no function right
and it can arrive at results that i don't know if they're completely mathematically describable
so a computation is kind of done
something interesting compared to a pov plus see there's
something reminiscent of that step from the basic operations of addition
to taking a step towards new all networks that's reminiscent of
what life on earth and its origins was doing do
you think we're creating sort of the next step in our evolution in creating
artificial intelligence systems that i don't
know i mean you
know if there's so much in the universe
already it's hard to say
well i'm
standing in his hold are human beings working on additional abstraction layers and possibilities yet appear
so does
that mean that human beings don't need dogs you
know no like like there's so many things that are all simultaneously
interesting
and useful but you've seen through i agree you've seen great
and greater level abstractions
and built in artificial machines
right do
you think when you look at humans you think that the look of all life
on earth as a single organism building
this thing this machine that greater
and greater levels of abstraction do you think humans are the peak
the top of the food chain in this long
arc of history on earth
or do you think we're just somewhere in the middle are we are we the basic functional
operations of a cpu are we the c++
program the python perl network like somebody's you
know people have calculated
like how many operations
does the brain do and something you
know i've seen the number 10 to the 18th about bunch of times arrive different ways so
could you make a computer that did 10 to the 20th operations
yes sure do
you think we're gonna do that now is
there something magical about how brains compute things i don't know you
know my personal experiences
interesting cuz you know you think
you know how you think and then you have all these ideas and
you can't figure out how they happened
and
if you meditate you know the like
what what you can be aware of is interesting
so i don't know if brains are magical
or not you know the physical evidence says no lots of people's personal experiences yes
so
what would be funny as if brains are magical
and yet we can make brains with more computation you
know i don't know what to say about that but what
do you think magic is an emergent phenomena
what would be our than me i don't know
teller of what what
what in your view is consciousness
with with consciousness
yeah like what you know cautiousness
love things
that are these deeply human things that seems to emerge from our brain is that something
that we'll be able to make
encode in chips that get faster
and faster and faster and faster the flick of 10 our conversations
no but nobody really knows can you summarize it in a couple of couple of words
many people have observed that
organisms run at lots of different levels right
if you got two neurons somebody said you'd have one sensory neuron and one motor neuron right
so we move towards things and away from things
and we have physical integrity and safety
or not right
and then
if you look at the animal kingdom
you can see brains that are a little more complicated
and at some point there's a planning system
and then there's an emotional system that's you know happy about being safe or unhappy
about being threatened right
and then our brains have massive numbers of structures you know like planning
and movement
and thinking
and feeling
and drives
and emotions
and we seem to have multiple layers of thinking systems
and we have a brain a dream system that nobody understands whatsoever
which i find completely hilarious and
you can think in a way that those
systems are more independent
and you can observe you know the different parts of yourself can observe i don't
know which one's magical i don't know which ones not computational
so is it possible that it's all computation probably is
there a limit to computation i don't think so do
you think the universe is a computer i think
he seems to be it's a weird kind of computer
because
if it was a computer right
like when they do calculations
on what it how much calculation it takes to describe quantum effects is unbelievably high
so
if it was a computer
when you built it out of something that was easier to compute right
that's that's a funny it's a funny system
but then the simulation guys
have pointed out that the rules are kind of interesting
like when you look really close it's uncertain
and the speed of light says you could only look so far and things can't be simultaneous
except for the odd entanglement problem
where they seem to be like the rules are all kind of weird
and somebody
said physics is like having 50 equations with 50 variables to define 50 variables like
you know it's it's you
know like physics itself has been a shitshow for thousands of years it
seems odd when you get to the corners of everything you know it's either uncomputable
or on definable
or uncertain it's
almost like the designers the simulation are trying to prevent us from understanding it perfectly
but
but also the things that require calculations requires
so much calculation that our idea of the universe of a computer is absurd
because every single little bit of it takes all the computation in the universe to figure out gee
that's a weird kind of computer you know you say the simulation is running in the computer
which has by definition infinite computations not infinite
oh you mean if the universe is infinite
yeah
piece of our universe seems to take infinite computation
i hit you're out just a lot whoa
a lot some pretty big number compute this little teeny spot takes all the mass
in the local one little year by one like your space it's close enough to infinite
so it's a heck of a computer if it is one i know it's it's
it's a weird it's a weird description
because the simulations description seems too the break when you look closely at it but
the rules in universe seemed to imply something's up that
seems a little arbitrary the whole the universe the whole thing the the laws of physics you
know it just seems like like
how did it come out to be yeah
the way it is but lots of people talk about that it's you know it's like i
said the two smartest groups of humans are working on the same problem different different aspects
and they're both complete failures
so that's kind of cool
they might succeed eventually well
after two thousand years the trend isn't good two
thousand years is nothing in the span of the history of the universe
so we have some time but the next thousand years doesn't look good either so that's
what everybody says that every stage but with
moore's law as you've just described
not being dead the exponential
growth the technology the future seems pretty incredible
well it'll be interesting that's for sure that's right so
what are your thoughts on ray
kurzweil sense that exponential improvement and technology will continue indefinitely that is that how you see moore's law do
you see moore's law more broadly
and since the technology of all kinds has a way of stacking
s curves on top of each other
where it'll be exponential
and then we'll see all kinds of what was an exponential of a million mean that's
that's a pretty amazing number
and that's just for a local little piece of silicon
now it's imagine you say decided to get a
thousand tons of silicon to collaborate in one computer at a million times the density like
now you know you're talking i don't know 10 to the 20th more computation power then
our current already unbelievably fast computers like
nobody knows what that's going to mean you know the sci-fi guys called you know computron 'i'm like
when like a local civilization turns the nearby star into a computer i like
i don't that's true
but so just even when you shrink a transistor
the that's
only one dimension of the ripple effects of that but people tend to think about computers
the cost problem right
so computers are made out of silicon
and minor amounts of metals
and you know this
and that none of those things cost any money like
there's plenty of sand like like
you could just turn the beach and a little bit ocean water in the computers
so all the cost is
and equipment to do it and the trend on equipment is once
you figure out a build the equipment the
trend of cost is zero elon said first you figure out what
configuration you want the atoms in and then
how to put them there right
yeah cuz well what here's you know his his great insight is people
are how constrained i have this thing i know how it works and then little
tweaks to that will generate something as opposed to what do i actually want
and then figure out how to build it it's a very different mindset
and almost nobody has it obviously
well
let me ask on that topic you
were one of the key early people in the development of autopilot at least in the hardware side elon
musk believes that autopilot
and vehicle autonomy
if you just look at that problem can follow this kind of exponential improvement in
terms of the ha the
how question that we're talking about there's no reason why i can't
what are your thoughts on this particular space of vehicle autonomy
and you're a part of it and elon musk's
and tesla's vision well the computer you need to build was straightforward
and you can argue well doesn't need to be 2 times faster
or 5 times or 10 times
but that's just a matter of time
or
price in the short run so that's that's not a big deal you
don't have to be especially smart to drive a car
so it's not like a super hard problem
i mean the big problem with safety is attention
which computers are really good at not skills
well let me push back on one you see everything you said it's correct
but we as humans
tend to
tend to take for granted
how how incredible our vision system is so you can drive a car of 2050 vision
and you can train a neural network to extract
a distance of any object in the shape of any surface from a video
and data
but that really simple not simple i look that's a simple data problem it's
not it's not simple it's
because you because it's not just detecting object it's understanding the scene
and it's being able to do it in a way that doesn't make errors
so the beautiful thing about the human vision system
and the entire brain around the whole thing is we were able to fill in the gaps it's
not just about perfectly detecting cars it's inferring the occluded
cars it's trying to it's it's understanding
the i think it's mostly a bigger problem you
so you think what data you know with compute with improvement of computation with improvement in collection
well there is a you know when
you're driving a car and somebody cuts you off your brain has theories
about why they did it you
know they're a bad person they're
distracted they're dumb you
know you can listen to yourself right
so
you know if you
think that narrative is important to be able to successfully drive a car then current
autopilot systems can't do it but if cars
are ballistic things with tracks and probabilistic changes of speed and direction and roads are fixed
and given by the way they don't change dynamically
right you can map the world really thoroughly you can place every object really thoroughly
right you can calculate trajectories of things really thoroughly right
but everything you said about really thoroughly has a different degree of difficulty
so you
could say at some point computer
autonomous systems will be way better it's things
that humans are allows yet like it'll be better at abstention they'll
always remember there was a pothole in the road that
humans keep forgetting about they'll
remember that this set of roads
how these weirdo lines on it the computers figured out once and especially
if they get updates
so if somebody changes a given like that akita robots
and stuff somebody said is to maximize two givens
okay right
so
though having a robot
pick up this bottle
cap is ways you put a red dot on the top
because
then you have to figure out you know if you want to do
a certain thing with it you know maximize
the givens is the thing and autonomous systems are happily maximizing the givens like humans
when you drive someplace new you remember
it because you're processing
it the whole time and after the 50th time you
drove to work you
get to work you don't know how you got there right
you're on autopilot right
autonomous cars are always on autopilot
but the cars have no theories about why they got cut off or why they're in traffic
so they'll never stop paying attention right
so i tend to believe you do have deaf theories mental models of other people especially pedestrians cyclists
but also with other cars everything you said is
like is actually essential to driving driving is a lot more complicated than people realize
i think so sort of to push back slightly but cut into traffic right
yeah you can't just wait for a gap you have to be somewhat aggressive you'd be surprised
how simple a calculation for that is i may
be on that particular point but there's a that it may
be asked you to push back i would be surprised you know
what yeah i'll just say where i stand i would be very surprised
but i think it's you might be surprised
how complicated it is that
i'd say that i tell people's like progress disappoints
in the short run the surprises in the long run it's very possible yeah i suspect
in 10 years it'll be just like taken for granted yeah
but you're probably right
now look like it's gonna be a $50 solution that nobody cares about like
gps is like wow gps is we have satellites in space that
tell you where your location is it was a really big deal now everything is the gps i
mean yeah it's true but i do think that systems
that involve human behavior are more
complicated than we give them credit for so we
can do incredible things with technology that don't involve humans
but when you look humans are less complicated than people you
know frequently obscure i've maybe i stand off right out of large numbers of patterns
and just keep doing it over
but i can't trust you because you're a human that's something something
a human would say but i might my
hope was on the point you've made is even if no
matter who is right eve there i'm hoping
that there's a lot of things that humans aren't good at that machines
are definitely good i like you said attention
and things like that well they'll be
so much better that the overall picture of safety in autonomy
will be obviously cars will be safer even if they're not as good i'm
a big believer in safety
i mean there are already the current
safety systems like cruise control that doesn't let you run into people and lane-keeping there
are so many features that you just look at the pareto of accidents
and knocking off like 80% of them you
know super doable just a wing guard on the autopilot team
and the efforts there the
it seems to be that there's a very intense scrutiny by the media
and the public in terms of safety the pressure the bar but before autonomous vehicles
what are your sort of as a person they're working on the hardware
and trying to build a system that builds a safe vehicle
and
so on what
was your sense about that pressure is it unfair is it expected of new technology it
seems reasonable i was interested i talked to both american
and european regulators
and i was worried that
the regulations would write into the rules technology solutions like modern brake systems imply hydraulic brakes
so
if you'll read the regulations to meet the letter of the law for brakes it
sort of has to be hydraulic right
and the regulator said there they're interested in the use cases like
a head-on crash an offset crash don't hit pedestrians don't
run into people don't leave the road don't
run a red light or a stop light they were very much into the scenarios
and you know and they had they had all the data about
which scenarios injured
or killed to most people
and for the most part those conversations were like
what's the right thing to do to
take the next step
now elan is very interested also in the benefits
of autonomous driving or freeing people's time and attention as well as safety
and i think that's also an interesting thing but
you know building an autonomous system so they're safe and safer
and people seemed since the goals to be tannic seifer's
and people having the bar to be safer than people
and scrutinizing accidents seems philosophically
you know correct
so i think that's a good thing
what r is
is different than the things you've worked at new intel amd apple with autopilot chip design
and hardware design
what are interesting
or challenging aspects of building this specialized kind of competing system in the automotive space i mean
there's two tricks to building like an automotive computer one is to
software our team the machine learning team is developing algorithms that are changing fast
so as you're building the the accelerator you have this you know worry
or intuition that the algorithms will change enough that the accelerator will be the wrong one right
and there's the generic thing which is if you build a really good general-purpose computers
hey it's performance is one
and then gpu guys will deliver about 5x to performance for the same amount of silicon
because instead of discovering parallelism you're given parallelism
and then special accelerators get another two to five x on top of a gpu
because you say i know the math is always 8-bit integers
and two 32-bit accumulators
and the operations are the subsets of mathematical possibilities
so although you know ai accelerators have a claimed performance benefit over gpus
because in the narrow math space you're nailing the algorithm
now you still try to make it programmable
but the ai field is changing really fast so there's a you
know there's little creative tension era of i want the acceleration afforded by specialization
without being over specialized
so that the new algorithm is
so much more effective that you'd have been better off on a gpu
so there's attention there to
build a good computer for an application like automotive there's
all kinds of sensor inputs
and safety processors
and a bunch of stuff so one of loans goal is to make it super affordable
so every car gets an autopilot computer
so
some of the recent startups you look at and they have a server in the trunk
because they're saying i'm going to build this autopilot computer replaces the driver
so their cost budgets ten or twenty thousand dollars
and eelain's constraint was i'm gonna put one every in every car whether people buy autonomous
driving or not so
the cost constraint he had in mind was great right
and to hit that you
had to think about the system design that's complicated it's
it's fun you know it's like it's like it's craftsmen's
work like a violin
maker right you could say stradivarius is this incredible thing the musicians are incredible
but the guy making the violin
you know picked wood and sanded it and then he cut it you
know and he glued it and you know and he waited for the right day
so
that when you put the finish on it didn't
you know do something dumb that's craftsmen's work right
you may be a genius craftsman
because you have the best techniques
and you discover a new one
but most engineers craftsmen's work and humans really like to do that you know smart humans
oh no everybody
oh i
know i used to i dug ditches when i was in college
i got really good at it satisfying
yeah
so digging ditches is also craft malware
yeah of course
so
so there's an expression called complex mastery behavior
so when you're learning something that's fun because you're learning something when
you do something that's wrote and simple it's not that satisfying
but if the steps that you have to do or complicate it and you're
good at them it's satisfying to do them and then
if you're intrigued by it all as you're doing them you sometimes learn new things that
you can raise your game
but christmas work is good in engineers like engineering is complicated
enough that you have to learn a lot of skills and
then a lot of what you do is then craftsmen's
work which is fun autonomous
driving building a very
a resource-constrained computer
so computer has to be cheap enough that put in every single car that's
essentially boils down to
craftsmen's work it's saying genius
so there's thoughtful decisions
and problems to solve and trade-offs
to make do you need 10 cameron ports or 8 you know you're
building for the current car or the next one you
know how do you do the safety stuff
you know there's there's a whole bunch of details
but it's fun but it's not like i'm building a new type and they're all networked
which has a new mathematics
and a new computer at work do
you know that that's like there's a there's more invention than that
but the rejection to practice once you picked the architecture you look inside
and what do you see adders
and multipliers
and memories
and you know the basics
so computers is always just this weird set of abstraction layers of ideas
and thinking that reduction to practice is transistors
and wires and you know pretty basic stuff
and that's
an interesting phenomena by
the way that like factory work like
lots of people think factory work is road assembly stuff i've
been on the assembly line like
the people work that really liked it it's a really great job it's
really complicated putting cars together is hard right
and in the cars moving
and the parts are moving and sometimes the parts are damaged
and you have to coordinate putting
all the stuff together and people are good at it they're
good at it and i remember one day i went to work and the
line was shut down for some reason and then
some of the guys sitting around were really bummed because they they had reorganized
a bunch of stuff
and they were gonna hit a new
record for the number of cars built
that day and they
were all gung ho to do it and these were big tough buggers
yeah you know but
what they did was complicated
and you couldn't do it
yeah
and
i mean well
after
a while you could but you'd have to work your way up cuz you know like
putting a bright what's
called the bright stuff at the trim on a car on a moving assembly line where
it has to be attached 25
places in a minute and a half is unbelievably complicated
and
and human beings can do it's really good i think
that's harder than driving a car by the way putting
together working working on the factory to smart
people can disagree
yeah i think drive driving a car will
get you in the factory something will
see you're not for us humans driving a car is easy i'm saying building a machine that
drives a car is not easy ok ok driving a car is easy for humans
because we've been evolving for billions of years drive cars
yeah no juice the pail if the cars are super cool no
now you join the rest of the internet and mocking me ok
yeah
yeah intrigued by your you know your anthropology
yeah it says we have to go dig into that there's some inaccuracies there
yes ok
but in general
what have you learned in terms of thinking about passion
craftsmanship
tension chaos
you know the whole mess of it
or
what have you learned have
taken away from your time working with elon
musk working at tesla which is known to be a place of chaos innovation
craftsmanship
and i really like the way he thought like you think you have an understanding about
what first principles of something is and then you talk to you alone about it and you you
didn't scratch the surface you
know he has a deep belief that
no matter what you do is a local maximum right
i had a friend he invented a better electric motor and it
was like a lot better than what we were using and
one day he came by he said you know i'm
a little disappointed cuz
you know this is really great and you didn't seem that impressed and i said you
know and the super intelligent aliens come are they gonna be looking for you like
where is he the guy you built the motor
yeah probably not you know like like the
but doing interesting work that's both innovative
and let's say craftsmen's work on the current thing it's really satisfying it's good and
and that's cool and then
elon was good taking everything apart and like what's the deep first principle
oh no
what's really what's really you know you know you
know that that you know ability to look at it without assumptions
and
how constraints is super wild you
know we build rocket ship and using
the same car you know everything
and that's super fun and he's into it too like when
they first landed to spacex rockets at tesla we
had a video projector in the big room and like five
hundred people came down and when they landed everybody cheered
and some people cried it was so cool alright
but how did you do that well
it
was super hard and then
people say well it's chaotic really to
get out of all your assumptions you think that's not going to be unbelievably painful
and there's
elon tough yeah probably the people look back on it and say boy i'm really happy
i had that experience to go take
apart that many layers of assumptions
sometimes super fun sometimes painful
so it could be emotionally
and intellectually painful that whole process just stripping away assumptions
yeah i imagine 99% of your thought process is protecting your self conception
and 98% of that's wrong
yeah
now you got there math right no
you think your feeling when you get back into that one bit that's useful
and
now you're open
and you have the ability to do something different i don't
know if i got the math right it might be ninety nine point nine but in 850
imagining it the 50% is hard enough yeah
now for a long time i've suspected you could get better look
you can think better you can think more clearly you can take things apart and there's
lots of examples of that people who do that
so any line is an example of that parent
or an example says you know if i am i'm
fun to talk to certainly
i've learned a lot of stuff right
well here's the other thing it's like i talk like like i read books and
people think oh you read books well no i brought a couple books
awake for 55 years well maybe 50 cuz i didn't read learned read tall as h or something
and
and it
turns out when people write books they often take
20 years of their life where they passionately
did something reduce it to to 200 pages that's
kind of fun and then
the goat you go online and you can find out
who wrote the best books and who like you know that's kind of alda
so there's this wild selection process
and then you can read it and for the most part to understand it
and then you can go apply it like
i went to one company and i thought i haven't managed much before
so i read 20 management books and i started talking to him basically
compared to all the vp's running around i'd
run night read 19
more management books than anybody else
was it even that hard
yeah
and a half the stuff worked like first time it wasn't even rocket science but at
the core of that is questioning the assumptions
okay sort of entering
the thinking first principles
thinking sort of looking at the reality of the situation and using it using
that knowledge applying that knowledge so
mean yes so i would say my brain has this idea that you can question first assumptions
and
but i can
go days at a time and forget that and
you have to kind of like circle back data observation
because it is because part allen gene well it's hard to keep it front
and center
because you know you're you operate on so many levels all the time and you
know getting this done takes priority
or you know being
happy takes priority or you know screwing
around takes priority like like like
how you go through life it's complicated
yeah
and then you remember
oh yeah i could really i think first principles
so much that's that's tiring you
know what you do for a while that's kind of cool
so
just as the last question your sense from
the big picture from the first principles do
you think you kind of answered already
but do you think autonomous driving something we can solve on a timeline of years
so one two three five ten years as opposed to a century yeah definitely just
to linger and a little longer where's the confidence coming
from is it the fundamentals of the problem the fundamentals of building a hardware
and the software as a computational problem understanding
ballistics roles topography
it seems pretty solvable
i mean
and you can see this you know like like speech recognition
for a long time people are doing you know frequency
and domain analysis
and and all kinds of stuff and that didn't work for at all right
and then they did deep learning about it and it worked great and it took multiple iterations
and
you
know time is driving his way past the frequency analysis point you
know use radar don't run into things
and the data gathering is going up in the computations
going up and the algorithm understanding is going up and there's
a whole bunch of problems getting solved
like that the data side is really powerful but i disagree with both you
and you and i'll tell you and once again as i did before that that
when you add human beings into the picture the
it's no longer a ballistics problem it's something more complicated
but i could
be very well proven
cars are hardly damped in terms are ready to change like
the steering and the steering systems really slow compared to a computer the acceleration
of the acceleration is really slow
yeah on
a certain time scale on a ballistics
time scale but human behavior i don't know it
yeah
i shouldn't say it beans are really slow to weed weirdly
we operate you know half a second behind reality nobody
really understands that one either it's pretty funny
yeah
so no
i will be with very well could be surprised
and i
think with the rate of improvement in all aspects i'm both the computed in the the the software
and the hardware there's gonna be pleasant surprises all over the place
speaking of unpleasant surprises many people have worries about a singularity in the development of ai
forgive me for such questions you know what
when ai improves exponentially
and reaches a point of superhuman level general intelligence you
know beyond the point there's no looking back do
you share this worry of existential threats from artificial intelligence from computers
becoming superhuman level intelligent
no not really you
know like we already have a very stratified society
and then
if you look at the whole animal kingdom of capabilities
and abilities and interests
and you
know smart people have their niche and you know normal people have their niche and craftsmen's
have their niche and you know
animals have their niche i suspect
that the domains of interest for things that you know astronomically
different like the whole something
got 10 times smarter than us and wanted to track us all down because what we
like to have coffee at starbucks like
it doesn't seem plausible no is there an existential problem that how
do you live in a world where there's something way smarter than you and you
you based your kind of self-esteem on being
the smartest local person well there's what 0.1% of the population who thinks that because
the rest of the populations been dealing with it since they were born
so the the breadth of possible experience that can be interesting is really big and
you know super intelligence seems likely although we still don't know if we're magical
but i suspect we're not
and it seems likely that'll create possibilities that are interesting for us and it's
its interests will be interesting for that for whatever it is it's
not obvious why it's interest would somehow
want to fight over some square foot of dirt or you know whatever
then you know the usual fears
are about so you don't think you'll inherit some of the darker aspects of human nature depends
on how you think reality is constructed
so for for whatever reasons human
beings are and that's a creative tension in opposition with both are good and bad
forces like there's lots of philosophical understandings of that
right i don't know why that would be different
so
you think the evils is necessary for the good i mean the tension i don't know about evil
but like we live in a competitive world
where your good is somebody else's you know evil you
know there's there's the malignant part of it but that seems to be
self-limiting although occasionally it's it's super horrible
but
yeah look there's a debate over ideas
and some people have different beliefs
and that that debate itself is a process
so the at arriving at something you know i wouldn't continue
yeah
just you
but you don't think that whole process will leave humans behind in a way that's painful an emotionally
painful yes for the one for the point one percent they'll be there why isn't it already painful
for a large percentage of the population and
it is i mean society does have a lot of stress in it about
the 1% and the bath of this and about to that but you know everybody
has a lot of stress in their life about what they find satisfying
and
and you know know yourself seems to be the proper dictum
and pursue something that makes your life meaningful seems proper
and there's
so many avenues on that like there's
so much unexplored space at every single level
you know i'm somewhat of my nephew called me a jaded optimist you
know
so it's there's a beautiful tension that in that label
but
if you
were to look back at your life and
could relive a moment a set of moments
because there were the happiest times in your life outside of family
what would that be i
don't want to relive any moments i like that i like that situation
where you have some amount of optimism
and then the anxiety of the unknown
so
you love the unknown do you the
mystery of it i don't know about the mystery it sure gets your blood pumping
what
do you think is the meaning of this whole thing of life on this pale blue dot it
seems to be what it does
like the universe for whatever reason
makes atoms
which makes us
which we do stuff
and we figure out things
and we explore things
and that's just what it is it's not just
yeah it is you
know jim i don't think there's a better place to end it it's a huge honor
and well
super fun thank you so much for talking today all right great thanks
for listening to this conversation and thank you to our presenting sponsor cash app downloaded
use code lex podcasts you'll
get ten dollars and ten dollars will go to first a stem education nonprofit
that inspires hundreds of thousands of young minds to become future leaders and innovators
if you
enjoy this podcast subscribe
on youtube give it five stars an apple podcast follow on spotify supported on patreon
or simply connect with me on twitter
and
now let me leave you with some words of wisdom from gordon moore for
everything you try works you aren't trying hard enough
thank you for listening and hope to see you next time
you