joe rogan podcast. check it out. > > the joe rogan experience.
> > train by day. joe rogan podcast by night. all day. > > hello. hey, joe.
> > good to see you again. we were just talking about
was that the first time we ever spoke or did
was the first time we spoke at at spacex? > > spacex.
> > spacex.
the first time when you were giving elon that crazy ai chip,
> > right? djx spark.
> > yeah.
oo, that was a big moment.
that was a huge
> > that felt crazy to be there. i was like watching these wizards of tech like exchange information
and
and you're giving him this crazy device, you know,
and then the other time was
uh
i was shooting arrows in my backyard and
randomly get this call from trump and he's hanging out with you.
president trump called and i called you. > > yeah.
it's just > > we were talking about you. [laughter] > > it's just talking about
he was talking about the us ufc thing he was going to do in his front yard.
> > yeah.
and he pulls out.
he's jjs, look at this design.
he's so proud of it.
and i go, " you're going to have a fight in the front lawn in the white house.
" he goes, " yeah, yeah, you're going to come.
this is going to be awesome.
" and he's showing me his design and how beautiful it is.
and he goes, and somehow your name comes up. he goes, " do you know joe?
" and i said, " yeah, i'm going to be on his podcast.
" he let's call him. [laughter] > > he's like a kid. > > i know.
let's call him.
it's so he's like a 79y old kid.
> > oh, he's so incredible. > > yeah, he's an odd guy. just very different, you know,
like the what you'd expect from him.
very different than what people think of him.
and also just very different as a president.
a guy who just calls you or texts you out of the blue.
also, he makes when you te you.
you have an android, so it won't go through with you, but with my iphone, he makes the text go big.
> > like,
you know,
usa is respected again. like [laughter] all caps
and it makes the te
the
the text enlarge is kind of ridiculous. > > well, the the 101 trump president
trump is very different. he he surprised me
f
first
of all
he's an incredibly good listener. almost everything i've ever said to him, he's remembered. > > yeah.
people don't
they only want to look at negative stories about him or negative narratives about him.
you know, you can catch anybody on a bad day.
like there's a lot of things he does where i don't think he should do.
like i don't think he should say to a reporter rep reporter, " quiet piggy.
" like that's pretty ridiculous.
also objectively funny.
i mean, it's unfortunate that it happened to her.
i wouldn't want that to happen to her, but it was funny.
just ridiculous that the president does that. i wish he didn't do that.
but other than that, like he's he's an interesting guy.
like he's a lot of different things wrapped up into one person, you know? you know, part of part of his charm, well, part of his genius is yes.
he says what's on his mind. > > yes.
> > and which is like an anti-olitician in a lot of ways.
> > so, you know, what's on his mind is really what's on his mind, > > which i i do some people some people would rather be lied to.
> > yeah.
but but i i like the fact that he's telling you what's on his mind. um,
almost every time he explains something, he says something, he starts with his, you could tell, his love for america, what he wants to do for america.
and everything that he thinks through is very practical and very common sense. and, you know,
it's very logical
and um
i still remember the first time i i met him
and so this was i
i'd never known him, never met him before. and
um
uh
secretary lutnik called and we met right before
right at the beginning of the administration.
he said he told me what was important to president trump
that that
um
uh
that united states manufactures on shore
and that was really important to him
because because
uh
it's important to national security.
he wants to make sure
that that the important critical technology of our nation is built in the united states
and that we re-industrialize and get good at manufacturing again
because it's important for jobs.
> > it just seems like common sense, right? > > incredible common sense.
and and that was like literally the first conversation i had with secretary letic um
and he was talking about how
how
um
that he started
he started our conversation with uh jensen.
this is secretary lutnik
and i i just want to let you know that you're a national treasure.
uh
nvidia
is a national treasure and whenever you need access to the president
um
the administration
uh
you call us.
we're always going to be available to you.
literally, that was the first sentence.
> > that's pretty nice.
> > and it was completely true.
every single time i called, if i needed something, i want to get something off my chest, um, express some concern,
uh,
they're always available. incredible.
it's just unfortunate we live in such a politically polarized society
that you can't recognize good common sense things if they're coming from a person that you object to.
and that, i think, is what's going on here.
i think most people generally a as a country, you know,
as a a giant community, which we are,
it just only makes sense that we have manufacturing in america that especially critical technology like you're talking about.
like it's kind of insane that we buy so much technology from other countries.
> > if united states doesn't grow, we will have no prosperity.
we can't invest in anything domestically or otherwise.
we can't fix any of our problems.
if we don't have energy growth, we can't have industrial growth.
if we don't have industrial growth, we can't have job growth. these
it's as simple as that, > > right? > >
and the fact that the fact that he came into office
and the first thing that he said was drill baby drill.
his point is we need energy growth.
without energy growth, we can have no industrial growth. and that was it saved
it saved the ai industry.
got
i got to tell you flat
out
if not for his progrowth energy policy
we would not be able to build factories for ai
not be able to build chip factories
we won't sure surely won't be able to build supercomputer factories
none of that stuff would be possible without all of that
construction
jobs would be challenged
right
electrical
you know
electrician
jobs
all of these jobs that are now flourishing would be challenged
and so i think he's got it right
we need energy growth
we want to re-industrialize the united states.
we need to be back in manufacturing.
every successful person doesn't need to have a phd.
every successful person doesn't have to have gone to stanford or mit.
and i think i think that that that you know that sensibility is is um spot on.
now, when we're talking about technology growth and energy growth,
there's a lot of people that go, " oh, no.
that's not what we need.
we need to, you know, simplify our lives and get back.
" but the the real issue is that we're in the middle of a giant technology race.
and whether people are aware of it or not, whether they like it or not,
it's happening. and it's a really important race
because whoever gets to whatever the event horizon of artificial intelligence is, whoever gets there first has massive advantages in a huge way.
do you agree with
that? well, first the part i i will say that we are in a technology race
and we are always in a technology race.
we've been in a technology race with somebody forever.
> > right. > > right. since the industrial revolution, we've been in a technology
> > since the manhattan project. > > yeah. > > or or you know,
even going back to the discovery of energy, right?
the united kingdom was where the industrial revolution was, if you will, invented
when they realized that they can turn steam and such into into energy into electricity.
all of that was invented largely in europe and the united states capitalized on it.
we were the ones that learned from it.
we industrialized it.
we diffused it faster than anybody in europe.
they were all stuck in discussions about policy and jobs and disruptions.
meanwhile, the united states was forming.
we just took the technology and ran with it.
and so i i think we were always in in a bit of a technology race.
world war ii was a technology race.
manhattan project was a technology race.
we've been in the technology race ever since during the cold war.
i think we're still in a technology race.
it is probably the single most important race. it is the technology is
uh
it gives you superpowers. you know whether it's information
superpowers or energy
superpowers or military superpowers is all founded in technology
and so technology leadership is really important
> > well
the problem is if somebody else has superior technology
right
that's that's the issue
it seems like with the ai race
people are very nervous about it
like you know
elon has famously said there was like 80 % chance it's awesome
20 % chance we're in trouble and people are worried about that
%
rightly
so.
i mean that you know if you had 10 bullets in a a a revolver
and you know you
you took out eight of them
and you still have tw two in there and you spin it, you're not going to feel real comfortable
when you pull that trigger.
it's terrifying, > > right? > > and when we're working towards this ultimate goal
um
of ai, it it just it's impossible to imagine
that it wouldn't be of national security interest to get there first.
we should
the question is what's there? that's the
that was the part that > > what is there? > > yeah.
i'm not sure.
> > and i don't think anybody i don't think anybody really knows.
> > that's crazy though.
if i ask you, > > you're the head of nvidia.
if you don't know what's there, who knows? > > yeah.
i i think it's probably going to be much more gradual than we think. it won't
it won't be a moment. it won't be
it won't be as if um somebody arrived and nobody else has.
i don't think it's going to be like that.
i think it's going to be things that just get better and better and better and better
just like technology does.
> > so, you are rosy about the future. you're
you're very optimistic about what's going to happen with ai.
> > obviously, will you make the best ai chips in the world? > > you probably better be.
> >
uh
h
if history is a guide, um
uh
we were always concerned about new technology.
humanity has always been concerned about new technology. there are always somebody who's thinking
there always a lot of people who are quite concerned. were quite concerned
and and and so
if
if history is a guide,
it is the case
um
that all of this concern is channeled into making the technology safer. and so for example,
in the last several years, i would say ai technology has increased probably in the last two years alone,
maybe a 100x.
let's just give it a number, okay? it's like a car two years ago was 100 times slower.
so ai is 100 times more capable today.
now, how did we channel
that technology? how do we channel all of that power? we directed it to um
causing the ai to be able to think, meaning that it can take a problem that we give it,
break it down step by step. it does research before it answers.
and so it grounds it on truth.
it'll reflect on that answer.
ask itself, is this the best, you know, answer that i can give you.
am i certain about this answer? if it's not certain about the answer
or highly confident about the answer, it'll go back
and do more research.
it might actually even use a tool
because that tool provides a better solution than it could hallucinate itself.
as a result, we took all of that computing capability
and we channeled it into having it produce a safer result, safer answer,
a more truthful answer
because as you know,
one of the greatest criticisms of ai in the beginning was that it hallucinated,
> > right? > >
and so if you look at the reason why people use ai so much today is
because the amount of hallucination
has reduced. you know,
i use it almost
i
well
i used it the whole trip over here
and so so i think
the
uh
the capability
most people think about power
and they think about
you know
maybe as an explosion power
but the technology power
most of it is channeled to towards safety.
a car today is more powerful but it's safer to drive.
a lot of that power goes towards better handling.
you know, i'd rather have a
well,
you have a 1000 horsepower truck.
i think 500 horsepower is pretty good.
no, i thousand's better.
i think a th00and is better.
> > i don't know if it's better, but it's definitely faster. > > yeah.
no, i think it's better.
you can get out of trouble faster. um, i enjoyed my 599 more than my 612. it was
i think it was a better
better
horsepower is better. my 459 is better than my 430.
more horsepower is better. i i think more horsepower is better. i think it's better handling. it's better control.
in the case of
in the case of technology, it's also very similar in that way, you know.
and so if you
if you look at what we're going to do with the next thousand times of performance in ai, a lot of it is going to be channeled towards more reflection, more research, thinking about the answer more deeply.
so when you're defining safety, you're defining a it as accuracy, > > functionality.
> > functionality. okay. > > it
it does what you expect it to do.
and then you take all the the the technology in the horsepower, you put guard rails on it, just like our cars.
we've got a lot of technology in in a car today.
a lot of it is goes towards, for example, abs.
abs is great. and so, uh, traction control, that's fantastic.
without a without a computer in the car, how would you do any of that, > > right?
> >
and
that little computer, the computers
that you have doing your traction control is more powerful than the computer that went to apollo 11.
and so you want that technology, channel it towards safety, channel it towards functionality.
and so
when people talk about power, the advancement of technology, often times i i i feel what they're thinking
and what we're actually doing is very different.
> > well, what do you think they're thinking? well, they're thinking somehow that this
this
uh
this ai is being powerful and their their mind probably goes towards a sci-fi movie.
the definition of power, you know,
often times the definition definition of power is military power or physical power.
but in in the case of technology
power
when we translate all of those operations
it's towards more refined thinking
you know
more reflection
more planning
more options
> > i think the big fears that people have is one
a big fear is military applications
that's a big fear
> > because people are very concerned that you're going to have
> > ai systems that make decisions that maybe an ethical person wouldn't make
or a moral person wouldn't make based on achieving an objective versus based on, you know, how it's going to look to people.
> > well,
i'm
i'm happy that that
uh
our military is going to use ai technology for defense
and i think that that
um
uh
andural
building military technology. i'm happy to hear that. i'm happy to see
um
all these tech startups now channeling their technology capabilities towards defense and military applications.
i think you needed to do that. > > yeah,
we had palmer lucky on the podcast.
he was demonstrating some of the stuff i put his helmet on. and we show we
he showed some videos how you could see behind walls and stuff like it's nuts. > > and he's
he's actually the perfect guy to go start that company. > > 100
%. [laughter] yeah.
%. it's like he was born for that. yeah.
he came in here with a copper jacket on. he's a freak. [clears throat]
it's [laughter] awesome.
he's awesome. but it's also
it's a
you know
an unusual intellect channeled into that very bizarre field is what you need, you
and i think it's
it's
uh
i think i'm happy that we're making it so more socially acceptable.
you know, there was a time where
when somebody wanted to channel their technology capability and their intellect into defense technology, uh
somehow they're vilified.
um
but
uh
we need people like that.
we need people who enjoyed enjoy that part of uh application of technology.
> > well, people are terrified of war, you know.
so it depends.
> > best way to avoid it has excessive military might.
> > do you think that's absolutely the best way? not not diplomacy, not working stuff out.
> > all of it.
you have to have military might in order to get people to sit down with you. > > right.
exactly. all of it. >
>
otherwise, they just invade.
> > that's right.
[laughter] why ask for permission?
> > again,
like you said,
history.
go back and look at history.
um,
when you look at the future of ai
and
and you just said that no one really knows what's happening, do you ever sit down and ponder scenarios?
> > like
what do you
what do you think is like bestcase scenario for ai over the next two decades?
um
the best case scenario is that ai diffuses into everything that we do
and
uh
our
everything's more efficient
but the threat of war remains a threat of war.
uh,
cyber security remains a super difficult challenge.
somebody is going to try to breach your security.
you're going to have thousands of millions of ai agents protecting you from that threat.
your technology is going to get better.
their technology is going to get better. just like cyber security. right now, while we speak, we're being
we're seeing cyber attacks all over the planet on just about every front door you can imagine.
and and yet you and i are sitting here talking.
and so the reason for that is
because we know that there's a whole bunch of cyber security technology in defense.
and so we just have to keep amping that up, keep stepping that up.
this episode is brought to you by visible.
when your phone plans as good as visible, you've got to tell your people.
it's the ultimate wireless hack to save money and still get great coverage and a reliable connection.
get one line wireless with unlimited data and hotspot for $ 25 a month.
taxes and fees included, all on verizon's 5g network.
plus, now for a limited time, new members can get the visible plan for just $ 19 a month for the first 26 months.
use promo code switch 26 and save beyond the season.
it's a deal so good you're going to want to tell your people.
switch now at visible. com / rogan.
terms apply. limited time offers subject to change. see visible. com for planned features and network management details.
that's a big issue with people is the the worry that technology is going to get to a point
where encryption is going to be obsolete.
encryption is just it's no longer going to protect data.
it's no longer going to protect systems. do you anticipate that ever being an issue
or do you think there's it's as the defense grows, the threat grows, the defense grows,
and it just keeps going on
and on and on and they'll always be able to fight off any sort of intrusions?
> > not forever.
some intrusion will get in and then that we'll all learn from it.
and you know the reason why cyber security works is
because of course the technology of defense is advancing very quickly.
the technology offense is advancing very quickly.
however, the benefit of the cyber security defense is that socially the community
all of our companies work together as one.
most people don't realize this.
there's a whole community of cyber security experts.
we exchange ideas.
we exchange best practices.
we exchange what we detect. the moment something has been breached or maybe there's a loophole
or whatever it is,
it is shared by everybody. the patches are shared with everybody.
> > that's interesting.
> > yeah. most people don't realize this. > > no,
i had
no
i had no idea.
i've assumed that it would just be competitive like everything else. > > we work together. interesting.
has that always been the case? > > uh,
it surely has been the case for about about 15 years.
it might not have been the case long ago, but this this > > what do you think started off
that cooperation? > > um,
people recognizing it's a challenge and no company can stand alone.
> > and the same thing is going to happen with ai.
i think we all have to decide work working together
uh
to stay out of harm's way is
is our best chance for defense.
then it's basically everybody against the threat.
> > and it also seems like you'd be way better at detecting
where these threats are coming from and neutralizing them.
> > exactly.
because the moment you detect it somewhere, > > you're going to find out right away.
> > it'll be really hard to hide. > > that's right.
> > yeah. > > that's how it works. that's the reason why it's safe.
that's why i'm sitting here right now instead of, you know,
locking everything down in video.
[laughter] > > it's not only am i watching my own back,
i've got everybody watching my back.
and i'm watching everybody else's back.
> > it's a bizarre world, isn't it?
when you think about
that cyber threat, > > this idea about cyber security is unknown to the people who are talking about ai threats.
they're
i think
when they think about ai threats
and ai cyber security threats, they have to also think about how we deal with it today.
now, there's no question that ai is a new technology and it's a new type of software.
in the end, it's software
just it's a new type of software and so it's going to have new capabilities
but so will the defense
you know where you use the same ai technology to go defend against it.
so you do you anticipate a time ever in the future
where it's going to be impossible where there's not going to be any secrets
where the bottleneck between the technology that we have and the information that we have.
information is just all a bunch of ones and zeros.
it's out there on hard drives and the technology has more and more access to that information.
is it ever going to get to a point in time
where there's no way to keep a secret? > > i don't think
> > because it seems like that's where everything is kind of headed in a weird way.
> > i don't think so.
i think the quantum computers were supposed to
will
yeah.
quantum computers will make it possible
will make it so that the previous quantum
previous encryption technology is obsolete.
but that's the reason why the entire industry is working on postquantum encryption technology.
> > what would that look like? > > new algorithms.
> > but the crazy thing is
when you hear about the kind of computation that quantum computing can do.
> > yeah. > > and the the power that it has. yeah.
> > where you know you're looking at
> > all the supercomputers in the world.
it would take billions of years and it takes them a few minutes to solve these equations.
like how do you make encryption for something
that can do
that? i'm not sure, but there's [laughter] but i've got a bunch of scientists who are working on that.
> > boy, i hope they [snorts] could figure it out.
> > yeah, we got a bunch of scientists who are expert in that.
and > > is the ultimate fear that it can't be breached
that quantum computing will always be able to to decrypt all other quantum computing encryption? > > i don't think
that
> > it just gets to some point where it's like, stop playing the stupid game. we know everything.
> > i don't think so. > > no, > > because i
i'm
you know,
history is guide.
history is a guide before ai came around.
that's my worry. my worry is this is a totally,
you know,
it's like history was one thing
and then nuclear weapons kind of changed all of our thoughts on war
and mutually assured destruction came everybody to stop using nuclear bombs.
> > yeah.
> > my worry is that > >
the thing is joe is that that ai is not going to
it's not like we're cavemen
and then all of a sudden one day ai shows up.
every single day we're getting better and smarter because we have ai
and so we're stepping on our own ai's shoulders.
so when when that whatever that ai threat comes, it's a click ahead.
it's not a galaxy ahead, > > you know,
it's just a click ahead. and so so i think i think the
the
the idea that somehow this ai is going to pop out of nowhere
and somehow think in a way that we can't even imagine thinking
and do something that we can't possibly imagine i think is far-fetched.
and the reason for that is because we're all have
we all have ais
and you know there's a whole bunch of ais being in development.
we know what they are and we're using it and and so every single day we're getting
we're close to each other.
> > but don't they do things that are very surprising? > > yeah.
but so you you have an ai that does something surprising.
i'm going to have an ai and my ai looks at your ai and goes
that's not that surprising.
> >
the fear for the lay person like myself is that ai becomes sentient
and makes its own decisions and then ultimately decides to just govern the world.
do it its own way.
they're like, " you guys, you had a good run, but > > we're taking over now.
" > > yeah, but my my ai is gonna take care of me.
i mean, [laughter] so that's the
this is the cyber security argument. > > yes.
> > do you have an ai
and it's super smart, but my ai is super smart, too. and and maybe your ai.
let let's pretend
let's let's pretend for a second that we understand what consciousness is
and we understand what sentience is and and that in fact
> > and we really are just pretending.
> > okay, let's just pretend for a second that we we believe that. i don't believe
actually
i don't actually don't believe that
but nonetheless we
let's pretend we believe that. > > so your
your
your ai is conscious and my ai is conscious
and and let's say your ai is you know
wants to
i don't know
do something surprising. my ai is so smart that it won't
it might be surprising to me, but it probably won't be surprising to my ai.
and so maybe my ai thinks it's surprising as well,
but it's so smart the moment it sees it the first time, it's not going to be a surprise the second time, just like us.
and so i feel like i think the idea that that only one person has [clears throat] ai
and that one person's ai is compares
everybody else's ai is neanderthal
[snorts] is um
probably unlikely.
i think it's much more like cyber security.
> > interesting.
> > i think the fear is not that your ai is going to battle with somebody else's ai.
the fear is that ai is no longer going to listen to you.
that's the fear is that human beings won't have control over it after a certain point
if it achieves sensience and then has the ability to be autonomous
> > that there's one ai.
> > well, they just combine. > > yeah.
becomes one ai > > that it's a life form.
> > yeah.
> > but
that's the there's arguments about
that, right? that we're dealing with some sort of synthetic biology that it's not as simple as new technology
that you're creating a life form.
> > if it's like life form,
let's go along with that for a while. i think if it's like life form,
as you know,
all life forms don't agree. and so i'm going to have to go with your life form
and my life form are going to agree
because my life form is going to want to be the super life form.
and and now that now that we have disagreeing life forms, uh
we're back back again to where we are.
well, they would probably cooperate with each other.
it would just the reason why we don't cooperate with each other is we're territorial primates.
but ai wouldn't be a territorial primate.
it would realize the folly in that sort of thinking and it would say, " listen,
there's plenty of energy for everybody. we we don't need to dominate. we don't need
we're not trying to acquire resources and take over the world.
we're not looking to find a good breeding partner.
we're just existing as a new super life form that these cute monkeys created for us.
" okay. well, that would be a
that would be a um
a superpower with no ego, > > right?
and and if it has no ego, why would it have the ego to do any harm to us?
> > well, i don't assume that it would do harm to us,
but the the fear would be that we would no longer have control
and that we would no longer be the apex species on the planet.
this thing that we created would now be.
[laughter] > > is that funny? > > no.
> > i just think it's not gonna happen.
> > i know you think it's not gonna happen, but > > it could, right?
and here's the other thing is like > > if we're racing towards could
yeah.
> > and could could be the end of human beings being in control of our own destiny.
> > i just think it's extremely unlikely. > > yeah.
> > that's what they said in the terminator movie [laughter] > > and it hasn't happened.
> > no, not yet.
but you guys are working towards it. um
the
the thing about you're saying about conscience and sensience
that you don't think that ai will achieve consciousness or that the question is
what's the definition? > > yeah.
what's the definition of
> > what is the definition to you? > >
um
uh
consciousness
um
uh
f
i guess
first of all
uh
you need to know about your own existence. um,
you have to have experience, not just knowledge and intelligence. the concept of a machine having an experience.
i'm not well,
first of all,
i don't know what defines experience,
why we have experiences, right? > > yeah.
and why this microphone doesn't uh
and so it
i think i know
i
well
i think i
i
i think i know what consciousness is the sense of experience
the ability to know self versus um
uh
the ability to be able to reflect
know our own self
the sense of ego
i think all of all of those human experiences
uh
probably is what consciousness is
but why it exists versus the concept of knowledge and intelligence
which is what ai is defined by
today
it has knowledge
it has intelligence
artificial intelligence
we don't call it artificial consciousness
the ability to uh
perceive believe, recognize, understand, um, plan, uh, perform tasks. those things are foundations of intelligence
to know things, knowledge.
i don't, it's clearly different than consciousness.
> > but consciousness is so loosely defined. how can we say that?
i mean, doesn't a dog have consciousness? yeah.
> > dogs seem to be pretty conscious. > > that's right.
> > yeah.
so, and that's a lower level consciousness than a human being's consciousness. > > i'm not sure.
yeah. right.
well, > > the question is what lower level intelligence? it's lower level intelligence, but i don't know
that it's lower level consciousness.
> > that's a good point.
right. > > because i believe my dogs feel as much as i feel. > > yeah.
they feel a lot. right. > > yeah.
they get attached to you. that's right.
they get depressed if you're not there. > > that's right.
exactly. > > there's
there's
definitely that.
> > yeah.
um
the the concept of experience, > > right? > > um
but isn't ai interacting with society?
so, doesn't it acquire experience through that interaction? > > um
i don't think interactions is experience. i think experience is
uh
experience is a collection of feelings. i think
> > you're aware of that ai
um
i forget which one
where they gave it some false information about one of the programmers having an affair with his wife
just to see how it would respond to it
and then when they said they were going to shut it down
it threatened to blackmail him and reveal his affair
and it was like whoa
like it's conniving
like if that's not learning from experience and being aware that you're about to be shut down
which would imply at least some kind of consciousness
or you could kind defined it as consciousness
if you were very loose with the term
and if you imagine that this is going to exponentially become more powerful.
wouldn't
that ultimately lead to a different kind of consciousness
than we're defining from biology? well, first of all, let's just break down what it probably did.
it probably read somewhere.
there's probably text that that in these consequences certain people did that.
i could imagine a novel, > > right? > > having those words related.
> > sure.
> > and so inside > > it realizes it strategy for survival is
> > it's just a bunch of numbers
> >
that it's just a bunch of numbers
that that in the in the collection of numbers that relates to a husband cheating on a wife.
um
has subsequently a bunch of numbers that relates to blackmail and such things.
however, whatever the revenge was, > > right? > > and so it has spewed it out.
> > and so it's just like, you know, it
it's just as if i'm asking it to write me a poem in shakespeare. it just whatever the words
are in the world
in in that dimensionality, this dimensionality is all these vectors and in in multi-dimensional space.
these words that were in the prompt that described the affair
um
subsequently led to one word after another led to
you know
some revenge and something
but it's not because it had consciousness
or you know
it just spewed out those words generated those words > >
i understand what you're saying that patterns that human beings have exhibited both in literature and in real life
> > that's exactly right
> > but it at a certain point in time
one would say, " okay,
well, it couldn't do this two years ago and it couldn't do this four years ago.
" like
when we're looking towards the future, like at what point in time
when it can do everything a person does,
what point in time do we decide that it's conscious?
if it absolutely mimics all human thinking and behavior patterns, > > that doesn't make it conscious.
> > it becomes in disccernible.
it's it's aware.
it can communicate with you the exact same way a person can. like is con is consciousness
are we putting too much weight on that concept
because it seems like it's a version of a kind of consciousness.
> > it's a version of imitation.
> > imitation consciousness, right? but if it perfectly imitates it, > > i still think it's a per
it's an example of imitation.
> > so it's like a fake rolex when they 3d print them and make them > > indestruable.
the question is what's the definition consciousness?
> > yeah. > > yeah. > > that's the question.
and i don't think anybody's really clearly defined that.
that's what get
where it gets weird and that that's
where the real doomsday people are worried that you are creating a form of consciousness that you can't control.
i believe it is possible to create a machine that imitates human intelligence
and has the ability to understand information, understand instructions, break the problem down, solve problems, and perform tasks.
i believe that completely. i believe that that
um
we could have a computer that has a vast amount of knowledge.
some of it true, some of it not true.
some of it generated by humans, some of it generated synthetically.
and more and more of knowledge in the world will be generated synthetically going forward. you know,
until now
the knowledge that we've we have are knowledge that we generate
and we propagate
and we send to each other and we amplify it and we add to it and we modify it.
we change it.
in the future, in a couple of years, maybe two
or three years, 90 % of the world's knowledge will likely be generated
by ai.
> > that's crazy. > > i know.
but it's just fine. > > but it's just fine. > > i know.
and the reason for that is this.
let me tell you
why.
> > okay? > > it's because
um
what difference does it make to me that i am learning from a textbook that was generated
by a bunch of people i didn't know
or written by a book that you know
from somebody i don't know
uh
to
knowledge generated by ai computers that are assimilating all of this and reynthesizing things.
to me, i don't think there's a whole lot of difference. we still have to
we still have to fact check it. we still have to make sure that it's you know
based on fundamental first principles
and we still have to do all of that just like we do today.
> > is this taking into account the kind of ai that exists currently? and do you anticipate that
just like we could have never really believed that ai would be
at
least
a person like myself would never believe ai would be as so ubiquitous and so worth it. it's
it's so powerful today and so important today.
we never thought that 10 years ago.
never thought
that, > > right? > > you imagine like what are we looking at 10 years from now? > > i i think
that if you reflect back 10 years from now, you would say the same thing
that we would have never believed that
> > but > > in a different direction, > > right?
but if you
if you go forward 9 years from now
and then ask yourself what's going to happen 10 years from now, i think it'll be quite gradual.
um,
one of the things that elon said that makes me happy is he
he's
he believes that we're going to get to a point where it's not
it's not necessary for people to work
and not meaning that you're going to have no purpose in life, but you will have
in his words
universal high income
because so much revenue is generated
by ai
that it will take away this need for people to do things
that they don't really enjoy doing just for money.
and i think a lot of people have a problem with that
because their entire identity
and who how they think of themselves and how they fit in the community is what they do.
like this is mike.
he's an amazing mechanic. go to mike
and mike takes care of things.
but there's going to come a point in time
where ai is going to be able to do all those things much better than than people do.
and people will just be able to receive money.
but then what does mike do? mike is, you know, really loves being the best mechanic around.
you know, what does the guy who, you know, codes,
what does he do
when ai can code infinitely faster with zero errors? like what what happens with all those people?
and that is
where it gets weird.
it's like because we've sort of wrapped our identity as human beings around what we do for a living.
> >
you know, when you meet someone, one of the first things you meet somebody at a party, hi
joe.
what's your name? mike.
what do you do? mike
and you know mike's like, " oh, i'm a lawyer.
" " oh, what kind of law? " and you have a conversation, you know,
when mike is like, " i get money from the government.
i play video games. " > > gets weird. > > mhm.
> >
and i think
um
the concept sounds great until you take into account human nature.
and human nature is that we like to have puzzles to solve and things to do
and
and an identity
that's wrapped around our idea that we're very good at this thing that we do for a living.
> > yeah.
yeah,
i think
um
let's see, let me start with the more mundane
and i'll work
work backwards, okay? work forward. uh
so
one of the predictions from uh
jeff hinton
who who started the whole deep learning phenomenon
the deep learning technology trend
and
uh
in incredible incredible researcher
professor at university of toronto
uh
he invented
discovered or invented the the idea of of back propagation
which
uh
allows the neural network to learn.
and um
and as
as as you know
uh
for for the audience,
software historically was humans
applying first principles and our thinking to
uh
describe an algorithm that is
then
codified just like a recipe that's codified in software.
it looks just like a recipe.
how to cook something looks exactly the same just in a slightly different language. we call it python
or c or c + + or whatever it is.
in the case of deep learning, this invention of artificial intelligence, we put a structure of a whole bunch of neural networks
and a whole bunch of math units
and we make this large structure.
it's like a switchboard of little u mathematical units and we connect it all together. um,
and we give it the input that the software would eventually receive
and we just let it randomly guess what the output is.
and so we say,
for example,
the input could be a picture of a cat.
and and um
one of the outputs of the switchboard is where the cat signal is supposed to show up.
and all of the other signals, the other one's a dog, the other one's an elephant, the other one's a tiger.
and all of the other signals are supposed to be zero when i show it a cat.
and the one that is a cat should be one.
and i show at a cat through this big huge network of switchboards and math units
and they're just doing multiply and adds multiplies and ads. okay? and and uh
and this thing, this switchboard is gigantic.
the more information you're going to give it, the more the bigger this switchboard has to be.
and what jeff hinton discovered was a invented was a way for you to guess
that put the cat signal in
put the cat image in
and that cat image you know could be a million numbers
because it's you know
a megapixel image
for example
and it's just a whole
a whole bunch of numbers
and somehow from those numbers it has to light up the cat signal. okay, that's the bottom line.
and if it
the first time you do it, it just comes up with garbage.
and so it says the right answer is cat.
and so you need to increase this signal
and decrease all of the other and back propagates the outcome through the entire network.
and then you show another.
now it's an image of a dog
and it guesses it takes a swing at it
and it comes up with a bunch of garbage and you say
no
the answer is
this is a dog
i want you to produce dog
and all of the other switch
all the other outputs have to be zero
and i want to back propagate that and just do it over and over and over again.
it's just like
uh
showing a a kid
this is an apple, this is a dog, this is a cat.
and you just keep showing it to them until they eventually get it.
okay.
well, anyways, that big invention is deep learning.
that's the foundation of artificial intelligence, a piece of software that learns from examples.
that's basically we machine learning, a machine that learns. uh
and so so one of the the big first applications was image recognition
and one of the most important image recognition applications is radiology. > >
and so
so
uh
he predicted
about 5 years ago that in five years time the world won't need any radiologists
because ai would have swept the whole field.
well, it turns out ai has swept the whole field.
that is completely true.
today, just about every radiologist is using ai in some way.
and what's ironic though, what's what's interesting is that the number of radiologist has actually grown.
and so the question is why?
that's kind of interesting, right? > > it is.
and so the prediction was in fact that 30 million radiologists will be wiped out.
but as it turns out, we needed more.
and the reason for that [clears throat and cough] is
because the purpose of a radiologist is to diagnose disease, not to study the image.
this
the image studying is simply a task to in service of diagnosing the disease.
and so now the fact that you could study the images more quickly
and more precisely without ever making a mistake and never gets tired.
you could study more images. you could study it in 3d form instead of 2d
because you know the ai doesn't care whether it studies images in 3d or 2d.
you could study it in 4d.
and so the now you could study images in a way that radiologist radiologists can't easily do
and you could study a lot more of it.
and so the number of tests that people are able to do increases and
because they're able to serve more patients, the hospital does better.
they have more clients, more patients.
as a result, they have better economics.
when they have better economics, they hire more radiologists because their purpose is not to study the images.
their purpose is to diagnose disease.
and so the question is the what i'm leading up to is ultimately what is the purpose? what is the purpose of the lawyer?
and has the purpose changed? what is the purpose? you know, one of the examples
that i gave is is
um
that i would give
is
for example
uh
if my car became self-driving will all chauffeers be out of jobs?
the answer probably is not because for some per
for some chauffeers
they
for some people who are driving you
they could be protectors
some people
um
they're part of the experience
part of the service
so when you get there
they you know they could take care of things for you
and so for a lot of different reasons not all chauffeers would lose their jobs
some chauffeers would lose their jobs
and
uh
many chauffeers would change their jobs and the type of applications of autonomous vehicles will probably increase
you know
the usage of the technology within
find new homes
and so i i think you have to go back to what is the purpose of a job
you know
like
for example
if ai comes along
i actually don't believe i'm going to lose my job because my purpose isn't to
i have to look at a lot of documents
i study a lot of emails
i look at a bunch of diagrams
you know
um
the question is what is the job and and
uh
the purpose of somebody
probably hasn't changed
a lawyer
for example
help people that probably hasn't changed
studying legal documents
generating documents
it's part of the job
not the job
> > but don't you think there's many jobs that ai will replace
> > if your job is automation
> > yeah
if your job is the task
> > right
so automation > >
yeah
factor
if your job is the task
> > that's a lot of people > > it could be a lot of people
but it'll probably generate like for example
> >
uh
let's say
we
i'm super excited about the the the robots elon's working on.
it's still a few years away. when it happens, when it happens,
um
there's a whole new industry of technicians and people who have to manufacture the robots, right? > > mhm.
> > and so that that job never existed.
and so you're going to have a whole industry of people taking care of
like
for example,
you know,
all the mechanics and all the people who are building things for cars, supercharging cars, uh
that didn't exist before cars
and now we're going to have robots. you're going to have robot apparel.
so a whole industry of [laughter] right.
isn't that right? because i want my robot to look different than your robot.
> > oh god. > > and so [laughter] you're going to
you're going to have a whole, you know, apparel industry for robots.
you're going to have mechanics for robots and you have
you know people who comes and maintain your robots
> > automated though.
> > no, > > you don't think so? you don't think [clears throat] they'll be all done
by other robots > > eventually?
and then there'll be something else. > > so you think ultimately people just adapt
except if you are the task
> > which is a large percentage of the workforce.
> > if your job is just to chop vegetables,
quezin art is going to replace you.
> > yeah.
so people have to find meaning in other things. your job has to be more than the task.
> > what do you think about elon's belief that this universal basic income thing will eventually become necessary?
> > many people think that.
andrew yang thinks
that > > he was one of the first people to sort of sound
that alarm during the the 2020 election.
yeah,
i i guess
um
yeah,
both ideas probably won't exist at the same time
and and
um
as in life, things will probably be in the middle.
one idea, of course, is that there'll be so much abundance of resource that nobody needs a job
and we'll all be wealthy.
on the other hand,
um
we're going to need universal basic income.
both ideas don't exist at the same time, > > right? > >
and so we're either going to be all wealthy or we're going to be all
> >
how could everybody be wealthy though? but > > because
scenario
wealthy
not because you have a lot of dollars, wealthy because there's a lot of abundance.
like
for example,
today we are wealthy of information.
you know, this is some a concept several thousand years ago only a few people have.
and so, uh, today we have wealth of a whole bunch of things, resources that that historic point.
yeah.
and so, we're going to have wealth of resources, things
that we think are valuable today that in the future are just not not that valuable, you know,
and so it
because it's automated. and so i think i think the question maybe maybe partly it's hard to answer
partly because it's hard to talk about infinity and it's hard to talk about a long time from now
and and the reason for that is because there's just too many scenarios to to consider.
but i think it
i think
in the next several years, call it 5 to 10 years, there are several things
that i i believe in hope.
um, and i say hope
because i'm not sure.
one of the things that i believe is that the technology divide will be substantially collapsed.
and of course the alternative viewpoint is that ai is going to increase the technology divide.
now the reason why i believe ai is going to reduce the technology divide.
i is because we have proof
the evidence is that ai is the easiest application in the world to use.
chat gpt has grown to almost a billion users frankly practically overnight.
and if you're not exactly sure how to use,
everybody knows how to use chatpt.
just say something to it. if you're not sure how to use chatpt,
you ask chatd how to use it.
no tool in history has ever had this capability. a quez an art,
you know,
if you don't know how to use it, you're kind of screwed.
you're going to walk up to it
and say, " how do you use a quezin art? " you're going to have to find somebody else.
and so, but an ai will just tell you exactly how to do it.
anybody could do this.
it'll speak to you in any language.
and if it doesn't know your language, you'll speak it in that language
and it'll probably figure out that it doesn't completely understand your language.
go learns it instantly and comes back and talk to you.
and so i think the the technology divide has a real chance finally
that you don't have to speak python
or c + + or forran.
you can just speak human and whatever form of human you like.
and so i think that that has a real chance of closing the technology divine.
now, of course, the counternarrative would say that ai is only going to be available for the nations
and the countries that have a vast amount of resources
because ai takes energy
and ai takes um a lot of gpus and factories to be able to produce the ai.
no doubt at the scale that we would like to do in the united states.
but the fact of the matter is your phone's going to run ai just fine all
by itself, you know,
in a few years.
today, it already does it fairly decently.
and so the the the fact
that every every country, every nation, every every society will have the benefit of very good ai.
it might not be tomorrow's ai.
it might be yesterday's ai,
but yesterday's ai is freaking amazing.
you know, in 10 years time, 9year-old ai is going to be amazing.
you don't need, you know, 10 year old ai. you don't need frontier ai
like we need frontier ai because we want to be the world leader.
but for every single country, everybody, i think the ele the capability to elevate everybody's knowledge
and capability and intelligence, uh,
that day is coming.
the octagon isn't just in las vegas anymore.
it's right in your hands with draftkings sportsbook, the official sports betting partner of ufc.
get ready
because
when dwabish willie
and yan face off again at ufc 323, every punch, every takedown, every finish, it all has the potential to pay off in real time.
new customers bet just $ 5. and if your bet wins, you get paid $ 200 in bonus bets.
and hey, missouri, the wait is over.
draftkings sportsbook is now live in the show me state.
download the draftkings sportsbook app and use promo code rogan.
that's code rogan to turn five bucks into 200 in bonus bets if your bet wins.
in partnership with draftkings, the crown is yours. gambling problem? call 1800 gambler.
in new york, call 8778
wire or text hope 467-369.
in connecticut, help is available for a problem gambling. call 888789-7777 or visit ccpg. org. please play responsibly.
on behalf of bootill casino and resort in kansas, pass through of per wager tax may apply in illinois.
21 and over.
age and eligibility varies by jurisdiction void in ontario.
restrictions apply. bet must win to receive bonus bets which expire in 7 days.
minimum odds required.
for additional terms and responsible gaming resources, see dkg.
co / audio.
limited time offer.
> > and also energy production, which is the real bottleneck
when it comes to third world countries and > > that's right,
> > electricity and all all the resources that we take for granted.
> > almost everything is going to be energy constrained.
and so if you take a look at
um
one of the most important technology advances in history is this idea called moore's law.
moore's law was the started basically in my generation
and my generation is the generation of computers.
i graduated in 1984
and that was basically at the very beginning of the pc revolution. and the microprocessor and and um
every single year it approximately doubled
and we describe it as every single year we double the performance.
but what it really means is that every single year the cost of computing halfed.
and so the cost of computing in the course of five years reduced by a factor of 10.
the amount of energy necessary to do computing to do any task
reduced by a factor of 10.
every single 10 years
100 a th00and
10,
100, 000 so on
and so forth.
and so each one of the clicks of moore's law,
the amount of energy necessary to do any computing reduced. that's the reason why you have a laptop today
when back in 1984 sat on the desk, you got to plug in,
it wasn't that fast
and it consumed a lot of power. today,
you know,
it is only a few watts.
and so moore's law is the fundamental technology, the fundamental technology trend that made it possible.
well, what's going on in ai? the reason why nvidia is here is
because in we invented this new way of doing computing.
we call it accelerated computing.
we started it 33 years ago. took us about 30 years to really made a huge breakthrough. in that
in that 30 years or so we took computing
you know
probably a factor of
well
let me just say
in last 10 years
the last 10 years
we improved the performance of computing by 100, 000 times.
whoa.
imagine a car over the course of 10 years that became a 100, 000 times faster
or at the same speed
100, 000 times cheaper
100, 000 times less energy.
if your car did that, it doesn't need energy at all.
what i mean what what i'm trying to say is that in 10 years time
the amount of energy necessary for artificial intelligence for most people will be minuscule
utterly minuscule
and so we'll have ai running in all kinds of things and all the time
because it doesn't consume that much energy and so if you're a nation that uses ai
for
you know almost everything in your social fabric
of course you're going to need these ai factories
but for a lot of countries
i think you're going
you're going to have excellent ai and you're not going to need as much energy.
everybody will be able to come along
is my point.
> > so currently that that is a big bottleneck, right? is energy.
> > yeah, it is the bottleneck.
> > the bottleneck is this.
so was it google
that is making nuclear power plants to operate one of its ai factories? > > oh, i haven't heard
that.
but i think in the next six, seven years, i think you're going to see a whole bunch of small nuclear reactors.
> > and by small,
like how big are you talking about? hundreds of megawws.
yeah.
> > okay. and that these will be local to whatever specific company they have. > > that's right.
will all be power generators. > > whoa. > > you know,
just like
just like your
you know,
somebody's farm.
> > it probably is the smartest way to do it, right? > >
and it takes the burden off
yeah.
takes the burden off the grid. it takes and you could build as much as you need
> > and you can contribute back to the grid.
it's a really important point that i think you just made about moore's law and the relationship to pricing
because you know a laptop today
like you can get one of those little mac macbook airs.
they're incredible. they're so thin, unbelievably powerful. battery life is charge it. > > yeah.
battery [laughter] life's crazy. and uh
it's not that expensive
relatively speaking.
like something like that. > > i remember.
> > and that's just moore's law, right? > > then there's the nvidia law.
> > oh, > > just right.
the the the law i was talking to you about, the computing
that we invented, > > right? > >
the reason why we're here, this new this new way of doing computing
> > is like mo's law on energy drinks. i mean, it's [laughter] it's like mo's law
it's
it's like
yeah.
moore's law and joe rogan.
> > wow.
that's interesting. > > yeah.
that's us.
> > so, explain that. um
this
this chip that you brought to elon,
what
what's the significance of this? it's like
why is it so superior?
and so in 2012, jeff hinton's lab,
this gentleman i was talking talking about,
um
ilas suscober,
alex kresevski, um
they made a breakthrough in computer vision in literally creating a piece of software called alexnet.
and its job was to recognize images. and it recognized images at a c
at a level
computer vision which is fundamental to intelligence. if you can't perceive, you can't
it's hard to have intelligence.
and so computer vision is a fundamental pillar of not the only but fundamental pillar of.
and so breaking computer vision
or breaking through in computer vision is pretty foundational to almost everything that everybody wants to do in ai.
and so in 2012, their lab in toronto
uh
made
this
made this breakthrough called alexnet.
and alexet was able to recognize images so much better
than any human created computer vision algorithm in the 30 years prior.
so all of these people, all these scientists
and we had many too working on computer vision algorithms
and these two kids, ilia and alex under the the
uh
under under
jeff hinton took a giant leap above it and it was based on this thing called alexet
this neural network.
and the way it ran, the way they they made it work was literally buying two nvidia graphics cards
because nvidia nvidia's gpus
we've been working on this new way of doing computing and our gpus application
and it's basically a supercomputing application to back in 1984 in order to process computer games
and what you have in your racing simulator that is called an image generator
supercomputer. and so nvidia started our first application was computer graphics
and we applied this new way of doing computing where we do things in parallel in instead of sequentially.
a cpu does things sequentially. step one, step two, step three.
in our case, we break the problem down and we give it to thousands of processors.
and so our way of doing computation is much more complicated.
but if you're able to formulate the problem in the way that we created called cuda,
this is the invention of our company.
if you could formulate it in that way, we could process everything simultaneously.
now, in the case of computer graphics, it's easier to do
because every single pixel on your screen is not related to every other pixel.
and so, i could render multiple parts of the screen at the same time.
not not completely true because, you know,
maybe maybe the way lighting works or the way shadow works, there's a lot of dependency and and such.
but computer graphics
with all the dis
with all the pixels, i should be able to process everything simultaneously.
and so we we took this embarrassingly parallel problem called computer graphics
and we applied it to this new way of doing computing.
nvidia's nvidia's accelerated computing.
we put it in all of our graphics cards. kids were buying it to play games.
we're
you probably don't know this, but we're the largest gaming platform in the world today.
> > oh, i know that.
oh, > > okay.
> > i used to make my own computers.
i used to buy your graphics cards. > > oh, that's super cool.
> > yeah.
[laughter] set up sli with two graphics cards. > > yeah,
i love it. okay, that's super cool.
> > oh, yeah, man.
i used to be a quake junkie. > > oh, that's cool.
> > yeah.
> > okay, so sli, i'll tell you the story in just a second
and how it led to elon.
i'm still answering the question.
and so, anyways,
these these two kids trained this model using the technique i described earlier on our gpus
because our gpus could process things in parallel.
it's essentially a supercomput in a pc.
the reason why you used it for quake is because it is the first consumer supercomputer.
okay.
and so anyways, they made that breakthrough.
we were working on computer vision at the time.
it caught my attention and so we went to learn about it.
simultaneously this deep learning phenomenon was happening all over all over the country.
universities after another recognized the importance of deep learning
and all of this work was happening at stanford, at harvard, at berkeley, just all over the place.
new york university, l yan lakun, andrew yang at stanford, so many different places.
and i see it cropping up everywhere. and so my curiosity asked,
you know,
what is so special about this form of machine learning?
and we've known about machine learning for a very long time.
we've known about ai for a very long time.
we've known about neural networks for a very long time. what makes now the moment?
and so we realized
that this architecture for deep neural networks back propagation the way deep neuronet networks were created.
we could probably scale this problem, scale the solution to solve many problems.
that is essentially a universal function approximator.
okay? meaning meaning you know
back when you're in in in school
you have a
you have a box inside of it is a function
you give it an input
it gives you an output
and and the
the reason why i call it universal function approximator
is that this computer
instead of you describing the function
a function could be a new equation
fals
ma
that's a function
you write the function in software
you give it input
f mass acceleration, it'll tell you the force.
okay? and the way this computer works is really interesting.
you give it a universal function.
it's not fals, just a universal function. it's a big huge deep neural network
and instead of describing the inside, you give it examples of input and output
and it figures out the inside.
so you give it input and output and it figures out the inside.
a universal function approximator.
today it could be newton's equation.
tomorrow it could be maxwell's equation. it could be kulum's law. it could be thermodynamics equation. it could be
you know shingers's equation for quantum physics. and so you could put any
you could have this
describe almost anything
so long as you have the input and the output.
so long as you have the input and the output
or it could learn the input and output.
> > and so we took a step back and we said, " hang on a second.
this isn't just for computer vision.
deep learning could solve any problem.
all the problems that are interesting so long as we have input and output.
now what has input and output? well, the world.
the world has input and output.
and so we could have a computer that could learn almost anything. machine learning, artificial intelligence.
and so we reasoned that maybe this is the fundamental breakthrough that we needed.
there were a couple of things that had to be solved.
for example, we had to believe that you could actually scale this up to giant systems.
it was running in a they had two graphics cards, two gtx 580s, [laughter] which
by the way is exactly your sli configuration.
yeah.
okay.
so, that gtx 5880 sli was the revolutionary computer that put deep learning on the map.
> > wow.
> > it was 2018 and you were using it to play quake.
> > wow. that's crazy. > > that was the moment.
that was the big bang of modern ai.
we were lucky because we were inventing this technology, this computing approach. we were lucky that they found it.
turns out they were gamers and it was lucky they found it. and it
it was lucky that we paid attention to that moment.
it was a little bit like, you know,
that star trek,
you know,
first contact.
the vulcans had to have seen the warp drive at that very moment.
if they didn't witness the warp drive, you know,
they would have never come to earth and everything would have never happened.
it's a little bit like if i hadn't paid attention to that moment, that flash.
and that flash didn't last long.
if i hadn't paid attention to that flash
or our company didn't pay attention to it, who knows what would have happened, but we saw that
and we reasoned our way into this is a
this is a universal function approximator.
this is not just a computer vision approximator.
we could use this for all kinds of things.
if we could solve two problems. the first problem is that we have to prove to oursel
it could scale.
the second problem we had to wait for
i guess
contribute to and wait for
is the world will never have enough data on input and output
where we could supervise the ai to learn everything.
for example, if we have to supervise our children on everything they learn,
the amount of information they could learn is limited.
we needed the ai, we needed the computer to have a method of learning without supervision.
and that's where we had to wait a few more years, but un unsupervised ai learning is now here.
and so the ai could learn by itself.
and and the reason why the ai could learn by itself is
because we have many examples of right answers.
like
for example,
if i want to learn
uh
if i want to teach an ai how to predict the next word,
i could just grab it, grab a whole bunch of text we already have, mask out the last word
and make it
try and try and try again until it predicts the next one.
or i mask out random words inside inside the text and i make it try and try and try
until it predicts it.
you know, like
uh
mary
mary goes down to the bank.
is it a river bank or a money bank?
well, if you're going to go down to the bank, it's probably a river bank. okay. so, and it
it
it might not be obvious even from that. it might need and uh and uh
and caught a fish. okay. now you know it's must be the riverbank. and so so you give
you give these ais a whole bunch of these examples
and you mask out the words, it'll predict the next one.
okay? and so unsupervised learning came along.
these two ideas, the fact that it's scalable and unsupervised learning came along.
we were convinced that we ought to put everything into this and help create this industry
because we're going to solve a whole bunch of interesting problems.
and that was in 2012.
by 2016, i had
i had built this computer called the dgx1.
the one that you saw me give to elon is called dgx spark.
the dgx1 was $ 300, 000. it cost nvidia a few billion dollars to make the first one.
and instead of two chips
sli,
we connected eight chips with a technology called mvlink,
but it's basically sli supercharged.
okay. > > okay. > >
and so we connected eight of these chips together instead of just two.
and all of them work together
just like your quake rig did to solve this deep learning problem
to train this model. and so i create
we created this thing. i announced it at gtc and at one of our annual annual events
and i described this deep learning thing, computer vision thing and this computer called djx1.
the audience was like completely silent. they had no idea what i was talking about.
[laughter] and i was lucky because i i had known elon
and
uh
i helped him build the first computer for model 3
the model s.
and
uh
when he wanted to start working on autonomous vehicle, i helped him build the computer
that went into the the model s av system, his full full self-driving system.
we were basically the fsd computer version one. and so we we're already working together
and
um
when i announced this thing, nobody in the world wanted it.
i had no purchase orders.
not not one. nobody wanted to buy it. nobody wanted to be part of it except for elon.
he goes,
he was at the event and we were doing a fireside chat about the future of self-driving cars.
i think it's like 2016.
yeah, 20
maybe at that time
it was 2015.
and he goes, " you know what? i have a company that could really use this.
" i said, " wow, my first customer.
" and so, so i was pretty excited about it. and he goes, " uh,
yeah.
uh,
we have this company. it's a nonprofit company. " and all the blood drained out of my face. yeah.
[laughter] i just spent a few billion dollars building this thing.
cost $ 300, 000.
and you know the chances of a nonprofit being able to pay for this thing is approximately zero.
and he goes,
you know,
this is a
it's an ai company and
uh
it's a nonprofit and and
we could really use one of these supercomputers.
and so i i picked it up. i built the first one for ourselves.
we're using it inside the company.
i boxed one up.
i drove it up to san francisco and i delivered to elon in 2016.
a bunch of researchers were were there.
peter beiel was there, ilia was there, and there was a bunch of people there. and uh
i walk up to the second floor
where they were all kind of in a room this smaller than your place here.
and and uh
uh
that place turned out to have been open ai
> > 2016.
> > wow. > > just a bunch of people sitting in a room. > > it's not really
uh
nonprofit anymore, though, is it? > > they're not
they're not nonprofit anymore. yeah. > > weird how that works. > > yeah. yeah.
but anyhow, anyhow, elon was there. the yeah, it was
it was really a great great moment. > > oh, yeah.
there you go.
yeah, that's it.
[laughter] > > look at you, bro.
same jacket.
> > look at that.
i haven't aged. > > not not a lick of black hair, though. > >
uh
the size of it is
it's significantly smaller. that was the other day. spacex. > > oh, yeah.
there you go. > > yeah.
look at the difference.
> > exactly the same industrial design. he's holding it in his hand > > here.
here's the amazing thing.
djx1 was one pedlops.
okay, that's a lot of flops. and djx spark is one pedlops.
nine years later. > > wow. > > the same
the same amount of computing horsepower > > in a much smaller > > shrunken down.
yeah.
> > and instead of $ 300, 000, it's now $ 4, 000.
and it's the size of a small book. > > incredible.
> > crazy. > > that's how technology moves. anyways,
that's the reason why i wanted to get
give him the first one
> > because i gave him the first one
2016.
> > it's so fascinating. i mean you
if you wanted to make a story for a film
i mean that would be the story that
like
what
what better scenario
if
if it really does become a digital life form
how funny would it be that it is birthed out of the desire for computer graphics for video games
[laughter] > > exactly > > kind of cra
it's kind of crazy
> > kind of crazy when you think about it that way
> > because it's just
> > perfect origin
computer graphics was one of the hardest computer supercomputer problems generating reality
> > and also one of the most profitable to solve because computer games are so popular. > >
when nvidia started in 1993, we were trying to create this new computing approach.
the question is what's the killer app? and the the problem we wanted to the
the company wanted to create a new type of computing pro
a computing architecture
a computing a
a new type of computer that can solve problems that normal computers can't solve.
well, the applications that existed in the industry in 1993 are applications that normal computers can solve
because if the normal computers can't solve them, why would the application exist?
and so, we had a mission statement for a company that has no chance of success.
[laughter] but i didn't know that in 1993.
it just sounded like a good idea, > > right?
and so if we created this thing that can solve problems, you know,
it's like you actually have to go create the problem.
and so that's what we did in 1993. there was no quake. john carmarmac hadn't been reduced
doom
released doom yet.
you probably remember that.
> > sure.
yeah.
> > and and
uh
there were no applications for it.
and so i went to japan because the arcade industry had this at the time of sega,
if you remember.
> > sure.
> > the arcade machines, they came out with 3d arcade systems, virtual fighter, daytona, virtual cop,
all of those arcade games were in 3d for the f very first time.
and the technology they were using was from martin marietta,
the flight simulators.
they took the guts out of a flight simulator and put it into an arcade machine.
the system
that you have over here, it's got to be a million times more powerful than that arcade machine.
and that was a flight simulator for nasa.
whoa. and so they took the guts out of that. they were
they were using it for flight simulation for jets and, you know,
space shuttle
and
and they took the guts out of that. and sega
uh
had this brilliant computer de developer. his name was yuzuki.
yuzuki and miiamoto.
sega and nintendo.
these were the, you know, the incredible pioneers, the visionaries,
the incredible artists,
and they're both very, very technical. they were the origins really of of the gaming industry.
and y suzuki pioneered 3d graphics gaming
and
um
so i went
we
we created this company and there were no apps and we were spending all of our afternoons
you know
we told our family we were going to work
but it was just the three of us
you know who's going to know
and so we went to curtis's my
one of one of the founders went to curtis's townhouse and
uh
chris and i were married
we have kids
i already had spencer
at madison.
they were probably 2 years old. and um
and
uh
chris's kids are about the same age as ours.
and we would go to work in this townhouse.
but you know,
when you're a startup
and the mission statement is the way we described, you're not going to have too many customers calling you.
and so we had really nothing to do.
and so after lunch, we would always have a great lunch.
after lunch, we would go to the arcades and play the sega v,
you know,
the sega virtual fighter
and daytona
and all those games
and analyze how they're doing it, trying to figure out how they they were doing that.
and so we decided, um, let's just go to japan
and let's convince sega to move those applications into the pc.
and we would start the pc gaming
the 3d gaming industry partnering with sega.
that's how nvidia started.
> > wow.
> >
and so
so
uh
in exchange for them part developing their games for our computers in the pc, we would build a chip for their game console.
that was the partnership.
i build a chip for your game console. you port the sega games to us
and um
and then they paid us a you know
at the time
a quite a significant amount of money to build that game console
and that was kind of the beginning of nvidia getting started and we thought we were on our way
and so so i started with a business plan
a mission statement
that was impossible
we lucked into the sega partnership
we started taking off
started building our game console.
and about a couple years into it, we discovered our first technology didn't work. it was it
it would have been a flaw.
it it was a flaw.
and all of the technology ideas that we had the architecture concepts were were sound,
but the way we were doing computer graphics was exactly backwards.
you know, instead of i won't bore you with the technology,
but instead of inverse texture mapping,
we were doing forward texture mapping.
instead of triangles, we did curved surfaces. so, other people did it flat, we did it round.
um,
other technology, the technology that ultimately won,
the technology we use today has has zbuffers. it automatically sorted.
we had an architecture with no zbuffers.
the application had to sort it.
and so we chose a bunch of technology approaches that three major technology choices.
all three choices were wrong. okay. so this is how incredibly smart
we were.
and so
[laughter] and so in 1995
early mid95
we realized we were going down the wrong path.
meanwhile, the silicon valley was packed with 3d graphics startups
because it was the most exciting technology of that time.
and so 3d fx and rendition and silicon graphics was coming in. intel was already in there
and you know
gosh
like what added up eventually to a hundred different startups we had to compete against.
everybody had chosen the right technology approach and we chose the wrong one.
and so we were the first company to start. we found ourselves essentially dead last with the wrong answer.
and so the company was in trouble
and um
ultimately we had to make several decisions. the first decision is well
if we change
now we will be the last company.
and even if we changed into the technology that we believe to be right, we'd still be dead.
and so that argument,
you know,
do we change
and therefore be dead? don't change and make this technology work somehow or go do something completely different.
that question stirred the company strategically and was a hard question. i eventually, you know, advocated
for
we don't know what the right strategy is, but we know what the wrong technology is.
so, let's stop doing it the wrong way
and let's give ourselves a chance to go figure out what the strategy is.
the second thing, the second problem we had was our company was running out of money
and i had
i was in a contract with sega and i owed them this game console
and if that contract would have been cancelled, we'd be dead. we would have vaporized instantly. and so so
uh
i went to japan and i explained to
the ceo of sega, erie madri,
really great man.
he was the former ceo of honda usa.
went back to sega to run sega.
went back to japan to run sega.
and i explained to him that i was
uh
i guess i was what
33 years old. you know,
when i was 33 years old, i still had acne.
and i got this this, you know, chinese kid. i was super skinny. and he
he was already kind of elder. and
uh
i went to him and i said i said, " listen, i've got some bad news for you.
" and and first, the technology that we promised you doesn't work.
and second, we shouldn't finish your contract
because we'd waste all your money and you would have something that doesn't work.
and i recommend you find another partner to build your game console.
> > whoa.
> > and so i'm terribly sorry that we've set you back in your product roadmap. and third,
even though you're going to
i'm asking you to let me out of the contract, i still need the money
because if you didn't give me the money, we'd vaporize overnight.
and so i explained it to him humbly, honestly.
i gave him the background.
explain to him why the technology doesn't work, why we thought it was going to work, why it doesn't work.
and um
and i asked him to
uh
convert the last $ 5 million
that they were to complete the contract to give us that money as an investment instead.
and he said, " but it's very likely your company will go out of business, even with my investment.
" and it was completely true.
back then, 1995, $ 5 million was a lot of money.
it's a lot of money today.
$ 5 million was a lot of money.
and here's a pile of competitors doing it right.
what are the chances that giving nvidia $ 5 million that we would develop the right strategy
that he would get a return on that $ 5 million or even get it back? 0
%.
you do the math. it's 0
if i were sitting there right there, i wouldn't have done it.
$ 5 million was a mountain of money to sega at the time.
and so i told him that that that
um
uh
if you invested that $ 5 million in us, it is most likely to be lost.
but if you didn't invest that money, we'd be out of business and we would have no chance.
and i i told him
that i i don't even know exactly what i said in the end, but i told him
that i would understand if he decided not to, but it would make the world to me if he did.
he went off
and thought about it for a couple days and came back and said, " we'll do it.
" > > wow.
strategy to how to correct what it was doing wrong. did you explain that to him? > > wait,
oh man,
wait until i tell you the rest of it's scarier. even scarier. > > oh no.
[laughter] > > and so so um so what he what he decided was was
uh
jensen was a young man he liked. that's it.
> > wow.
to this day. > > that's nuts.
> > i was
>
> boy,
do you owe what the world owes that guy. > > no doubt, > > right? > > well,
he's
he
c
he's he celebrated today in japan.
> >
and if he would have kept that five
>
> the the investment,
i think it'd be worth probably about a trillion dollars today. i know.
but the moment we went public, they sold it.
they go, " wow, that's a miracle. " so, [laughter] > > wow.
> > they sold it. yeah.
they sold it at nvidia valuation about 300 million. that's our ipo valuation. 300 million. > > wow.
> >
and so, so anyhow, i was incredibly grateful. um,
and then now we had to figure out what to do
because we still were doing the wrong strategy, wrong technology.
so unfortunately we had to lay off most of the company. we shrunk the company all back.
all the people working on the game console,
you know,
we had to shrunk it all. shrink it all back. and um
and then
and then somebody told me that,
but jensen,
we've never built it this way before.
we've never built it the right way before. we've only know how to build it the wrong way.
and so nobody in the company knew how to build this supercomputing image generator
3d graphics thing that silicon graphics did.
and so so
uh
i said, " okay, how hard can it be? you got all these 30 companies, you know,
50 companies doing it.
how hard can it be? " and so luckily there was a textbook written by the company silicon graphics.
and so i went down to the store.
i had 200 bucks in my pocket.
and i bought three textbooks, the only three they had, $ 60 a piece.
i bought the three textbooks. i brought it back and i gave one to each one of the architects
and i said, " read that and let's go save the company. " > > [laughter] >
>
and so [gasps and sighs]
so they they
they read this textbook, learned from the giant at the time, silicon graphics, about how to do 3d graphics.
but the thing that was amazing
and what makes nvidia special today is
that the people
that are there are able to start from first principles, learn best known art, but reimplement it in a way
that's never been done before.
and so
when we re-imagined the technology of 3d graphics, we reimagined it in a way
that manifest today the modern 3d graphics.
we really invented modern 3d graphics, but we learned from previous known arts and we implement it fundamentally differently.
> > what did you do that changed it? well, you know,
the ultimately ultimately
the
um
uh
the simple
the simple answer is that the way silicon graphics works
uh
the geometry engine is a bunch of software running on processors.
we took that
and eliminated all the generality, the general purposeness of it
and we reduced it down into the most essential part of 3d graphics
and we hardcoded it into the chip.
and so instead of something general purpose, we hardcoded it very specifically into just the limited applications, limited functionality necessary for video games.
and that capability that super
and and because we reinvented a whole bunch of stuff, it supercharged the capability of that one little chip.
and our one little chip was generating images as fast as a $ 1 million image generator.
that was the big breakthrough.
we took a million dollar thing
and we put it into the graphics card that you now put into your gaming pc.
and that was [snorts] our big invention. and then
and of course
the question is is
um
uh
how do you compete against these 30 other companies doing what they were doing? and and there we did
we did several things. one
uh
instead of building a 3d graphics chip for every 3d graphics application, we decided to build a 3d graphics chip for one application.
we bet the farm on video games.
the needs of video games are very different than needs for cad, needs for flight simulators.
they're related, but not the same.
and so we narrowly focused our problem statement so i could reject all of the other complexities
and we shrunk it down into this one little focus
and then we supercharged it for gamers.
and then the second thing that we did was we created a whole ecosystem of working with game developers
and getting their their games ported
and adapted to our silicon so
that we could get turn essentially what is a technology business into a platform business into a game platform business.
so we, you know,
geforce is
really
today
it's also the most advanced 3d graphics technology in the world, but a long time ago
geforce is really the game console inside your pc. it's, you know,
it runs windows, it runs excel, it runs powerpoint,
of course,
those are easy things, but its fundamental purpose was simply to turn your pc into a game console.
so we
we were the first technology company to build all of this incredible technology in service of one audience gamers.
now
of course
in 1993
the gaming industry didn't exist.
but by the time that john carmarmac came along and the doom phenomenon happened
and then quake came out
as you know
that entire world
oh
that entire community boom took off.
do you know where the name doom came from? > > it came from this se
there's a scene in the movie the color of money
where tom cruz
who's this
uh
elite pool player shows up at this pool hall
and this local hustler says what he got in the case and he opens up this case.
he has a special pool queue.
he goes in here and he opens it up. he goes, " doom. > > doom.
" [laughter] > > and that's where it came from. yeah.
cuz carmarmac said that's what they wanted to do to the gaming industry. > > doom.
> > that when doom came out, it would just be everybody be like, " oh, we're fucked.
" > > oh, wow.
> > this is doom.
> > that's awesome.
> > isn't that amazing? that's amazing.
> > cuz it's the perfect name for the game.
> > yeah. > > and the name came out of that scene in that movie.
> > that's right.
well, and then
of course,
uh,
tim sweeney
and > > epic games and, uh,
and the 3d gaming genre took off. > > yes.
> > and so, if you just kind of
in the beginning was no gaming industry.
we had no choice but to focus the company on one thing.
that one thing, > > it's a really incredible origin story. > > oh, it's
it's amazing. like you must be like
look back
> > a disaster is what
> > a $ 5 [laughter] million
that pivot with that conversation with that gentleman
if he did not agree to that
if he did not like you
what would the world look like
today
that's crazy
then then our entire life hung on another gentleman and so so now here we are
we built
so
before geforce
it was revo
revo 128 saved the company
it revolutionized computer graphics
the performance cost performance ratio of 3d graphics for gaming was off the charts amazing.
and we're getting ready to to ship it. get well, we're
we're building it, but we're
so
as you know,
$ 5 million doesn't last long. and so every single month, every single month,
uh
we were drawing down
you have to build it, prototype it.
you have to design it, prototype it, get the silicon back, which costs a lot of money.
test it with software
because without the software testing the chip, you don't know the chip works.
and then you're going to find a bug
probably
because every time you test something
you find bugs, which means you have to tape it out again, which is more time, more money.
and so we did the math.
there was no chance anybody was going to survive it.
we didn't have that much time to tape out a chip, send it to a foundry tsmc,
get the silicon back, test it, send it back out again. there was no no shot, no hope.
and so the math, the spreadsheet doesn't allow us to do that.
and so i heard about this company and this company built this machine.
and this machine is an emulator.
you could take your design, all of the software that describes the chip,
and you could put it into this machine.
and this machine will pretend it's our chip.
so i don't have to send it to the fab, wait until the fab sends it back, test.
i could have this machine pretend it's our chip
and i could put all of the software on top of this machine called an emulator
and test all of the software on this pretend chip
and i could fix it all before i send it to the fab.
> > whoa.
and if and and if i could do that when i send it to the fab, it should work.
nobody knows, but it should work.
and so we came to the conclusion
that let's take half of the money we had left in the bank.
at the time it was about a million dollars.
take half of that money and go buy this machine.
so instead of keeping the money to stay alive, i took half of the money to go buy this machine.
well, i call this guy up. this
the company's called ios.
call this company up and i say, " hey, listen.
i heard about this machine.
i like to buy one.
" and they go, " h, that's terrific, but we're out of business.
" i said, " what? you're out of business? " he goes, " yeah, we had no customers.
" [laughter] i said, " wait, hang on a sec.
so, you never made the machine? " they [snorts] can say, " no,
no,
no.
we made the machine.
we have one in inventory if you want it, but we're out of business.
" so, i bought one out of inventory.
okay. after i bought it, they went out of business. > > wow.
> > i bought it out of inventory.
and on this machine, we put nvidia's chip into it and we tested all of the software on top.
and at this point, we were on fumes.
but we convinced ourselves that chip is going to be great.
and so i had to call some other gentleman. so i called tsmc. and i told tsmc that
listen,
tsmc is the world's largest founder today.
at the time they were just a few hundred million dollars large, tiny little company.
and i explained to them what we were doing. and um
i explained to him
i told him i had a lot of customers. i had one, you know,
diamond multimedia,
probably one of the companies you bought the graphics card from back in the old days.
and i i said, you know,
we have a lot of customers,
and the demand's really great,
and we're going to tape out a chip to you, and i like to go directly to production
because i know it works.
> > [snorts] >
>
and they said, " nobody has ever done that before.
nobody has ever taped out a chip that worked the first time.
and nobody starts out production without looking at it.
" but i knew that if i didn't start the production, i'd be out of business anyways.
and if i could start the production, i might have a chance.
and so tsmc decided to support me
and
uh
this gentleman is named morris chang.
morris chang is the father of the foundry industry, the founder of tsmc.
really great man. he decided to support our company.
i explained to them everything.
he decided to support us frankly
probably because they didn't have that many other customers anyhow
but they were grateful and i was immensely grateful
and as we were starting the production
morris flew to united states and
uh
he didn't
so many words
asked me so
but he asked me a whole lot of questions that was trying to tease out
do i have any money
but he didn't directly ask me that
you know
and so the truth is that we didn't have all the money
but we had a strong po from the customer
and if it didn't work
some wafers would have been lost
and i'm you
know i i'm not exactly sure what would have happened
but we would have come short
it would have been
it would have been rough
but they supported us with all of that risk involved
we launched this chip turns out to been completely revolutionary.
knocked the ball out of the park.
we became the fastest growing technology company in history to go from zero to $ 1 billion.
> > so wild that you didn't test the chip. > > i know.
we tested afterwards. yeah, we tested afterwards. > > afterwards, but [laughter] production already. but by the way,
by the way,
that methodology that we developed to save the company is used throughout the world today.
> > that's amazing. > > yeah,
we changed
we changed the whole world's methodology of designing chips. the whole world's uh
rhythm of designing chips. uh
we changed everything.
> > how well did you sleep those days? it must have been so much stress, [laughter] > > you know.
um,
what is that feeling where where
uh
the world just kind of feels like it's flying? it
you
you have this
what do you call that feeling? you can't
you can't stop the
the feeling that everything's moving
super fast
and you know
and you're laying in your laying in bed and the world just feels like you know it
you
and you're
you feel deeply anxious
uh
completely out of control.
um
i've felt that probably a couple of times [laughter] in my life.
it's during that time. > > wow. > > yeah. it
it was incredible.
> > what an incredible success story.
> > but i i learned i learned a lot. i learned i learned about
i learned several things. i learned i learned
uh
how to develop strategies.
um
i learned how to
uh
and when i
when i you know
our company learned how to develop strategies.
what are winning strategies?
we learned how to create a market. we created the modern 3d gaming market. we learned how
and
and so that exact same skill is how we created the modern ai market.
it's exactly the same. > > wow. > > yeah.
exactly the same skill. exactly the same blueprint.
and
uh
we learned how to
deal with crisis, how to stay calm, how to think through things systematically.
we learned how to remove all waste in the company
and work from first principles and doing only the things that are essential.
everything else is waste because we have no money for it to live on fumes at all times.
and the feeling no different than the feeling i had this morning
when i woke up that you're going to be out of business soon.
that you're
you know
the phrase
30 days from going out of business
i've used for 33 years because > > you still feel that. > > oh yeah.
oh yeah.
every morning. every morning. > >
but but you guys are one of the biggest companies on planet earth.
but the the feeling doesn't change. > > wow. > > the
the sense of vulnerability, the sense of uncertainty, the sense of insecurity.
uh
it
it doesn't leave you.
> > that's crazy.
we were, you know, we had nothing. we had nothing. we were dealing with giant. > > oh, yeah.
oh, yeah. every day, every moment.
> > do you think
that fuels you? is
that part of the reason why the company's so successful?
that you have
that hungry mentality, that you never rest, you're never sitting on your laurels, you're always on the edge.
i have a greater drive from not wanting to fail than the drive of wanting to succeed.
[laughter] > > isn't
that like sex coaches would tell you
that's completely the wrong psychology? > > the world has just heard me say
that for out loud for the first time.
> > but but it's true. > > well, that's how fascinating.
fear of failure drives me more than the than the the greed or whatever it is.
> > well, ultimately
that's probably a more healthy approach
now that i'm thinking about it
because like the fear
> > i'm not ambitious
for example,
[laughter] you know, i just want to stay alive, joe.
i want the company to thrive,
you know,
i want us to make an impact. > > that's interesting.
> > yeah. > > well, maybe that's why you're so humble. that's what
maybe that's what keeps you grounded, you know,
because with the kind of spectacular success the company's achieved, it would be easy to get a big head.
> > no.
> > right.
but isn't that interesting? it's like the if you were the guy that your main focus is just success.
you probably would go, " well, made it.
nailed it.
i'm the [laughter] man.
> > drop the mic.
" > > instead, you wake up, you're like, " god, we can't [_ _] this up.
" > > no. exactly. every morning. every morning. no. every moment.
yeah.
that's crazy.
> > before i go to bed.
> > well, listen.
if i was a major investor in your company, that's what i'd want running it.
i'd want a guy who's > > yeah.
> > that's what i work.
that's why i work seven days a week.
every moment i'm i'm awake.
> > you work every moment.
> > every moment i'm awake.
> > wow. > > i'm thinking about solving a problem. i'm thinking about
> > how long can you keep this up? > > i don't know.
but so [laughter] could be next week.
sounds exhausting.
> > it is exhausting.
> > it sounds completely exhausting.
> > always in a state of anxiety.
> > wow. > > always in a state of anxiety. > > wow.
kudos to you for admitting that.
i think that's important for a lot of people to hear
because, you know, there's probably some young people out there that are in a similar position to
where you were
when you were starting out
that just feel like, oh, those people that have made it, they're just smarter than me
and they had more opportunities than me and it's just like it was handed to them
or they're just in the right place at the right time.
and > > joe, i just described to you somebody who didn't know what was going on, [laughter] actually did it wrong.
> > yeah. yeah.
and the ultimate diving catch like two or three times. > > crazy.
> > yeah.
> > the ultimate diving catch is the perfect way to put it.
> > you know, it's just like the edge of your glove.
[laughter] > > it probably bounced off of somebody's helmet and landed at the edge.
[laughter] > > god, that's incredible.
that's incredible.
but it's also it's really cool that you have this perspective that you look at it that way
because you know a lot of people that have delusions of grandeur
or they have
you know
> >
and their rewriting of history often times had them somehow extraord extraordinarily smart
and they were geniuses and they knew all along and they were
they were spot-on.
and the business plan was exactly what they thought.
and > > yeah, > > they destroyed the competition and you know
and they emerged victorious.
[laughter] > > meanwhile, you're like, i'm scared every day.
> > exactly. [laughter] exactly. > > that's so funny.
oh my god, that's amazing.
> > it's so true, though.
> > it's amazing.
> > it's so true.
well, but i i think there's nothing inconsistent with being a leader and being vulnerable. you know, i
the company doesn't need me to be a genius right all along, right? absolutely certain about what i'm trying to do
and what i'm doing.
the the company doesn't need that. the company wants me to succeed. you know, the thing that
and we started out today talking about president trump
and i was about to say something and listen, he is my president.
he is our president. we should all
and we're talking about just because it's president trump,
we all want him to be wrong.
i think that united states, we all have to realize he is our president, we want him to succeed
because > > no matter who's president attitude.
> > that's right.
> > we want him to succeed.
we need to help him succeed because it helps everybody, all of us succeed.
and i'm lucky that i work in a company
where i have 40, 000 people who wants me to succeed.
they want me to succeed
and i can tell
and they're all every single day to help me overcome these challenges
trying to realize realize what i describe to be our strategy doing their best.
and if it's somehow wrong or not perfectly right
to tell me so that we could pivot
and the more vulnerable we are as a leader
the more able other people are able to tell you
you know that
jensen
that's not exactly right or > > right
right
> >
have you considered this information or
and the more vulnerable we are
the more able we're actually able to pivot
if we put ourselves into this superhuman capability
then it's hard for us to pivot strategy,
> > right?
> > because we were supposed to be right all along.
> > and so if you're always right, how can you possibly pivot?
because pivoting requires you to be wrong.
and so i've got no trouble with being wrong.
i just have to make sure
that i stay alert, that i reason about things from first principles all the time.
always break things down to first principles.
understand why it's happening.
reassess continuously. the reassessing continuously is kind of partly what causes continuous anxiety, > > you know,
because you're asking yourself, were you wrong yesterday? are you still right? is this the same? has
that changed? has that condition
is that worse than you thought?
> > but god, that mindset is perfect for your business, though,
because this business is ever changing
> > all the time.
i've got competition coming from every direction.
so much of it is kind of up in the air and you have to invent a future
where a 100 variables are included and there's no way you could be right on all of them.
and so you have to be
> > you have to surf.
> > wow.
that's a good way to put it.
you have to surf. yeah. you're surfing waves of technology and innovation. > > that's right.
you can't predict the waves. you got to deal with the ones you have. > > wow.
and but skill matters
and i've been doing this for 30
i'm the longest running tech ceo in the world. > > is that true?
congratulations.
that's amazing.
> > and you know people ask me
how is
one
don't get fired. [laughter] that'll stop a short heartbeat. and then two don't get bored. > > yeah.
> > well, how do you maintain your enthusiasm?
well, the honor truth is is not always enthusiasm. it's, you know,
sometimes is enthusiasm.
sometimes it's just good oldfashioned fear and then sometimes, you know, a healthy dose of frustration, you know,
it's whatever keeps you moving.
> > yeah.
just all the emotions. i think,
you know,
> > ceos,
we have all the emotions, right? you know,
and so probably probably jacked up to the maximum because you're
you're kind of feeling it on behalf of the whole company.
i'm feeling it on behalf of everybody at the same time. and it kind of, you know,
encapsulates into into somebody.
and so i have to be mindful of the past.
i have to be mindful of the present. i've got to be mindful of the future.
and um
you know, it
can't
it's not without emotion. it's not just it's
it's not just a job.
let's just put it that way.
> > it doesn't seem like it at all.
i would imagine one of the more difficult aspects of your job currently
now that the company is massively successful is anticipating
where technology is headed and where the applications are going to be.
> > yeah. > > so, how do you try to map that out? > > yeah. there there
um
there
there's a whole bunch of ways
and and it takes it takes
um
takes a whole bunch of things
but let me just start
uh
you have to be surrounded by amazing people and nvidia is now
you know
if you look at
look at
um
the large tech companies in the world today
most of them have a business in advertising or social media
or you know
content distribution
and at the core of it is really fundamental computer science
and so the company's business is not computers
the company's business is not technology
technology drives
the company is the only company in the world that's large
whose only business is technology
we only build
techn
we don't advertise
the only way that we make money is to create amazing technology and sell
and so
to be that
to be nvidia
today, you're the number one thing is you're surrounded by the finest computer scientists in the world.
and that's my gift.
my gift is that we've created a company's culture, a condition
by which the world's greatest computer scientists want to be part of it
because they get to do their life's work and create the next thing
because that's what they want to do. because maybe they're not
they don't want to be in service of another business.
> > they want to be in service of the technology itself.
and we're the largest form of its kind in the history of the world.
> > wow. > > i know.
it's pretty amazing. > > wow. > > and so so one,
you know,
we have a we we have got a great condition.
we have a great culture.
we have great people. and then now now now the question is how do you systematically
um
be able to see the future
stay alert of it
and
uh
reduce
the
the the likelihood of missing something or being wrong.
and so there's a lot of different ways you could do that.
for example, we have great partnerships.
we we have fundamental research.
we have a great research lab, one of the largest industrial research labs in the world today.
and we partner with a whole bunch of universities and other scientists. we do a lot of open collaboration
and so i'm constantly working with researchers outside the company. we have the benefit of having amazing customers
and so i have the benefit of working with elon and you know
and others in the industry
and we have the benefit of being the only pure pure play technology company that can serve
uh
consumer
internet
industrial
manufacturing
um
scientific
computing
healthcare
financial
services
all the industries that we're in. they're all signals to me. and so they all have mathematicians and scientists
and
and so
because i i have the benefit now of a radar system > >
that is the most broad of any company in the world
working across every single industry
from agriculture to energy to video games.
and so the ability for us to have this vantage point, one doing fundamental research ourselves
and then two working with all the great researchers, working with all the great industries, the feedback system is incredible.
and then finally, you just have to have a culture of staying super alert.
there's no easy way of being alert except for paying attention.
i haven't found a single way of being able to stay alert without paying attention. and so, you know,
i probably read several thousand emails a day.
> > how how do you have a time for that? > > i wake up early.
this morning i was up at 4 : 00.
> > how much do you sleep? > > uh, six, seven, six, seven hours.
> > yeah.
> > and then you're up at 4 reading emails for a few hours before you get going.
> > that's right.
yeah.
> > wow. every day. > > every single day.
not one day missed. [sighs] including thanksgiving, christmas.
> > do you ever take a vacation? > > uh,
yeah.
but they're
um
my definition of a vacation is when i'm with my family.
and so if i'm with my family, i'm very happy. i don't care where we are.
> > and you don't work then
or do you work a little? > > no.
no.
i work a lot. [laughter] > > even like if you go on a trip somewhere, you're still working.
> > oh, sure.
oh, sure.
> > wow. every day. > > every day.
> > but my kids work every
you make me tired just saying this.
> > my kids work every day. both of my kids work at nvidia.
they work every day.
> > wow.
> > yeah. i'm very lucky. > > wow.
> > yeah.
it's brutal now
because, you know,
it's just me working every day. now we have three people working every day
and they want to work with me every day
and so it's it's a lot of work.
> > well, you've obviously imparted that ethic into them.
> > they work incredibly hard. i mean, there's no unbelievable.
> > but my parents work incredibly hard. > > yeah.
i was
i was born with the work gene, > > the suffering gene. [laughter] > > well, listen, man.
it has paid off. what a crazy story. it was just it's really an amazing origin story. it really
i mean, it has to be kind of surreal to be in the position that you're in now
when you look back at how many times that it could have fallen apart and humble beginnings.
but joe,
this is great.
it's a great country.
you know, i'm an immigrant. my parents sent my older brother and i here first. we're
we're in thailand. i was born in taiwan, but my dad had a job in thailand.
he was a chemical and instrumentation engineer, incredible engineer.
and his job was to go start an oil refinery.
and so we moved to thailand, lived in bangkok. and um
in 19
i guess
time frame,
you know how
thailand
every so often
they would just have a coup. you know,
the military would have an uprising
and all of a sudden one day there were tanks and soldiers in the streets
and my parents thought, you know, it probably isn't safe for the kids to be here.
and so they contacted my uncle. my uncle lives in tacoma, washington. and um
we had never met him and my parents sent us to him.
> > how old were you? > >
uh
i was about to turn nine and my older brother
almost turned 11
and so the two of us came to united states
and we stayed in with our uncle for a little bit while he looked for a school for us
and my parents didn't have very much money
and they never been to united states. my father was.
i'll tell you that story in a second.
and um
and so my my uncle found a school that would accept foreign students and affordable enough for my parents.
and
that school turned out to have been in onita, kentucky, clark county, kentucky, the epicenter of the opio crisis today.
cold country. clark county, kentucky is was the poorest county in america when i showed up.
it is the poorest county in america today.
and so we went to the school, it's a great school, um,
onita baptist institute in a town of a few hundred.
i think it was 600 at the time that we showed up. no traffic light. and um
i think it has 600 today. it's quite an amazing feat actually.
the ability to hold your population for [laughter] when it's 600 people. it was quite a magic
quite a magical thing. however they did it.
and and so
uh
the school had a mission of being an open school for any children who would like to come.
and what that basically means is that if you're a trouble student, if you have a troubled family,
um
if you're, you know,
whatever your background,
you're welcome to come to onita baptist institute, including kids from international who would like to stay there.
> > did you speak english at the time? > > uh,
okay.
yeah.
yeah. okay. yeah.
and so we showed up and
uh
my first my first thought was gosh
there are a lot of cigarette butts on the ground.
100 % of the kids smoked. [laughter] so right away
you know this is not a normal school. > > nineyear-olds? > > no,
i was the youngest kid.
> > okay. 11 year olds. > > my roommate was 17 years old. wow. > > yeah.
he just turned 17. and he was jacked and and um
i don't know where he is now.
i know his name, but i don't know where he is now. but anyways,
uh
that night we got
and and the second thing i noticed when you walk into the into your dorm room is
uh
there are no drawers and no closet doors.
just like a prison.
and there are no locks so that people could check check up on you.
and so i go into my room and he's 17
and
uh
you know
get ready for for bed and he had all this tape all over his body
and
uh
turned out he was in a knife fight and he's been stabbed all over his body
and these were just fresh wounds. > > whoa.
and the other kids were hurt much worse. and uh
so he was my roommate, the toughest kid in school, and i was the youngest kid in school.
it was a
it was a junior high, but they took me anyways
because if i walked about a mile across the kentucky river, the swing bridge, the other side is a middle school
that i could go to
and then i can go to that school and i come back and then i stay in the dorm.
and so basically onita baptist institute was my dorm when i went to this other other school.
my older brother went went to um
went to the junior high. and so we were there for a couple of years. um
every kid had
every kid had chores. my older brother's chore was to work in the tobacco farm, you know.
so tobac
they raised tobacco so that they could raise some extra money for the school.
kind of like a penitentiary.
> > wow.
and my job was just to clean the dorm.
and so i i was 9 years old.
i was cleaning toilets.
and for a dorm of 100 100 boys, i i clean more bathrooms than anybody.
and i just wish that everybody was a little bit more careful, you know.
[laughter] but anyways, i was the youngest kid in school. the my memories of it was really good. um,
but it was a pretty tough
it was a tough town. > > sounds like it. > > yeah. town kids, they all carried
everybody had knives.
> > everybody had knives.
everybody smoked.
everybody had a zippo lighter. i smoked for a week. > > did you? > > oh, yeah.
sure.
> > how old were you? > > i was nine. yeah.
> > when you nine?
you were nine, you tried smoking.
> > yeah.
i got myself a pack of cigarettes. everybody else did. > > did you get sick? no.
i i got used to it, you know,
and i learned how to blow blow smoke rings and, you know,
[snorts] you know,
breathe out of my nose, you know,
take it in out of through my nose.
i mean, there was a all the different things that you learned.
yeah.
> > at nine.
> > yeah.
> > wow. you just did it to fit in or it looked cool. > > yeah.
[clears throat]
because everybody else did it, > > right? > > yeah.
and and then i did it for a couple weeks, i guess.
and i just rather have i had a quarter,
you know,
i had a quarter a month
or something like that. i just rather buy popsicles and fried sickles with it. i was nine, you know,
[laughter] > > right? > > i chose
i chose the the better path. > > wow.
> > that was our school. and then my parents came to united states two years later
and
um
we met him in tacoma, washington.
> > that's wild.
it it was a really crazy experience.
what a strange formative experience. > > yeah. tough kids. > > thailand
to one of the poorest places in america or if not the poorest as a 9-year-old. > > yeah.
it was my first experience with your brother. > > wow. > > yeah. yeah.
no,
i i remember
and what breaks my heart
probably the only thing
that really breaks my heart of about
that experience was so we didn't have enough money to make you know international phone calls every week
and so my parents gave us this tape deck
this iowa tape deck and a tape
and so every month we would sit in front on that tape deck
and that my older brother jeff
and i, the two of us would just tell them what we did the whole month.
> > wow.
> > and we would send that tape
by mail
and my parents would take that tape
and record back on top of it and send it back to us.
> > wow.
> > could you imagine if
for two years
> > wow.
is that tape still existed of these two kids just describing their first experience with united states.
like i remember telling my parents that that
uh
i joined the swim team and
my roommate was really buff
and so every day we spent a lot of time in the in the gym
and so
uh
every night
100 push-ups, 100 sit-ups every day
in the gym.
so, i was nine years old. i was getting
i was pretty buff and i'm pretty fit.
and uh
and so i joined the soccer team. i joined the swim team
because if you join the team, they take you to meets
and then afterwards you get to go to a nice restaurant.
and that nice restaurant was mcdonald's.
> > wow.
> >
and and i recorded this thing.
and i said, " mom and dad, we went to the most amazing restaurant today.
this whole place is lit up.
it's like the future.
" and [snorts] the food comes in a box [laughter] and the food is incredible.
the hamburger is incredible. it was mcdonald's. [snorts] but anyhow, it
it wouldn't it be amazing? > > oh my god.
two years recording.
yeah.
two years. yeah.
what a crazy connection to your parents, too. just sending a tape and them sending you one back
and it's the only way you're communicating for two years. > > yeah.
wow.
yeah.
no,
i've
my parents are incredible
actually.
they're just they're
uh
they grew up really poor
and um
when they came to united states, they had almost no money.
uh
probably one of the most impactful memories i have is
is
uh
we
they came and we were
we were staying in a
in a
uh
apartment complex and they had
they had just rent back in the
i guess people still do rent rent
a bunch of furniture and we were messing around
and
uh
we bumped into the coffee table and crushed it.
it's made out of particle wood and we crushed it. and i just still remember my
the look on my mom's face, you know,
because they didn't have any money and she didn't know how she was going to pay it back.
and but anyhow, that's that kind of tells you how hard it was for them to come here.
they they left everything behind
and all they had was their suitcase
and the money they had in their in their pocket and they came to united states.
> > how old were they pursued the american dream? they were in their 40s. > > wow.
> > yeah.
late late 30s. > > pursued the american dream. this is
this is the american dream.
i'm the first generation of the american dream.
> > wow.
> > yeah.
it's hard not to love this country.
> > that's > > it's it's hard not to be romantic about this country.
> > that is a romantic story. that's an amazing story. > > yeah.
and and my dad found his job literally in the newspaper,
you know,
the ads and he calls people. got a job. > > what did he do? > >
uh
he was a consulting engineer
and a and a consulting firm and they helped people build oil refineries, paper mills and fabs.
and that's what he did. he was an he
he's really good at factory design
instrumentation engineer.
and so he's
he's brilliant at that.
and so he did that
and my mom
uh
worked as a maid
and
uh
they found a way to raise us.
> > wow.
that's an incredible story, jensen.
it really is.
every all of it from your childhood to the perils of nvidia almost falling. [laughter] it's really incredible, man.
> > it's a great story. yeah.
i i've lived a great life.
> > you really have. and it's a great story for other people to hear, too. it really is.
> > you don't
you don't have to go to ivy league schools to succeed.
this country creates opportunities.
has opportunities for all of us.
you do have to strive.
you have to claw your way here.
> > yeah. > > but if you put in the work, you can succeed. nobody works with
> > a lot of luck and a lot of
> > a lot and > > good decision-making > > and the good graces of others.
> > yes, that's really important. > > yeah.
you and i spoke about two two people who are very dear to me. um
but the list goes on. the people
the people at nvidia who have
have
uh
helped me
um
uh
many friends that are on the board
the decisions
you know
them
giving me the opportunity
like when we were inventing this new computing approach
i tanked our stock price because we added this thing called cuda to the chip
we had this big idea
we added this thing called cuda to the chip
but nobody paid for it
but our cost doubled
and so we had this graphics chip company and we invented gpus, we invented programmable shaders,
we invented everything modern computer graphics,
we invented real-time tracing.
that's why it went from gtx to rtx.
we invented all this stuff, but every time we invented something, the market doesn't know how to appreciate it, but the cost went way up.
and in the case of cuda that enabled ai, the cost increased a lot. it
and
but i really we really believed it
you know
and so if you believe in that future and you don't do anything about it
you're going to regret it for your life
and so we always
you know
i always tell the team
do you believe
what do we believe this or not
and if you believe it and so grounded on first principle is not random
you know
hearsay
and we believe it
we've got to
we owe it to ourselves to go pursue it
if we're the right people to go do it
if it's really really hard to do. it's worth doing and we believe it.
let's go pursue it. well, we pursued it. we we launched the product. nobody knew.
it was exactly what
like when i launched dgx1 and the entire audience was like complete silence.
when i launched cuda,
the audience was complete silence.
no customer wanted it.
nobody asked for it.
nobody understood it. nvidia was a public company. > > what year was this? this is
uh
let's see 200
20 years ago
2005.
> > wow. > > our stock price just went
our valuation went down to like two or three billion dollars
> > from > > from about 12 or something like that.
i crushed it.
> > [laughter] > > in a very bad way.
> > yeah. > > what is it now though? > > h
yeah,
it's higher.
[laughter] > > very humble of you.
[gasps] > > it's higher.
but it changed the world. > > yeah, > > that invention changed the world. > > it's a
it's an incredible story, johnson.
it really is.
> > thank you.
> > i like your story.
it's incredible. ah, > > my story is not as incredible. my story is more weird, you know.
it's much more fertuitous and weird.
> > okay. what are the three milestones that most important milestones that led to here?
> > that's a good question.
um, > > what was step one? > > i think step one was seeing other people do it.
step one was in the initial days of podcasting, like in 2009
when i started, podcasting had only been around for a couple of years.
um,
the first was adam curry, my good friend, who was the podfather.
he he invented podcasting.
and then, you know,
um,
i remember
adam corolla had a show because he had a radio show.
his radio show got cancelled
and so he decided to just do the same show but do it on the internet.
and that was pretty revolutionary. nobody was doing that.
and then there was the experience that i had had doing different morning radio shows like opie
and anthony in particular
because it was fun and we would just get together with a bunch of comedians,
you know,
i'd be on the show with like three or four other guys that i knew
and it was always just looked forward to it.
it was was just such a good time
and i said, " god, i miss doing that.
it's so fun to do that.
i wish i could do something like that. " and then i saw tom green setup.
tom green had a setup in his house
and he essentially turned his entire house into a television studio
and he did an internet show from his living room.
he had servers in his house and cables everywhere. had to step over cables. i was
this is like 2007.
i'm like tom
this is nuts. like this is
> > and i'm like you got to figure out a way to make money from this. like this
everybody
i wish everybody in the internet could see your setup.
it's nuts. i just want to let you guys know that
[laughter] > > it's not just this.
> > yeah.
so that was the the beginning of it is just seeing other people do it
and then saying all right
let's just try it
and then
so the beginning days
we just did it on a laptop
had a laptop with a webcam and just messed around
had a bunch of comedians come in
we would just talk and joke around and i did it like once a week
and then i started doing it twice a week
and then all a sudden i was doing it for a year
and then i was doing it for two years
then it was like
oh
it's starting to get a lot of viewers
a lot of listeners
you know
and then i just kept doing
it's
all it is.
i just kept doing it because i enjoyed doing it. well, was there any setback? > > no.
no,
there was never really a setback really. > > no,
> > it must have been. or you kind of > > you're just
you're just resilient. > > or you're just tough.
> > no.
no.
it wasn't tough or hard.
it was just interesting.
so, i just it the the > > you were never once punched in the face. > > no,
not in the show.
no,
not really.
not not doing the show.
> > you never did something that that big blowback. nope.
not really.
no, it all just kept growing.
> > it kept growing and the thing stayed the same from the beginning to now.
and the thing is, i enjoy talking to people.
i've always enjoyed talking to interesting people.
> > i could even tell just
when we walked in, the way you interacted with everybody, not just me.
> > yeah, that's cool.
> > people are cool. > > yeah, that's cool.
you know, i i
it's a an amazing gift to be able to have so many conversations with so many interesting people
because it changes the way you see the world
because you see the world through so many different people's eyes
and you have so many different people
have different perspectives and different opinions and different philosophies and different life stories.
and you know, it's an incredibly enriching and educating experience having so many conversations with so many amazing people.
and that's all i started doing.
and that's all i do now.
even now, when i booked the show, i do it on my phone.
and i basically go through this giant list of emails of all the people
that want to be on the show
or that request to be on the show.
and then i factor in another list
that i have of people that i would like to get on the show that i'm interested in.
and i just map it out and that's it.
and i go, " oh, i'd like to talk to him.
" > > if it wasn't because of president trump,
i wouldn't have been bumped up on that list. [laughter] > > no,
i wanted to talk to you already.
i i just think, you know, what you're doing is very fascinating.
i mean, how would i not want to talk to you?
and then today, it proved to be absolutely the right decision. > > well,
you know,
listen,
it's
it's strange to be an immigrant one day.
going to onita baptist institute with with the students that were there
and then here
nvidia's one of the most consequential companies in the history of companies.
> > it is a crazy story. > > it has to be that journey is
is a
and it's very humbling and > > and um
i'm very grateful.
> > it's pretty amazing man. > > surrounded by amazing people. you're very fortunate and you've also
you seem very happy and you seem like you're 100 % on the right path in this life.
you know,
> >
everybody says you must love your job. not every day. [laughter] > > that's not
that's part of the beauty of everything is that there's ups and downs.
it's never just like this giant dopamine high. > > we leave
we leave this impression here. here's here's an impression i don't think is healthy. we
we
um
people who are successful
leave the impression often that that our job gives us great joy.
i think largely it does that our jobs were passionate about our work. um
and that passion relates to
it's just so much fun. i think it largely is,
but it it it distracts from
in fact
a lot of success comes from really really hard work.
> > yes, > > there's long periods of suffering
and loneliness and uncertainty and fear and embarrassment and humiliation.
all of the feelings that we most not love that creating something from the ground up
and and elon will tell you something similar
very difficult to invent invent something new
> > and people people don't believe you
all the time
you're humiliated
often disbelieved most of the time
and so so people forget that part of success
and
and i i don't think it's health.
i think it's it's good that we pass that forward
and let people know that that it's just part of the journey.
> > yes.
> > suffering is part of the journey. > > you will appreciate it
so these horrible feelings that you have when things are not going so well.
you will appreciate it so much more when they do go well. > > deeply grateful. > > yeah.
> > yeah.
deep deep pride.
incredible pride.
in incredible incredible gratefulness and and and surely incredible memories.
absolutely.
jensen, thank you so much for being here.
this was really fun.
i really enjoyed it
and your story is just absolutely incredible
and very inspirational and and i you know, i think it really is the american dream.
it is the american dream.
> > it really is. thank you so [music] much. thank you. all right. bye, everybody. [music]