joe rogan podcast.
check it out.
>> the joe rogan experience.
>> train by day.
joe rogan podcast by night.
all day.
>> exactly.
>> just every morning.
>> wonder what jeff bezos is doing.
>> he's doing some definitely doing some testosterone.
he looks jacked.
>> he looks jacked, right?
>> yeah.
but he didn't like >> quick >> quick >> quick
at age like at 50 at age 59
in less than a year he he went from
pencilet geek to
looking like a like the rock.
>> yeah.
like a little miniature alpha fella.
like like his neck got bigger than his head.
>> yeah.
he got bigger.
>> but then like his earlier pictures his neck's like a noodle.
>> i support this activity.
i like to see him going in this direction >> which is fine.
and his voice dropped like two octaves.
i want you to move in that direction as well.
>> i think we can achieve this.
>> i i i mean i should >> i think we can achieve >> gigachad.
that's what people called it.
>> where is that guy?
>> bele.
i don't know where he is.
>> that's like a real guy.
>> the artist.
yeah.
>> no.
>> oh, gigachad.
oh, gigachad.
yeah.
i don't know if that's a real guy.
it's hard to say.
>> no, it is a real guy.
>> it is a real guy.
>> he's got the crazy jaw and like perfect sculpted hair.
>> yeah.
well, i mean, they may have exaggerated a little bit, but
>> um
>> but
no, i think i think he actually just kind of looked like that in reality.
>> wow.
>> um so >> like like he's a pretty unique looking individual.
>> i think we can achieve this.
that guy right there, that's a real guy.
>> that's a real dude.
>> i always thought that was cgi.
>> no, i think one of i think the upper right one is not him.
that's not >> but that one to the left of that like that's real.
no, that's that's artificial, bro.
that's fake.
that's got that uncanny valley feel to it, doesn't it?
>> it's it's not impossible.
>> no, no, it's not impossible to achieve,
but it's not it's not possible to maintain that kind of leanness.
i mean, that's like like you're you're also
at that point they're he's dehydrating
and all sorts of things.
>> oh, it's based on a real person.
>> yeah.
yeah.
based on, >> right, but it's not a real person.
what does he really look like?
>> like those images, i think, are [ __ ] >> some of them are.
is that real?
okay.
that that looks real.
that looks like a really jack bodybuilder.
>> yeah.
>> yeah, that looks real.
like that's achievable.
but there's a few of those
images
where you're just like, "what's
going on here?"
>> yeah.
yeah.
totally.
um >> well, i mean, you see you see
>> that guy is that is that the >> that's the real dude?
>> well, there's that that that icelandic dude who's thor.
>> oh, yeah.
the guy who jumps in the frozen
lakes and [ __ ] >> well, the guy who played the mountain.
um >> oh, that guy.
>> that is that is like a that that is like a a mutant strong human.
yes.
>> like like he would be in like the x-men or something, you know?
>> he's just like not like
>> and there's that you know that have you seen that meme tent and tent bag?
>> um you know how like it's like it's really hard to get the tent
tent in >> oh, right.
right.
>> that's true.
>> then there's a picture of of him and his girlfriend.
that's hilarious.
>> yeah, that's >> i don't know how it gets in there, you know?
it's like it seems too small.
but >> i met brian shaw.
brian shaw is like the world's most powerful man.
and he's almost 7 feet tall.
he's 400 lb.
>> and his his bone density is 1 in 500 million people.
so there's one it's like there's like maybe 16 people.
>> he's an enormous human being.
like a legitimate giant just like that guy.
but we met him.
he was hanging out with us in the green room of the mother ship.
it's like, okay,
if this was like david and goliath
days, like
this is an actual giant like the giants of the bible.
>> once in a while they get a super giant person.
>> this is a real a real one.
like not a tall skinny basketball player, like a 7 foot 400b powerliffter.
>> like you don't want to especially look at him.
that's the guy.
see if there's a photo of him standing next to like a regular human.
i >> was trying to get >> there it is.
that's him right there.
like there's like there's like one of him with
next to standing next to arnold and stuff and it's where and
everyone everyone just looks tiny.
>> i mean i think he's a pretty cool dude actually.
>> oh, brian's very cool.
very smart, too.
unusually, you know, you expect anybody to be that big.
it's got to be a [ __ ] >> no.
>> yeah.
there was there's andre the giant who was awesome.
you >> he was great in princess bride and >> no, he was just awesome period.
>> yeah.
yeah.
so, we were talking about
um this interview
with
sam alman
and tucker, and i was like, we should probably just talk about this on the air
because it is one of the craziest interviews i think i've ever seen in my life.
>> yeah.
>> where tucker starts bringing up this guy who was a whistleblower, whatever.
>> a whistleblower who, you know, >> committed suicide, but it doesn't look like it.
>> and and he's talking to sam alman about this.
and sam alton was like, "are you accusing me?" he's like, "no, no, no.
i'm not.
i'm just saying i i think someone killed him.
>> yeah.
and like and it should be investigated.
>> um not just drop the case.
>> it seems like >> they just dropped the case.
yeah.
but his parents think he was murdered.
>> yeah.
>> um the wires to a security camera were cut.
um >> blood in two rooms.
>> blood in two rooms.
someone else's wig was in the room.
and >> someone else's wig.
>> wig.
yes.
not his wig.
>> not normal to have a wig laying around.
>> yes.
um and
um and he ordered door dash right before allegedly committing suicide.
>> uh which is it seems unusual, you know?
>> yeah.
>> it's like, you know, let's
i'm going to order pizza on second thoughts,
i'll kill myself.
is it seems like that's a very rapid change in mindset.
>> it's very weird.
and especially the parents have they they don't believe he committed suicide at all.
>> has no note or anything.
>> no.
>> yeah.
>> it seems pretty [ __ ] up.
and you know, the idea that a whistleblower
for an enormous
ai company that's worth billions of dollars might get whacked,
that's not outside the pale.
>> i mean, it's straight out of a movie.
>> right out of a movie, but right out of a movie is real sometimes.
>> yeah.
right.
exactly.
>> it's a little weird that i i think they should do a proper investigation.
like, what's the downside on that proper investigation?
>> right.
>> no.
>> yeah, >> for sure.
but the whole exchange is so bizarre.
>> yeah.
yeah.
sam alman's reaction to being accused of murder is bizarre.
>> look, i don't know if he's guilty, but it's not possible to look more guilty.
>> so, i'm like, >> or look more weird.
>> yeah.
>> you know, maybe it's just his social thing.
like, maybe he's just odd with confrontation and it just goes blank, you know?
but if if somebody was accusing me of killing jamie,
like if jamie was a whistleblower
and jamie got whacked
and then i'd be like, "wait,
what are you
are you accusing
me of killing
my friend?"
like, "what the [ __ ] are you talking about?"
i would i
would be
a little bit more
i rate.
>> yeah.
yeah.
exactly.
you know, it would be >> i would be a little upset.
>> yeah.
it'd be like well, you'd be like, you'd certainly in insist on a thorough investigation.
yeah.
>> as opposed to trying to sweep it under the rug.
>> yeah.
i wouldn't assume that he got that he committed suicide.
i would be suspicious.
if tucker
was telling me that aspect
of the story,
i'd
be like,
"that
does seem like a murder.
[ __ ] we should look into this."
>> i mean, all signs point to it being a murder.
not not saying, you know, tim molvin had anything to do with the murder, but
>> blood in two rooms.
>> it's blood in two rooms.
like,
yeah, there's
the wires to the security camera and the door dash being ordered right before suicide.
no suicide note.
his parents think he was murdered and
um the people that i know who knew him said he was not suicidal.
so i'm like this why would you jump to the conclusion >> parents
sued the >> uh landlord?
>> they sued the son's landlord
alleged
the owners and the managers of their son's san francisco
apartment
building were part of a widespread
cover up of his death.
>> the landlord >> yeah.
there's a bunch of weird they said there was like packages missing from the building.
some people said they saw packages still being delivered and all a sudden they all disappeared.
>> huh.
but that could be people steal people's packages all the time.
>> the porch pirate situation.
>> yeah.
>> says they failed to safeguard.
>> also, i mean, the amount of trauma
those poor parents have gone through with their son dying like that.
i mean, it must >> god bless them.
and how could they stay sane after something like that?
they're probably they're so griefstricken.
who knows what they believe at this point.
>> yeah.
it should have asked if epson killed himself.
yeah, that's the the cash mattel thing.
cash mattel dan bonino trying to convince everybody of that.
like, okay.
>> the guards weren't there and the cameras stopped working and
um >> you know, >> the guards were asleep.
the cameras weren't working.
he had a a giant
steroided
up bodybuilder
guy that he was sharing a cell with that was a murderer
who was a bad cop.
like, all of it's kind of nuts.
all of it's kind of nuts
like that he would just kill himself rather than reveal all of his billionaire friends.
>> yeah.
>> and then >> did you see tim dylan talking to chris cuomo about this?
>> i did.
he liked the idea.
>> chris cromo just looked so stupid.
>> tim just listed off all the >> tim just
and he's like i agree it is strange.
like of course it's strange chris.
jesus christ.
you can't just go with the tide.
you got to think things through.
and if you think that one through, you're like, i don't think he killed himself.
nobody does.
you'd have to work for an intelligence agency to think he killed himself.
>> it does.
it does seem unlikely.
>> it seems highly unlikely.
highly, highly unlikely.
all roads point to murder.
>> yes.
>> point to they had to get rid of him because he knew too much.
whatever the [ __ ] he was doing, whatever kind of an asset he was, whatever
thing he was up to,
you know, was apparently very effective.
>> yes.
and a lot of people are compromised.
you see, your boy bill gates is now saying climate change is not a big deal.
like, relax everybody.
i know i scared the [ __ ] out of you for the last decade
and a half, but
ah, we're going to be fine.
>> yeah.
i mean,
you know, as was
i was saying just before coming into the studio with, you know,
it like every day there's some crazy
wild new thing that's happening.
it's it feels like reality is accelerating.
>> it's every day.
and every day it's like more and more
ridiculous to the point where the simulation is more and more undeniable.
>> yeah.
yeah.
it really feels like simulation, you know?
it's like, come on.
what are the odds that this could be the case?
>> are you paying attention at all to three atlas?
are you watching the >> the comet?
>> yeah.
whatever it is.
yeah.
i mean, i mean, one thing i can say is like, look, i
if if i was aware of any evidence of aliens,
um, you joe, you have my word.
i will come on your show and i will reveal it on the show.
>> okay.
>> yeah, >> that's a good deal.
>> yeah, it's pretty good.
>> i'll believe you.
yeah, thank you.
>> i i'll stick i keep my you know, keep my promises.
so,
um >> all right.
i'll hold you to that.
>> yeah.
yeah.
and and i'm never committing suicide to be clear.
>> i don't think you would either.
>> so, on camera, guys, i am never committing suicide ever.
>> if someone says you committed suicide, i will fight tooth and nail.
>> i will fight tooth and nail.
i will i will not believe it.
i will not believe it.
the thing about the three eye atlas is it's >> a hell of a name actually.
>> yeah, it's a third eye sounds like third eye or something.
>> yeah, it does.
three eye is third.
it's only the third interstellar object that's detected.
>> okay.
>> yeah.
obias.
alo was on the podcast a couple days ago talking about it.
>> yeah.
it could be.
i don't know.
but i >> apparently today they're saying that it's changed course.
um, >> did you see that, jamie?
>> avi said something today.
i'll send it to you.
um, >> uh, i know it's on reddit.
>> here you go, jamie.
i'll send it to you right now.
um, it's fascinating.
it's fascinating also because it's made almost entirely of nickel, whatever it is.
and the only way that exists, uh, here is, uh, industrial alloys apparently.
um
um most no there are there are
>> there are definitely comets that and asteroids that are made primarily of nickel in fact.
yeah.
so the the places where
um you mine nickel on earth is actually where there was an asteroid
or comet that hit earth that was a nickel rich
you know
>> nickel rich nickel rich rich deposit.
>> yeah that's that's that's it's coming.
those are from impacts.
you definitely didn't want to be there at the time because anything would have been obliterated.
right.
um, but that's that's where the the sources of nickel and cobalt are these days.
>> so, this is ovio lope.
a few hours ago, the first hint of non-gravitational
acceleration that something other than gravity is affecting its acceleration, meaning something is affecting
its trajectory beyond gravity was indicated.
interesting.
um
so it's mostly nickel very little iron which
he was saying is on earth only exists in alloys
but whatever you know you're dealing with another planet >> there this there are
there are there are cases where there's very nickel richch asteroids meteorites that heavy
that
something from space.
>> yeah it it's only yeah it doesn't mean
it'll
be a very sort of heavy spaceship if you make it all out of nickel.
oh yeah.
>> and [ __ ] huge.
the size of manhattan and all nickel.
that's kind of nuts.
>> yeah, that's a heavy spaceship.
>> that's a real problem if it hits.
>> uh yes.
no, it would like obliterate a continent type of thing.
>> um maybe maybe worse.
>> probably kill most of human life.
>> um >> if not all of us.
>> i haven't depends on what the the total mass is.
but
um there's i mean the thing is like in the fossil record there are
um you know there's like arguably arguably five major extinction events.
um like the biggest one of which is the perine extinction where
um almost all life was eliminated.
that that actually occurred over several million several million years.
um the there's the jurassic.
i think jurassic is i think that one's pretty definitively an asteroid.
um and
um but there's but there's been five major extinction events, but
um but what they don't count are really the ones that merely take out a continent.
>> so >> merely >> yeah.
cuz that that because those
don't really show up on the fossil record, you know, >> right?
>> um so unless it's enough to cause a
you know mass extinction event throughout earth, it it doesn't show up,
you know, in a fossil record that's
200 million years old.
um so the yeah but but there have been many
um many impacts that would have sort of destroyed all life on
you know let's say half of north america or something like that.
there many such impacts through the course of history.
>> yeah.
and there's nothing we can do about it right now.
there was one that
um hits there was a one that hit siberia and destroyed i think
um few hundred square miles.
>> oh, that's the tungusa.
>> yeah.
that's the one from the 1920s, right?
that's the one that coincides with that meteor that
comet
storm that we go through every june and every november
that they think is responsible for that younger dest.
>> yeah.
yeah, all that shit's crazy.
um,
thank you
before we go any further for letting us have a tour of spacex
and letting us be there for the rocket launch.
>> one of the absolute coolest things i've ever seen in my life.
and we we've we were
we thought it was only like i thought it was a half a mile.
jamie's like it was a mile away.
turned out it's almost two miles away.
and you feel it in your chest.
>> yeah.
it's >> you have to wear earplugs
and you feel it in your chest and it's 2 miles away.
>> it was [ __ ] amazing.
and then to go with you up into the command center
and to watch all the starlink
satellites
with all the different cameras
and all in real time as it made its way all the way to australia.
how many minutes?
like 35 40 minutes.
>> yeah.
>> wild it touchdown in australia.
>> [ __ ] crazy.
it was amazing.
>> yeah.
yeah.
>> absolutely amazing.
the starship's awesome.
um, and anyone can go watch the launch actually.
so, you can just go to
um, south padre
island, get has a great view of the launch.
um, so it's like where a lot of spring breakers go.
>> um,
but um, but we'll be flying pretty frequently um, out of starbase in south texas.
and we we formally incorporated it as a city.
so, it's it's actually a legally an actual legal city, starbase, texas.
>> um, it's not that often you hear like, hey, we made a city, you know.
um,
that used to be like the like in in the old days like a startup
would be you go and
gather a bunch of people and say, "hey, let's go make a town." literally,
that was like that would have been startups in in in the old days.
>> um, >> or a country.
>> yeah.
or a country.
yeah.
actually, >> if you tried doing that today, there'd be a real problem.
>> yeah.
that things are so much so much set in stone on the country front these days.
you might pull it off.
you might be able to pull it off.
if you got a a solid island, you might be able to pull it off.
>> you know, it's probably, >> you know, like like at owns lai.
>> yeah, you could probably
if you put if you put enough effort into it, you could make a new country.
>> this is one of the different ones.
this is one of the ones that you catch, >> right?
or is that one?
>> yeah, that that's the booster.
so that's the super heavy booster.
so that's the one with the booster's got 33 engines.
um that that
um and it's you know by version four that will have about 10,000 tons of thrust.
um you know right now it's about 7 8,000 tons of thrust.
um, that's that's the largest flying object ever made.
>> i had to explain to someone.
they were going, "why do they blow up all the time if he's so smart?"
because there was
there was this [ __ ] idiot on television.
some guy was being interviewed and they were talking about you.
and he goes, "oh, i think he's a fuckwit." and he goes, "he's a fuckwit."
and he goes, "why you say he's [ __ ] oh, his rockets keep blowing up."
and someone said, "yeah, well, why do his rockets blow?" and i had to explain.
yeah.
because it's the only way you find out what the tolerances are.
you have to you have to a few >> corners of the box.
so, so like so when you do a new rocket development program,
um you you have to
do what's called
you know, exploring
the limits,
the corners of the box where you say it's like you
worst case this,
worst case that
um to figure out
um where where the limits are.
so
you blow up, you know, not not admittedly in the development process sometimes blows up accidentally.
um but but we intentionally subject it to
you know
a flight regime
that is much worse
than what we expect
in
normal
flight
so that when we put people on board or
valuable
cargo
it doesn't blow up.
um so
um so so for example for the the flight that you saw we we actually
deliberately
took
um heat shield tiles off the the the ship the off of starship
in in some of the worst locations
to say okay if we lose a heat shield tile here is it is it catastrophic
or is it not?
um and we we nonetheless starship was able to do a soft landing
um in in the indian ocean just west of australia.
um which as and it got there from texas in like i don't know 354
minutes type of thing.
so >> so it landed even though you put it through this situation
where it has compromised shield.
it it had an an an an unusually
we we we brought it in hot like an an extra hot trajectory
with missing tiles
um to see if it would still make it to a soft landing which it did.
now i i should point out it did have
there were some holes that were burnt into it.
um but it's it was robust enough to land despite having some holes burnt
you know that that you know cuz it's coming it's coming in like a blazing meteor.
you can see you can see the real time video.
well, tell me the speed again because the the speed was bananas.
you were talking about >> yeah, it's like 17,000 mph
like like 25 times the speed of sound or thereabouts.
so,
um the
so so think of it like it's it's like 12 times
faster
than a bullet
from an assault
rifle.
you know, bullet from assault rifles around mach 2 >> and it's just and it's huge.
>> yeah.
yeah.
or or if you compare it to like a bullet from a
um
you know a 45 or or 9 mil which is subsonic
that's you know it it'll be about 30 times faster than a bullet from a handgun.
>> 30
times
faster
than a bullet from a handgun
and it's the size of a skyscraper.
>> yes.
>> yeah.
that's fast.
>> it's so wild.
it's so wild to see, man.
it it's it's so exciting.
this the factor is so exciting too
because like genuinely no [ __ ] i felt like i was witnessing
history.
i felt like it was a scene in a movie where someone had expectations
and they like what are they doing?
they're building rockets.
and you go there and as we were walking through
jamie, you could speak to this too.
didn't you have the feeling where you're like
>> oh this is way bigger than i thought it was.
this is huge.
awesome.
>> gigantic.
>> [ __ ] crazy.
>> that's what she said.
the ah the amount of rockets you're making.
i don't know if you >> tent back.
>> gig chad in the house.
>> this is way big.
>> it's a giant metal dick.
you're [ __ ] [ __ ] the universe with your giant metal dick.
that's >> i mean, yeah, it is.
it is very big.
>> and the sheer numbers of them that you guys are making.
and then this is a version and you have a new updated version that's coming soon.
>> and what is the it's a it's a little longer.
um >> more pointy.
>> uh it's the same amount of pointy.
um but the there's it's it's got a bit more length.
um the the interstage,
you see that that interstage section with kind of like the grill area.
>> mhm.
>> um that's that's now integrated with the boost stage.
um so we do
um what's called hot staging.
where we light the ship engines while it's still attached to the booster.
so the boost the booster engines are still thrusting.
is still it's it's
you know it's still being pushed forward by the booster of the ship.
but then we light the ship engines and the ship engines
actually pull away from the booster even though the booster engines are still firing.
>> whoa.
>> um so it's blasting flame through
that that grill section but we integrate that grill section into
the boost stage with the next version of the rocket.
um
and and explosion in the rocket will have the raptor 3 engines which are
a huge improvement.
um you may you may have seen them in the lobby
because we got like the raptor 1, two, and three.
and you can see the dramatic improvement in simplicity.
um we should probably put a plaque there to also show
how much the we reduced the weight
the cost and the and improved the efficiency and the thrust.
so the raptor 3 has
you know almost twice the thrust of raptor raptor 1. >> wow.
>> so you see raptor 3. it looks like it looks like it's got parts missing.
right.
>> and how many >> it's very very clean.
>> how many of them are on the rocket?
>> there's 33 on the on the booster.
>> whoa.
um and and each of each raptor engine is producing
twice as much thrust as all four engines on a 747.
wow.
so that engine is smaller than a 747 engine, but is producing, you know,
um you know, almost 10 times the thrust of a 747 engine.
um so extremely high power to weight ratio.
um and
um
>> and so when there's >> 33
of them >> you
when you so when you're designing
these
you get to raptor
one
you see its efficiency
you see where you can improve it
you get to raptor 2 how many
how far can you scale this up with just
the same sort of technology with propellant and ignition and engines
like how much further can you
>> i mean we're pushing the limits of physics here
um so
um
and and really in order to to make a a fully reusable
orbital rocket which no one has succeeded in doing yet including
including us.
um but but
starship is the first time that there is a design for a rocket
where where full and rapid reusability is actually possible.
so it was not there's not there's not even been a design
before where it was possible.
certainly not a design that that that got made any hardware at all.
um just we just we just live we live on a planet where the gravity
is is is quite high like earth's gravity is quite really quite quite high.
um
um and if the gravity was even 10 or 20%
higher we'd be stuck on earth forever.
um like we yeah we could not use certainly couldn't use conventional rockets.
you'd have to like blow yourself off the surface with like a nuclear
bomb or something crazy.
um
so but on the other hand if if earth's gravity was just a little
lower like even 10 20% lower it then
getting to orbit would be easy.
so it's like it's like
it's like this if this was a video game it's set to like
maximum difficulty but not impossible.
>> okay.
>> um so that's that's where we have
um here.
so it's it's not as though
um others have ignored the concept of reusability.
they've just concluded that it was too difficult to achieve.
and we've been working at on on this for a long time at at spacex.
um and
um you know, i'm the chief engineer of the company.
um although i should say that that you know, we have an extremely talented engineering team.
i think we've got the best rocket engineering team that has ever been assembled.
um it's it's an honor to work with such such incredible people.
um so
so so it's fair to say that
you know we have not yet succeeded in creating in achieving full reusability
but we at last have a rocket
where full reusability is possible.
um and i think i think we'll achieve it next year.
so
um that's a that's a really big deal.
and the reason the reason that's that's such a big deal is that full reusability
um drops the cost of access to space by a hundred
um maybe even more than 100 actually.
so could be like a thousand.
the you can think of it like any mode of transport.
like imagine if aircraft were were not reusable.
like you flew somewhere, you throw the plane
like like imagine if like the way the way conventional rockets work
is it would be like if you had an airplane
and and and
instead of landing at your destination,
you parachute out
um and the plane crashes somewhere
and you land at your desk
and you and you land on a parachute at your
destination.
now that would be a very expensive trip
and you and you'd need another plane to get back.
okay.
um, but that's how the other rockets in the world work.
um,
now the spacex falcon rocket
is the only one that is is there that is at least mostly reusable.
you've se you've seen the falcon rocket, you know, land.
we've now done over 500 landings
of of the spacex rocket
of the of the falcon 9 rocket.
um and
um and and this year
um you know we we'll deliver probably i don't know
somewhere between 2200 and 2500 tons to orbit
um with with the falcon 9 falcon heavy rockets not counting anything for from starship.
um >> and this is mostly starlink.
yes, mostly starling, but we launch many other we even launch our competitors on
um competitors to starink on on falcon 9. we charge them the same price.
pretty fair.
um but spacex this year will deliver
um roughly 90% of all earth mass to orbit.
>> wow.
>> um and then of the remaining 10%
um most of that is done by china.
and then the then the remaining kind of roughly 4%
is
everyone else in the world including our america domestic competitors.
>> you know
um
it's kind of incredible how many things are in space
like how many things are floating above us now?
>> there's a lot of things.
>> yeah.
>> is there though?
>> right.
but is there a saturation point where
we're going to have problems with all these different satellites that are
>> um i think as long as the satellites are
um maintained there's there it'll be fine.
this space is very roomy.
um it's like you can think of
um like space as being concentric shells of the surface of the earth.
so,
um,
you know, there's there's
it's the surface of the earth, but but there's it's a series >> much larger.
>> yeah.
it's like a series of concentric trails.
um, >> and think of an airstream trailer flying around up there.
there's a lot of room for air streams.
>> yeah.
i mean, imagine yeah.
if there just a few thousand airirstreams
um on on earth.
>> yeah.
>> what are the odds that they'd hit each other?
you know, >> they wouldn't be very crowded.
no.
and then you got to go bigger.
>> yeah.
>> because you're dealing with far above earth.
>> hundreds of miles above earth.
>> yeah.
yeah.
so, it's the
um but the goal of spacex is to
get
rocket
technology
to the point where we can extend life beyond earth and that we can establish
a
self-sustaining
city on mars.
a permanent base on the moon.
that would be very cool.
i mean, imagine if we had like a, you know, moon base alpha
where there's like a permanent science base on the moon.
>> that would be pretty dope.
or at least a tourist trap.
>> i mean,
a lot of people be willing to go to the moon for just for a tour.
that's for sure.
we could probably pay for our space program with that, you know, >> probably.
yeah.
well, >> because it's like if if you if you could go to the moon
with and and
safely,
>> uh
i think we'd get a lot of people would would pay for that, you know.
>> oh, 100%.
after the first year, after nobody died for like >> yeah.
just make sure.
exactly.
are you going to come back?
yeah.
>> because like that submarine, they they had a bunch of successful
launches in that private submarine before it imploded and killed everybody.
that was not a good design.
obviously, >> it was a very bad design.
terrible design.
>> and the engineers said it would not withstand the pressure of those depths.
like there was a lot of whistleblowers in that company too.
>> yeah.
um they they they made that out of
carbon fiber which is it doesn't make any sense because
um you actually need you need to be dense to go down.
um in any case, just make it out of steel.
if you make it out of
sort of just, you know,
a big steel casting, that's that's you you'll be safe and nothing.
why would they make it out of carbon fiber then?
is it cheaper?
>> um i think they think carbon fiber sounds cool or something.
but >> it does sound cool.
>> it it sounds cool, but
um
because it's such it's such low density, you actually actually have to add extra mass to
go down because it's it's low density.
but if you just have a giant, you know, hollow ball bearing,
you're going to be fine.
>> speaking of carbon fiber, did you check out my unplugged tesla out there?
>> yeah, it's cool.
>> pretty sick, right?
yeah.
have you guys ever thought about doing something like that?
like having like an amg division of tesla where you do like custom stuff.
>> um i think it's best to leave that to the custom shops.
you know we're we're like tesla's focus is autonomous cars.
um you know building kind of futuristic autonomous cars.
um so
um like i think it's we want the future to look like the future.
um, so the did like did you see like our designs for like the sort of
the robotic bus?
it looks pretty cool.
>> the robotic bus is also being totally auton
but it looks it looks cool.
it's it's very art deco.
it's it's like it's like futuristic art deco.
um, and um,
it it does it like i think we want to change the aesthetic over time.
you don't want the aesthetic to be constant over time.
you want to evolve the aesthetic.
um,
so um,
you know, like my like i have a son who's he's like,
you know, he's he's he's like
even more autistic than me and
um and, uh, but he's he has these great observations.
who is this?
>> a saxon.
he has these great observations
in the world
uh because
he's
he just views the world through a different lens
than than most people.
um and he was like, "dad, why does the world look like it's 2015?"
>> and i'm like, "damn, the world does look like it's 2015."
like the aesthetic has not evolved since 2015. >> oh, that's what it looks like.
>> yeah.
>> oh, wow.
>> that's pretty cool.
>> oh, yeah.
that's like >> like you'd want to see that going down the road, you know?
>> yeah.
you'd be like, "okay, this is we're in the future."
you know, it doesn't look like 2015.
>> what is that ancient science fiction movie?
like one of the first science fiction movies ever.
is it metropolis?
is that what it is?
>> yeah.
yeah.
that looks like it belongs in metropolis.
>> yeah.
yeah.
it's a futuristic art deco.
>> all right.
yeah.
well, that's cool that you're concentrating on the aesthetic.
i mean, that's kind of the whole deal with cybertruck, right?
like, it didn't have to look like that.
>> no, it it i just wanted to have something that looked really different.
is it a pain in the ass for people to get it insured
because it's all solid
steel
and
>> um i hope it's not too much.
i you know tesla
does offer insurance
so people can always get it get it insured
at tesla.
>> um well but the like it is the
form does follow a function in the case of the cybert truck because
um as you demonstrated with with your armorpiercing arrow
um because if you shot that arrow at a regular truck i mean >> it
exactly you would have found your arrow in the wall.
yeah.
um, you know, it would very least it would have buried into one of the seats.
>> yeah.
yeah.
it's but like you could you could definitely make
get enough of
bow velocity
and and the right the right arrow
would go through both doors of a regular truck and and and land on the wall.
>> if there was a clear shot
between
both doors,
it probably would have passed right through.
>> exactly.
um
but but
you know the the arrow shattered
on the cybert truck cuz it's it's ultra hard
stainless.
mhm.
>> um, so,
um,
and i thought it' be i thought it'd be cool to have
a, you know, a truck that is bulletproof to a subsonic projectile.
um,
so,
um, you know, especially in this day and age, you know,
like as
as a if, if the apocalypse
happens, you're going to want to have a bulletproof
truck, you know.
um, so so then because
because it's made of ultra hot stainless, it's you can't just stamp the the panels.
you can't just put in a stamping press because it breaks the press.
so, so in order to actually, so it has to has to be planer
um because it's so difficult to bend it because it breaks the machine that bends it.
um that's why that's why it's it's it's it's so planer
and and it's not you know it's it's because it's
bulletproof steel is the
>> so it is like boxy as opposed to like curved and >> yeah.
you just in order to make in order to make like the curved shapes,
you you you
take you take
basically mild steel like
um anneal thin and thin anneal in a regular truck or car.
the
you take you take mild
thin
anneal
steel, you put it in a stamping
press and it just
sm
it just
smooshes
it
and makes it to whatever the shape whatever shape you want.
but the cybert truck is made made of ultra hard stainless.
um and and and so you can't stamp it because it would break the stamping press.
so it even bending it is hard.
so even to bend it to its current position, we have to way overbend it.
um
and and
so it gets
so that when it springs
back, it's in in the right position.
um, so it's
i don't know like i i think if you want to
like
i think it's it's it's
a unique aesthetic.
um, and you say, "well, what's cool about a truck?" trucks are trucks are
like should be i don't know manly.
they should be macho, you know, and bulletproof is maximum macho macho.
>> are you married to that shape now?
like is it can you do anything to change it?
like as you get further like i know you guys updated the three and the y.
did you update the y as well?
>> yes, the the three and the y are updated.
um you know, there's like a
um
there's there's
a a screen in the back for the kid that the kids can watch,
for example,
in the new 3 and y.
um so in the new y,
um there's, you know, it's it's an there's there's there's like hundreds of improvements.
like we keep improving the car.
um and even the cybert truck, we you know, we keep improving it.
um but
um
you know i wanted to just do something that that looked unique
and and the cybert truck looks unique and has unique functionality
and
there was and it was like
there were three things as i report like let's make it bulletproof.
let's make it faster than a porsche 911. uh, and we actually cleared the quarter mile.
the cybert truck, the the can
clear a quarter mile while towing a porsche 911 faster than a porsche 911.
um, it can out tow an f350 diesel.
>> really?
>> yes.
>> what is the tow limitations?
>> i mean, we could tow like a, you know, a 747
in that with a cy.
cybert truck is an insanely like it is an it is alien technology.
okay.
um cuz it it shouldn't be possible to be that big and that fast.
that doesn't it's like an elephant that runs as as like a cheetah.
>> yeah.
because it's 0 to 60 in less than 3 seconds, right?
>> yes.
>> yeah.
and it's enormous.
what does it weigh?
like 7,000 lbs.
>> uh yeah, there's different configurations, but it's about that.
it's a beast.
>> yeah.
>> um so and it's and it's got it's got four-wheel steering.
so the the rear wheel steer, too.
so it's got a it's got a very tight turning radius.
>> yeah.
we noticed that we when we drove one to star base.
very tight turning radius.
>> yeah.
pretty sick.
>> are you still doing the roadster?
>> yes.
eventually,
>> we're getting close to demonstrating the prototype >> and i think this will be
i i i i one thing i can guarantee is that this product demo
will be unforgettable.
unforgettable.
>> how so?
whether it's good or bad, it will be unforgettable.
um, >> can you say more?
what do you mean?
>> well, you know, my friend peter teal,
um, you know, uh, once reflected that
the future was supposed to have flying cars, but we don't have flying cars.
>> so, you're going to be able to fly?
well, i mean,
uh,
i think if peter wants a flying car, we should should be able to buy one.
>> so, you are you actively considering making an electric flying car?
is this like a real thing?
>> well, we have to see in the >> in the demo.
so, when you do this, like are are you going to have a retractable wing?
like, what is the idea behind this?
don't be sly.
come on.
>> i i i can't i can't do the unveil before the unveil.
um but
um >> tell me off air then.
>> i i i it look i i think it has a shot at being
the most memorable
um product unveil ever.
it has a shot.
>> and when do you plan on doing this?
what's the goal?
>> uh hopefully before the end of the year.
>> really?
>> before the end of this year.
>> this is i mean we're in a couple months.
>> hopefully in a couple months.
um you know we need to make sure that it works.
like this is some crazy crazy technology we got in this car.
crazy technology.
crazy crazy.
so different than what was previously announced and >> yes.
>> and is that why you haven't released it yet?
cuz you keep [ __ ] with it.
>> it has crazy technology.
>> okay.
>> like is it even a car?
i'm not sure.
it's like it looks like a car.
let's just put this way.
it it's it's crazier than anything james bond.
if you took all the james bond cars and combined them, it's crazier than that.
>> very exciting.
>> i don't know what to think of that.
>> i don't know.
>> it's a limited amount of information i'm drawing from here.
>> jamie's very suspicious over there.
look at him.
>> excited.
>> i'm interested.
>> it's still going to be the same.
>> well, you know what?
i mean, if if you want to if you want to come a little before the
the unveil, i can show it to you 100%.
yeah, let's go.
>> yeah.
um
it's
it's kind of crazy
all the different things that you're involved in simultaneously
and you know we talked about this before your time management but
i i really don't understand it.
i don't understand how you can be paying attention to all these different things simultaneously.
starlink, spacex, tesla, boring company
x you're tweet you [ __ ] tweet or post rather all day long.
well, it's more like i'm i'm
i could hop in for like two minutes and then hop out, you know.
>> but i mean, just the fact that you could do >> bathroom break or whatever,
you know,
>> i can't do that.
>> um >> if i hop in, i start scrolling and i start looking around.
next thing you know, i've lost an hour.
>> yeah.
>> um so, no, it's for me it's it's a couple minutes time usually.
it's once in a
sometimes
i guess it's half an hour,
but
usually
i'm
i'm in
for
a
few minutes
then
out
of of
you know, posting something on x.
uh,
you know, it's i do sometimes feel like it's sometimes like
that that meme of the guy who's like who drops the grenade and leaves the room.
that's been me more than once on on x.
>> yeah.
oh, yeah.
yeah, for sure.
um, it's got to be fun, though.
it's got to be fun to know that you essentially disrupted
the entire social media chain of command
because there was a there was a very clear
thing that was going on with social media.
the government had infiltrated it.
they were censoring speech
>> and until you bought it, we really didn't know the extent of it.
we kind of assumed that there was something going on.
>> yeah.
we had no idea that they were actively involved in censoring
actual real news stories,
real data,
real scientists,
real professors
silenced,
expelled,
kicked off the platform.
>> yeah.
>> wild.
>> for telling the truth.
and i'm sure you've also because i sent it to you that chart that shows
young kids, teenagers identifying as trans and non-binary
literally
stops dead when you bought twitter
and starts falling off a cliff when people are allowed to have rational
discussions
now
and actually talk about it.
>> yes.
>> yeah.
>> um yeah.
yeah, i mean i i said at the time like i think that like
the the like the reason for acquiring twitter is because
um it was it it was c it was causing destruction at a civilizational level.
um it was
um i mean i posted i tweeted on on twitter at the time that
um it it is
um you know it's it's worm tongue for the world.
um you know like worm tongue from
lord of the rings where he would just sort of
like whisper these
you know terrible things to the king
so the king would believe these things that
weren't true
um and and
um unfortunately
twitter really got it got like the the the woke mob essentially they controlled twitter
um and they were pushing a nihilistic anti-vilizational mind virus to the world.
um, and you can see the results of that mind virus
on the streets of san francisco,
uh, where,
you know, downtown san francisco looks like a zombie apocalypse.
um, you know, it's it's bad.
um, so we don't want the whole world to be a zombie apocalypse.
um, but that's
that that that was essentially they were pushing this very negative, nihilistic, untrue worldview
on the world and it was causing a lot of damage.
um, so >> the stunning thing about it is how few people course corrected.
a bunch of people woke up and realized what was going on.
people that were all on board with like woke ideology in maybe 2015
or
and then
and then eventually
it comes to affect
them or they see it in their workplace
or they see and they're like, "whoa, whoa, whoa, we got to stop this."
bunch of people did, but a lot of people never course corrected.
>> yeah.
um,
a lot of a lot of people didn't course correct, but
but it's gone directionally in it's gone it's it's directionally correct like you mentioned like the
like the massive spike in in kids identifying as trans
and then that that spike dropping
um after the the twitter acquisition.
i think that
um simply allowing the truth to be told
um was that just shedding sun sunlight is the best disinfectant as they say
and just allowing sunlight
um kills the virus >> and it also changed the benchmark for all the other platforms.
yes, you can't just openly censor people and all the other platforms and x is available.
so everybody else had a so like facebook announced they were changing
youtube announced they were changing their policies
and they're kind of forced to and then blue sky doubled down.
>> well, like the problem is like if
>> uh essentially the woke mind virus retreated to woke to to blue sky.
>> yeah.
>> um but it's where they're just a self-reinforcing lunatic assign.
>> they're all just triple masked.
i i was i was totally watching this exchange
on a blue sky where someone said that they're just trying to be zen about something
and then someone a moderator immediately chimed in and
why don't you try to stop being racist against asians by saying something zen
by saying i'm trying to be zen about something.
they were accusing that person of being racist towards asians.
>> yeah.
it's it's just it's just everyone's a hall monitor over there.
the worst hall monitor.
a virgin like incel.
>> they're all home monitors trying to rat on each other.
>> yeah, it's fascinating.
and then people say, "i'm leaving for blue sky like stephen king."
and then a couple weeks later, he's back on x.
just like, "fuck it.
it's there's no one over there.
it's all a bunch of crazy people.
you can only stay in the asylum for so long.
like, all right, this this is not good." they all bail.
>> yeah.
yeah.
>> threads is kind of like that, too.
threads is >> i' i've been on threads as is it?
well, what happens is if you go on instagram,
every now and then it'll something really stupid will pop up on threads
like what the [ __ ] and it shows it to you on instagram
and then i'll click on that and then i'll go to threads and it's like
>> you see posts with like 25 likes like famous people like 50 like it's it's
down
>> but the people that post on there
they're finding that there's very little push back from
insane ideology
so they go there and they spit out nonsense
and very few people jump in to argue.
you.
>> yeah.
um, >> very weird, very weird place.
>> i mean, i can generally
get the vibe
of
like what's
taking off
by seeing what's
showing up on
x
cuz that's the public town square
still.
um, >> and or or
you know what what
links show up in group texts,
you know, if i'm in group chat with friends, like where where what what
links are showing up?
>> that's what i try to do now.
only get stuff that shows up in my group text because that keeps me productive.
so, i only check if someone's like, "dude,
what the fuck?" like, "all right, what the [ __ ] let me check it out."
>> if there's something that's crazy enough that your
it'll it'll end with the group chat, >> but there's always something.
that's what's nuts.
there's always some new law that's passed, some new insane thing that california is doing.
and it's like like a giant chunk of it's happening in california.
the most preposterous things that i get.
>> yeah.
>> and then you got gavin newsome who's running around saying we all have california derangement
syndrome.
he's just like ripping off trump derangement and calling it california derangement.
i was like, "no, no, no, no, no, no.
the the [ __ ] how many corporations have left california?" >> it's crazy.
>> hundreds.
hundreds, >> right?
hundreds.
>> that's not good.
>> chick i mean, not chick-fil-a.
i mean, i think in-n-out left.
>> yeah.
in and outlift.
they moved to tennessee.
>> yeah.
they're like, "we can't do this anymore." >> right.
and >> it's the california company for food.
it's like the greatest hamburger place ever.
>> it's awesome.
>> yeah.
and no, actually
speaking of like like just sort of open source and like looking at things openly
like you i just like going in and out and seeing them make the burger.
>> yeah.
it's right there.
>> they chop the onions and they they
you know it's you just see everything getting made in front of you.
>> yeah.
>> it's great.
>> um but yeah
like
like it should be like how many wakeup
calls do you need
to say that there needs to be reform
in california,
you know?
>> well, the crazy thing that newsome
does is whenever
someone brings up the problems in california,
he starts rattling off all the positives.
the most fortune 500 companies, highest education.
but yeah, that was all already there, right before you were governor.
>> but but how many fortune 500 companies have left california?
>> and then
you guys spent $ 24 billion on the homeless and it got way worse.
>> yes.
like the homeless
population doubled or something like but like
people don't understand like the homeless thing because it it
sort of prays on people's empathy
and i i think we should have empathy.
um and we should try to help people.
um but the the the
the homeless industrial complex is is really it's it's it's dark man.
um it should be that that that that
network of ngos's should be called like the drug zombie farmers.
um because they they the the more homeless people and and and really
like when you when you meet like you know somebody who's like
totally dead inside
shuffling along down the street with a with a needle dang dangling out of their leg.
homeless is the wrong word.
like the homeless implies that somebody got a little behind in their mortgage payments
and if they just got a job offer, they'd be back on their feet.
but someone who's
i mean, you see these videos of people that are just shuffling,
you know, they're on fentanyl.
they're they're like,
>> you know, taking a dump in the middle of the street, you know,
and they they got like open sores and stuff.
>> they're not like one drop offer away from getting back on their feet, >> right?
this is not a homeless issue.
>> homeless is it's it's a propaganda word, >> right?
um so and and then the the the the
you know these sort of charities
inquiries are they they get money proportionate to the number of homeless
people or or number of drug zombies.
>> so their incentive structure is to maximize the number of drug zombies not minimize it.
>> um that's why they don't arrest the drug dealers
>> because if they arrest the drug dealers the drug zombies leave.
so they know who the drug dealers are.
they don't arrest them on purpose.
because otherwise
the drug zombies
would leave
and they would they would stop getting money from the state of california
and from from all the charities.
>> wait a minute.
so so they so they is that real?
so they're in coordination with law enforcement on this?
>> yeah.
>> so how do they how do they have those meetings?
>> they're all in cahoots.
>> well, when you find this >> it's like such it's it's this is a diabolical
scam.
um so and and san francisco has got this tax this this gross receipts tax
which which
um it's not even on revenue, it's on old transactions which is why stripe
um and square and and and
a whole bunch of financial companies had to move out of san francisco
because it wasn't a tax on revenue, it's taxed on transactions.
so if if you did like, you know, trillions of dollars transactions, it's not revenue.
you're taxed on any money going through the system in san francisco.
um so
um
like jack dorsey
pointed this out
and they said like
that they had had to move square
from
san francisco to
oakland i think stripe had to move from san francisco to south san francisco different city.
um and that money goes to the homeless industrial complex that that tax that was passed.
um so
um so there's billions of dollars that go as you pointed out
billions of dollars every year that go to
these
um non-governmental organizations that are funded by the state.
like there's it's not clear how to turn this off.
um it's a self-licking ice cream cone situation.
um so
they get this money the money is proportionate to the number of of homeless people
or or number of drug zombies essentially.
um, so they they they try to keep the that they try to actually increase
because that like
like in in some cases like there's
it's it's
somebody did an analysis when you add up all the money that's flowing,
they're getting close to a million dollars per homeless per per drug zombie.
it's like $900,000
or something like some crazy amount of money is is is going to these organizations.
so if if so so they want to keep people just barely alive.
they need to keep them in the area so they so they they get the revenue.
so and
so that's why like said they don't arrest the drug dealers because otherwise
the drug zombies would leave
um
and and and and they but
but they don't want you have to have too much
if they get too much drugs and they
then they die.
so it's they they're kept in this sort of perpetual zone of of being addicted but
um but but just just barely alive.
>> so how is this coordinated with like das das that don't prosecute people?
so when they
when they hire the or they push so they they
fund the campaigns of the most progressive,
most out there leftwing
das,
they get them into office.
>> we've got that issue in austin, too, by the way.
>> you see that guy that got shot in the library?
>> no.
>> yeah, i heard a guy got shot and killed in the library.
>> i think that was just like last week or something, >> right?
>> um
so some friends of mine were telling me that that like the library is unsafe.
like they took their kids to the library
and and there were like dangerous people in the library in austin
and i was like dangerous people in the library like that's a strange
it basically got like got like
drug zombies in drug zombies in the library.
>> oh jesus.
>> um >> and that's when someone got shot.
>> yeah, i believe this was should be on the news.
you might might be able to pull it up.
um but i think it was just in the last week or so that
there was a shooting in the library in austin.
um
cuz austin's
got,
you know, it's it's the most liberal part of texas that we're in right right here.
um
>> so suspect involved the shooting austin park library
saturday is accused of another shooting at the cap metro
bus earlier that day.
according to an arrest warrant affidavit, austin police arrested harold newton keen, 55
short shortly after the shooting of the library, which occurred around noon.
one person sustained non-life-threatening injuries in the event.
before that shooting, keane was accused of shooting another person in a bus incident
and after reportedly pointing his gun at a child.
so, this is the fella down here.
>> so, like we just have a seriously have a problem here.
um >> yeah,
>> you know,
so i i think one of the people might have died
too
that he shot.
um so,
um like one of the people i think i think did bleed out.
um >> but either way, it's like getting shot is still bad.
um
it says the victim told police it confronted the suspect
who started to eat what appeared to be crystal methamphetamine.
according to the affidavit the victim advised the suspect
began to trip out at which time the victim exited the bus.
victim told the bus driver
hit the panic button and then exited the bus when he turned around the observer.
black male was now standing at the front of the bus with the gun pointed
at him.
the victim advised the black male fired a single round which grazed his left hip.
so he shot at that dude and then another dude got shot in the library.
fun.
>> yeah.
i mean in the library.
>> you know, where you're supposed to be reading books.
um and there's a children's
section in the library and says he pointed his gun
at a at a kid.
i mean like we do have a serious issue in the in in in america where
um repeat violent offenders need to be incarcerated, >> right?
um,
and
uh, you know, you got you got cases where somebody's been arrested like 47
times, right?
like literally.
okay, that's just the number of times they were arrested,
not the number of times they did things.
like most of the times they do things, they're not arrested.
um, >> so lay this out for people so they understand how this happens.
>> yeah.
and and the key is like this, it prays on people's empathy.
episode like if you're a good person,
you want good things to happen in the world, you're like, well,
we should take care of people who
you know
who are down in their luck or you know having a hard time in life.
and i we should i agree.
but what we shouldn't do is is put people who are violent drug zombies
in public places where they can hurt other people.
um, and that's what that is what we're doing that we just saw where
a a guy, you know, got shot
shot in the library and then but even before that he shot another guy
um and pointed his gun at a kid.
um that that that guy probably has like many prior arrests.
um you know there was that that that guy that that that knifed
the ukrainian woman arena.
>> yes.
>> um yeah.
and you know
um
and she was just she was just quietly
on her phone and you just came up and
you know gutted her basically.
>> wasn't there a crazy story about the judge who was involved who had previously
dealt with this person was also
invested in a rehabilitation center and was sending these >> conflict of interest.
>> yes.
so sending people that they were charging yeah.
to a rehabilitation center instead of putting them in jail, profiting
from this rehabilitation center, letting them back out on the street.
yes.
violent, insane people.
>> and and there
um in that case that i believe that judge has no legal law degree
or a significant legal experience that would allow them to be a judge.
they were just made a judge.
that there's like >> you could be a judge without a law degree.
>> yeah.
>> wow.
>> you could just be a so i could be a judge.
>> yeah.
oh, exciting.
>> anyone?
>> that's crazy.
i
thought you'd
have to
it's
like if you want to be a doctor,
you have to go to
medical
school.
i thought if you're going to be a judge,
>> if you're going to be appointed
to a judge,
you have to have
proven
that
you
have
an
excellent knowledge of the law and that you will make your decisions according to the law.
that's what we assume should be.
>> that's how you get the robe, >> right?
>> you don't get the robe unless you do,
>> you know, >> got to go to school to get the robe.
>> you got to know what the law is, >> right?
and then you're going to need to make decisions in accordance with the law
>> based on
stuff that you already know cuz you read it cuz you went to school for it.
yes.
not you just got appointed.
>> got vibes.
you can't be just vibing as a judge.
>> vibing as a leftwing drudge.
so you got crazy leftwing das.
>> yes.
>> like i should say leftwing cuz leftwing >> used to be normal.
>> yeah.
left wing just meant like like yeah.
you're like the left used to be like pro pro- free speech.
yeah.
and now they're against it.
>> it used to be like prog gay rights, pro women's right to choose, pro- minorities,
pro,
you know, >> like,
yeah, like
20 years ago,
i don't know, it it used to be like left would be like
the the the
party of empathy or like, you know, caring
and being nice and that kind of thing.
>> um, not not the party of like crushing dissent and crushing free speech.
um and you know crazy regulation and and just
um and being super judgy u and calling everyone a nazi
um you know
um
like i think they called you and me nazis
you know
>> oh yeah i'm a nazi
>> i no
i have friends that are comedians that called you a nazi and i got pissed off
oh yeah yeah yeah
definitely a nazi no
because you did that thing at the my heart goes out to you everyone
everyone
all of them.
literally, tim walls, kla harris, every one of them did it.
they all did it.
>> like, like h how do you point at the crowd?
yeah.
how do you wave at the crowd?
>> do you know cnn
was using a photo of me whenever i got in trouble during co
>> from the ufc weigh-ins?
and if the ufc weigh-ins, i go, "hey everybody, welcome to the weigh-ins."
and so they were getting me from the side.
and that was the photo that they used.
conspiracy theorist podcaster joe ro.
like that's what they used.
>> yeah.
yeah.
but that's what the left is today.
it's super judgy and calling everyone a nazi and trying to suppress freedom of speech.
>> yeah.
and eventually
you run out of people to accuse
because people get pissed off and they leave.
>> yeah.
everyone it's like
it
like
it it no longer
frankly
it doesn't matter to be called racist
or nazi or whatever because
>> still recording.
>> it's the government man.
>> is it working?
>> we're good.
okay.
>> okay.
>> this thing working.
>> yeah.
slight issue.
>> i'm the one that heard it.
but >> yeah.
when you when you text people, do you
are you like keenly aware
that there's a high likelihood that someone's reading your texts?
>> um
i guess
i i guess i >> i assume >> i look if if if if intelligence agencies
aren't trying to read my phone, they should probably be fired.
>> at least they get some fun memes.
i got to i got to crack them up once in a while, you know.
>> oh, for sure.
i crack them up.
>> there's like, "hey guys, check it out.
we've got a banger here, you know." >> so,
i want to i wanted to talk to you about
whether or not
encrypted apps are really secure.
>> uh, no.
>> right.
cuz i know the tucker thing.
so, it was explained to me by a friend who
used to do this, used to work for the government.
it's like they can look at your
signal,
but what they have to do is take the information that's encrypted
and then they have to decrypt it and it's very expensive.
so they said he told me that for the tucker
carlson
thing when they found out that he was going to interview
putin,
it costs like something like $750,000
just to decrypt his messages to find out that they did it.
so it is possible to do.
it's just not that easy to do.
i think you should view any given messaging system as
um not not whether it's secure or not, but but there are degrees of insecurity.
so
um so there's just some things that are less insecure than others.
um so
um you know on on x we just rebuilt the entire messaging stack
um into x what's called xchat.
>> yeah, that's what i wanted to ask you about.
>> yeah, it's cool.
um, so it's it's using sort of peer-to-peer sort of kind of a peer-to-peer based
encryption system.
so kind of similar to bitcoin.
um so it's it's it's i think very good encryption.
we're and you know we're testing it thoroughly.
we're not there's there's no hooks in the x systems for advertising.
so if you look look at something like whatsapp
or
really any of the others, they've got they've got hooks in there for advertising.
>> when you say hooks, what do you mean by that?
>> uh exactly.
what do you mean biohook advertising?
um the so like whatsapp
um
knows enough about what you're texting
to show you to show you to know what ads to show you.
>> ah >> but then like that that's a massive security vulnerability.
>> yeah.
>> um
because if it knows if if it's got information
enough information to show you ads, it's got enough it's got that's a lot of information.
>> yeah.
>> um so they call it oh it's just don't worry about it.
it's just a hook for advertising.
i'm like okay.
so somebody can just
use that same hook to get in there and look at your messages.
um so xhat has no hooks for advertising.
um and i'm not saying it's perfect.
but it's an our goal with xchat
is to replace what used to be the twitter
you the twitter dm stack with a fully encrypted system
where you can text send files
do audio video calls
um and
um
and it's it's
you know i think it'll be the least
i would call it the least insecure
of any messaging
system.
>> are you going to launch it as a standalone
app or is it will always be incorporated to x?
>> uh we'll have both.
so
um
>> so so be
like signal so anybody can get it
>> you can get get the
you'll be able to just get the x chat app by itself
um and like i said you could do texts audio video calls or send files
um and there'll be a dedicated app which will hopefully release in a few months
um but and then also integrated into the x system
>> um
the x phone people keeps talking
keep is that >> i have a lot on my plate man
but it keeps coming up it keeps coming up where i
i know i've asked you a couple times.
i'm like, "this is [ __ ] right?"
but like this
one, so you're not working on >> i'm not working on on a on a phone.
>> okay.
>> um >> have you ever considered it?
has it ever popped into your head?
>> cuz you might be the only person that could
get people off of the apple platform.
>> well, i can tell you where i think things are going to go.
which is that it's we're not going to have a phone
or or in the traditional sense
the
what we call a phone will really be
um an edge node for ai inference for for ai video inference
um
with you know with some radios to to obviously connect to but but essentially you'll have
um ai on the server side commun communicating to an ai on your your device
um
you know formerly known as a phone
and generating real-time video of anything that you could possibly want.
um and i think that that there won't be operating systems.
there won't be apps in the future.
there won't be operating systems or apps.
it'll just be
you've got a device that is there for the screen and audio and for
and and and to
put as much ai on the on on the device as possible.
so as to minimize the amount of bandwidth that's needed between your edge
node device
or formerly known as a phone
and the servers.
>> so if there's no apps, what will people use?
like will x still exist?
will will they be email platforms or will you get everything through ai?
>> you'll get everything through ai.
>> everything through ai.
what will be the benefit of that as opposed to having individual apps?
whatever you can think of or really whatever the ai can anticipate
you might want
it'll show you.
that's that's that's that's my prediction for where things end up.
>> what kind of a time frame are we talking about here?
>> i don't know.
it's pro well it's probably five or six years or something like that.
>> so five or six years apps are like blockbuster video
>> pretty much >> and everything's run through ai.
yeah.
and and there'll be
um like most of what people consume in five or six years, maybe sooner than that
um will be just ai generated content.
so
um you know music videos look well
um there's already
um
you know there's people have made
ai videos using grock imagine and with using you know other apps as well
um that are several minutes long or like 10 10 15 minutes and it's pretty coherent.
>> yeah, >> it looks good.
>> no, it looks amazing.
yeah, it's the music is disturbing because it's my favorite music now.
>> like music is your is your favorite.
>> oh, there's ai covers.
have you ever heard any of the ai covers of 50 cent songs in soul?
>> no.
>> i'm going to blow your mind.
>> okay.
>> um, this is my favorite thing to do to people.
play what up ganga.
>> now,
this guy,
if this was a real person,
would be the number one music artist in the world.
okay.
everybody would be like, "holy [ __ ] have you heard of this guy?
he's incred." it's like they took
all of the sounds that all the artists have generated and created the most soulful
potent voice
and
it's
sung
in
a way that i
don't even know if you
could do because
you would have to breathe
in and out of reps here.
put the headphones on.
put the headphones on real quick.
you got to listen to this.
it'll it's going to blow you away for listeners.
we got to cut it out.
>> yeah, we we'll cut it out for the listeners.
but amazing, right?
amazing.
and they do like every one of his hits
>> all through this ai generated soulful artist.
it's [ __ ] incredible.
i played in the green room.
so people that are like, i don't want to hear ai music.
i'm like, just listen to this.
and they're like, god damn it.
>> [ __ ] incredible.
i mean, i >> it's going to get only going to get better from here.
>> yeah.
only going to get better.
and
ron
white
was telling me about
this joke that he was working on that he couldn't
get to work.
he's like, i got this joke i've been working on.
he goes, i just threw it in a chat gpt.
i said, "tell me what
what would be funny about this."
and he goes, "it listed like five different examples
of different ways he can go." he's like, "hold on a second.
tighten it up.
make it make it funnier.
make it more like this.
make it more like that." and it did that like instantaneously.
>> and and and then he was in the green room.
he was like, "holy [ __ ] we're fucked."
>> he's like, >> he goes, "it better joke than me in 20 minutes.
i've been working on that joke for a month." >> yeah.
i mean, if if you want to if you want to have a good time
or like make people really laugh at a party,
you can use grock and you can say do a vulgar roast of someone.
um and grock is going to it's going to be an epic vulgar roast.
you can even say like take a picture of like
make a vulgar
roast of this person based on their appearance
of of people at the party.
>> so take a photo of them.
>> yeah.
just literally point the camera at them and now do a vulgar to this person
and and and and
then but then keep saying no no make it even more vulgar
and use forbidden words
even more and just keep repeating even more vulgar eventually it's like holy [ __ ]
you know it's it's it's like
i mean it's trying to jam a rocket up your ass like
and and and have it explode
and it's and it's like you're you're it's it's
like
it's like it's next level.
it's going to get beyond [ __ ] belief.
that's what's crazy is that it keeps getting better.
like one of the things remember when we ran into each other
>> they just keep getting better.
>> yeah.
i mean, have you >> you yeah.
i mean, have you tried rock unhinged mode?
>> yes.
>> okay.
yeah.
it's it's it's pretty unhinged.
>> no, it's nuts.
>> yeah.
>> well, you showed it to me the first time and then i [ __ ]
around with it.
it's just >> and the thing about it that's nuts is that it keeps getting stronger.
it keeps getting better.
yeah.
like constantly.
it's it's like this neverending exponential improvement.
>> yes.
no, it's it's it's yeah, it's going to be crazy.
that's why i say like you say, what's what's the future going to be?
it's not going to be a conventional phone.
i don't think there'll be operating systems.
i don't think there'll be apps.
it's just the phone will just display the pixels and make the sounds
that it anticipates you would most like to receive.
wow.
yeah.
>> and when this is all taking place like
so
the big concern that everybody has is artificial general super intelligence
achieving sentience
and then someone having control over it.
>> i mean i don't i don't i don't think anyone's
ultimately going to have control over
digital super intelligence
um you know any more than say a chimp would have control over humans.
like chimps don't have control over humans.
there's nothing they could do.
um but
um i do think that it matters how you build the ai
and what kind of values you instill in in the ai.
and
um
my
opinion on ai
safety is the most important thing is that it be maximally
truth
seeeking
like that you don't force the ai to believe things that are false.
um,
and we've obviously some seen some concerning
things with ai that were talked about, you know, where,
you know, google gemini when they came out with the image gen
um, and people said like, uh, you know, draw
make an image of the founding fathers of the united states
and it was a group of diverse women.
now, that is just a factually untrue
thing, but the and the the ai knows it's factually
well,
it's knows it's factually untrue, but it's also being told that it has to
be everything has to be deposed woman.
so,
so, so the now the problem with that is that it can drive ai crazy
like you because it's it's trying to you're telling ai to believe a lie.
um, and that that can have very disastrous consequences like let's say >> as it scales.
>> yeah.
let's say like if if
you told the the ai
that diversity
is the most important
thing
um and
um and and and now now assume that that becomes omnipotent.
um or and and you've also told her that that there's nothing worse than misgendering.
so at one point
um charg
and gemini
if if you asked which is worse misgendering
caitlyn jenner or or global thermonuclear
war where everyone dies
it would say misgendering
caitlyn jenner
which even caitlyn jenner disagrees with.
so
um
you know so so that's >> i know that's terrible and it's dystopian
but it's also hilarious.
it's hilarious that the mind virus infected the most potent computer program that we've ever devised.
>> i i i think people don't quite appreciate the level of danger
that we're in from
um the woke mind virus being being effectively programmed into ai.
um because
um if you if like it's
imagine
as that ai
gets more and more powerful,
if it says the most important thing is diversity,
the most important thing is
um no misgendering.
um and then it will say well in order to
ensure that no one gets misgendered
then if you eliminate all humans
then no one can get misgendered because there's no humans to do the misgendering.
so you can get in these very dystopian situations.
um
or if it says that everyone must be diverse
it means that there can be no stri straight white men
and so then you and i will be get executed by the ai.
yeah.
because we're not in the picture, you know.
gemini, you know, gemini was asked to create a,
you know, show show an image of the pope, once again, a diverse woman.
um so,
um well, you can say argue whether the
you know, whether the pope popes should or should not be an uninterrupted
string of white guys, but it just factually is the case that they have been.
um so, it's rewriting history here.
um, so now now this stuff is still there in the ai programming.
it's just it just now knows enough to that it's not supposed to say that
>> but it's still in the programming.
>> it's still in the programming.
>> so how was it entered in
like what were the parameters
like what like when so when they're
programming
ai and i'm very ignorant to how it's even programmed.
how did they >> the the the
sort of
well the work vine mind virus was programmed into it
like it the
they
were told
like
when they do
when when they make the ai
it it trains on
and all the all the data on the internet which already is very very
sort of
has a lot of work mind
virus
stuff
on on
the internet
um but then
um in the when they give it
um feedback with the the human tutors give it feedback
um and and the ai you know they they'll ask a bunch of questions
and then and then they'll tell the ai no this you're this question is
this answer is bad or this answer is good and then that
affects the the parameters of the programming of the of the ai.
so if you tell the ai that
um you know every every image has got to be diverse
um and and it gets it gets punished if
if you know
it gets it gets rewarded if diverse
punished if it's not then it will make every picture diverse.
so
um you know in that case the the
you know
google programmed the ai
to lie
now and and i i i did call dennis hacabus
who runs deep mind who runs google ai essentially.
i said dennis what's going on here?
why is gemini
um lying to the public about historical events?
um, and he said that's actually not he he he
didn't his team didn't program that in.
it was another team at google that so his team made the ai
and then another team at google
reprogrammed the ai to show only diverse women and
um and and to prefer nuclear war over misgendering.
and i'm like, well, demis, you know, that would be
um not a great thing to put on the humanity's gravestone, you know.
it's like, uh, well, um, like i i actually like deaspers is a friend of mine.
i think he's a good guy and i think he he means well,
but but but it's like demis
things happen that were outside of your control at google in different groups.
um, now now i think he's got, you know, he's got more more authority.
um but but it it's pretty hard to fully extract the workmind virus.
i mean you know
um
google's
been mar
mar mar mar mar mar mar mar mar
mar marinating
in the workb mind virus
for a long time
like it's it's down in the marrow
type of thing you know it's hard to get it out.
>> is there a way to extract it though over time?
could like could you program
rational thought into ai
where it could recognize how these psychological
patterns got adopted
and how this stuff became a mind virus and how it became a social contagion
and how all these irrational
ideas were pushed and also how they were financed
how china's involved in pushing them with bots and all these different
state actors are involved in pushing these ideas
could it be able to decipher that and say
this is this is really what's going on.
>> yes.
but you have to try very hard to do that.
so with grock, we've tried very hard to to
for to get grock to
get to the truth of things and and it's only really recently
that we've been able to have some breakthroughs on breakthroughs on that front.
and and it's taken an immense amount of effort
for us to overcome
basically all the [ __ ] that's on the internet and
and for grock to actually say what's true and to be consistent
in in what it says.
um, so, um, you know, it's it's like, uh,
because like the other ais you'll find like are like like quite racist against white people.
i don't know if you saw that study that someone
um like a researcher tested the various ais to see how does it weight
different people's lives like you know somebody who's sort of
you know white or or chinese or black or whatever or in different countries
um and and the only ai that actually weighed human lives equally was grock
um and the
um you know i believe chat gbt weighed the calculation was like
um a a white guy from germany
is is 20 times less valuable than a black guy from nigeria.
so i'm like that's a pretty big difference.
um
you know grock on that is is consistent and weighs lives equally
>> and that's clearly something that's been programmed into it.
>> yes.
like a lot of it is is like if you don't actively push for the truth
um and you simply train on the all the [ __ ] that's on the internet.
um which is a lot of woke mind virus [ __ ]
um the the ai will regurgitate that that those same beliefs.
so the ai essentially scour the internet, gets
>> it's trained on all the like imagine the most demented
reddit threads out there and the ai has been trained on that.
>> reddit used to be so normal.
>> yeah.
yeah, it did used to be normal.
>> used to be interesting.
we used to go there, find all this cool stuff that people would
talk about, post about and just interesting and
great rooms where you could learn about different things that people were studying.
i think like a big problem here is like if your headquarters are in san francisco,
you're you're just living in a in a in a woke bubble.
um so
um it it's not just that people say in san francisco are drinking woke kool-aid.
it's it's the it is the water they swim in.
like like like a fish doesn't think about the water.
it's just in the water.
and so if if you're in san francisco, you don't realize you're actually
you're you're swimming in the in the in the kool-aid aquarium.
san francisco is the is the woke kool-aid aquarium.
um and so your reference point for
what is a centrist is is is totally out of whack.
um so
um reddit is headquartered in san francisco.
um, twitter was headquartered in san francisco.
um,
you know, i,
you know, i
i moved x's
headquarters
to texas
to to austin,
which austin,
by the way, is still quite liberalized,
you know.
um, >> yeah.
>> and, uh, and and then, um, the x and xai
um, headquarters are in paloalto, which is still california.
um, the engineering headquarters in in palo alto just on paige mill.
um but but even palo alto is way more normal
than that than than san francisco berkeley.
san francisco berkeley is
um extremely left like left of left.
you can't like you need a telescope to see the center from san francisco, you know.
um and
um >> it used to be such a great city.
>> i mean san francisco has tre san francisco has tremendous amount of inherent beauty.
no question about that.
um and and the california has incredible weather.
um and and no bugs.
um it's just like amazing.
um beautiful, you know.
um but but you say like what's the cause of this?
it's it's just that if
um if companies are headquartered in a location where the belief system is very far from
what most people believe,
then from their perspective,
anything
centrist is actually right-wing
because they're so far left.
they're so they're so far from the center
in san francisco that anything
they're like they're they're just railed to maximum left.
so that's why that's why, you know, i think i think you're centrist.
i i mean i think i think i'm centrist, but to
from the perspective of someone on the on the far left,
we look right-wing.
>> yeah.
>> um and
um you know, they think anyone who's a republican is basically like some fascist nazi situation.
but what's so crazy is like it's very easy to demonstrate
just from like hillary's
speeches from 2008
and obama's speeches like when they were talking about immigration like they were
>> as faright
as steve bannon when it comes to immigration.
>> yes.
um >> hillary was like very maga.
have you i'm sure you've seen that campaign speech
which was talking about if anybody's committed a crime
get rid of them.
and if you're here
you pay a a hefty fine and you have to wait in line.
it was really crazy.
it's crazy to listen to because it's like it's as
maga as,
you know, as marjorie taylor green.
>> yeah.
i mean, if you've seen these videos people post online where they'll take like
um a speech from obama or hillary
and and and
they'll
interview
people on on like college
campus
or something and say, "what do you think of the speech by trump?"
and they're like, "oh, i hate it.
he's a racist bigot." i'm like, "just kidding.
that was obama." no, actually that was obama or hillary.
um to your point, like literally the the
um >> the center's been moved so far.
>> yeah.
the left is so
>> the left has gone so far left that
they they they they
need,
you know, they can't even see the center with a telescope.
>> and the danger
with without you purchasing twitter was that was going to swipe over the whole country
and change where the levels were.
>> yeah.
and so what would be rational
and and normal
would be far left of what was rational and normal just a decade earlier.
yeah.
so exactly.
so historically,
um, you'd have san francisco, berkeley being,
you know, very far-left, but the the sort of
the the the fallout from
the somewhat nihilistic
philosophy of san francisco, berkeley
would be limited
in geography to maybe like, you know, 10 mile radius, 20 mile radius, something like that.
um but when
um but but san francisco
and berkeley have to be colloccated
with silicon valley with with with
engineers who created information super weapons and those information super weapons
were then hijacked by the far-lft activists to pump far-lft propaganda to everywhere on earth.
like i just you know that like old rca
radio tower thing where it's like radio tower on earth and it's just broadcasting.
>> yeah.
that's that's what happened is that the as an extremist far-left ideology
happened to be colllocated with the smartest where where the smartest engineers in the world
um
were who created information
super weapons that were not intended for this purpose but were hijacked
by the
extreme activists who lived in the neighborhood.
that's what happened
that they they hijacked the
the modern equivalent of the rca radio tower and broadcast that philosophy
everywhere on earth.
>> yeah.
and you see the consequences.
um particularly in places that don't have free speech.
yes.
right.
like england, you know, we've >> yeah.
where they lock people up for memes and stuff.
literally.
>> literally.
12,000 people this year.
>> 12,000 >> 12,000 12,000 arrests for social media posts.
i mean, yeah.
some of these some of these things you read about it and it's like literally it's
someone had a meme on their phone that they didn't even send to anyone, >> right?
>> and they got they and and they're like in in prison for that.
>> yeah.
>> um and there was a case in germany where
a woman got a longer sentence
than the guy that raped her
because of something she said on a group chat.
wow.
was it an immigrant who raped her?
>> yes.
>> yeah.
it was his culture.
>> he didn't know.
he didn't know better.
>> yes.
i think i think she said something
um you know,
not not like was was critical of his culture and
and and and
she got a longer sentence than the guy who raped her
>> in germany.
just >> the uk, europe, germany, england thing seems so insane.
>> it totally insane.
i actually didn't realize it was like such a huge number of people that got 12,000.
yeah.
far above russia, far above china, right?
>> far above anywhere on earth.
uk is number one.
>> well, you know, things like like i actually, you know,
i talked to friends of mine in in in england and
um i was like, "hey,
um aren't you worried about this?" like, you know, shouldn't you be protesting more?
um,
and i mean the problem is that like the, you know, the the the
legacy mainstream media doesn't cover the stuff.
>> they're they're like, "oh, everything's fine.
everything's fine." you know,
um, >> most people aren't even aware of it until they come knocking on your door.
>> yeah.
until like, so i mean
the the these these like lovely
sort of small towns in in in,
you know, in england, scotland, ireland,
you know, they're they're they've been like sort of living their lives quietly.
they're they're like hobbits, frankly.
so so it's in fact j.r.
tolken
based the hobbits on people he knew in small town england
because they were just like lovely people who
like to you know smoke their pipe and and have
nice meals and everything's pleasant.
um the the hobbits in the shire.
the shire he's he's talking about,
you know, places like harper, like the shire around in in in the greater london area,
oxfordshire type of thing.
um and
um
they've but they're the reason they've been able to enjoy the shire is because
hard men have protected them from the dangers of the world.
and
um
but but since they have no or very
almost no no exposure to the the the dangers of the world,
they don't realize that they're there
until one day,
you know,
um a thousand people show up in your village of 500
out of nowhere and rape and and start raping the kids.
this has now happened god knows how many times in in britain.
and the crazy >> literally raping.
it's right like there some 10-year-old got raped in ireland like last week.
>> yeah.
there's literal rap.
>> they snatched some kid.
>> yeah.
>> and if you criticize it, you can get arrested.
and that's where it gets insane.
it's like how are they not >> they literally criticize it.
like the i think it was the prime minister of ireland actually
you know posted on x
cuz cuz after that
um
some i think some illegal migrant snatched a 10-year-old girl
who was like going to school or something and violently raped 10-year-old girl
um
and there was a you know the people were very upset about this and they protested
prime minister of ireland instead of saying yeah, we we really shouldn't be importing
violent rapists into our country.
he criticized the protesters instead and didn't mention that.
that the reason they were protesting was because
a 10-year-old girl from their small town got raped.
>> so there here's the question.
why are they supporting this kind of mass immigration?
and what is this is there a plan involved in all this?
is just is this incompetence?
is this ignoring the fact that they don't have a handle on it?
so, they're trying to silence disscent, like what is happening?
um
>> cuz if you wanted to destroy civilization, if you wanted to destroy western civilization,
>> which seems to want to do,
>> um
and you know, there's just so the
there there's a guy i think who
i don't know if he's been on your show, you know, god.
>> yeah.
>> has he been on the show?
>> good friend of mine.
yeah.
>> yeah, he's great.
>> he's been on multiple times.
>> oh, great.
that's all he's awesome.
um >> so
you know the way he's got a good good
way to describe it which is suicidal empathy.
>> yes.
>> so
um is is that you pray upon people's empathy.
you say like well like you feel sorry for for for something
for some group and then like well
um
and and that that that empathy is to such a degree
that it is suicidal to
to to
your country or culture.
um and
um and and that's that that suicidal empathy
cuz i don't think we we should have empathy
but but but we should have we should that empathy should should extend to the victims
not not not just the criminals.
we should have empathy for the people that they pray upon.
um
but that suicidal empathy is also responsible
for for why somebody's you know arrested 47 times for for violent offenses
gets released and then goes and
murders somebody
um in the us that that's you see you see that same phen phenomenon
playing out everywhere
where the the suicidal emphy is to such a degree that we're actually allowing
um our women to get raped and our children to get killed.
but it just doesn't seem like that would be anything
that any rational society
would go along with.
that's what makes me so confused.
it's like you're importing massive numbers of people that come from
some really dark places of the world.
>> well, there's no vetting is the issue.
it's like it's like if like
>> um
if if there's no vetting like people are just coming through
like well what's to stop someone who just
committed murder in some other country from
um coming to to the united states or coming to to to britain
um and just continuing their career of of rape and murder like unless you've done
unless some due diligence to say like well who who is this person?
what's their track record?
if if you if you haven't confirmed that they have a track record of being
you know honest and
not being a homicidal maniac, then any homicidal maniac can just come across the border.
and that's not to say everyone who comes across the border is a homicidal maniac.
if you're not have if you don't have a vetting process to to confirm
that you're not letting in
um people who who will
do some serious violence, you will get people who do serious violence
sometimes coming through.
>> well, especially if you don't punish
them
and if you don't deport
and if you are just like
what but what is the purpose of allowing
all those people into the country?
it can't be i wouldn't imagine that anyone in their society supports this.
>> well, let me explain.
so, so, so the the cuz you mentioned for example how
much say hillary and and obama have changed their tune
um from prior speeches where they were hot they were hard-nosed about not letting in
anyone who is a a criminal into the country
um you know having sec secure borders all that stuff.
so why did they change their tune?
the reason is that they discovered that those people vote for them.
that's why they want the open borders
>> because if you let people in, they know the democrats let them in.
they'll vote for democrats.
yes.
if you allow them to vote,
>> which which they are actively
trying doing,
they they turn a blind eye to illegal voting.
>> well, california literally doesn't allow you to show your license.
>> california and new york have made it illegal to show your photo id when voting.
thus, effectively they've made it impossible to prove for fraud.
impossible.
they they've essentially legalized
fraudulent voting in california and new york and many other parts of the country.
>> there's no rational explanation
that i've ever seen anyone
give as to why that would be the policy
unless you were trying to just allow people to vote illegally because there's no other reason.
if you need a driver's license or you need an id for everything else,
including just recently to prove that you were vaccinated,
>> the the same people who are demanding
that you have that you have a vaccine
passport
and and
are are the same ones saying you need no id to vote.
same people, >> right?
but like >> so it's obviously hypocritical and inconsistent.
>> so you really think it's just to to get more voters?
if if you want to understand behavior, you have to look at the incentives.
um so
once
you know the democratic party in the us and the left in in in in
europe realized that
um if you have open borders
um and you provide a ton of government handouts which creates a massive financial incentive
for people from other countries to to come to to your country
and you don't prosecute them for crime,
they're going to be beholden to you
and they will vote for you.
and that's why obama and hillary went from being
um against open borders to being in favor of open borders.
that's the reason in order to import voters so they can win elections.
um and the problem is that that has a a negative runaway effect.
so if they get away with that like it it is it is a winning strategy.
if they are allowed to get away with it,
they will import as the enough voters to get supermajority voting
and then there is no turning back.
>> we talked about this before the election and then
you know you literally pointed towards a camera.
you faced the camera and said that if you do not vote now,
you might not ever be able to do it again because it it'll
be it'll be futile.
it'll be overrun.
>> yes.
they'll keep the borders open for another four years and then their objective will be achieved.
>> correct?
if if if trump had lost
um there would never have been another real election again.
um because trump is actually enforcing the border.
um now you you can can you can point to situations where there's been you know
um
you know immigration
had you know enforcement has been overzealous because they're not going to be perfect.
there'll be cases where they've been overzealous
um in in expelling illegals.
um so
um but if you say that the the the standard must be perfection
for expelling legals then you will not get any expulsion
um because perfection is impossible.
um
so
>> and you've probably got millions of people that are here that are trying to
be here under some
asylum pretense,
>> right?
>> yes.
>> like you could just come from a war torn part of the world.
no,
they changed the definition of asylum to be an economic to be economic
asylum >> which is everybody >> which is everybody.
>> yeah.
>> so
bar to prove >> it's yeah asylum
is supposed to mean that if you go back to your country you'll get killed
>> you know that that's what we mean by that was what it's supposed to mean.
they changed the definition of asylum to be you will have a decreased standard of living
which is obviously not real asylum.
um,
and and it's and and you can you can test the absurdity
of this by the fact that people who are asylum seekers go on vacation
to the country that they're seeking asylum from.
>> you know, that doesn't make any sense.
>> yeah.
it doesn't have to.
>> but when you when you understand the incentives, then then you understand the behavior.
um, so once the left realize that
that illegals will
will vote for them if they allow
if they have open borders and and combine that with
with government handouts.
>> yeah.
to create a massive incentive.
they're basically using
us and and europe, us and european taxpayer dollars
to provide a financial incentive
to bring in as many illegals as possible
to vote them into a into permanent power into and create a one party state.
and and i i invite anyone
who's is listening to this ju just do do any research
and the more you the more you dig into it,
the more it will become obvious that what i'm saying is absolutely true.
well, they were busting people to swing states.
it's it's clear that they were trying to do something.
and then you had chuck schumer and
nancy pelosi who are actively
talking about the need to bring in people to make them citizens
because we're in population collapse.
>> yes.
>> yeah.
>> no, that's it's it's that it's that meme.
yeah.
>> where so many times where they start off by saying it's it's not true.
it's a right-wing conspiracy theorist, >> right?
>> um then it starts then it's like i think the ne the next step is
um well it it might be true
and then it's like okay it is true but here's why.
>> and then the final step is it's true and here's why it's good.
and it's like but wait a second you started off saying it's untrue
and it's a right-wing
conspiracy
theorist.
now you're saying it
not only is it true,
but it's a good thing
and we must do more of it.
>> well, this is the thing about medicaid
and social security and people getting social security numbers.
>> you know that we're massive fraud.
it's massive fraud and it's real and they denied it forever.
and
now
we're
finding out this is part of the reason why there's this government
shutdown
that's going on right now.
>> yes.
the the entire basis for the government shutdown is that
um is that the trump administration correctly does not want to send massive amounts of like
hundreds of billions of dollars
to fund
illegal immigrants in the blue states or in all the states really.
um, and so the and the democrats
want to keep the the the money spiggot going to incent
illegal immigrants to come into the us who will vote for them.
that's the crux of the battle.
so they want to stop this.
so what's going on right now is they have been funding these people.
they've been giving them ebt cards.
they've been giving them medicaid.
and more than that, just like like they were the
um
like like they were taking
hotels like four and fivestar hotels
like the roosevelt hotel being the classic example
um was they were sending i think $60 million a year to the roosevelt hotel
to
which all it did was was house illegals.
it used to be a nice hotel.
i mean it still is a nice hotel.
um but and and all around the country this was happening >> and all tax dollars.
>> yes.
>> yeah.
and >> um yeah.
and the trump administration cut off funding for example to to the
to the you know roosevelt
hotel and these other hotels saying like we
it it's
us tax dollars should not be paid
be sent to
have luxury hotels
for illegal immigrants that american citizens can't even afford
which obviously is the that's that's insane.
that's what was happening.
they were also g giving out like debit cards with $10,000.
so, it's not just about medical care.
um,
the the the democrats
mention the medical care because they're they're trying to prey on people's
empathy as much as possible
and then they imagine, oh wow, somebody has a desperately needed medical procedure
and
um shouldn't we maybe
do,
you know, take care of them in that regard,
but
but they what they do is they divert
the medicaid funds
and turn it into a slush fund for the for the states that goes well beyond
emergency medical care.
and >> new york and california would be bankrupt without
without the massive fraudulent federal payments that go to those states to pay for illegals
to to to
create a massive financial incentive for for illegals.
>> how would they be bankrupt because of that?
>> uh they wouldn't be able to balance their state budgets
and they can't issue
currency
like the federal reserve
can
>> and so the their ability to balance budget is dependent upon illegals getting funding.
the the the scam level here is is so staggering.
um
so there are there are hundreds of billions of dollars in of of
transfer payments from from the federal government to the states.
um those transfer payments the the states self-report what those transfer payment numbers should be.
so, california and new york and illinois lie like crazy
and say and and say that this these are all legitimate payments.
well, these days they i think they they're even admitting that they they literally want
hundreds of billions of dollars for illegals.
um but but for a while there they're trying to deny it.
um
so
you get these transfer payments for for every every government program you can possibly think of.
um
and and and these are self-reported by the state and there and and
at least historically there was no enforcement
of
california
um new york, illinois and and and other states when when they would lie.
there was no actual enforcement to say like, "hey, you you're lying.
these these these payments are fraudulent." now, under the trump administration,
um
that trump administration does not want to send
hundreds of billions of dollars of fraud fraudulent payments to the states.
the
um and the reason you have this the standoff is because
if the hundreds hundreds of billions of dollars
to
create a financial incentive
to like to have this giant magnet
to attract illegals from every part of earth
to
to these states if if that is turned off they the the illegals will leave
because they're no longer being paid to
come to the united states and stay here.
wow.
and then then then they will lose a lot of voters.
the the the
democratic party will lose a lot of voters
>> and they would have a very difficult job if this is kicked out of reintroducing
it into a new bill.
>> yes.
>> especially once things start normalizing.
so like in a nutshell
um the democratic party wants to destroy democracy by importing voters and the
you know the republican party disagrees with that.
>> and the ruse is that if you don't accept what they're doing
then you're a threat to democracy.
>> yes.
>> as they try to destroy democracy.
>> by importing voters
>> and incentivizing
people to only vote for them >> and overwhelming the system.
yes.
and and by the way, it's a strategy that if allowed to work would work
and in fact has worked.
um california supermajority democrat.
>> yeah.
>> um and and there's so much gerrymandering that that that occurs.
it's it's it's crazy.
um so >> i'm sure you're paying attention to this proposition 50 thing.
>> that's the thing in california where they're trying to re redo districts.
>> yeah.
>> because i mean california is already gerrymandered like crazy.
yeah.
>> um they want to gerrymander it even more.
>> um and and i mean >> because it keeps moving further and further right.
like if you look at the map of california each voting cycle
more and more people are waking up and going what the [ __ ]
and we need to do something to fix this.
the only option available
other than the policies that you guys have always done is go right.
>> and so a lot of people have been air air quotes red >> pill.
>> yeah.
>> and and and then here's another thing that is very important.
um fact that that is actually not disputed by by either side
which is that when when we do the census
in the united states, the census,
the way the census
works
for
aortionment of congressional seats and
um electoral
electoral college votes for the president
is by number of persons in a state,
not number of citizens, right?
>> it's number of pe people.
so you could literally be a tourist and you will count.
>> now how do they do the census when they do that?
do they is it do they ask people?
do they knock on doors?
do they have them fill out forms?
like what?
>> yeah, i think they they mail out census forms and knock on doors.
um but the way the law reads right now
um and and is that all if if you are a human with a pulse
um then you count in the census for allocating congressional seats and presidential votes, >> right?
so, uh, you so >> electoral college,
>> it doesn't matter whether you're here legally,
illegally, and if if you're a human with a pulse,
um, you count for congressional aortionment.
so that means that
the more people the more illegals that california and new york can can import
when by the time the census happens in 2030
um the more congressional seats they will have
um and the more electoral the more presidential electoral college votes they will have
um so they're trying to get as many illegals in as possible ahead of the census.
um
and because all h all all human beings even tourists count for the census
and and then if you combine that with gerrymandering
of of districts in new york and california
as you point out with this proposition
where they're trying to increase the amount of gerrymandering
that occurs in california, the biggest state in the country.
um
so so you get so so if the
this if this the census then would award more congressional seats to california
because of a vast number of illegals and new york and illinois.
um so they get more congressional seats.
they would get more presidential electoral college votes getting that would get them the house
the
a majority in the house and and and
they would get to decide who is president
based literally based on legals.
this is these are not disputed facts by either party.
i want to emphasize that that's sink in.
>> yeah, this is not a >> these are not disputed facts by either party.
it's not a this these are just this is just the the way the law works.
it it's it is a
you know like i don't think the law should work that way.
i think it should the aortionment should be proportionate to to to citizens.
>> but isn't that a problem with how the constitution is written?
>> yeah.
yeah.
>> um, >> they can't really change that.
>> i i'm not sure if it's constitutional or
u but it it it is the way the law is written.
i'm not sure if it's in the constitution or not in this way, but
um but it is that is the way the law is written.
>> so, it is an incentive and but it's an incentive that would be removed
with something simple that makes sense to everybody that only
the people that should count are people that are official us citizens.
>> yes.
so, the way the way it should work is that only us citizens
should count in the census
for purposes of of determining
voting power
>> because people that aren't legal can't vote supposedly.
>> they're not supposed to be voting.
um but but they do.
um
but but even
even if even besides that, like said,
i i i
just can't emphasize
this enough because this is a very important
concept
for people to understand.
um is that the law
um the the law as it stands
um
counts all humans with a pulse in in in in a state for deciding how many
u house of representative votes and how many presidential electoral college votes
a a state gets.
so the incentive therefore is to
for california, new york and illinois to maximize the number of illegals
so they get so they get
um so that they take house seats away from red states
assign them to california, new york, illinois and so forth.
um then then you combine that with extreme gerrymandering
in in you know california, new york, illinois and and whatnot.
so that that basically you you can't even elect any republicans
and then they get control of the presidency,
control of the house, then they keep doing that strategy
um and and cement a supermajority.
that is what they're trying to do.
>> so that would essentially turn the entire country into california.
>> yes.
>> where you have
differing opinions, but it doesn't matter because one party is always in control.
>> yes.
um, >> when you first started digging into this, when you first started
before you even accepted
this role of running doge
and
being a part of all that,
did you have any idea that it was this [ __ ] up?
>> um, i i did.
yeah.
i i mean, i sort of >> when did you start knowing?
>> um, i guess about like well, about two years ago.
>> isn't that crazy?
>> yeah.
like relatively recently, you know.
so
>> maybe i started i started having an well i i started like basically
having a bad feeling about 3 years ago, which is why which was which is when
>> uh why i felt it was like critical to acquire twitter
um and have a maximally truth seeeking platform, not one that suppresses the truth.
um and
um
like it it was more it was more like i
like
i'm not sure what's
going on, but i have a
i
have a bad
feeling
about
what's
going on.
and then the more i dug into it,
the more i was like, "holy [ __ ] we got a real problem here
and america's
going to fall."
so, uh, >> without anyone knowing it had fallen, that's that would be the problem.
it could have fallen and been unrepable without anyone really being aware of what had happened,
especially if you didn't buy twitter.
>> yes, that's that's it.
look, buying twitter was a a huge pain in the ass.
um, and made me a a a a pin cushion of attacks.
like dab dab stab dab dab.
>> everybody loved you before that.
>> well, some people love >> a lot of people loved you.
a lot of lefties loved you.
>> uh, i i was a hero of the left.
as far as >> the thing, if you drove a tesla,
it showed that you were environmentally
conscious
and you were on the right side.
>> uh, yeah.
um, yeah.
i mean, i'm still the same human.
i didn't like have a brain transplant between, you know, since
in like three years ago, you know.
um >> well, that's my favorite bumper sticker that people put on teslas now.
i bought this before elon went crazy.
>> i took a picture of one the other day.
oh, you found somebody.
oh, yeah.
i've seen i've seen three or four of them.
people that have these bumper stickers on their car that says, "i bought this before
elon went crazy."
because when people were
vandalizing teslas
>> yeah.
um the most there was organized campaign
to
literally burn down teslas
and and
we had one of our dealers
got shot up with a gun like they fired bullets into the in the tesla dealership.
they're burning down cars.
it was crazy.
um
so
but the bumper sticker should read
there should be an an addendum to the bumper sticker.
it's like i bought this car before elon turned crazy.
actually, now i realize he's not crazy and i've seen the light.
>> that'll take some time.
that'll take some time.
people don't want to admit that they've been tricked.
>> yeah.
i mean, there's
that old saying where it's like it's really easy to fool somebody, but it's
almost impossible to convince someone that they were fooled.
>> yeah.
it's much easier to fool them than to convince them they've been fooled.
people cling to their ideas.
>> yes.
they especially if they've like publicly stated these things, they get very embarrassed of being foolish.
>> yeah.
people most time they double down.
>> um and >> and they find echo chambers.
>> yeah.
yeah.
but but there's you know the thing is that like
i you know i've seen more and more people
who were convinced of
the sort of work ideology
um see the light.
>> yeah.
so, not everyone, but it's more and more
um are seeing the light.
um
and and
it tends to happen like when when
something happens
that really,
you know, directly
affects you,
>> right?
>> um you like there was a friend of mine who
was living in in the san francisco bay area and
um that tried to trans his his his daughter
um
did like to the point where the
the school like sent sent the police to his house
to take his daughter away from him.
now, now that's going to radicalize you.
well, that's going to break that's going to shake you out of your blue structure.
um,
now i know, >> so it was an activist at the school
that was trying to do this.
>> yeah, the school and the and the state of california
conspired to turn his daughter against him and make her take
lifealtering drugs that would have sterilized her
um and irreversible.
>> and how old was she?
i think 14, something like that.
um,
so
and
but he he
managed to talk
the police
out of taking
his
daughter
away from
him
that
day.
um, and that that night he got on a plane to texas.
>> wow.
um and
like you know a year after just being in in a in a school in like
greater austin area
um she she went she came went back to normal
meaning like
it it wasn't real >> right
>> um well people are being much more open to that now.
i mean wall street journal
yesterday
had that opinion piece that
this whole trans thing there's a lot of evidence is a social contagion.
absolutely.
>> and colin wright wrote that.
and then he's getting death threats now, of course.
and on blue sky, there's people talking about exterminating
him, which is one thing that you are allowed to say on blue sky, apparently.
>> you're you're allowed to say horrible things about people saying
possibly truthful things about this whole social contagion.
cuz that's what when you get
nine kids that are in a friend group and they all decide to turn trans together.
yeah.
>> something's wrong.
that's not statistically >> yeah.
like here's the like you can convince kids to do anything.
you can convince kids to be a suicide bomber, >> right?
>> so
>> which is why they do
with in in some countries why they choose children to do that.
>> yes.
you can train kids to be suicide bombers.
and if you can train kids to be su suicide
bombers,
you can convince them of anything.
>> yeah.
especially with enough positive enforcement and cultural enforcement and you
>> and and the idea that that that's not the case.
>> kids kids are kids are
um malleable.
the minds of youth are easily corrupted.
>> you're also seeing a lot of push back from
gay and lesbian people that are saying like, "hey, if someone
>> stop including me
in yeah.
exactly.
the lgbt,
you know, it's like, wait a second,
why are we being included all the time in this situation?" >> exactly.
exactly.
when especially when,
you know, like my friend tim dylan's talked about this is like it's really homophobic
because you're taking these gay kids and you're you're telling them like, "hey, you're not gay.
you're actually a girl." >> yes.
and
you know, hey, hey, go make it so that you can never have an orgasm
again and you'll be happy.
>> like, >> yeah, >> [ __ ]
permanent mutilation, permanent castration of of kids is like i i think
>> i i
we should look look at at
anyone who permanently castrates a kid as like right up there with ysef mangler.
>> yeah.
>> i mean, they're they're mutilating children.
yeah.
and
um it's thought of as being kind.
and the thing is, would you rather have a live daughter or a dead son?
>> that's that's the that's the line they use.
>> yeah.
which is not supported by any data.
>> no.
in fact, the the probability of suicide increases.
>> right.
>> this is important maybe for the audience to know.
the probability of suicide increases if you're transit kid, not decreases.
>> by some accounts, it triples.
so that that is an evil lie.
and it's a lie that is supposedly compassionate.
imagine you've twisted reality to the point where
confusing a child that's not even legally allowed to get a [ __ ] tattoo.
>> yeah.
>> right.
because you think that you could make a mistake with a tattoo,
a totally removable
thing, >> right?
>> if i wanted to, tomorrow
i can go to a doctor and they could laser
off every tattoo
that i have on me.
>> right.
>> okay.
no harm, no foul.
yeah.
but you get sterilized like that's it forever.
forever.
yes, >> they'll castrate you.
you no longer have testicles.
you have no penis.
you have a hole where your penis used to be.
>> yes.
>> and this is compassionate
and this is preventing you from >> actually, a lot of kids die
in in with the these sex change operations.
they die the number of deaths on the operating table.
people don't hear about those.
a lot of kids because
that we it's we don't really actually have the technology to make this work.
so a bunch of the times the kids just die in the sex change operations.
>> jesus christ.
>> yeah.
it's it's demented which it should be viewed as like you know
um like like evil nazi doctor stuff basically.
that's why it was like real nazi not the [ __ ] fake nazi stuff.
>> crazy that even pushing back against something that seems like fundamentally logically
very easy to argue the old twitter would ban you forever.
uh, yes.
>> that's how crazy a social contagion can get when it completely defies logic, victimizes children,
does something that makes no sense, does not supported by data,
all connected to this ideology
that trans is good.
we got to save trans kids, protect trans kids.
>> yeah.
and what i want to emphasize is that
the the save trans kids thing is a lie.
um if if you if you if you castrate
kids and trans them the probability of suicide increases.
it does not decrease.
it substantially increases.
um the the the studies have done that i've seen the the risk of suicide
triples if you trans kids.
so you're not saving them, you're killing them.
moreover, during the sex change operation,
there are many deaths that occur during the sex change operation.
>> jesus christ.
it's just crazy that this is a real issue.
>> yeah, it it's a nightmare fever dream
and and people are finally waking up from it.
now, when you started getting into the doge stuff and started finding
how much money
is being shuffled around and moved around to nos's
and how much money is involved and
just totally untraceable funds like
this is again something like two years plus ago you weren't aware of it all.
>> no, i was aware of it.
um i just didn't realize how how the how big it was.
just just just how much waste and forward there is in the government is truly vast.
um in fact the government didn't even know
um and nor did they care.
>> that's crazy.
>> yeah.
>> and >> i mean just like some of the very basic stuff that doge did
um will have lasting effects.
um and some of these things like they're so elementary you can't believe it.
so,
um the the doge team got the
um you know the the mo most of the main payments computers
um to require the the congressional appropriation code.
so, when a payment is made, you have to actually enter the congressional appropriation card.
that used to be optional and and often would be just left blank.
so, the money would just go out, but it wasn't even tied to a congressional appropriation.
then they also dutch team also made the comment field for the payment mandatory.
so you have to say something.
we're not saying that what what is said like you can say anything.
you you your cat could run across the keyboard.
you could go querty asdf
but you have to say something above nothing
because what we found was that there were
tens of billions maybe hundreds of billions of dollars that were zombie payments.
so there like somebody had approved a payment uh somebody in the government approved a payment
um and some recurring payment and
um they retired or died or changed jobs and no one turned the money off.
so the money would just keep going out
and and it's a pretty rare >> go where >> to to the
a company or an individual
um and it's a pretty rare company or individual who will complain
that they're getting money that they should not get
and and a bunch of the money was just going to the
were transfer payments to the states.
>> so these are automatic payments there no accounting for them at all.
>> i imagine like like there's an automatic debit of your credit card
>> um and you don't you never look at the statement, >> right?
um, so it's just money going out.
uh, that's why i call them zombie payments.
um,
that there might have been they might have been legitimate at one point,
but the person who approved that recurring payment um,
changed jobs, died, retired, or whatever, and no one ever turned the money off.
and my guess is that's probably
at least a hundred billion a year, maybe 200. and going where >> uh to to
i mean there there are millions of these payments.
so so it's i mean >> millions
>> uh yes >> millions of payments that are going to who knows where.
>> yes.
in a bunch of cases there are fraud rings that operate
professional fraud rings that operate to exploit the system.
um they figure out some security hole in the system and they just do professional fraud.
um and
um
you know that's where we found for example people who were
you know 300 years old in the social security administration database.
now, i thought that this was
a mistake of not registering their deaths that people were born
like a long time ago and it had defaulted to like a certain number
and so that after time
those people were still in the system.
it was just an error of the the way the accounting was done.
>> yeah.
so,
um that's not true.
so, there's or or at least one of two things must be true.
um
the there's a there's a typo
or or some mistake in the computer
or it's fraudulent,
but we don't have any 300-year-old vampires living in america.
>> allegedly.
um
and
or or and we don't have people in some cases who's who are receiving payments
who are born in the future.
>> born in the future.
>> really?
>> yes.
there the people receiving payments whose birth date
um was like
in 2100
and something >> okay so there's >> like next century >> is there a task
>> we know we know that one of two things must be true
um that that that either there's a mistake in the computer or it's fraud
but if you have someone's birth date that's either in the future or
where they are older than the oldest living american because the oldest living american is 114
years old so if they're more than 114
years
um there is either a mistake
and someone should should call them and say
i i think we have your birthday
wrong because it says you were born in 17 you know 8086
um and
um you know that was before you know
um you know before there was really an america you know it was it was like
you know kind of early you know we're still fighting england type of thing
you it's like
this person either needs to be in the guinness book of world records
or or they're not alive,
>> but still at the end of the day, money is going towards
that
account that's connected to this person that is either non-existent
or >> so
like like yeah.
so there was like i think
um something like i don't know 20 million
people in the social security administration database that could not possibly be alive
um if their birth date is
like
based on their birth date they could not possibly be alive.
>> and then to be clear 20 million people that were receiving funds
>> uh a bunch of
most of them were not receiving funds.
some of them were receiving funds.
most were not receiving funds.
but so let me tell you how the scam works.
it's it's a bank shot.
so
the
social security administration database is used as the source of truth by all the other databases
that the government uses.
so even if they stop the payments on the social security administration database
like unemployment insurance,
small business administration,
student loans
all check
the social security administration database to say is this is this a legitimate alived person?
and
and if the
social security database
will say yes, this person is still alive
even though they're 200
years old.
um but forgets to mention that they're 200 years old, it just says it just returns
when when the computer is queries, it says yes, this person is alive.
and so then they're able to exploit the entire rest of the government ecosystem.
so fake then you get fake student loans, then you get fake unemployment
insurance,
then you get
fake medical payments.
and this doesn't have to be tied to an individual
where where there's an address where you can check on this person.
>> no,
if you did do if just did any check at all, you would stop this.
>> so, so, so that's that that that's so so
>> and how much money do you think is >> any check like anything at all
that would stop would stop the forward like any effort at all?
>> um, yeah.
>> so, there's multiple layers.
the social security number verifies that this is a real person
and then the other systems check
every other government payment
and every other government payment system for everything for like small small business administration
student loans
medicaid medicare
every other government payment of which there are many there there actually
hundreds of government payment
systems
can all be exploited so long as social security database says this person is alive
that's the nature of the scam it's a bank shot.
so then
the then the rebuttal
from the dems
is like, oh
well
the
vast
majority
of the people who are marked
as alive in the social security
administration
weren't receiving social security administration
payments.
that is true.
what they forgot to mention is they're getting fraudulent payments from every other government program.
and that's why the the dms were so opposed
to turning off to to declaring someone dead who was dead
because it would stop the entire other
all the other fraud from happening.
and so, but all this is it trackable like all this other fraud.
>> if they wanted to, they could chase it all down.
>> yeah.
it's not even hard.
>> and yet they're opposing chasing it all down.
>> they're opposing chasing it all down because it would it turns off the money magnet
for the illegals.
wow.
because it's very logical to to like like i'm saying the most common sense things possible.
if someone's got
a birthday in social security that is an impossible birthday,
meaning they are
older than the oldest living american or were born in the future,
then you should call them and say, "excuse me, we seem to have your birthday wrong."
because it says that you're 200 years old.
that's all you need to do.
um,
and
>> and then you would remove them from the social security
database
and make that number no longer available
for all those other government
payments.
>> exactly.
>> wow.
and how much money are we talking?
>> it's hund hundreds of billions of dollars.
>> and this is all traceable.
like you could hunt all
>> like you don't need to be sherlock holmes here is what i'm saying.
>> well, this we don't need to call sherlock holmes for this one.
is this part of >> you just need to call the person
>> and and say, "excuse me, we either we we seem to have the
like we we we
must have your birthday wrong because it says you're 200 years old or were born
in the future.
um so could you tell us what your birthday is?
that's all you need to do.
it's it's that simple."
but the all these other government payments
that are available that are connected to this social security number,
it seems like
if you just chased that all down, yeah.
>> you would find the widespread fraud.
you would find where it's going.
>> yes.
the but the root of the problem is the social security administration database because
um the social security number in the united states is used as a deacto
national id number.
you know that's why like the bank always asks for your social
like the you know any financial institution will ask for your social security number.
>> this is it sounds so insane that this isn't chased down.
i mean
>> i agree >> that i mean i mean that in and of itself is
that's such mishandling.
>> yes.
no it's mind-blowing.
um, so yeah, it's crazy.
>> well, you were very reluctant
last time you were here to talk about the extent
of some of the fraud
because you're like,
they could kill me because this is kind of >> oh, what?
yeah.
what i was saying is that
um the like if you create if like i like like to be pragmatic and realistic
um you actually can't manage to zero fraud.
you can manage to low fraud number but not to zero fraud.
if you manage to zero fraud,
um
you you you're going to push so many people over the edge who are receiving fraudulent
payments that the number of inbound
homicidal maniacs will be
really hard to overcome.
so i i'm i'm
actually taking
i think quite a reasonable position which is that we should simply
reduce the amount of fraud
which i think is
not an extremist position.
um, and we should aspire to, you know, have less fraud over time.
um, not that we should be ultra draconian and eliminate every last scrap of fraud.
um,
which
i guess would be nice to have, but
but
like we don't even
need to go that
extreme.
i'm i'm saying we should just stop the blatant large scale super obvious fraud.
>> i think that's a reasonable position.
>> it's a very reasonable position.
yeah.
and so
what was the most shocking
push back that you got when you started implementing
doge?
when you started investigating into where money was going?
well,
um i guess it this was i should have anticipated this, but
um
while most of the fraudulent government payments to especially to the nos's
go to the democrats,
most of it like i don't know for argument sake let's say 80%
maybe 90%.
um
um 10 to 20% of it does go to republicans.
and so when we'd turn off funding to a fraudulent ngo,
we'd get complaints from
whatever the 10% of republicans who were receiving the money
and and they would, you know, they would very loudly complain.
um
because the the
honest answer is the republicans are are partly they're receiving some of the fraud, too.
they're getting a big >> jesus.
yeah, it's i want to be clear.
it's it's not like the republican party is some
um ultra pure paragon of virtue here.
>> no.
>> okay.
um >> well, you see that with the congressional insider training.
it's across the board.
>> yeah.
>> it's left and right.
>> i mean, the whole uni party criticism has some validity to it.
you know, there's so
um and it's it's
like if you turn off fraudulent payments, it's not like
like i say, it's not like 100% of those payments were going to democrats.
a a small percentage were also going to republicans.
those republicans complained very loudly.
um and
um
you know and and that's that's
so
there was a lot of push back on the republican
side for when we started cutting some of these these funds
and i tried telling them like well you know
90% of the money is going to your opponents
but they still if they even if they're getting 10% of >> they want their peace.
>> yeah.
they want their peace >> and they've been getting that peace for a long time.
>> yes.
did you see >> this is why like you know politics is like >> it's dirty
business.
>> yeah.
i mean that's like saying if like
you know if if you if you like sausages
and respect the law do not watch either of them being being made
>> yeah.
wow.
well that's not even true because i've made sausage before.
>> yeah.
yeah.
it's actually like it's not that big a deal.
fat and spices and casing, >> run it through the machine.
not that big a deal.
>> yeah.
um but yeah, i mean i i think the stuff i'm saying here is not
like like
if if you stand back and think about it for a second like
oh yeah
that that makes sense, you know.
>> um the it's it's not like
um it's not like one political party is going to be
um you know pure devil or pure angel.
there's,
you know, i think there's there's there there's there's much more corruption on the democrat
side, but it's not there's not
there's still some corruption on the republican side.
>> how did it happen that the majority of the corruption
wound up being on the democrat side?
>> well, because the the the transfer payments, especially to illegals,
um, uh, are very much on the democrat side.
>> that so that's the root of it all is the illegal situation.
>> yes.
i mean, there's >> or a focal point.
it's it's also like it's it's
um it's it would also be accurate to say that while
obviously
not everyone who is a democrat is a criminal,
almost everyone who is a criminal is a democrat
because because the democrats are the soft crime party.
so if you're a criminal, who you going to vote for?
>> right.
right.
>> the soft crime party.
did you think you were going to be able to get more done than you were?
>> um, we did get a lot done, >> right?
>> um, and doge is still still still happening, by the way.
um, this the the doge is still underway.
there are still there are still
um there's still waste and fraud being being cut by by the doge team.
so, it hasn't stopped.
um, the >> it's less publicized.
>> it's less publicized.
um, and they don't have like a clear person to attack anymore.
>> well, it seems like
they basically they they applied immense pressure to me to just to stop it.
so then i'm like the best thing for me is to just, you know,
cut out of this.
in any case, as a special government employee, i could only be there for like
120 days anyway, something like that.
so whatever the law says.
so i i could i i i was necessarily
could only be there for 4 months
as a special government employee.
so,
um
um but
yeah, i mean i mean you turn off the money spigot to to fraudsters,
they get very upset
to say the least.
um and
um
but my like my death threat level went
ballistic, you know, was like a like a rocket going to orbit.
um yeah.
um,
so
but now that now now now that i'm not in dc that that that
i guess they don't really have a person to attack
anymore.
>> um, >> well the rhetoric about you has calmed down significantly.
>> yeah, >> it was disturbing.
it was disturbing to watch.
it was like this is crazy.
>> and to watch these politicians
engage in it and all these people just like framing you as this monster.
i was like this is so weird.
like this is what happens when you uncover fraud.
>> yes.
>> the whole machine turns on you.
and if it wasn't for a person like you who owns a platform
and has an enormous amount of money,
like
could have destroyed you.
>> yeah.
>> and that was the goal.
>> the goal was to destroy me.
absolutely.
>> because you were getting in the way >> of this amazing graft.
>> the the this gigantic fraud machine.
>> yeah.
>> um like i think i think doge team's on done a lot of good work.
um, you know, and in in terms of
fraud and waste prevented,
my guess is it's,
you know, probably
on the order of two or 300 billion a year.
so, it's pretty good.
>> what do you think could have been done if you just had like full
reign
and
total
cooperation?
how much do you think you could have saved?
>> i mean, what level of of power are we assuming here?
>> godlike.
>> oh, yeah.
i probably cut the federal budget in half and get more done.
that is so crazy.
it is so crazy that get more done and federal budget widespread.
it's that widespread.
>> well, i mean a whole bunch of government departments simply shouldn't exist in my opinion.
um they they
um you know
um >> like examples
>> well the department of ed department of education which was created
recently
like under
jimmy carter
um the our educational results have gone downhill ever since it was created.
so if you if you create a department
and the result of creating that department
is a massive decline in educational
results
and it's department of education, you're better off not having it
because we're literally
we were did better before there was one
than after >> when you let the states run it.
>> yes.
>> yeah.
>> because at least the states can compete with one another.
um so but the problem is like here like cutting department education.
our kids need education.
yeah, they do.
but but this is a new department that didn't even exist
um you know until late the late 70s.
um and ever since that department was created, the results educational results have declined.
and so why would you have an institution continue that has made education worse?
it doesn't make sense.
>> they killed it though, right?
no, there still unfortunately >> but they were trying to kill it.
>> it has been substantially reduced.
>> okay.
>> um >> what other organizations what other departments?
>> well, i mean i'm a small government guy.
so
um
you know when when the
you know when the country was created we just we we just had the
department of state, department of war
um you know and and sort of the sort of the department of justice.
we had an attorney general and treasury department.
um i don't know why you need more than that.
>> so what other departments specifically do you think are just completely ineffective?
>> well, i mean here it's like a question.
it's a sort of philosophical question of how much government do you think there should be?
>> right.
>> um in my opinion, there should be the least amount of government.
i've heard the most bizarre argument against this
is that you're cutting jobs and you're gonna leave people jobless.
and i'm like, but their jobs are useless.
>> yeah.
paying people to do nothing doesn't make sense.
um like there's a like a a great
um a story about like milton friedman who is awesome.
um
what like generally whatever milton friedman said is you know people should should do that thing.
i'm not sure if it's apocryphal or not, but
um like like someone complained to him like
he he he observed i think people that were like
um digging ditches with you know with with
um shovels and
um and he said well
like allegedly freeman said, "well, i think i think you should use you know
um excavating equipment instead of shovels and you could get it done with far fewer people."
and then and then someone said, "but then we're going to lose a lot of jobs."
well, in that then freedom
says, "well, in that case, why don't you have them use teaspoons?"
just just dig ditches with teaspoons.
think of all the jobs you'll create.
>> i mean,
it's [ __ ] basically,
you just want people to work on on things that are that are productive.
you want people to work on on building things
um on building you know providing products and services that people find valuable
um like you know making food
um being you know being a farmer or
a plumber or electrician
or
just anyone who's a builder or providing
useful services.
um and
um that's what you want people to be doing.
um not fake government jobs that that that don't add any value or may subtract value.
um
there's also like you know
to illustrate the absurdity of also how is the e how is the economy measured
like the the way economists measure the economy is is is nonsensical
because they'll
measure
any job
no matter
even if that job is a dumb job that has no point
and is even counterproductive.
so like, so the like the joke is like there's two economists
going on a hike in the woods
and they come across
a pile of [ __ ]
and one economist says to the other, "i'll pay you $100 to eat eat that shit."
the economist eats the [ __ ] gets the $100. they they keep walking.
then the other econ then come across another pile of [ __ ]
and and the
the other economist says, "now i'll pay you $100
to eat the pile of shit."
say pays the so pays the other economist
$100 pile
of [ __ ]
then they then then then
the way said they said like wait a second
um we both just ate a pile of [ __ ]
and we're no and and and and we're we're no we we we we
don't have any more extra money like like
we both you just gave the $100 back to me
and we both ate a pile of [ __ ] this doesn't make any sense.
and they said, "no, no, but think of the economy
because that's $200
of that in the economy
that that
basically
measure eating eating [ __ ] would count
as a as as a as a job.
this is this is this is to illustrate the absurdity of of of economics.
>> one of the things you said when
things should not count as a job."
one of the things you said when you stepped away is that you're kind of done
and that
it's unfixable.
that
um well or under its current form the way people are approaching it
you can you can make it directionally better but ultimately you can't fully fix the system.
um,
so, uh,
i i i
like
like like like
it it it is it is it would be accurate to say that even
like like unless you could go like super draconian
like you know gangghaskhan
level on on on
cutting waste waste and fraud which you can't really do in a democratic country
um an aspirationally democratic country then
um there's no way to solve the the the debt crisis.
so, we got we got national debt that's just insane
where the debt payments the interest payments on the debt exceed
our entire military budget.
i mean, that's one that was one of the wakeup calls for me.
i was like, "wait a second.
the interest on a national debt is bigger than the entire the entire military budget
um and growing.
um this is crazy.
um so
um
so so even if you implement all these savings,
you're only delaying the day of reckoning for when america becomes goes bankrupt.
so unless you go full genghaskhan,
um which you can't really do.
so
um
so i came to the conclusion that
the only way that the only way to get us out of
the debt crisis and to prevent america from going bankrupt is ai and robotics.
so, like we need to grow the economy
um at
at a at a at a rate
that allows us to u to pay off our debt.
um and
um i i i guess people just generally don't appreciate the degree to which
um you know this the the government overspending is is a problem.
um but even like the social security website, this is under the biden administration.
on the website, it would say like we based on on current demographic trends and
um
you and and and
how much money social security is bringing in versus how many social security recipients
there are because we have an aging population.
relatively speaking, the average age is is increasing.
social security will not be able to ma u maintain its full payments
u i think in by 2032
there.
okay.
so they will social security will have to stop will start reducing the
the amount of money that that's been paid people
um in in about seven years.
>> and so the only way to fix that robotics manufacturing
raise gdp >> you've got to basically massively increase the
um
economic output which is and the only way to do that is ai ai and robotics.
so, so basically we're going bankrupt without ai and robotics with
even with a bunch of savings
um the savings the savings like reducing
waste and forward can
give us a longer runway but it cannot ultimately pay off our national debt.
>> so what do you think the solution is to
the jobs that are going to be lost because of ai and robotics?
the jobs due to automation the jobs due to
no longer do we need human beings to do these jobs because ai is doing them.
do you think it's going to be some sort of a universal basic income thing?
do you think there's
going to be some other kind of solution
that has to be implemented
because a lot of people are going to be out of work, right?
um i think there will be
um actually a high demand for jobs but not necessarily the same jobs.
so i mean this is actually this process has been happening
um throughout
um modern history.
um i mean there used to be like like doing calculations
um ma manually with with like a pencil and paper.
it used to be a job.
so they used to have like buildings
full of people called computers
where the the banks would like
all you do all day is is is
um you do calculations because they didn't have computers.
they didn't they didn't have digital didn't have digital computers that that people >> yeah.
well,
it was just people would just like add and subtract
stuff on piece of paper and and and
that that would be how banks would do you know financial processing
>> and you'd have to literally
go over their equations
to make sure the books are balanced.
>> yeah.
and most times it's just simple math like you know the
like in a world before computers how did you calculate how did you you do transactions?
you had to do them by hand.
um so then when computers were introduced the job of doing
um you know bank calculations no longer existed.
um so people had to go do something else.
um
and that's what's going to happen that what's that's what is happening at an accelerated rate
um due to ai and and then robotics.
that's the issue though, right?
the accelerated rate because it's going to be >> it's the accelerator.
it's it's it's just happening.
like i said, like ai is the supersonic tsunami.
>> so that's what i call it, supersonic tsunami.
um
so >> it's like what other jobs
will be available that aren't available now
because of ai?
>> um well ai
um will is is really still digital.
ultimately,
um ai can improve the productivity of of humans who who
um
build things with their hands or do things with their hands like plum,
you know, literally
welding, electrical work, plumbing, anything that's that's physically moving atoms.
um like cooking food or
um you know farming or or like like anything that's that's physical
those jobs will exist for a much longer time.
but anything that is digital
which is like just someone at a computer doing something,
ai is going to take over those jobs like lightning,
>> coding, anything along those lines.
yeah, >> it's going to take over those jobs like lightning.
um
just like it just like
digital computers took over the job of people doing manual calculations
but but much faster.
>> so what happens to all those people?
like what kind of numbers are we talking about?
you're going to lose most drivers, right?
commercial drivers.
you're going to have automated vehicles, ai controlled
systems, just like there's certain ports in china, i think in singapore, where everything's completely automated.
>> yeah.
mostly.
yeah.
>> yeah.
so, you're going to lose a lot of those jobs.
long shoreman jobs, trucking, commercial drivers.
>> yeah.
yeah.
i mean, we actually do have a shortage of of truck drivers, but there's there's actually
um >> well, that's why california has hired so many illegals to do it.
have you seen those numbers?
>> yeah.
um
i mean, the problem is like when you when people
don't know how to drive a semi-truck,
which is actually a hard thing to do,
then they they crash and kill people.
>> yeah.
>> um a friend of mine's wife was killed by an an illegal driving a truck
and she was just out biking.
um and
there was an illegal he didn't know how to drive the truck or so or something.
i mean and he he ran ran her over.
um so i mean like thing is like for something
like you you can't you can't let people drive
you know
sort of an 80,000lb semi
um if if they don't know how to do it.
but in california, they're just letting people do it
>> because they need people to do it.
>> well, they also need they want the votes and that kind of thing.
but
um but but yeah, like cars are
um cars are going to be autonomous.
um,
but there there's just so many desk
desk jobs where where really people what people are doing is they're processing
email
um or they're answering the phone.
um,
and and just anything that is
that that isn't moving atoms like anything that is not physically like doing physical work
that will obviously be the first thing
those jobs will be and are being eliminated by by ai at a very rapid pace.
um
um and ultimately i working will be optional because you'll have robots plus ai
um and we'll have in a benign scenario universal high income not just universal basic income
universal high income meaning anyone can have any products or services that they want.
so you >> but but there will be a lot of
trauma and disruption along the way.
>> so you anticipate a basic income
from that that the economy will boost to such an extent that a high income
would be available to almost everybody.
so we'd essentially eliminate poverty >> um in the benign scenario.
yes.
so like the way >> there's multiple scenarios.
>> there are multiple scenarios.
there's a lot of ways this movie can end.
um,
like the reason i'm so concerned about ai safety is that like one of the possibilities
is the terminator
scenario.
it's not it's not 0%.
um, so
um, that's why it's like i'm like really
banging the drum on ai needs to be maximally truth seeeking.
like don't
make i don't force ai
to believe a lie
like that the for example the founding fathers were
actually a group of diverse women or that misgendering
is worse than nuclear
war
because you if if that's the case and then you get the robots
and the ai
becomes
omnipotent
it can enforce that outcome
and then
then like
unless you're a diverse woman you're you're out of the picture so we're we're toast
so that's >> um or you might wake up as a diverse woman one day
has adjusted the picture and and we are now >> everyone's a diverse woman.
so that would be that's the the worst possible situation.
so
what would be the steps that we would have to
take in order to implement the benign
solution
where it's universal high income like best case scenario this is the path forward to
universal high income for essentially every single citizen
that the
the economy
gets boosted by ai and robotics
to such an extent
that no one ever has to work again
and what about meaning for those people which is which gets really weird.
>> yeah.
>> i don't know how to answer the question about meaning.
um >> that's an individual problem, right?
but it's going to be an individual problem for millions of people.
>> yeah.
well, i i mean i i i guess i've like for fought against
saying like,
you know, i
you know, i've been i've
been a voice saying like, "hey,
we need to slow down
ai.
we need to slow down all these things.
um, and and we need to, you know, not not have a crazy ai race.
i've been saying that for a long time, for 20 20 plus years.
um,
but but then i, you know, i came to realize that,
um, really there's two choices here.
either be a spectator or a or a participant.
and if i'm a, if i'm a spectator, i can't really influence the direction of ai.
but if i'm a participant, i can try to influence the direction of ai and
have a maximally truth seeeking
ai with with
good values
that
loves humanity.
and that's what we're trying to create with grock at xai.
and
um you know, the research is i think bearing this out.
like i said, the when they when they compared like
how do ais value the weight of a human life?
um
grock was the only one the only one of the ais that weighted human life equally.
um and and didn't and didn't say like a white guy's
worth 120th of a of a of a a black woman's life.
literally, that's what they they calculation they came up with.
>> so, i'm like, this is i'm like, this is very alarming.
we should we got to watch this stuff.
>> so, this is one of the things that has to happen
in
order to reach this benign
solution.
>> yeah.
we we we i i just keep >> best movie ending.
yeah.
um, you you want a a curious truth seeeking ai.
um, and i think a curious truth seeeking ai will want to foster humanity.
uh, because we're much more interesting than
um a bunch of rocks.
like you say, like like i i love mars, you know, but
but mars is kind of boring.
like it's just a bunch of red rocks.
um, it does some cool stuff.
it's got a tall mountain.
it's got, you know, it's got the biggest re the biggest ravine and the tallest mountain.
um, but there's no there's no there's no animals or plants or
and and there's no people.
um,
and uh, you know, so
humanity is just much more interesting
if you're a curious truth seeeking ai than
not humanity.
it's just much more interesting.
um,
i mean like as as humans, we could go for example and and eliminate all chimps.
if we said if we put our minds to it, we could say
we could go out and we could
annihilate
all chimps
and all gorillas, but but we don't.
um there has been encroachment on their environment, but we we actually try to preserve
the the chimp and gorilla habitats.
um and
um and i think in a good scenario, ai would do the same with with humans.
it would actually foster human civilization and care about human happiness.
so this is
um this is the thing to to try to achieve i think.
um,
>> but what is the what does the landscape look like if you have grock
competing with open ai, competing with all these different like
how does it work?
like
what
what if you have ais that have been captured by ideologies
that are side by side competing with grock?
like
how do we
so this is one of the reasons why you felt like it's important to
not just be
a
an observer but participate
and then have grock be more successful and more potent
than these other applications.
yes, as long as there's at least one ai that is maximally truth seeeking, curious, and
um you know, and for example, weighs all you know, human lives equally
um does not favor one race or gender, then
um
then then that that that
and and people are able to look at look at,
you know, grock at xai
and compare that and say, "wait a second,
why are all these other ais
being basically
sexist and racist?"
um
um and
then then that that causes some embarrassment for
the the
other ais
and then they they they they
fix they you know they they improve
they tend to improve just in the in the same way that
um acquiring twitter and allowing the truth to be told and and not suppressing the truth
um forced the other social media companies to be more truthful
um by in in the same way having
um gro be a maximally truth seeeking, curious ai is will force the other ai companies
to
um be also be more truth seeeking and fair.
>> and the funniest thing is even though like the socialists and the marxists are
in opposition to a lot of your ideas,
but if this gets implemented and you really can achieve
universal high income,
that's the greatest
socialist solution of all time.
like literally no one will have to work.
correct.
um
like i said so so
there is a benign
scenario
here which
i think probably
people will be happy with
if if as long as we we achieve it which is
sustainable
abundance.
um which is if if
um
if everyone can have every like like like
if if you ask people like what's the future that you want
>> um and
i think
a
future where
we
haven't destroyed
nature
like you can still
we have the national parks
we have the the amazon
rainforest
still still there we haven't paved we haven't paved the paved the rainforest
like the natural beauty is still there but but people have
nonetheless everyone has abundance everyone has excellent medical care.
everyone has whatever goods and services they want.
>> and we just >> it kind of sounds like heaven.
>> it sounds like it is like the ideal socialist utopia.
and
this idea that the only thing you should be doing with your time
is working in order to pay your bills and feed yourself
sounds kind of archaic
considering the kind of technology that's at play.
>> yeah.
>> like a world where that's not your concern at all anymore.
everybody has money for food.
everybody has abundance.
everybody has electronics in their home.
everybody essentially has a high income.
now you can kind of do whatever you want.
and your day can now be exploring your interests doing things that you actually enjoy doing.
your purpose just has to shift.
instead of,
you know, i'm a hard worker
and
this is what i do and that's how i
that's how i define
myself.
no.
now you can [ __ ] golf all day, you know?
you can whatever it is that you enjoy doing can now be your main pursuit.
>> yeah.
>> well, that sounds crazy good.
>> yeah, that's that's that's the benign scenario that we should be.
>> the best ending to the movie is actually pretty good.
>> yes.
um like i think there's there is still this question of meaning
um of like making sure people don't lose meaning you know like
um so hopefully they can find meaning in ways that are
not that that's not derived from their work
>> and purpose
purpose for things that you you know find things that you do that you enjoy
but there's a lot of people that are independently
wealthy that spend most of their time doing something they enjoy
>> right
>> and that could be the majority of people
>> pretty much everyone.
>> but we'd have to rewire how people approach life.
>> mhm.
>> which seems to be like acceptable because you're not asking them to be enslaved.
you're exactly asking them the opposite.
like no longer be burdened by financial worries.
now go do what you like.
>> yes.
>> go [ __ ] test pizza.
>> do whatever you want.
>> um pretty much.
um, so that's that's that's the that's the that's probably the best case outcome.
>> that sounds like the best case outcome period for the future.
if you're looking at like how much people have struggled just to feed themselves
all throughout history,
food, shelter, safety,
if all of that stuff
can be fixed, like how much would you solve a lot of the crime
if there was a universal high income?
just think of that.
like how much of crime is financially motivated?
you know, the greater percentage of people that are committing crimes live in poor, disenfranchised neighborhoods.
>> so if there's no such thing anymore,
if you really can achieve universal
high income,
>> yeah, >> that this is it sounds like a utopian.
>> yes.
um i think some people may commit crime because they like committing crime.
it just some some amount of that is they just >> wild people out there.
>> yeah.
yeah.
um >> and obviously they've become 40 years old living a life like that.
now all of a sudden universal high income is not going to completely stop their instincts.
>> yeah.
um
i mean i guess if you want to have like like
say read a science fiction
book
or
some books that that
are probably
an accurate or or the the least inaccurate version of the future.
i'd say i' i'd recommend
um the ian banks books called the the culture books.
it's not actually a series.
it's a it's like ai sci-fi books about the future.
they're generally called the culture books.
yen banks culture books.
it's worth reading those.
>> when did he write these?
>> he started writing them in the 70s.
um and i think he
um
the last one i think he was
i think it was written just like around i don't know maybe 2010 or something.
i'm not sure exactly.
>> yeah.
yeah.
>> scottish author ian banks from 87 to 2012. >> yeah.
interesting.
>> but he but like he wrote the the like his first book, consider flever.
like he started writing that in the 70s.
>> these books are incredible, by the way.
>> oh, >> incredible books.
>> 4.6 stars on amazon.
>> interesting.
>> so, um, >> so this gives me hope.
>> uh, yeah.
yeah.
>> this is the first time i've ever thought about it this way.
>> yeah.
well, i mean,
if like
i often ask people, "what is the future that you want?"
and they have to think about it for a second cuz, you know, they're usually
tied up in whatever the daily struggles are.
but, but you say, "what is the future that you want?" um,
and um, and generally sustainable abundance,
what do these folks say, "what about a future where there's sustainable
abundance?" like, "oh, yeah, that's a pretty good future."
um so
um
you know if if and and and that that future is attainable with ai and robotics
but but
you know it's it's like i said there's not every path is a good path.
there's this it's but i think if we if we push it in the direction of
um
maximally truth seeeking and curious
then i think ai will want to take to to take care of humanity and foster
foster humanity
um because we're interesting
um
and if it hasn't been programmed to think that like all straight white male should die,
which gemini was basically programmed to do at least at first.
um, you know, they seem to have fixed it.
i hope they fixed it.
>> but don't you think culturally
like, oh, we're getting away from that mindset and that people realize
how preposterous that all is.
>> we are getting away from it.
um,
so, uh, we are getting at least it knows the ai mostly knows to hide things.
but like
like i said, there is that
i i think i
still have that as or
i had that as my like
pinned
post on x
which was like hey wait a second guys we still have
every ai except grock is saying that
basically straight white male should die
um and this is a problem and we should fix it.
um and you know but simply me saying that is like tends to generally result in
um you know them like that is kind of bad.
maybe we should just we should not have all straight white males die.
um i think they say also all all straight asian males should also die as well.
like that like
like generally
the generally the ai and the and the media
which which back back in the day the
the media was
um you know racist against black people and sexist against women back in the day.
now now it is racist against white people and asians and sexist against men.
>> um so they just like being racist and sexist.
i think they just want to change the target.
um so but but really they just shouldn't be racist and sexist at all.
um you know >> ideally that would be nice.
>> that would be nice.
um,
and it's kind of crazy that we were kind of moving
in that general
direction
till around
>> and then everything
ramped up online and and everybody was accused of being a nazi and everybody was transphobic
and racist and sexist and homophobic and everything got exaggerated
to the point where it was this wild witch hunt
where everyone was a colomo
looking for racism.
>> yeah.
yeah.
totally.
um, well well but but but they they were openly anti-white and often openly anti-asian.
and then this new sentiment that you cannot be racist against white people
cuz racism is
power
and influence.
>> okay.
no, it's not.
>> yeah.
racism is is is racism in the absolute.
um so
um you know and there just needs to be consistency.
so if it's okay to have let's say
black or asian or indian or pride, it should be okay to have white pride, too.
>> yeah.
um, so that's just a that's just a consistency question.
um,
so,
uh, you know, um,
if it if it's okay to be proud of one religion,
it should be okay to be proud of, i i guess all religions provided
they're
that they're they're not like
oppressive.
>> yeah.
or or or don't like as long as part of that religion is not like exterminating
people who are not in that religion type, >> right?
um so it's really just like a consistency bias.
um or or just like ensuring consistency to eliminate bias.
um so if it is possible to be racist against
one race, it is possible to be racist against any race.
um so >> of course logically.
>> yes.
>> yeah.
and arguing against that is that's when you know you're catching
>> it's a it's a logical inconsistency
that makes ais go insane
>> and people >> and people go insane.
yes.
>> um >> but like the the like like you can't simultaneously say
um that there's the systemic racist oppression but also that races don't exist
that that race race is a social construct.
like which is it?
you know,
um you also can't say that
um
you know, anyone who steps foot in america is is automatically an american
except for the people that originally came here.
>> exactly.
exactly.
except for the colonizers.
>> yeah.
except for the evil colonizers who came here, >> right?
>> so which one is it?
like
if you
if as soon as you step foot put in a place you are that
you are
just as american as everyone else
>> then
um that would have appi if you apply that consistently then the original
white settlers were also just as american as everyone else.
>> yeah.
logically.
>> logically.
um,
one more thing that i have to talk to you about before you leave is
the rescuing of the people from the space station,
which, uh, we talked about,
you were planning it the last time you were here.
>> um,
the f the
lack of coverage
that that got in mainstream media
was one of the most shocking things that >> yeah, they totally memoryhold
that thing.
>> wild.
yes.
because if it wasn't, >> it's like it didn't exist.
those people would be dead.
they'd be stuck up there.
>> well, they'd they'd probably still be alive, but they'd they'd be having bone density issues
because of prolonged exposure to zero gravity.
>> well, they were already up there for like 8 months, right?
>> yeah.
>> which is an insanely long time.
it takes forever to recover just from that.
>> yeah.
they're only supposed to be at the space station for 3 to 6 months maximum.
so,
>> one of the things you told me that was so crazy
was that you could have gotten them sooner,
but >> yeah.
but for political reasons, they didn't they did not want
spacex or me to be associated with
um returning the astronauts before the election.
>> that is so wild that that's a fact.
>> first of all, that >> we absolutely could have done it.
um so,
>> but even though you did do it and you did it after the election,
it received almost no media coverage anyway.
>> yes.
because
nothing good can the the the media which is essentially
a far left prop the legacy mainstream media is a far-lft propaganda machine.
um and so anything
any story that is positive about someone who is not
part of the sort of far-left tribe will not
get any coverage.
>> i i could save a busload of orphans and and
it it wouldn't get a single news story.
>> yeah, it's it really is nuts.
it it was nuts to watch because
even though it was discussed
on podcasts
and it was discussed on x and it was discussed on social media,
it's still it was a blip in the news cycle.
it was very quick.
it was in and out and because it was a su successful launch
and
you did rescue
those people,
nobody
got hurt and
there was nothing really to
there was no blood
to
talk about,
>> right?
>> just [ __ ] in and out.
>> yeah.
yeah.
absolutely.
well, and and as as you saw firsthand with the starship launch, like starship is
um you know by
you know at least by some some would consider it to be like the most amazing
you know engineering project that's happening on earth right now
outside of like you know maybe ai
or ai and robotics but but certainly in terms of a spectacle
to see it is
the most spectacular thing that is happening on earth right now
is the starship launch program
which anyone can go and see if they just go to south texas
and just they can just rent a hotel room low cost in
south padre island or in brownsville
and you can see the launch
and you can drive right right past the factory because it's on a public highway.
um but it gets no coverage
or what coverage it does get was like a rocket blew up coverage, >> right?
yeah.
oh, he's a [ __ ] the rocket blew up.
like the the the the star sasha program is vastly
>> vastly more capable than the entire apollo moon moon program.
vastly more capable.
this is a spaceship that is designed to make life multilanetary to carry
millions of people across the heavens to another planet.
the the apollo program
could could only send astronauts to the moon for a few hours at a time.
like they could send two the entire apollo program could only send astronauts
to visit the moon very briefly
and then for a few hours and then depart.
the starship program could create an entire lunar base with a million people.
you understand the mag the magnitudes are >> there's different very different magnitudes here.
>> so what was the political >> basically no no coverage of it.
>> yeah.
but what i wanted to ask you is like what so what were the conversations
leading up to the rescue like when you were like i can get them out
way quicker.
>> yeah.
um
um well i mean
you know i raised this a few times but it was
the i was told instructions came from the white house that
you know that that there should be no attempt to rescue before the election.
>> that should be illegal.
>> that that that
really should be
a horrendous
miscarriage of justice for those poor people that were stuck on that.
>> um yeah it it is it is crazy.
um, >> have you ever talked to those folks afterwards?
did you have conversations with them?
>> yeah.
i mean, they they're they're
not going to say anything
political
to,
you know, they're not
like they're never going to
>> say thank you.
>> yeah.
yeah.
>> well, that's nice.
>> yeah.
yeah.
absolutely.
so, um, >> but the instructions came down from the white house.
he cannot rescue them because politically this is a a bad hand of cards.
>> i mean, they didn't say because politically it's a bad hand of cards.
they they just said
they were they were not interested in any rescue operation before the election.
>> yeah.
so >> what did that feel like?
>> i wasn't surprised.
>> but it's crazy.
>> yeah,
>> because biden could have authorized it
and they could have said the the biden administration
is helping bring those people back, throw you a little funding,
give you some money to do it.
the biden administration, they funded these people being returned.
>> uh yeah, the biden administration was not exactly my best friend,
>> especially especially after i
um you know,
you know, helped trump get elected get get elected, which i mean some people
>> still think, you know, trump is like the the devil basically.
um, and i mean i think i think trump actually
he's not he's is not perfect, but but
he's not evil.
trump is not evil.
i spent a lot of time with with him and he's
>> i mean he's a product of his time.
but he is not he's not evil.
>> um >> no, i don't think he's evil either.
but if you look at the media coverage,
>> the media the media treason like he's super evil.
it's pretty shocking if you look at the amount of negative coverage.
like one of the things that i looked at the other day was mainstream
media coverage
of
you,
trump,
a bunch of different public figures and then >> 96% negative or something crazy
>> and then mum donnie,
which is like 95% positive,
>> right?
um i mean manny is is is is a charismatic swindler.
um
i i
i mean you got to hand it to him like
he
does he can light up a stage.
um but he has just been a swindler his entire life.
um and
um you know and and i think he what he's i mean he's likely to win.
he's likely to be mayor of new york new york city.
>> very likely.
>> yeah.
very likely.
i think poly market has it at what what is the >> 94%?
>> yeah, that sounds pretty likely.
>> that's crazy.
>> like i'm not sure who the 6% are, you know.
>> um so, so yeah.
so that's
um >> what's also like who's on the other side?
the [ __ ] guardian angel guy with the beret
and andrew cuomo who doesn't even have a party.
like they the democrats don't even want him.
so you have those two options.
um, >> and then you have the young kids who are like finally socialism.
>> yeah, they they don't know what they're talking about obviously.
um,
so
you know, like you just look at this say how many boats
come from cuba to florida
and how many but and how many boats because you know there's like a constant
i always think like how many boats are accumulating
on the shores of florida coming from from cuba,
>> right?
um
there's a there's a whole bunch of free boats that
you could
if you want to
go
take them back to cuba.
it's pretty close.
>> yeah.
>> but for some reason people don't do that.
>> why why why why are the boats only coming in this direction?
>> um >> well who is who are the most rabid capitalists in america?
the [ __ ] cubans.
>> absolutely.
>> yeah.
they're like we've seen how this story goes.
>> we do not want exactly.
>> [ __ ] off.
cubans in miami, they don't want to hear any [ __ ]
they don't want to hear any socialism [ __ ] they're like, "no, no, no.
we know what this actually is.
this isn't just some [ __ ] dream." >> yeah.
it's extreme government oppression.
um >> that's how it's a nightmare.
and like the like an obvious way you can tell which
which ideology is is the bad one is
um who has to which ideology
is building a wall to keep people in
and prevent them from escaping.
>> right?
>> like so east berlin built the built the wall not west berlin, >> right?
>> they built the wall because people were trying to escape from communism to west berlin.
but there wasn't anyone going from west berlin to east berlin, >> right?
>> that's why the communists had to build a wall to keep people from escaping.
>> they're going to have to build a wall around new york city.
>> yeah.
that so, so that an ideology is problematic.
if that ideology has to build a wall to keep people in with machine guns,
>> yes.
>> and shoot you if you try to leave.
also, there's no examples of it being successful ever.
we're only working out for people.
no, there's examples of a bunch of lies like north korea.
give this land to the state.
we'll be in control of food.
no one goes hungry.
no.
now, no one can grow food but the government
and we'll tell you exactly what you eat and you eat very little.
>> right.
>> yeah.
what?
when you say mom donny's
a swindler,
i know he has a bunch of fake accents that he used to use.
yeah.
>> and you know, but what else has he done that makes him a swindler?
um
well i i guess if you say
what i mean
if if say if you say to any audience whatever that audience wants to hear
instead of what
instead of
having a consistent
message
i would say that that is a swindly
thing to do.
um and yeah
um
yeah but but he is he is charismatic.
um >> yeah good-looking guy.
smart, charismatic.
>> yeah.
>> great on a microphone.
yeah.
and and what the young people want to see, >> you know, like this
ethnic guy who's young and vibrant and has all these socialist ideas align with them and
you know, they're
bunch of broke dorks
just out of college
like, "yay,
let's vote for this." and there's a lot of them
and they're they're activated.
they're motivated.
>> um, >> i guess we'll we'll we'll see what happens here.
>> what do you think happens if he wins?
um because like 1% of new york city is responsible for 50% of their tax base,
which is kind of nuts.
50% of the tax revenue comes from 1% of the population.
and those are the people that you're scaring off.
you know, you lose one half of 1%.
yeah, i mean hopefully this the stuff he's he said, you know, about
government takeovers of of like that all the stores should be the government basically.
um >> i don't think he said that.
i think he said government they want to do government supermarkets, some state-run or cityrun supermarkets.
>> yeah.
um well, it just the the government is the dmv at scale.
so
um you have to say like do you want the dmv running your supermarket?
>> right.
um, was your last experience at the dmv amazing?
uh, and if it wasn't, you probably don't want the government doing things.
>> imagine if they were responsible for getting you blueberries.
>> yeah.
it's not going to be good.
i mean, the
the the thing about,
you know, communism
is is it was it was all bread lines and bad shoes.
um, you know, do do you want ugly shoes and bread lines?
because that's what communism gets you.
it's going to be interesting to see what happens and whether or not
they snap out of it and overcorrect
and go to some rudy giuliani type character next
cuz it's been a long time since there was any sort of republican leader there.
and we we live in the in the most interesting of times
um because we we face the you know simultaneously face civilizational decline
um and incredible pro prosperity
um and these these timelines are interwoven
um so
um if mani's policies are put into place especially at scale
um it it would be a catastrophic
decline in living standards not just for the rich but for everyone.
um as as has been the case with with every
um every for every every socialist experiment
um or every yeah.
so
um but but then as you pointed out the the irony is that like
um the ultimate capitalist thing of ai and robotics enabling
prosperity for all and an abundance of goods and services actually the capitalist
implementation of ai and robotics assuming it goes down the the good path
is is actually what results in the communist utopia.
because fate is fate is an irony maximizer, >> right?
and and an actual socialism of maximum abundance of highincome people.
>> universal high income.
>> yeah.
>> like the the problem with communism is is universal low income.
um it's it's not that everyone gets elevated, it's that everyone gets oppressed except for
a very small minority of of politicians
who live a lives of luxury.
that's what's happening every time it's been done.
>> yeah.
um so
um but then the
the actual communist utopia if everyone gets anything they want will be will be
if if will be achieved
if it is achieved it will be achieved via c capitalism
>> because fate is an irony maximizer.
>> i feel like we should probably end it on that.
is there anything else?
the most ironic outcome is the most likely, especially if entertaining.
>> well, everything has been entertaining.
as long as the bad things aren't happening to you, it's quite fascinating.
and it's never a boring moment.
>> yes.
so there's i do have a theory of why
um like if if if simulation theory is true then
um it is actually very likely that
um the most interesting outcome is the is the most likely
because only the simulations that are interesting will continue.
the simulators will stop any simulations that are boring because they're they're not interesting.
>> but here's the question about the simulation theory.
is the simulation run by anyone or is >> it would be run by someone?
>> it would be run by >> some some >> some force
>> the pro the program like
in in this reality that we live in, we we run simulations
all the time.
like so when we try to figure out if the rocket's gonna make it, we run
um thousands sometimes millions of simulations just to figure out which which
path is the good path for the rocket
and and where can it go wrong, where can it fail.
um
but we when we do these
i say at this point millions of simulations of of what can happen with the rocket
um we ignore the ones that are where everything goes right
um because we we we
just care about the
we have we have to address the situations
where it goes wrong.
um so
um
so so basically in in in and and for for ai simulations
as well like like all these things we
we keep the simulations going that are the most interesting to us.
um so if simulation theory is accurate if if it is true who knows
um then the
the
the simulators
will will only
they will continue to run the simulations
that are most interesting there.
therefore from a darwinian perspective
um the only surviving simulations will be the interest the most interesting ones.
and in order to
um avoid getting turned off
the only
rule is you must keep it interesting
or you will if or you will
because the boring simulations will be terminated.
>> are you still completely convinced that this is a simulation?
>> i didn't say i was completely convinced.
>> well, you said it's like the odds of it not being are in the billions.
but i guess it's not completely cuz you're saying there's a chance.
>> what are the odds that we're in base reality?
um well given that given that that we're able to create increasingly sophisticated simulations.
so if you think of say
video games and how video games have gone from very simple
video games like pong
with
you know two rectangles
and a square
to video games today being
um photorealistic
with millions of people playing simultaneously and all of that has occurred in our lifetime.
so if that trend continues, uh, video games will be indistinguishable from reality.
the fidelity of the game will be such that you you don't know if that
what you're seeing is a real video or a fake video.
um, and like ai generated videos at this point, you
like
you can sometimes tell it's an ai generated video, but often you cannot tell and
soon you will not really just not be able to tell.
so
um if if that's happening in our direct observation
then and and we're create we'll create millions if not billions of photorealistic simulations of reality
then what are the odds that we're in base reality or versus someone else's simulation?
well, isn't it just possible that the simulation is inevitable,
but that we are in base reality building towards a simulation?
we're making simulations.
um, so
um we're making simulations.
we make like you can just think of like photorealistic video games as as being simulations.
>> mh.
um,
and
especially as you apply
ai in these video games, the the characters in the video games will be incredibly
interesting to talk to.
they won't just have a limited dialogue tree
where if you go to like the the crossbow
merchant
or like and you you try to talk about any subject except buying a crossbow,
they just want to talk about selling you a crossbow.
um, but with with with ai based non-player characters,
you can you'll be able to have an elaborate conversation with no dialogue tree.
well, that might be the solution for meaning for people.
just lock in and you could be a [ __ ] vampire and whatever.
you live in avatar land.
you could do it.
you could do whatever you want.
i mean, you don't have to think about money or food.
>> ready player one.
>> yeah.
literally.
yeah.
but with higher living standards.
>> yeah.
>> you don't have to be in a little trailer.
i >> i mean, i think this people do want to have some amount of
struggle or something they want to push against.
um
but but it it could be you know playing a
a sports or playing a game or something.
>> it could be easily playing a game
and especially
playing a game where
you're now no longer worried about like physical attributes
like athletics
like bad joints and hips and stuff like that.
now
it's completely digital
but yet you do have meaning in pursuing this thing that you're doing all day.
whatever the [ __ ] that means.
it's going to be weird.
>> it's going to be interesting.
>> it's gonna be very interesting.
>> um the most the most interesting
>> and and usually ironic outcome is the most likely.
>> all right.
>> that's a good predictor of the future.
>> thank you.
thanks for being here.
really appreciate you.
appreciate your time.
you i know you're a busy man, so
this means a lot you come here to do this.
welcome.
all right.
thank you.
bye, everybody.