the following is a conversation with leonard susskind he's a professor of theoretical physics at stanford university
and founding director of stanford institute of theoretical physics he's
widely regarded as one of the fathers of string theory
and in general is one of the greatest physicists of our time both as a researcher
and an educator this is the artificial intelligence podcast perhaps
you noticed that the people have been speaking with are not just computer scientists
but philosophers mathematicians writers psychologists physicists
and soon other disciplines to me ai is much bigger than deep learning bigger
than computing it is our civilizations journey into understanding
the human mind and creating echoes of it in the machine
if you
enjoy the podcast subscribe on youtube give it five stars and itunes supported on patreon
or simply connect with me on twitter at lex friedman spelled fri d ma a.m. and
now here's my conversation with leonard susskind
you work two more friends with richard fineman house he influenced you changed
you as a physicist
and thinker
what
i saw i think what i saw was
somebody who could do physics in this deeply intuitive way his
style was almost a closed his eyes and visualize the phenomena that he was thinking about
and through visualization
i'll flank the mathematical highly mathematical and very very sophisticated technical
arguments that people would use i think that was also natural to me but i saw
somebody who was actually successful at it who
could do physics in a way that that i regarded as
simpler more direct more intuitive
and while
i don't think he changed my way of thinking i do think he validated it he
made me look at it and say yeah that's something you
can do and get away with practically
even get away with it
so do you find yourself whether you're thinking about quantum mechanics
or black holes or string theory using intuition as a first step
or step throughout using visualization
yeah very much so very much so i tend
not to think about the equations i tend not to think about the symbols i tend to try
to visualize the phenomena themselves
and then
when i get an insight that i think is valid i might
try to convert it to mathematics
but i'm not a math and then a natural mathematician
or i'm good enough at it i'm
good enough at it but i'm not a great mathematician
so for me the way of thinking about physics is first intuitive first
visualization
scribble a few equations maybe
but then try to convert it to mathematics
experiences that other people are better at converting into mathematics
and i am
and yet you've worked very counterintuitive ideas
so
how that's true that's naive is something connor into every their
rewiring your brain in new ways
yeah
quantum mechanics is not intuitive very little of modern physics is intuitive intuitive
or what does intuitive mean it
means the ability to think about it with basic classical physics the physics that that
we evolved with throwing stones
splashing water or whatever it happens to be quantum
physics general relativity quantum field theory are deeply unintuitive in that way but you know after time
and getting familiar with these things you develop new intuitions
i always said you rewire
and
it's to the point
where me
and many of my friends find many my friends
can think more easily quantum-mechanically
than we can classically we've gotten so used to it i mean
yes our neural wiring in our brain is such that we understand rocks
and stones and water and
so i'm sort of evolved evolved
for you do you think it's
possible to create a wiring of neuron
like state devices that more naturally understand
quantum mechanics understand wave function understand these weird things
well i'm
not sure i think many of us have evolved
the ability to think quantum mechanically to some extent
but that doesn't mean you can think like an electron
that doesn't mean an another example forget
for a minute quantum mechanics just
visualizing four dimensional space or five dimensional space or six dimensional space i think we're fundamentally
wired to visualize three dimensions i can't even visualize two dimensions
or one dimension without thinking
about it as embedded in three dimension in space if
i want to visualize a line i think of the line as being aligned
in three dimensions right well
i think of the line as being aligned
on a piece of paper with a piece of paper being in three dimensions i never
seem to be able to in some abstract
and pure way
visualize in my head the one dimension
the two dimension the four dimensions
the five dimensions and i don't think that's ever gonna happen
the reason is i think our neural wiring is just set up for that on
the other hand we do learn ways to think about five
six seven dimensions and we learn ways we learn mathematical
ways and we learn ways to visualize them
but they're different and
so
yeah i think i think we
do rewire ourselves whether we can ever completely rewire
ourselves to be completely comfortable with these concepts i doubt
so
that it's completely natural there was a tour it's completely natural so i'm sure there's some
what you could argue creatures that live in it two-dimensional
space
yeah
and there are
and
um well it's romanticizing
the notion of course we're all living as far as we know in three-dimensional space but how
do you how do those creatures imagine 3d
space well probably the way we imagined 4d by using some mathematics
and some equations
and some some tricks
okay
so jumping back to a fireman just for a second
he had a little bit of an ego
yes
what do you think ego is powerful
or dangerous in science i think
both both both i
think you have to have both arrogance
and humility you
have to have the arrogance to say i can
do this nature is difficult nature
is very very hard i'm smart enough i can do it i can win
the battle with nature on the
other hand i think you also have to have the humility to know that
you're very likely to be wrong on any given occasion everything you're thinking could suddenly change
young people can come along and say things you won't understand
and you'll be lost
and flabbergasted
so
i think it's a combination of both you better recognize that
you're very limited and you better be
able to say to yourself
i'm not so limited
that i can't win this battle with nature it
takes a special kind of person who can
manage both of those i would say and i would say there's echoes of that in
your own work a little bit of ego a little bit of outside
of the box humble thinking i hope
so
so it was their time
where you
complete you felt you looked at yourself and asked am i completely wrong about this
oh yeah
but the whole thing about specific things the whole thing that way which cold thing me
and me
and my ability to do this thing
oh those
kinds of doubts those first of all did you have those kinds of doubts no
i had different kind of doubts i came from a very working-class background
and i was uncomfortable in academia for
oh for a long time
but they weren't doubts about my ability of my
they were just the discomfort
and being in an environment that
my family hadn't participated in
i know nothing about as a young person
i didn't learn that there was such a thing called physics
until i was almost 20 years old
so i
did have certain
kind of doubts but not about my ability i don't
think i was too worried about whether i would succeed or not i
never
i never felt this insecurity am i ever gonna get a job that
veteran never occurred to me that i wouldn't
maybe you could speak a little bit to this sense of what is academia for
because i do feel a bit uncomfortable in it mm-hm
there's
something i can't put quite into words what you have that's not doesn't
if we call it music you
play a different kind of music than a lot of academia
what
how have you joined this orchestra
how
do you think about it i don't
know that i thought about it as much as i just felt it yeah
you know thinking is one thing feeling is another thing i felt like an outsider
until a certain age when i suddenly found myself the ultimate insider in academic physics
and
that
was a sharp transition in the world i wasn't the young man i was probably
50 years old you were never quite it
was a phase transition you were never quite free milk in the middle yeah
that's right i wasn't i always
felt a little bit of an outsider the beginning a lot
and outside earth
my way of thinking was different my approach to mathematics was different
but also
this my social background that i came from was different
now these days half the young people i meet their parents were professors my
that was not my case
so
yeah
but then all of a sudden at
some point i found myself at they're very much the center of maybe
not the only one at the center
but certainly one of the people in the center of a certain kind of physics
and all that put away i mean i went away in a flash
so
maybe maybe a little bit with fineman
but in general
how
do you develop ideas do
you work their ideas alone do you brainstorm with others oh both
both very definitely both
the earth the younger time i spent more time with myself
now
because i'm at stanford because i'm
because i
have a lot of ex students
and i you know people who who are interested in the same thing i am i
spend a good deal of time almost on a daily basis interacting
brainstorming as you said it's
a it's a very important part i spend
less time probably completely self focused
and
the paper and just sitting there staring at it
what are your hopes for quantum computers
so
machines that are based on that have some elements of leverage quantum mechanical ideas
yeah it's not just leveraging quantum mechanical ideas
you can simulate quantum
systems on a classical computer simulate
them means solve the schrodinger equation for them or solve the equations of quantum
mechanics on a computer
on a classical computer but the classical computer is not doing is not
a quantum mechanical system itself of course it is that everything is made of quantum mechanics
but it's not some functioning it's not a functioning as a quantum system it's
just solving equations the quantum computer is truly a quantum system
which is actually doing the things that you're
programming it to do you
want to program a quantum field theory
if you
do it in classical physics that program is not actually
functioning in the computer as a quantum field theory it's just solving some equations
physically
it's not doing the things that that
the quantum system would do the quantum computer is really a quantum mechanical system
which is actually carrying out the quantum operations you can measure it at the end it
intrinsically satisfies the uncertainty principle it is limited
in the same way that quantum systems are limited by uncertainty
and so forth and it really is a quantum system that means that
what you what you're doing when you program something
for quantum system is they're actually building a real
version of the system
the limits of a classical computer classical computers are enormous ly limited when it comes to
the quantum systems enormously limited
because you
probably heard this before but
in order to store the amount of information that's in a quantum state of
400 spins
that's not very many 400 i can put in my path with 400
pennies in my pocket
so we'll be able to simulate
the quantum state of 400
elementary quantum systems qubits
we call him to
do that would take more information
than can possibly be stored in the entire universe if it were packed
so tightly that
you
couldn't pack anymore in right 400
cubits on the other hand if your
quantum computer is composed of four hundred qubits
it can do everything four hundred qubits can do
what kind of space
if you just intuitively
think about the space of algorithms that
that unlocks for us so
there's a whole complexity theory around classical computers measuring
the running time of things and pe
so on what
kind of algorithm is just intuitively do you think it's you
know mocks for us okay
so we know that there are a handful of algorithms
that can seriously be quantum of classical computers
and which can have exponentially
more power and this is a mathematical statement nobody's exhibited this in the laboratory it's
a mathematical statement we know that's true
but it also seems more
and more that the number of such things is very limited only very very special
problems
exhibit that much advantage for a quantum computer
others of standard problems to
my mind as far as i can tell the great power of quantum computers will actually
be to simulate quantum systems if you're
interested in a certain quantum system
and it's too hard to simulate classically
you
simply build a version of the same system
you build a version of it you build a model of it that's actually functioning
as the system you
run it and then
you do the same thing you would do the quantum system you
make measurements on it quantum
measurements on it the advantages you can run it much slower you
could say why bother why not just use the real system and
why not just do experiments on the real system well
real systems are kind of limited you can't change them you can't like them
you can't slow them down so that you can poke into them you
can't modify them an arbitrary kinds of ways to see what would happen if i if
i change the system a little bit
so i think that quantum computers
will be extremely valuable in
in understanding
quantum systems at the lowest of the fundamental laws they're
actually satisfying the same laws as the systems that they're simulating that's right okay
so in the one hand you have things like factoring in factoring is the great
thing of quantum computers factoring large numbers that
doesn't seem that much to do with quantum mechanics right
it seems to be almost a fluke
that a quantum computer can solve the factoring problem in a short time
so though
and those problems seem to be extremely special rare
and it's
not clear to me that there's gonna be a lot of them on
the other hand there are a lot of quantum systems chemistry there's solid-state
physics there's material science there's quantum gravity there's all kinds of quantum of quantum field theory
and some of these are actually turning out to be applied sciences as well as very fundamental sciences
so we
probably will run out of the ability to solve equations for these things you
know solve equations by the standard methods of pencil
and paper and solve the equations by the method of classical computers
and
so
what we'll do is we'll build versions of these systems
run them and run
them under controlled circumstances or
we can change them manipulate them make
measurements on them and find out all the things we want to know
so in finding out the things we want to know about
very small systems right
now the is there something we can also find out about the macro level about
something about it the function
and forgive me of our brain
biological systems the the stuff that's about one meter in size versus much much smaller well
what the only excitement is about among the people that i interact with is understanding
black holes that falls black holes are big things
there are many many degrees of freedom there is another kind of quantum system that is big it's
a large quantum computer
and one of the things we learned is that the physics of large quantum
computers is in some ways similar to the physics of large quantum
black holes and we're using that relationship
now you asked you didn't ask about quantum computers
or systems you didn't ask about black holes you asked about brains
yeah i bought stuff that's in the middle of the - it's different
so
but black holes are there's
something fundamental about black holes it feels to be very different in the brain
yes
and they also function in a very quantum mechanical way right
okay
it is first of all unclear to me but of course it's unclear to me i another
i'm not a a neuroscientist i have
i don't even have very many friends who are neuroscientists i would
like to have more friends who are neuroscientists
i just don't run into them very often
among the few neuroscientists
i've ever talked about about this they are pretty convinced that the brain functions classically
there is not intrinsically a quantum mechanical system
or doesn't
make use of the of the special features entanglement coherent
superposition are they right i don't know i sort of hope that wrong with just because i like
the romantic idea that the brain is a quantum system
and
but i think that i think probably not
the other thing big systems can be composed of lots of little systems
materials the materials are that we work with and so forth are
three large systems
and a large piece of material but they're bagan they're made out of quantum systems
now one of the things that's been happening over the last a good number of years is with
discovering materials
and quantum systems
which function
much more quantum mechanically then
than we imagine topological insulators this kind of thing that kind of thing those are macroscopic systems
but they just superconductors
superconductors i have
a lot of quantum mechanics in them you
can have a large chunk of superconductor
so it's a big decent material on the other hand it's functioning
and its properties depend very very strongly on quantum mechanics and to
analyze them you need the tools of quantum mechanics
if we can go on to black holes mm-hmm
and looking at the universe as a information processing system as a computer as a giant computer
what's the power of thinking of the universe as an information processing system
but what is perhaps its use besides the mathematical use of discussing black holes
and your famous debates
and ideas around that to
human beings
or life in general as information processing systems well all systems are information processing systems
you poke them they change a little bit they evolve all systems
or information processes there's no extra magic to us humans it
certainly feels consciousness intelligence feels like magic sure though where does it emerge from
if we look at information processing
what are the emergent phenomena that come from viewing the world is an information processing system here
is what i think my thoughts are not worth much of this if you ask me about physics
my thoughts may be worth something
yes if you ask me about this i'm not sure my thoughts are worth anything
but as i said earlier i think when we do introspection when we imagine doing introspection
and try to figure out what it is when we do and we're thinking i think
we i think we get it wrong i'm
pretty sure we get it wrong everything i've heard about the way the brain functions is
so counterintuitive
for example you have neurons
which detect the vertical lines you have different neurons
which detect lines at 45 degrees you have different neurons i never
imagined that there were whole circuits
which were devoted to vertical lines in the brain yeah
doesn't seem to we where when my brain works my
brain seems to work put my finger up vertically
or if i put it horizontally or
if i put it this way or that way it
seems to me it's the same the same circuits that are it's not the way it works
the way the brain is compartmentalized
seems to be very very different than
what i would have imagined if i were just doing
psychological introspection
about how things work my conclusion is that we won't get it right that way but
how
will we get it right i think maybe computer scientists
will get it right eventually i
don't think that any ways near it i don't even think they're thinking about it
but by computer eventually we will build machines perhaps
which are complicated enough
and partly engineered partly evolved maybe evolved by machine learning
and so forth this machine learning is very interesting by machine learning will evolve systems
and we may start to discover mechanisms that
that have implications for
how we think and for what what does consciousness thing is all about and
we'll be able to do experiments on them and perhaps answer questions
that we can't possibly answer by by introspection
so that's a really interesting point you've in many cases
if you look even at string theory when
you first think about a system it seems really complicated like the human brain and through
some basic reasoning then
trying to discover a fundamental low-level
behavior of the system you find out that it's actually much simpler you one have
you you know is that generally the process and to do you have that also hope for biological
systems as well for all
the kinds of stuff we're studying at the human
level of course physics always begins by trying to find the simplest version of something an analyzer
yeah
i mean there are lots of examples where physics has taken
very complicated systems analyze them and found simplicity in them for sure i said superconductors
before it's an obvious one a superconductor seems like monstrously complicated
thing with all sorts of crazy electrical properties magnetic properties
and so forth and when
it finally is boiled down through its simplest
elements it's a very simple quantum mechanical phenomenon called spontaneous symmetry breaking and
which we in other context we learned about and we're very familiar with so
yeah i mean
yes we do take complicated things make them simple
but
what we don't want to do is take things which are intrinsically complicated
and fool ourselves into thinking that we can make them simple we
don't want to make i
don't know who said this but we don't want to make them simpler
than they really are right
okay is the brain a thing
which ultimately functions by some simple rules
or is it just complicated in terms of artificial intelligence
nobody really knows
what are the limits of our current approaches you mentioned machine learning
how do we create human level intelligence it
seems that there's a lot of very smart physicists who perhaps oversimplify
the nature of intelligence
and think of it as information processing
and therefore
that it doesn't seem to be any theoretical reason why we can't artificially create a human
level or super human level intelligence in fact the reasoning goes if you create human level intelligence
the same approach you just used to create human level intelligence should
allow you to create superhuman
level intelligence very easily exponentially
so
what do you think that way of thinking that
comes from physicists is all
about i wish i knew but there's a particular reason why i wish i knew
i have a second job i consult
for google ah not for google for google x i am
the senior academic advisor third to
a group of machine learning physicists at
now that sounds crazy because
i know nothing about the subject i know
very little about the subject on the other hand i'm good at giving advice so
i give them advice on things anyway i see these young physicists
who are approaching the machine learning problem
there is a myth there is a real machine learning
problem mainly why does it work as well as it does it
nobody really seems to understand why it is capable of doing the kind of generalizations
that it does and so forth
and
there are three groups of people who have thought
about this there are the engineers the engineers are incredibly smart
but they tend not to think as hard about why the thing is working
as much as they do how to use it obviously they
provided a lot of data and it is they who demonstrated that machine learning
can work much better than you have any right to expect the machine learning
systems are systems that the system is not too different
than the kind of systems if this is a study there's
not all that much difference between quantum
construction of mathematics physically
yes but in the structure the mathematics between a tension
network designed to describe a quantum
system on the one hand and the kind of networks that are used in machine learning
so
they're more
and more i think young
physicists are being drawn to this field of machine learning some very very good ones i work
with a number of very good ones not on machine learning but having lunch on having lunch
yeah
and i can tell you they are super smart they don't seem to be
so
arrogant about their physics backgrounds
that they think they can do things that nobody else can do
but those physics way of thinking i think will add will
i had great value to um will
bring value to the machine learning i believe it will and i think it already has
and
what time scale do you think predicting the future becomes useless in your long experience
and being surprised at new discoveries
sometimes a day sometimes 20 years there are things
which i thought
we were very far from understanding
which
practically in a snap of the fingers
or a blink of the eye suddenly
became understood completely surprising for me
there are other things which i looked at and i said we're
not gonna understand these things for 500 years in particular quantum
gravity the scale for that was 20 years 25 years and
we understand a lot and we don't understand it completely now
by any means but we're i thought
it was 500 years to
make any progress it
turned out to be very very far
from that it turned out to be more like 20 or 25 years from
the time when i thought it was 500 years
so for me can we jump around quantum gravity some basic ideas in physics
what is the dream of string theory mathematically
what is the hope where does it come from what
problems are trying to solve i don't
think the dream of string theory is any different
than the dream of fundamental
theoretical physics altogether understanding
a unified theory of everything i
i don't like thinking of string theory as a subject unto itself with
people called string theorists who are the practitioners of this thing called string theory i much
prefer to think of them as theoretical physicists
trying to answer deep fundamental questions about nature in particular gravity in particular gravity
and it's connection with quantum mechanics
and who at the present time find string theory a useful tool rather
than saying there's a subject
called string theorists i don't like being referred to as a string theorists
yes but as a tool is it useful to think about our
nature in multiple dimensions the strings vibrating i believe it is useful
i'll tell you what the main use of it has been up till now well
has had a number of main uses originally
string theory was invented then i know there i was there i was right
at the spot where it was being invented
literally
and it was being invented to understand
hey groans hey drones are sub-nuclear particles protons neutrons mesons
and
at
that time the late 60s early seventies it
was clear from experiment that these particles call hydrants had could vibrate could rotate could
do all the things that a little closed
string can do and
it was
and is a valid
and correct theory of these hydrants it's been experimentally tested
and that is a done deal it had
a second life as a theory of gravity the same basic
mathematics except on a very very much smaller distance scale
the objects of gravitation are nineteen
orders of magnitude smaller than a proton but
the same mathematics turned up the same mathematics turned up what
has been its value its value is that
it's mathematically rigorous in many ways and enabled us to to
find to find mathematical structures
which have both quantum mechanics
and gravity with rigor we
can test out ideas we
can test out ideas we can't test them in the laboratory that
nineteen orders of magnitude too small
or things that were interested in but we can test them out mathematically
and analyze their internal consistency by
now
forty years ago thirty five years ago so forth people
very very much questioned the consistency between gravity
and quantum mechanics stephen hawking was very famous for it rightly
so
now nobody questions that consistency anymore they don't because we have mathematically precise string theories
which contain both gravity
and quantum mechanics in a consistent way
so it's provided that
um that certainty that quantum mechanics
and gravity can coexist that's
not a small thing that's
a very huge thing it's a huge thing einstein be proud einstein
he might be appalled i don't know i'm like a very much yeah
he would certainly be struck by it yeah i think
that maybe at this time its biggest contribution to physics in illustrating almost definitively that quantum mechanics
and gravity are very closely related and not inconsistent
with each other is there a possibility of something deeper more profound that still is
consistent with string theory but is deeper
that is to be found well
you could ask the same theme of quantum mechanics is there something exactly yeah
yeah i think string theory is just an example of a quantum mechanical system that
contains both gravitation
and in quantum mechanics
so is there something underlying quantum mechanics perhaps something deterministic
so have something deterministic my
friend far out it wolf whose name you may know he's a very famous physicist dutch
not as famous as he should be but the heart
dispels names it's hard to say his name you know it's easy to spelling ' he's only person
i know his name begins with an apostrophe
and he's one of my heroes in physics
and it's a little younger than me but it's nonetheless one of my heroes the tufte believes
that there was some sub
structure to the world
which is classical in character the deterministic in character
which somehow by some mechanism that he has a hard time spelling out emerges
as quantum mechanics i
don't the wavefunction is somehow emergent the wavefunction
and not just the wavefunction
but the whole making the whole thing that goes with quantum mechanics uncertainty
and pango
meant all these things are emergent do
you think quantum mechanics is the bottom of the well as is the right
here i think is here
i think is where you have to be humble here's
where humility comes i don't think anybody should say anything
is the bottom of the well at this time
yes i think we i think we can reasonably say i
can
reasonably say when i look into the well i can't
see past quantum mechanics i don't
see any reason for it to be anything beyond quantum mechanics i
think a tuft is a sperry interesting
and deep questions i don't like his answers well
again let me ask if we look at the deepest nature of reality with whether it's deterministic
or
unobserved is probabilistic
what
does that mean for our human
level of ideas of free will is there any connection whatsoever from
this perception perhaps illusion of free will that we have and the fundamental
nature of reality the only thing i can say is i am i am
puzzled by that as much as you are the illusion of it the illusion of consciousness
the illusion of free will the illusion of self
does that connect to
how can a physical system do that and
and i am as puzzled as anybody there's echoes of it in the observer effect
yeah
so do you understand
what it means to be an observer i understand
it at a technical
level an observer is a system with enough degrees of freedom that it can record information and
which can become entangled with the thing that's measuring entanglement is the key when a system
which we call an apparatus
or an observer same thing
interacts with the system that it's observing it
doesn't just look at it it becomes physically entangled with it and it's that entanglement
which we call an observation
or measure
now does that satisfy me personally as an observer hmm
yes
and no i find it very satisfying that we have a mathematical representation of
what it means to observe a system
you are observing stuff right now
yeah the conscious level right is you think there's echoes of that
kind of entanglement in our macro scale yes absolutely for sure we're
entangled with quantum mechanically entangled with everything in this room if we weren't of
and it was just well we wouldn't be observing it
but on the other hand you can ask though i really am
i really comfortable with it and i'm uncomfortable with it in the same way that
i can never get comfortable with five dimensions
my my brain isn't wired for it are you comfortable with four dimensions a little
bit more because i can always imagine the fourth dimension this time so
the arrow of time are you comfortable with that arrow do
you think time is an emergent phenomena
or is it's fundamental to nature
that is a big question in physics right now all the physics that we do or
at least that the people that i am comfortable with talking to my
my friends
yeah my friends no
we all ask the same question that you just asked in space
we have a pretty good idea is emergent
and it emerges out of tan tangle mint and other other things time
always seems to be built into our equations as just
what newton pretty much were for newton
modified a little bit by einstein would have called time
and
and mostly in our equations it is not emergent
time in physics is completely symmetric forward
and bathymetric
so you
don't really need to think about the area of time for most physical phenomena the most microscopic phenomena
no it's
only when the phenomena involves systems
which are big enough for thermal
amyx to become important the entropy to become important for small
subsets a small system entropy is not a good concept
an entropy is something
which which emerges out of large numbers it's a probabilistic idea it's a statistical idea
and it's a thermodynamic idea thermodynamics requires lots
and lots and lots of little sub structures
okay
so it's not until you emerge
at the thermodynamic level that there's an arrow of time do we understand it
yeah
i think i think we understand better than most people think that most
people say they think we understand it yeah i think we understand it it's
just a statistical idea the you mean like second law thermodynamics entropy
and
so on yeah the pack of cards
and you're flinging it in the air and you look
what happens to it yeah
but what's random we understand it doesn't go from random to
simple it goes from simple to random
but do you think it ever breaks down
what i think you can do is in a laboratory setting you can take a system
which is somewhere intermediate between being small
and being large
and make it go backward a thing
which looks like it only
wants to go forward because of statistical mechanical reasons because of the second law you
can very very carefully manipulate it to make it run backward i don't
think you can take an egg humpty dumpty who fell on the floor yeah
and reverse that
but you can in a very controlled situation you can take systems
which appear to be evolving
statistically toward randomness stop
them reverse them and make them go back what's
the intuition behind that
how do how do we do that how do we reverse it a clue
you're saying closed system
yeah pretty much closed system
yes did you just say that time travel is possible no
i didn't say time travel is possible i said
you can make a system go backward in time
and you
don't like it go back you can make it reverse it steps
you can make it reverse its trajectory
yeah
how do we do what's the intuition there does it have is it just a fluke thing
that we can do at a small scale in the lab that doesn't have what
i'm saying is you can do it on a little
bit better than a small scale you
can certainly do it with
a simple small system small
systems don't have any sense of the arrow of time atoms atoms
no
sense of the arrow of time they're completely reversible it's
only when you have you know the second law of thermodynamics is the law of large numbers say
you can break the law because it's
not you can break german
isn't the break it but it's hard it
requires great care the bigger
the system is the more to care the more the harder it is you
have to overcome what's called chaos
and that's hard and it
requires more and more precision
for 10 particles you
might be able to do it with a with
some effort 400 particles it's really hard for a thousand
or a million particles forget it but not for any fundamental
reason just because it's technologically too hard to
make the system go backward
so
so note no time travel for engineering reasons
oh no
no no what is time travel time travel time
travel to the future that's easy
yes you just close your eyes go to sleep and you wake up in the future yeah
yeah good nap gets you there yeah good map gets you there right
but in reversing the second law of thermal
is a very difficult engineering effort i wouldn't call that time travel
because it gets to me too mixed up with what the science fiction calls time-travel
right this is just the ability to reverse a system
you take the system
and you reverse
the direction of motion of every molecule in it that
input you can do it with one molecule
if you
find a particle moving in a certain direction let's
not say a mama particle a baseball you
stop it dead and then you simply reverse its motion in principle that's not too hard
and it'll go back along its trajectory in
the backward direction just running the program backwards running the program backward
yeah okay
if you have two baseball's colliding well you can do it but you
have to be very very careful to get it just right
now ten baseball's really really tore better yet tend
ten billiard balls on an idealized frictionless billiard table mm-hmm
okay
so you start the balls all in a triangle right
and you're whack them yep depending on the game you're playing you the wacom
where you're really careful but the you're welcome
and they go flying off in all possible directions
okay try to reverse that
try to reverse that imagine
trying to take every billiard ball stopping
it dated sometime at some point
and reversing its motion
so it was going in the opposite direction if you did that with tremendous
care it would reassemble
itself back into the triangle
okay that is a fact
and you can
probably do it with two billiard balls maybe with three billion balls if you're really lucky
but
what happens is as the system gets more and more complicated you have to be more
and more precise not to make the tiniest error because the tiniest errors will get magnified
and you'll simply not be able to do the reversal
so
yeah you could that
but i wouldn't call that time travel
yeah that's something else
but
if you think think of it it
just made me think if we think the unrolling of state that's happening as a program if
we
look at the world so the idea of looking
at the world as a simulation as a computer
but it's not a computer it's just a single program a question arises that might be useful how
how hard is it to have a computer that runs the universe
okay
so
there are mathematical
universes that
we know about one of them is called anti de sitter space
where we
and it's quantum mechanics well i think we could simulate it in a computer
and a quantum computer classical
computer all you can do is solve its equations
you can't make it work like the real system if
we could build a quantum computer or big enough one robust
enough one we could probably
simulate a universe a small version of an anti-de sitter universe
and that the sitter is a kind of cosmology
so
i think we know how to do that the
trouble is the universe that we live in is not the anti-de sitter geometry it's the decent
or geometry and we don't really understand the quantum mechanics at all so
at the present time i would say we wouldn't have the vaguest
idea how to simulate a universe
similar to our own you
know we could ask oh we could we build in the laboratory a small version a
quantum mechanical version the collection of quantum computers entangled
and the couple together which
would reproduce the the phenomena that go on in the universe even on a small scale
yes
if you were anti de sitter space know
if it's the sitter space can you a slightly describe the sitter space and anti-de sitter space
yeah
what are the geometric properties of big
different they differ by a this is the sine of a single constant
called the cosmological constant
one of them is negatively curved the other is positively curved the anti-de sitter space
which is the negatively curved one you
can think of as an isolated
system in a box with reflecting walls you
could think of it as a system of quantum mechanical system isolated in an isolated environment the
sitter space is the one we really live in and that's the one that's exponentially expanding
exponential expansion dark energy whatever you want to call it and we don't understand that mathematically
do
we understand not everybody would agree with me but i don't understand
they would agree with me they definitely would agree with me that i don't understand it
what about their an understanding of the birth the origin no the bing bang so knows
what normally theories there are theories
my favorite is the one called eternal inflation the infinity
can be on both sides
on one of the sides and none of the sides so what my real opinion
okay
infinity on both sides
oh
boy
yeah
yeah that's why is that your favorite because it's the the most just
mind-blowing no
because we want a beginning no why do we want a beginning i
practiced it was the beginning of course and practice it was a beginning
but could it have been a
random fluctuation in an otherwise infinite time maybe in any case the the eternal inflation theory
i think if correctly understood it would be infinite in both directions
how do you think about infinity
oh god
so
okay of course you can think about mathematically
i just finished this i just finished this discussion with my friend sergey brin yes
how do you think about infinity i say well sergey brin is infinitely rich
how do you test that hypothesis
okay
essential good lines all right
yeah
so there's no there's really no way to visualize some of these things like ya
know this is a very good question those physics have any is
does infinity have any place in physics right right
and well i can say is very good question
so
what do you think of the recent first
image of a black hole visualized from the event horizon telescope it
it's an incredible triumph of science in itself the fact that there are black holes
which collide is not a surprise
and they seem to work exactly
the way they're supposed to work will
we learn a great deal from it i don't know i can i i we
might but the kind of things we learn won't really be about black holes
why there are black holes in nature of that particular mass scale
and why they're so common may
tell us something about the structure evolution of structure in the universe
but i don't think it's going to tell us anything new about black holes
but it's a triumph in the sense that you
go back a hundred years and it was a continuous development general
relativity the discovery of black holes ligo
the incredible technology that went into ligo
it is something that
i never would have believed was gonna happen you know 30 40 years ago and
i think it's a magnificent the structure magnificent thing
this evolution of general relativity
ligo high precision ability to measure things on a scale of 10 to the minus 21
so
so you're just astonishing
though we zoom all this just happy for us to this right
picture is it different you know
you've thought a lot about black holes is it how did you visualize them in your mind
and is the picture different than you know lies that no it simply confirmed
you know it's a magnificent triumph to have confirmed confirmed a direct observation
yeah that einstein's theory of gravity at the level of black hole collisions actually works is awesome
and it's really awesome you
know i know some of the people who were involved in that they
just thought married people
yeah
and the idea that they could carry this out i
just don't i'm shocked yeah just
these little homo sapiens
yeah just these little monkeys got together right
and took a picture of slightly advanced lemurs i think
what kind of questions can science not currently answer
but you hope might be able to soon well you you've already addressed them what is consciousness
for example do you think that's within the reach of science i think it's somewhat
within the reach of science but i think that
now i think it's in the hands of the computer scientists
and the neuroscientists
i'm not a physicist perhaps with the helper haps at some point
but i think physicists will try to simplify
it down to something that they can use their methods
and maybe they're not appropriate maybe we
maybe we simply need to do
more machine learning on bigger scales evolve machines machines
not only that learn but volve their own architecture
as a process of learning evolve in architecture
not under our control only partially
under our control but under the control of a machine learning
i'll tell you another thing that i find awesome
you know this google thing that they taught the computers
how to play chess yeah
yeah
okay they taught the computers
how to play chess not by teaching them how to play chess
but just having them play against each other against
each other itself against each other this is a form of evolution these
machines evolved they evolved
and intelligence
they evolved in intelligence without anybody telling them how to do it
and we're not engineered they just played against each other and got better and better and better
that makes me think that machines can evolve intelligence
what
exact kind of intelligence i don't know but in understanding that
better and better maybe we'll get better clues as to what there goes on your
life and intelligence is last question
what kind of questions can science not currently answer
and may never be able to answer yeah
is there an intelligence
out there that's underlies the whole thing you
can call them with the g word if you want i
can say are we a computer simulation with a purpose
is there an agent an intelligent agent that underlies
or is responsible
for the whole thing does
that intelligent agent satisfy
the laws of physics does it satisfy the laws of quantum mechanics is it made of atoms
and molecules yeah there's a lot of questions
and i
don't see this it seems to me a real question it's
an answerable question well it's answerable the questions have to be answerable to be real
some philosophers would say that a question is not a question unless it's answerable
this question doesn't seem to me answerable by any known method
but it seems to me real
there's no better place to end monitor thank you so much for talking about okay
you