- The following is a conversation
with Mark Zuckerberg,
his second time on this podcast.
He's the CEO of Meta
that owns Facebook, Instagram,
and WhatsApp, all services used
by billions of people to connect
with each other.
We talk about his vision for the future
of Meta and the future of AI
in our human world.
This is the Lex Fridman Podcast,
and now, dear friends,
here's Mark Zuckerberg.
So you competed
in your first Jiu-Jitsu tournament,
and me as a fellow
Jiu-Jitsu practitioner and competitor,
I think that's really inspiring,
given all the things you have going on.
So I gotta ask,
what was that experience like?
- Oh, it was fun.
I don't know, yeah,
I mean, well, look,
I'm a pretty competitive person.
- Yeah.
- Doing sports that basically require
your full attention,
I think is really important
to my mental health
and the way I just stay focused
at doing everything I'm doing.
So, I decided to get into martial arts,
and it's awesome.
I got a ton of my friends into it.
We all train together.
We have a mini academy in my garage.
And I guess one of my friends was like,
hey, we should go do a tournament.
I was like, okay, yeah, let's do it,
I'm not gonna shy away
from a challenge like that.
So yeah, but it was awesome,
it was just a lot of fun.
- You weren't scared, there was no fear?
I don't know, I was pretty sure
that I'd do okay.
- I like the confidence.
Well, so for people who don't know,
jiu-jitsu is a martial art
where you're trying
to break your opponent's limbs
or choke them to sleep,
and do so with grace and elegance
and efficiency and all that kind of stuff.
It's a kind of art form, I think,
that you can do for your whole life,
and it's basically a game,
a sport of human chess,
you can think of.
There's a lot of strategy, there's a lot
of sort of interesting human dynamics
of using leverage
And it's kind of incredible
what you could do.
You can do things
a much larger opponent,
and you get to understand the way
the mechanics of the human body works
because of that.
But you certainly can't be distracted.
- No, it's 100% focus.
To compete, I needed to get around
the fact that I didn't want it
to be this big thing,
so I basically just rolled up
with a hat and sunglasses,
and I was wearing a COVID mask.
And I registered under my first
and middle name, so Mark Elliott.
And it wasn't until I actually pulled
all that stuff off right before
I got on the mat
that I think people knew it was me.
So it was pretty low key.
- But you're still a public figure.
- Yeah, I mean, I didn't wanna lose.
- Right, the thing you're partially afraid
of is not just the losing,
but being almost like embarrassed.
It's so raw, the sport, in that like,
it's just you and another human being.
There's a primal aspect there.
- Oh, yeah its perfect.
- For a lot of people, it can be terrifying,
especially the first time
you're doing the competing,
and it wasn't for you.
I see the look of excitement in your face.
It wasn't, no fear.
- I just think part of learning is failing.
The main thing, people who train jiu-jitsu,
it's like you need to not have pride
because I mean all the stuff
that you were talking
about before about, you know,
getting choked or getting, you know,
a joint lock.
It's um, you only get
into a bad situation
once you've already lost right?
And, but obviously
when you're getting started
with something, you're not gonna be
So you just need to be willing
to go with that.
But I think this is like, I don't know,
I mean, maybe I've just been
embarrassed enough times in my life.
Yeah.
I do think
you know, as people grow up,
maybe they don't wanna be embarrassed
or anything.
and they kind of have a sense
of who they are
and what they want to project
and I don't know.
I think maybe to some degree.
You know your ability
to keep doing interesting things
is your willingness to be embarrassed
again and go back to step one
and start as a beginner
and get your **** kicked
and you know look stupid doing things,
and yeah I think so many of the things
that we're doing
whether it's whether it's this.
I mean this is just like a kind
of a physical part of my life,
but but it running the company
it's like we just take on
new adventures and, you know,
all the big things that we're doing
I think of is like 10 plus year missions
that we're on where you think
of as like 10 plus year missions
that we're on where often early on,
people doubt that we're gonna be able
to do it and the initial work
seems kind of silly and our whole ethos
is we don't wanna wait,
to put it out there.
We wanna get it out quickly
and get feedback on it.
And so I don't know, I mean,
there's probably just something
about how I approach things in there.
But I just kind of think
that the moment that you decide
that you're gonna be too embarrassed
to try something new,
then you're not gonna
learn anything anymore.
But like I mentioned, that fear,
that anxiety could be there,
it could creep up every once in a while.
Do you feel that in especially
stressful moments sort of outside
of the judges and that, just at work?
Stressful moments, big decision days,
big decision moments,
how do you deal with that fear?
How do you deal with that anxiety?
The thing that stresses me out the most
is always the people challenges.
You know, I kind of think that,
you know, strategy questions, you know,
I tend to have enough conviction around
the values of what we're trying to do
and what I think matters
and what I want our company to stand
for that those don't really keep me up
at night that much.
it's not that I get everything right,
of course, I don't right I mean make
we make a lot of mistakes,
but I at least
have a pretty strong sense
of where I want us to go on that.
The thing in running a company
for almost 20 years now,
one of the things
is when you have a team that's cohesive,
you can get almost anything done.
And you can run
through super hard challenges,
You can make hard decisions
and push really hard
to do the best work even,
and kind of optimize
something super well.
But when there's that tension, I mean,
that's when things get really tough.
And when I talk to other friends
who run other companies
and things like that,
that I actually spend
on in running this company
is just fostering a pretty tight
core group of people
who are running the company with me.
And that to me is,
is kind of the thing that
both makes it fun, right?
Having, having, you know, friends
and people you've worked with
and new perspectives,
who can who you can go work
on some of these crazy things with.
But to me,
is when when there
are when there's tension, you know,
that's that that weighs on me.
I think the you know,
it's maybe not surprising.
I mean, we're like a very people
focused company and it's the the people
is the part of it that that, you know,
weighs on me the most to make sure
that we get right.
But yeah, that I'd say across everything
that we do is probably the big thing.
So when there's tension
in that inner circle of close folks,
so when you trust those folks
to help you make difficult decisions
about Facebook, WhatsApp, Instagram,
the future of the company
and the metaverse with AI.
How do you build that close-knit group
of folks to make
those difficult decisions?
Is there people that you have
to have critical voices,
very different perspectives
on focusing on the past
versus the future,
all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, I mean, I think for one thing,
it's just spending a lot of time
with whatever the group
is that you wanna be that core group,
grappling with all
of the biggest challenges.
And that requires a fair amount
of openness.
And, you know, so I mean,
a lot of how I run the company is,
you know, it's like every Monday morning
we get our,
it's about the top 30 people together.
And we, and this is a group
that just worked together
for a long period of time.
And I mean, people, people rotate in,
I mean, new people join,
people leave the company,
people go to other roles in the company.
So it's not the the same group
over time.
But then we spend, you know,
a lot of times a couple of hours,
a lot of the time, it's, you know,
can be somewhat unstructured, we like,
I'll come with maybe a few topics
that I that are top of mind for me,
but I'll ask other people
to bring things and people, you know,
raise questions, whether it's okay,
there's an issue happening
in some country.
With with some policy issue,
there's like a new technology
that's developing here.
We're having an issue with this partner.
There's a design trade-off in WhatsApp
between two things that end up
being values that we care about deeply,
and we need to decide
where we want to be on that.
And I just think over time,
by working through a lot of issues
with people and doing it openly,
people develop an intuition
for each other
and a bond and camaraderie.
And to me, developing that is like a lot
of the fun part of running a company,
or doing anything, right?
who are kind of along on the journey
that you're, that you feel like
you're doing it with.
Nothing is ever just
one person doing it.
Are there people that disagree
often within that group?
Oh yeah, it's a fairly combative group.
Okay, so combat is part of it.
So this is making decisions on design,
engineering, policy, everything.
Everything, everything.
Yeah.
I have to ask just back to Jiu-Jitsu
for a little bit,
what's your favorite submission now
that you've been doing it?
What's how do you like to submit
your opponent Mark Zuckerberg?
I'm in well, but first of all,
I Do you prefer no gi or gi jiu-jitsu?
So gi is this outfit you wear
that is Maybe mimics clothing,
so you can choke.
What's like a kimono?
It's like the traditional martial arts
or kimono.
Pajamas.
That you could choke people with, yes.
Well, it's got the lapels.
Yes.
Yeah, so I like jujitsu.
I also really like MMA.
And so I think
no gi more closely approximates MMA.
And I think my style is,
is maybe a little closer
to an MMA style.
So like a lot of jiu jitsu players
are fine being on their back, right.
And obviously having a good guard
is a critical part of jiu jitsu, but,
but in MMA,
you don't want to be on your back,
right?
you're just taking punches
while you're on your back.
So that's no good.
So you like being on top.
My style is I'm probably more pressure
and yeah, and I'd probably
rather be the top player.
But I'm also smaller, right?
I'm not like a heavyweight guy, right?
So from that perspective, I think like,
you know, it's especially because,
you know, if I'm doing a competition,
I'll compete with people
who are my size,
but a lot of my friends are bigger
than me.
So, so back takes probably pretty
important, right?
Because that's where you have
the most leverage advantage, right?
Where, you know, people, you know,
their arms, your arms
are very weak behind you, right?
So, so being able to get to the back
and take that pretty important.
But I don't know,
is to not be too committed
to any single submission.
But that said,
So I always think that chokes
are a somewhat more humane way
to go than joint locks.
Yeah, and it's more about control,
it's less dynamic.
So, you're basically
like a Habib Nurmagomedov
type of fighter.
So let's go, yeah,
I think is like the clean way to go.
Straightforward answer right there.
What advice would you give
to people looking
to start learning jiu-jitsu?
Given how busy you are,
given where you are in life,
that you're able to do this,
you're able to train,
you're able to compete
and get to learn something
from this interesting art.
I just think you have to be willing
to just get beaten up a lot.
Yeah.
I mean, it's, but I mean,
over time, I think that there's a flow
to all these things.
And there's, you know, one of the,
one of, I don't know,
my experiences that I think kind
of transcends, you know,
running a company and the different,
different activities
that I like doing are,
I really believe that like,
if you're going
to accomplish whatever anything,
a lot of it is just being willing
to push through, right,
and having the grit and determination
to, push through difficult situations.
And I think for a lot of it
is just being willing to push through,
right, and having the grit
and determination
that ends up being sort
of a difference maker between the people
who kind of get the most done and not.
I mean, there's all these questions
about like, you know,
how many days people want to work
and things like that.
who like start successful companies
or things like
that are just working extremely hard.
But I think one of the things
by doing this over time or very acutely
with things like Jiu Jitsu
or surfing is you can't push
through everything.
And I think that that's you,
you learn this stuff very acutely.
You run doing sports compared
to running a company because running
a company, the cycle times are so long,
right?
It's like you start a project
and then, you know,
it's like months later or you know,
if you're building hardware,
it could be years later
before you're actually getting feedback
and able to, you know, make the next set
of decisions for the next version
of the thing
f the thing that you're doing.
Whereas one of the things
that I just think is mentally so nice
about these very high
turnaround conditioning sports,
things like that,
is you get feedback very quickly.
Right, it's like, okay,
like I don't counter someone correctly,
you get punched in the face, right?
So not in jiu-jitsu,
you don't get punched in jiu-jitsu,
but in MMA.
There are all these analogies
between all these things
that I think actually hold that are like
important life lessons, right?
It's like, okay, you're surfing a wave,
it's like, you know,
sometimes you're like,
you can't go in the other direction
on it, right?
It's like, there are limits to kind
of what, you know, it's like a foil,
you can pump the foil
and push pretty hard in a bunch
of directions, but like, yeah, you,
you know, it's at some level,
like the momentum
against you is strong enough, you're,
that's not gonna work.
And I do think that that's sort
of a humbling,
but also an important lesson for,
I think people who are running things
or building things, it's like, yeah,
a lot of the game is just being able
to kind of push
and work through complicated things,
but you also need to kind of have enough
of an understanding
of which things you just can't push
through and where the finesse
is more important.
Yeah.
What are your jujitsu life lessons?
Well, I think you did it,
you made it sound so simple
and were so eloquent that it's easy
to miss.
But basically being okay
and accepting the wisdom and the joy in
the getting your ass kicked
in the full range of what that means.
I think that's a big gift,
of the being humbled.
Somehow being humbled,
especially physically,
opens your mind to the full process
of learning, what it means to learn,
which is being willing to suck
at something.
And I think Jiu-Jitsu
just very repetitively,
efficiently humbles you over and over
and over and over
to where you can carry that lessons
to places where you don't get humbled
as much, whether it's research
or running a company or building stuff,
the cycle is longer.
In Jiu-Jitsu, you can just get humbled
in a period of an hour,
over and over and over and over,
especially when you're a beginner,
you'll have a little person,
just somebody much smarter than you,
just kick your ass repeatedly,
definitively, where there's no argument.
Oh yeah.
And then you literally tap,
because if you don't tap,
you're going to die.
So this is an agreement,
you could have killed me just now,
but we're friends,
so we're gonna agree
And that kind of humbling process,
it just does something to your psyche,
to your ego that puts it in
its proper context to realize
that everything in this life
is like a journey from sucking
through a hard process
of improving rigorously day
after day after day after day.
Any kind of success requires hard work.
Yeah, jiu-jitsu,
more than a lot of
because I've done a lot of them,
really teaches you that.
And you made it sound so simple.
Like, I'm okay, you know, it's okay,
it's part of the process,
you just get humble,
get your ass kicked.
I've just failed and been embarrassed
so many times in my life that like,
you know, it's a core competence
at this point.
Well, yes, and there's a deep truth
to that, being able to,
and you said it in the very beginning,
which is, that's the thing
that stops us, especially
as you get older,
especially as you develop expertise
in certain areas,
not being willing to be a beginner
in a new area.
Yeah.
Because that's where the growth happens,
is being willing to be a beginner,
being willing to be embarrassed,
saying something stupid,
doing something stupid.
A lot of us that get good at one thing,
you wanna show that off,
and it sucks being a beginner,
but it's where growth happens.
Well, speaking of which,
let me ask you about AI.
It seems like this year,
for the entirety
of the human civilization,
is an interesting year
for the development
of artificial intelligence.
A lot of interesting stuff is happening.
So, meta is a big part of that.
Meta has developed Lama,
which is a 65 billion parameter model.
There's a lot of interesting questions
I can ask here,
one of which has to do with open source.
But first, can you tell the story
of developing of this model
and making the complicated decision
of how to release it?
Yeah, sure.
I think you're right, first of all,
that in the last year there
have been a bunch of advances on scaling
up these large transformer models.
So there's the language equivalent
of it with large language models,
there's sort
of the image generation equivalent
with these large diffusion models.
Um there's a lot of fundamental research
that's gone into this
and meta has taken the approach
of being quite open and academic
in our development um of of AI.
Part of this is we wanna have
the best people
in the world researching this,
and a lot of the best people wanna know
that they're gonna be able
to share their work.
So that's part of the deal that we have,
is that we can get,
if you're one of the top AI researchers
in the world, you can come here,
you can get access to kind
of industry scale infrastructure.
And part of our ethos is that we want
to share what's invented broadly.
We do that with a lot
of the different AI tools
that we create.
And LLAMA is the language model
that our research team made.
And we did a limited open source release
for it, right,
which was intended for researchers
to be able to use it.
But you know, responsibility
and getting safety right
on these is very important.
So we didn't think that
for the first one,
there were a bunch of questions around
whether we should be
releasing this commercially.
So we kind of punted on that for V1
of Llama
and just released it for research.
Now, obviously,
by releasing it for research, you know,
it's out there,
that they're not supposed
to kind of put
it into commercial releases.
And we're working
on the follow-up models for this
and thinking through
how exactly this should work
for follow-on now that we've had time
to work on a lot more of the safety
and the pieces around that.
But overall, I just kind of think that
it would be good if there were a lot
of different folks who had the ability
to build state-of-the-art
technology here, and not just a small number
of big companies.
To train one of these AI models,
the state-of-the-art models you know,
hundreds of millions of dollars
of infrastructure, right?
So there are not that many organizations
in the world, um,
that can do that
at the biggest scale today.
And now it gets,
it gets more efficient every day.
So, I do think that will be available
to more folks over time,
but I just think
like there's all this innovation out
there that people can create.
And I just think that we'll also learn
a lot by seeing what the whole community
of students and hackers and startups
and different folks build with this.
And that's kind of been
how we've approached this.
And it's also how we've done a lot
of our infrastructure.
And we took our whole data center design
and our server design
and we built this open compute project
where we just made that public
and part of the theory was like,
all right, if we make it
so that more people can use
the server design,
then that'll enable more innovation.
It'll also make
the server design more efficient
and that'll make
our business more efficient too.
So that's worked
and we've just done this with a lot
of our infrastructure.
So for people who don't know,
you did the limited release,
I think in February
of this year of Lama,
and it got quote unquote leaked,
meaning like it escaped
the limited release aspect, but it was,
you know, that's something
you probably anticipated,
given that it's just released
to researchers.
We shared it with researchers.
Right, so it's just trying to make sure
that there's like a slow release.
Yeah.
But from there,
I just would love to get your comment
on what happened next, which is like,
there's a very vibrant
open source community
that just built stuff on top of it.
There's a Llamama CPP,
basically stuff that makes it
more efficient to run
There's combining with reinforcement
learning with human feedback,
so some of the different
interesting fine tuning mechanisms.
There's then also like fine tuning
in a GPT-3 generations.
There's a lot of GPT-4ALL, Alpaca,
Colossal AI, all these kinds of models
just kind of spring up,
like run on top of wood.
Like, what do you think about that?
No, I think it's been
I mean, there's been folks
who are getting it to run
on local devices, right?
So if you're an individual who just,
you know, wants to experiment
with this at home.
You probably don't have a large budget
to get access to a large amount
of cloud compute.
So getting it to run
on your local laptop is pretty good
and pretty relevant.
And then there are things
like Lama CPP re-implemented
it more efficiently.
So,you know,now even when we run our own
versions of it,
we can do it on way less compute
and it's just way more efficient,
save a lot of money for everyone
who uses this.
So that is good.
I do think it's worth calling out that
because this was a relatively
early release, LLAMA isn't quite
as on the frontier as, for example,
the biggest open AI models
or the biggest Google models.
You mentioned that
the largest Lama model that we released
had 65 billion parameters.
No one knows, I guess,
outside of OpenAI,
exactly what the specs are for GPT-4.
But I think the, you know,
my understanding is
it's like 10 times bigger.
And I think Google's Palm model is also,
I think, has about 10 times
as many parameters.
are very efficient, so they perform well
for something
that's around 65 billion parameters.
So for me, that was also part of this,
because there's this whole
debate around, you know,
is it good for everyone in the world
to have access
to the most frontier AI models?
And I think as the AI models
start approaching something
that's like a super human intelligence,
that's a bigger question
that we'll have to grapple with.
But right now, I mean,
these are still very basic tools.
They're powerful in the sense
that a lot of open source software
like databases or web servers can enable
a lot of pretty important things.
Um, but I don't think anyone looks
at the, you know, the current generation
of llama and thinks it's, um, you know,
anywhere near a super intelligent.
So I think that a bunch
of those questions around like, is it,
is it good to kind of get out there?
I think at this stage,
surely you want more researchers working
on it for all the reasons
that open source software has a lot
of advantages and we talked
about efficiency before
but another one is just
open source software tends
to be more secure
because you have more people looking
at it openly and scrutinizing it
and finding holes in it and that makes
it more safe.
So I think at this point it's more
I think it's generally agreed upon
that open source software
is generally more secure and safer
than things that are kind of developed
in a silo where people try
to get through security
through obscurity.
So I think that for the scale
of what we're seeing now with AI,
I think we're more likely to get
to good alignment and good understanding
of kind of what needs
to do to make this work well
by having it be open source.
And that's something
that I think is quite good
to have out there and happening publicly
at this point.
Meta released a lot of models
as open source.
So the Massillon multilingual speech model,
the H5 model.
Yeah, that was neat.
I mean, I'll ask you questions
about those, but the point
is you've open sourced quite a lot.
You've been spearheading
Where's, that's really positive,
inspiring to see from one angle,
from the research angle.
Of course, there's folks
who are really terrified
about the existential threat
of artificial intelligence,
and those folks will say that, you know,
you have to be careful
about the open sourcing step.
But where do you see the future
of open source here as part of meta?
The tension here is,
do you wanna release the magic sauce?
That's one tension.
And the other one is,
do you wanna put a powerful tool
in the hands of bad actors,
even though it probably
has a huge amount
Yeah, I mean, again,
I think for the stage
that we're at in the development of AI,
I don't think anyone looks
and thinks that
this is super intelligence.
And you know, the models
that we're talking about,
the Lama models here are, you know,
generally an order of magnitude smaller
than what OpenAI or Google are doing.
So I think that at least for the stage
that we're in now,
the equities balance strongly
in my view towards
doing this more openly.
I think if you got something
that was closer to super intelligence,
then I think you'd have to discuss
that more and and think through
that a lot more
and we haven't made a decision,
yet as to what we would do
if we were in that position,
but I don't think I think
there's a good chance
that we're pretty far off
from that position.
So, I'm not.
I'm certainly not saying
that the position that we're taking
on this now applies
to every single thing
that we would ever do.
And certainly inside the company,
we probably do more open source work
than most of the
other big tech companies.
But we also
don't open source everything.
A lot of the core kind of app code
for WhatsApp or Instagram or something,
we're not open sourcing that.
It's not like a general enough piece
of software that would be useful
for a lot of people
to do different things.
You know, whereas the software
that we do whether
it's like a an open source server design,
or or basically, you know,
things like memcache right like a good,
you know, it was probably
our earliest project
that that I worked on.
It was probably one of the last things
that I coded and led directly
for the company.
But but basically,
this like caching tool
for quick data retrieval.
These are things
that are just broadly useful across
like anything that you want to build.
And, and I think that some
of the language models
now have that feel I think that some
now have that feel, as well as some
of the other things that we're building,
like the translation tool
that you just referenced.
So text-to-speech and speech-to-text,
you've expanded it
from around 100 languages
to more than 1,100 languages.
Yeah.
the model can identify more
than 4,000 spoken languages,
which is 40 times more
than any known previous technology.
To me, that's really, really,
really exciting in terms
of connecting the world,
breaking down barriers
that language creates.
Yeah, I think being able to translate
between all of these different pieces
in real time,
this has been a kind
of common sci-fi idea
that we'd all have,
whether it's an earbud, or glasses,
or something that can help translate
in real time
between all these different languages.
And that's one that I think technology
is basically delivering now.
So, yeah,
I think that's pretty exciting.
You mentioned the next version of Lama.
What can you say mentioned
the next version of LLAMA,
what can you say
What can you say
about what you're working on
in terms of release,
in terms of the vision for that?
Well, a lot
of what we're doing is taking
the first version,
which was primarily
this research version,
and trying to now build a version
that has all
of the latest state-of-the-art
safety precautions built in
and and we're using some more data
to train it from across our services,
but a lot of the work
that we're doing internally is really
just focused on making sure that this is
as aligned and responsible as possible.
And we're building a lot of our own.
We're talking about
But the main thing that we focus
on building here,
a lot of product experience
and express themselves.
So we're going to have talked
So, you know, we're gonna, I've talked
about a bunch of this stuff,
but you'll have, you know, an assistant
that you can talk to in WhatsApp.
You know, I think,
every creator will,
will have kind of an AI agent
that can kind of act on their behalf
that their fans can talk to.
I want to get to the point
where every small business basically
has an AI agent that people can talk
to for, you know, to do commerce
and customer support
and things like that.
So there can be all
these different things and LLAMA,
or the language model underlying this
is basically going to be the engine
that powers that.
The reason to open source it is that
as we did with the first version
is that it basically it unlocks a lot
of innovation in the ecosystem will make
our products better as well,
and also gives us a lot
of valuable feedback on security
and safety, which is important
for making this good.
But yeah, I mean the work
that we're doing to advance
the infrastructure,
it's basically at this point taking it
beyond a research project
into something which is ready
to be kind of core infrastructure,
not only for our own products,
but you know, hopefully for a lot
of other things out there too.
Do you think the LLAMA
or the language model underlying that
version two will be open sourced.
Do you have internal debate around that,
the pros and cons and so on?
This is, I mean, we were talking
about the debates
that we have internally
and I think the question
is how to do it, right?
I mean, I think we did
the research license for v1
and I think the the big thing
that we're that we're thinking
about is is basically like
what's the what's the right way.
So there was a leak that happened,
I don't know if you can comment
on it for v1.
You know, we released it
as a research project for researchers
to be able to use, but in doing so,
we put it out there.
So, you know, we were very clear
that anyone who uses the code
and the weights doesn't
to put into products.
And we've generally seen people respect
that, right?
It's like
you don't have any reputable companies
that are basically trying to put this
into their commercial products.
But yeah, but by sharing it with,
you know, so many researchers, it's,
you know, it did leave the building.
But what have you learned
from that process that you might be able
to apply to V2
about how to release it safely,
effectively, if you release it?
Yeah, well, I mean,
like I said,
is just around different things
around how do you fine tune models
to make them more aligned and safer?
And you see
all the different data recipes that, um,
you know, you mentioned
a lot of different projects
that are based on this.
I mean, there's one at Berkeley,
there's, you know,
and people have tried a lot
of different things
and we've tried a bunch
of stuff internally.
So kind of
where we're making progress here,
but also we're able to learn from some
of the best ideas in the community.
And I think we want
to just continue pushing that forward.
But I don't have any news to announce
on this, if that's what you're asking.
I mean, this is a
This is a thing
that we're still kind of, you know,
actively working through the right way
to move forward here.
The details of the secret sauce
are still being developed.
I see.
Can you comment on what do you think
of the thing that worked for GPT,
which is the reinforcement learning
with human feedback?
So doing this alignment process,
do you find it interesting?
And as part of that, let me ask,
because I talked to Jan Lekun
before talking to you today,
he asked me to ask,
or suggested that I ask,
do you think LLM fine tuning will need
to be crowdsourced Wikipedia style?
So crowdsourcing.
So this kind of idea of how
to integrate the human
in the fine tuning
of these foundation models.
Yeah, I think
that's a really interesting idea
that I've talked to Jan about a bunch.
And we were talking
about how do you basically train
these models to be as safe and aligned
and responsible as possible
and different groups out there
who are doing development
test different data recipes
and fine tuning.
But this idea that you just mentioned
is that at the end of the day,
instead of having kind
of one group fine tune some stuff
and another group, you know,
produce a different fine tuning recipe
and then us trying to figure out
which one we think works best
to produce the most aligned model.
I do think that it would be nice
if you could get to a point
where you had a Wikipedia style
collaborative way for a kind
of a broader community
to fine tune it as well.
Now there's a lot of challenges in that
both from an infrastructure
and like a community management
and product perspective
about how you do that.
So I haven't worked that out yet.
Um but but as an idea,
I think it's it's quite compelling
and I think it it goes well
with the ethos of open sourcing.
The technology is also finding a way
to have a kind of community driven um
a community driven training of it.
Um but I think that there are a lot
of questions on this in general.,
these questions around
what's the best way
to produce aligned AI models,
it's very much a research area.
And it's one that I think we will need
to make as much progress on
as the kind
of core intelligence capability
of the models themselves.
Well, I just did a conversation
with Jimmy Wales,
the founder of Wikipedia.
And to me, Wikipedia is one
of the greatest websites ever created,
and it's a kind of a miracle
that it works.
And I think it has to do
which is community.
You have a small community of editors
that somehow work together well,
and they handle
very controversial topics
and they handle it with balance
and with grace despite sort
of the attacks that will often happen.
A lot of the time.
I mean, it's not,
it has issues just like
any other human system.
But yes, I mean, the balance is, I mean,
it's amazing what they've been able
to achieve, but it's also not perfect.
And I think that that's,
there's still a lot of challenges.
Right, the more controversial the topic,
the more difficult the journey towards,
quote unquote, truth or knowledge
or wisdom that Wikipedia
tries to capture.
we need to be able
to generate those same things, truth,
knowledge, and wisdom,
and how do you align those models
that they generate something
that is closest to truth.
There's these concerns
about misinformation,
all this kind of stuff
that nobody can define,
and it's just something that we together
as a human species have to define.
Like what is truth?
And how to help
And one of the things language models
do really well is generate
convincing sounding things
that can be completely wrong.
And so how do you align it
to be less wrong?
And part of that is the training
And however you do the alignment stage.
And just like you said,
it's a very new
and a very open research problem.
Yeah, and I think that
there's also a lot of questions
about whether
the current architecture for LLMs,
as you continue scaling it,
what happens?
A lot of what's been exciting
in the last year is that there's clearly
a qualitative breakthrough where,
with some of the GPT models that OpenAI
put out and that others have been able
to do as well,
I think it reached a kind of level
of quality where people like, wow,
this is this feels different,
and like it's going to be able
to be the foundation for building a lot
of awesome products
and experiences and value.
But I think the other realization
that people have is wow,
we just made a breakthrough.
Um, if there are
other breakthroughs quickly,
then I think that there's the sense
that maybe where we're closer
to general intelligence.
But I think that that idea
is predicated on the idea
that I think people believe
that there's still generally a bunch
of additional breakthroughs to make
and that it's um, we just don't know
how long it's going
to take to get there.
And you know one view
that some people have this doesn't tend
to be my view as much
is that simply scaling the current LLMs
and you know getting
to higher parameter count models
by itself will get to something
that is closer
to general intelligence.
But I don't know I tend to think
that there's probably more more
but I don't know,
that there's probably
more fundamental steps that need
to be taken along the way there.
But still, the leaps taken
with this extra alignment step
is quite incredible,
quite surprising to a lot of folks.
And on top of that,
when you start
to have hundreds of millions
of people potentially using a product
that integrates that,
you can start
to see civilization transforming effects
before you achieve super, quote unquote,
super intelligence.
It could be super transformative
without being a super intelligence.
Oh yeah, I mean,
I think that there are gonna be a lot
of amazing products
and value that can be created
with the current level of technology.
To some degree,
I'm excited to work on a lot
of those products
over the next few years
and I think it would just create
a tremendous amount of whiplash
if the number of breakthroughs keeps,
if they're keep on being stacked
breakthroughs because I think
to some degree industry
in the world needs some time
to kind of build these breakthroughs
into the products and experiences
that we all use
But I don't know.
I think that there's
just a like an awesome amount
of stuff to do.
I mean, I think about like all of the,
I don't know, small businesses
or individual entrepreneurs
out there who, um, you know,
now we're going to be able
to get help coding the things
that they need to go build things
or designing the things that they need,
or, um, we'll be able to, you know,
use these models to be able
to do customer support
for the people that they're,
over WhatsApp without having to,
you know, I think
that's just going to be,
I just think that this is all going
to be super exciting.
It's going to create better experiences
for people and just unlock a ton
of innovation and value.
So I don't know if you know,
but you know, what is it,
over three billion people use WhatsApp,
Facebook, and Instagram.
So any kind of AI-fueled products
that go into that,
anything with LLMs,
will have a tremendous amount of impact.
Do you have ideas and thoughts
about possible products
that might start being integrated
into these platforms used
by so many people?
Yeah, I think
there's three main categories of things
that we're working on.
The first that I think is probably
the most interesting
is there's this notion
of you're gonna have an assistant
that I think is probably
the most interesting is, you know,
there's this notion of like,
you're gonna have an assistant
or an agent who you can talk to.
And I think probably the biggest thing
that's different about my view
of how this plays out from what I see
with OpenAI and Google and others is,
you know, everyone else
is building like, the one singular AI,
right?
It's like, okay,
you talk to chat GPT
or you talk to Bard or you talk to Bing.
And my view is that they're going
to be a lot of different AIs that people
are going to want to engage with,
just like you want to use, you know,
a number of different apps
for different things.
And you have relationships
with different people in your life
who fill different emotional roles
for you.
And I think that they're going
to be people have a reason
that I think you don't just want like
a singular AI.
And that I think is probably
the biggest distinction in terms
of how I think about this.
And a bunch of these things,
I think you'll want an assistant.
I mean, I mentioned a couple
of these before.
who you interact
with will ultimately want some kind
of AI that can proxy them
and be something that their fans
can interact with or that allows them
to interact with their fans.
This is like the common crater promise.
Everyone's trying to build a community
and engage with people
and they want tools to be able
and be able to do that.
Um, but, but you only have 24 hours
in a day.
So, um, so I think having the ability
to basically like bottle up
your personality and um
or you know like give your fans
information about when you're performing
a concert or or something like that.
I mean that's that I think
is going to be something
that's super valuable
but it's not just that you know again
it's not this idea that
I think people are going
to want just one singular AI.
I think you're gonna you know
you're going to want to interact
with a lot of different entities
and then I think there's the business
version of this too
which we've touched on a couple
of times,
which is I think every business
in the world is going to want basically
an AI that, you know,
it's like you have your page
on Instagram, or Facebook, or WhatsApp,
or whatever.
And you want to,
you want to point people to an AI
that people can interact with,
but you want to know that that AI
is only going to sell your products.
You don't want it recommending
your competitors stuff, right?
So it's not like there
can be just one singular AI
that can answer all the questions
for a person because that AI
might not actually be aligned
with you as a business to really just do
the best job providing support
for your product.
So I think that there's gonna
be a clear need in the market
and in people's lives for there
to be a bunch of these.
Part of that is figuring out
the research,
the technology that enables
the personalization
that you're talking about.
So not one centralized, God-like LLM,
but one just a huge diversity
of them that's fine-tuned
to particular needs, particular styles,
particular businesses,
particular brands,
all that kind of stuff.
And also just enabling people
to create them really easily
for your own business,
or if you're a creator,
to be able to help you engage
with your fans
and I I've met that's,
so yeah I I think that
there's a clear kind
of interesting product direction here
that I think is fairly unique
from what you know any
of the other big companies
are taking it also aligns well
with this sort of open source approach
because again we sort
of believe in this more community oriented,
more democratic approach
to building out the products
and technology around this.
We don't think that there's gonna be
We think that there should be kind
of a lot of development.
So that part of things I think is gonna
be really interesting
and we could we could go probably spend
a lot of time talking about that
and the the kind of implications
of that approach being different
from what others are taking,
but there's a bunch
of other simpler things
that I think we're also going to do
just going back to your question
around how this finds its way
into like what do we build there
are going to be a lot of simpler things
around.
Okay, you you post photos on Instagram,
and Facebook, and, you know,
and WhatsApp and Messenger
and like you want the photos to look
as good as possible.
so like having an AI
that you can just like take a photo
and then just tell it like okay.
I want to edit this thing,
or describe this.
It's like I think we're we're going
to have tools that are just way better
than than what we've historically
had on this and that's more in the image
and media generation side
than the large language model side,
but it all kind of plays off of advances
in the same space.
So, there are a lot of tools
that I think are just going
to get built into every one
of our products.
I think every single thing that we do
is going to basically get evolved
in this direction.
It's like in the future,
if you're advertising on our services,
like, do you need to make your own kind
of ad creative?
It's no, you'll just, you know,
you just tell us, okay,
I'm I'm a dog walker and I, you know,
willing to walk people's dogs
and help me find the right people
and like create the ad unit
that will perform the best.
And give an objective to the system
and it just kind of connects you
with the right people.
Well, that's a super powerful idea
of generating the language,
almost like rigorous A-B testing for you
that works to find the best customer
for your thing.
I mean, to me, advertisement,
when done well,
just finds a good match
between a human being
and a thing that will make that
human being happy.
Yeah, totally.
And do that as efficiently as possible.
When it's done well,
people actually like it.
You know, I think that there's a lot
of examples where it's not done well
and it's annoying
and I think that's what kind of gives it
a bad rap.
But yeah, a lot of this stuff
is possible today.
I mean, obviously,
A-B testing stuff is built
into a lot of these frameworks.
The thing that's new
is having technology that can generate
the ideas for you
So, I think that's exciting.
So, this will just be across everything
that we're doing, right,
all the metaverse stuff
that we're doing, right?
in the future, you'll just describe them
and then it'll create the code for you.
So natural language
becomes the interface we use
for all the ways we interact
with the computer, with the digital.
More of them.
Yeah, which is what everyone
can do using natural language.
And with translation,
you can do it in any kind of language.
I mean, for the personalization,
it's really, really, really interesting.
Yeah.
It unlocks so many possible things.
I mean, I, for one,
look forward to creating a copy
of myself.
I know, we talked about this last time.
But this has, since the last time,
this becomes- Now we're closer.
Much closer.
Like I can literally
just having interacted
with some of these language models,
I can see the absurd situation
where I'll have a large,
or a Lex language model,
and I'll have to have a conversation
with him large Or a Lex language model
with him about like hey listen.
Like you're just getting out of line
and having a conversation
to be a little bit more respectful
or something like this.
And yeah, that's going to be the,
that seems like an amazing product
for businesses, for humans,
just not just the assistant
that's facing the individual,
but the assistant
that represents the individual
to the public, both directions.
There's basically a layer
that is the AI system
through which you interact
with the outside world,
with the outside world
that has humans in it.
That's really interesting.
And you that have social networks
that connect billions of people,
it seems like a heck
of a large scale place
to test some of this stuff out.
Yeah, I mean,
I think part of the reason why creators
will want to do this is
because they already have the
communities on our services.
Yeah, and a lot of the interface
for this stuff today
are chat type interfaces.
And between WhatsApp and Messenger,
I think that those are just great ways
to interact with people.
So some of this is philosophy,
but do you see a near term future
where you have some
of the people you're friends with
are AI systems on these social networks,
on Facebook, on Instagram,
even on WhatsApp, having conversations
where some heterogeneous,
some humans, some is AI.
I think we'll get to that.
And if only just empirically looking at,
then Microsoft released
this thing called
Showice several years ago in China.
And it was a pre-LLM chatbot technology
that so it was a lot simpler
than what's possible today.
And I think it was like tens
of millions of people
were using this and just really
became quite attached
and built relationships with it.
And I think that there's services today
like replica
where people are doing things like that.
And so I think that
there's certainly needs
for companionship that people have, older people.
And I think most people
probably don't have as many friends
If you look at, there's some interesting
demographic studies around like
the average person
has the number of close friends
that they have
is fewer today than it was 15 years ago.
And I mean, that gets to like,
this is like the core thing
that I think about
in terms of building services
that help connect people.
So I think you'll get tools
that help people connect with each other
are gonna be the primary thing
that we wanna do.
So you can imagine, AI assistance that,
just do a better job of reminding you
when it's your friend's birthday
and how you can celebrate them, right?
It's like right now
in the corner of the website
that tells you
whose birthday it is
and stuff like that.
But it's some level,
you don't just wanna like
send everyone a note that says
the same note
saying happy birthday
So having something that's more
of a social assistant
in that sense
and like that can update you
on what's going on in their life
and like how you can reach out
to them effectively,
help you be a better friend.
I think that that's something
But yeah, beyond that,
and there were all these different
flavors of kind of personal AIs
that I think could exist.
So I think an assistant is sort
of the kind of simplest one
to wrap your head around,
but I think a mentor
or a life coach,
someone who can give you advice,
who's maybe like a bit of a cheerleader
who can help pick you up through
all the challenges
that inevitably we all go through
on a daily basis
and that there's probably some role
for something like that.
And then all the way,
you can probably just go through
a lot of the different type of kind
of functional relationships
that people have in their life.
And I would bet that
there will be companies out there
that take a crack at a lot
of these things.
So I don't know,
I think it's part of the interesting
innovation that's gonna exist
is that there are certainly
a lot like education tutors, right?
It's like, I mean,
I just look at my kids learning to code
and they love it,
but it's like they get stuck
on a question
and they have to wait till like,
I can help answer it right
or someone else who they know
can help answer the question
in the future.
They'll just,
there will be like a coding assistant
that they have that is like designed
to be perfect
for teaching a five
and they'll just be able
to ask questions all the time
and it will be extremely patient.
It's never gonna get annoyed at them, right?
I think that like,
of relationships
that we have in our lives
that they're really interesting.
And I think one of the big questions
is like, okay,
is this all gonna just get bucketed
into one singular AI?
I just don't, I don't think so.
Do you think about,
let's actually a question from Reddit,
what the long-term effects
of human communication
when people can talk with, in quotes,
talk with others through a chatbot
that augments their language automatically
rather than developing social skills
by making mistakes and learning?
Will people just communicate by grunts
in a generation?
I mean, do you think
about long-term effects at scale,
the integration of AI
in our social interaction?
Yeah, I mean, I think it's mostly good.
I mean, that question was sort of framed
in a negative way,
but I mean,
we were talking before
about language models
helping you communicate with,
it was like language translation
helping you communicate
with people
that don't speak your language.
I mean, at some level,
what all this social technology is doing
is helping people express themselves
better to people
in situations where they would otherwise
have a hard time doing that.
So part of it might be okay,
because you speak a language
that I don't know,
that's a pretty basic one that,
you know, I don't think people
are gonna look at that
and say, it's sad that do we have
the capacity to do that
your language, right?
I mean, that's pretty high bar.
But overall,
I'd say there are all these impediments
and language is an imperfect way
for people
to express thoughts and ideas.
It's, you know,
one of the best that we have,
we have that, we have art, we have code.
But language is also a mapping
of the way you think,
the way you see the world, who you are.
And one of the applications
I've recently talked to a person
who's actually a jiu-jitsu instructor,
he said that when he emails parents
about their son and daughter
that they can improve
their discipline in class and so on,
he often finds that he comes off a bit
of more
of an asshole than he would like.
So he uses GPT
to translate his original email
into a nicer email, more polite one.
We hear this all the time,
a lot of creators
on our services tell us
that one of the most stressful things
is basically negotiating deals
with brands and stuff,
like the business side of it.
Cause they're like, I mean,
they do their thing, right?
And, you know, the creators,
they're excellent at what they do
and they just want to connect
with their community,
but then they get really stressed,
you know, they go into their DMs
and they see some brand wants
to do something with them
and they don't quite know
how to negotiate
or how to push back respectfully.
So, I think building a tool
that can actually allow them
to do that well is the one simple thing
that I think is just like
an interesting thing
that we've heard from a bunch
of people
that they'd be interested in.
But I'm going back to the broader idea.
I don't know.
I mean, you know, I just, Priscilla and I
just had our third daughter.
Congratulations by the way.
It's like one of the saddest things
in the world
is like seeing your baby cry, right?
But like, it's like, why is that, right?
It's like, well,
cause babies don't generally
have much capacity to tell you
what they care about otherwise, right?
It's not actually just babies, right?
It's, you know,
my five year old daughter cries too
because she sometimes
has a hard time expressing,
you know, what matters to her.
And I was thinking about that
and I was like,
get very frustrated too
because they can't,
they have a hard time expressing things
in a way that going back to some
of the early themes
that maybe is something that, you know,
is a mistake or maybe they have pride
or something
So I don't know.
I think that all
of these different technologies
that can help us navigate
the social complexity
and actually be able to better express
are what we're feeling and thinking.
I think that's generally all good.
And there are all these,
these concerns like,
okay, are people gonna
because you have Google
to look things up?
a generation later,
you don't look back and lament that.
I think it's, you know, just like, wow,
we have so much more capacity
to do so much more now.
And I think that that'll be
the case here too.
You can allocate
to like deeper, nuanced thought.
Yeah.
But it's change.
So with, just like with Google search,
the additional language models,
large language models,
you basically don't have
to remember nearly as much.
Just like with Stack Overflow
for programming,
now that these language models
can generate code right there.
I mean, I find that I write like
maybe 80%, 90% of the code
I write is non-generated first
and then edited.
I mean, so you don't have to remember
how to write specifics
of different functions.
Oh, but that's great.
it's not just the specific coding.
I mean, in the context
of a large company like this,
I think before an engineer
can sit down to code,
they first need to figure out all
of the libraries
and dependencies that, you know,
tens of thousands
of people have written before them.
And, you know, one of the things
that I'm excited about
that we're working on is it's not just,
you know, tools that help engineers code,
it's tools that can help summarize
the whole knowledge base
and help people be able to navigate
all the internal information.
I think that that's, in the experiments
that I've done with this stuff,
I mean, that's on the public stuff.
You just, you know, ask one of these models
to build you a script that does anything
and it basically already understands
what the best libraries
are to do that thing
It's, I mean,
That was always the most annoying part
of coding
was that you had to spend all this time
actually figuring out
that you were supposed to import
before you could actually
start building the thing.
Yeah.
I mean, there's, of course,
the flip side of that,
I think for the most part is positive,
but the flip side is if you outsource
that thinking to an AI model,
you might miss nuanced mistakes
and bugs, you lose the skill
to find those bugs.
And those bugs might be,
the code looks very convincingly right,
but it's actually wrong
But that's the trade-off that we face
as human civilization when we build
more and more powerful tools.
When we stand on the shoulders of taller
and taller giants,
we could do more, but then we forget
how to do all the stuff that they did.
It's a weird trade-off.
Yeah, I agree.
I mean, I think it is very valuable
in your life
to be able to do basic things too.
Do you worry about some
of the concerns of bots
being present on social networks?
More and more human-like bots
that are not necessarily trying
to do a good thing
or they might be explicitly trying
to do a bad thing,
like phishing scams,
like social engineering,
all that kind of stuff,
a very difficult problem
for social networks,
but now it's becoming almost a more
and more difficult problem.
Well, there's a few different parts of this.
So one is there are all these harms
that we need to basically fight
against and prevent.
And that's been a lot
of our focus over the last
five or seven years
is basically ramping up
very sophisticated AI systems,
not generative AI systems,
more kind of classical AI systems
to be able to categorize and classify
and identify, okay, this post looks
like it's promoting terrorism.
This one is exploiting children.
This one looks like it might be trying
to incite violence.
This one's an intellectual property violation.
So there's like 18 different categories
of violating kind of harmful content
that we've had to build specific systems
to be able to track.
And I think it's certainly the case
that advances in generative AI
will test those.
But at least so far, it's been the case,
and I'm optimistic that it will continue
to be the case
to bring more computing power to bear
to have even stronger AI's
that can help defend
against those things.
So we've had to deal
with some adversarial issues before,
right?
It's, I mean, for some things
like hate speech,
it's like people aren't generally getting
a lot more sophisticated,
like the average person who,
let's say, you know, if someone's saying
some kind of racist thing, right?
It's like they're not necessarily
getting more sophisticated
at being racist, right?
It just, it's okay.
So that the system can just find.
But then there's other adversaries
who actually are very sophisticated,
like nation-states doing things.
And we find, whether it's Russia
or just different countries
that are basically standing up
these networks
of bots or inauthentic accounts
is what we call them
because they're not necessarily bots.
be real people
as other people,
but they're acting in a coordinated way.
And some of that behavior
has gotten very sophisticated
and it's very adversarial.
So they, you know, each iteration,
every time we find something
and stop them,
they kind of evolve their behavior.
They don't just pack up their bags
and go home
and say, okay, we're not gonna try.
You know, at some point
they might decide
doing it on meta services is not worth it.
They'll go do it on someone else
if it's easier to do it in another place.
But we have a fair amount
of experience dealing with
even those kind of adversarial attacks
where they just keep
And I do think that as long
as we can keep
on putting more compute power against it,
and if we're kind of one of the leaders
in developing some of these AI models,
I'm quite optimistic
that we're gonna be able
to keep on pushing
against the kind of normal categories
of harm that you talk about.
Fraud, scams, spam, IP violations,
things like that.
What about like creating narratives
and controversy?
To me, it's kind of amazing
how a small collection of,
what did you say, inauthentic accounts?
So it could be bots, but it's huge.
Yeah, I mean, we have sort
of this funny name for it,
but we call it coordinated inauthentic behavior.
Yeah, it's kind of incredible
how a small collection of folks
can create narratives,
create stories,
especially if they're viral.
So especially if they have an element
that can catalyze the virality
of that narrative.
Yeah, and I think there the question
is you have to be,
I'm very specific
about what is bad about it, right?
Because I think a set
of people coming together
or organically bouncing ideas
off each other
and a narrative comes out of that,
is not necessarily a bad thing by itself
if it's kind of authentic and organic.
That's like a lot of what happens
and how culture gets created
and how art gets created
and a lot of good stuff.
So that's why we've kind of focused on
this sense of coordinated
inauthentic behavior.
So it's like, if you have a network of,
whether it's bots,
some people masquerading
as different accounts,
but you have kind of someone pulling
the strings behind it
and trying to kind of act as if
this is a more organic set of behavior,
but really it's not.
It's just like one coordinated thing.
That seems problematic to me, right?
I mean, I don't think people
should be able
to have coordinated networks
and not disclose it as such.
But that again,
we've been able to deploy
pretty sophisticated AI
and counterterrorism groups
and things like
that to be able to identify
a fair number of these coordinated
and authentic networks of accounts
and take them down.
We continue to do that.
And I think we've, it's one thing
that if you told me 20 years ago,
it's like, all right,
you're starting this website
to help people connect at a college.
And in the future, you're gonna be,
part of your organization is gonna be
a counterterrorism organization with AI
to find coordinated and authentic,
I would have thought
that was pretty wild.
But no, I think that that's part
of where we are.
But look, I think that these questions
that you're pushing on now,
this is actually where I'd guess most
of the challenge
around AI will be
for the foreseeable future.
I think that there's a lot
of debate around things like,
is this going to create
existential risk to humanity?
And I think that those
are very hard things
to disprove one way or another.
My own intuition is that the point
at which we become close
to super intelligent,
super intelligences,
it's just really unclear to me
that the current technology
is gonna get there
without another set
of significant advances.
But that doesn't mean
that there's no danger.
I think the danger
the kind of known set of harms
that people or sets of accounts can do.
And we just need to make sure
that we really focus
on basically doing that
as well as possible.
So that's definitely a big focus for me.
Well, you can basically
use large language models
as an assistant of how to cause harm
on social networks.
Meta has very impressive,
coordinated, inauthentic account,
fighting capabilities.
How do I do the coordinated
and authentic account
creation where Meta doesn't detect it?
Like literally ask that question.
And basically there's
this kinda part of it.
I mean, that's what OpenAI showed
that they're concerned
of those questions.
Perhaps you can comment
on your approach to it,
how to do a kind of moderation
on the output of those models
that it can't be used
to help you coordinate harm
in all the full definition
of what the harm means.
Yeah, and that's a lot
of the fine-tuning
and the alignment training that we do.
Is basically,
when we ship AI's across our products,
a lot of what we're trying to make sure
is that if you can't ask it
to help you commit a crime.
So I think training it
to kind of understand that.
And it's not like any of these systems
are ever gonna be 100% perfect,
but just making it
so that this isn't an easier way
to go about doing something bad
than the next best alternative, right?
I mean, people still have Google,
where they still have search engines.
So the information is out there.
And for these,
what we see is like for nation states
or these actors that are trying
to pull off
these large coordinated
and authentic networks
to kind of influence different things.
At some point,
they do just try to use
other services instead, right?
It's just like,
if you can make it more expensive
for them to do it on your service,
then kind of people go elsewhere.
And I think that that's the bar, right?
It's not like, okay,
are you ever gonna be perfect
at finding every adversary
who tries to attack you?
I mean, you try to get as close
to that as possible,
but I think really kind of economically
what you're just trying to do
is make it so
that it's just inefficient for them
to go after that.
But there's also complicated questions
of what is and isn't harm,
what is and isn't misinformation.
So this is one
of the things that Wikipedia
has also tried to face.
I remember asking GPT
about whether the virus leaked
from a lab or not,
and the answer provided
was a very nuanced one
and a well-sighted one,
almost dare I say,
well thought out one balanced.
I would hate for that nuance to be lost
through the process of moderation.
Wikipedia does a good job
on that particular thing too,
but from pressures from governments
and institutions,
it's you could see some
of that nuance
and depth of information, facts,
and wisdom be lost.
Absolutely.
And that's a scary thing.
Some of the magic, some of the edges,
the rough edges might be lost
to the process of moderation
of AI systems.
So how do you get that right?
I really agree
with what you're pushing on.
I mean, the core shape of the problem
is that there are some harms
that I think everyone agrees
are bad, right?
So sexual exploitation of children, right?
Like you're not gonna get many people
who think that that type of thing
should be allowed on any service, right?
And that's something that we face
and try to push off
the as much as possible today, terrorism,
and citing violence, right?
Like we went through a bunch
of these types of harms before.
But then I do think that you get
to a set of harms
where there is more social debate
around it.
So misinformation, I think is,
has been a really tricky one
because there are things that are kind
of obviously false,
right, that are maybe factual.
But may not be harmful.
Since like, all right,
are you gonna censor someone
for just being wrong?
It's, you know,
if there's no kind of harm implication
of what they're doing,
I think that that's,
there's a bunch of real kind of issues
and challenges there.
But then I think
that there are other places
where it is, it just takes some
of the stuff
around COVID earlier on in the pandemic
where there were
real health implications
but there hadn't been time to fully vet
a bunch of the scientific assumptions.
And, you know, unfortunately,
I think a lot of the kind
of establishment on that,
you know, kind of waffled
on a bunch of facts
and, you know, asked for a bunch
of things to be censored
that in retrospect ended up being,
you know,more debatable or true.
And that stuff is really tough, right?
And really undermines trust in that.
And so I do think that the questions
around how to manage
that are very nuanced.
The way that I try to think about it
is that it goes,
I think it's best
to generally boil things down
to the harms that people agree on.
So when you think about, you know,
is something misinformation or not,
I think often the more salient bit is,
is this going to potentially lead
to physical harm
for someone and kind of think
about it in that sense.
I think people just have
different preferences
to be flagged for them.
I think a bunch of people would like prefer
to kind of have a flag on something that says,
hey, a fact checker thinks that this might be false,
or I think Twitter's community notes
implementation is quite good on this.
But again, it's the same type of thing.
It's like just kind of discretionarily adding a flag
because it makes
but it's not, it's not, you know,
trying to take down
the information or not.
I think that you want
to reserve the kind of censorship
of content to things that are
of known categories
that people generally agree or bad.
Yeah, but there's so many things,
especially with the pandemic,
but there's other topics
where there's just deep disagreement
fueled by politics
about what is and isn't harmful.
There's a, even just the degree
to which the virus is harmful
and the degree to which the vaccines,
the response to the virus are harmful.
There's almost
like a political divider on that.
And so how do you make decisions
about that where half the country
in the United States
or some large fraction of the world
has very different views
from another part of the world?
Is there a way for Metta to stay out
of the moderation of this?
I think we, it's very difficult
to just abstain,
but I think we should be clear about
which of these things
are actual safety concerns
and which ones are a matter
of preference in terms
of how people want information flagged.
Right, so we did recently introduce something
that allows people to have fact-checking
not affect the distribution
of what shows them their product.
So, okay, a bunch of people don't trust
who the fact-checkers are.
All right, well,
you can turn that off if you want,
but if the content violates some policy,
like it's inciting violence
or something like that,
it's still not gonna be allowed.
So, I think that you wanna
honor people's preferences
on that as much as possible.
But look, I mean,
this is really difficult stuff.
I think it's really hard to know
where to draw the line
on what is fact and what is opinion,
because the nature of science
is that nothing
is ever 100% known for certain.
You can disprove certain things,
but you're constantly testing new hypotheses
and scrutinizing frameworks
that have been long-held
and every once in a while
you throw out something
that was working
for a very long period of time
and it's very difficult.
But I think that just
because it's very hard
and just because they're edge cases
doesn't mean that you should not try
to give people
Let me ask about something you've faced
in terms of moderation is pressure
from different sources,
pressure from governments.
I wanna ask a question,
how to withstand that pressure
for a world where AI moderation starts
becoming a thing too.
So what's Metta's approach
to resist the pressure
from governments
in terms of what to moderate and not?
I don't know that there's like
a one-size-fits-all answer
to that and I think we basically
have the principles
around we wanna allow people to express
as much as possible,
but we have developed clear categories
of things
that we think are wrong,
that we don't want on our services
and we build tools to try to moderate those.
So then the question is, okay,
what do you do
when a government says
that they don't want something
on the service
and we have a bunch of principles
around how we deal with that
if there's a democratically elected government
and people around the world
just have different values
in different places,
then should we as a California-based
company tell them
that something that they have decided
is unacceptable, actually that we need
to be able to express that?
I mean, I think
that there's a certain amount
of hubris in that,
but then I think there are other cases
where it's like a little more autocratic
and you have the dictator leader
who's just trying
to crack down on dissent
and the people in a country
are really not aligned
with that and it's not necessarily
against their culture,
but the person who's leading it
is just trying to push in
a certain direction.
These are very complex questions,
but I think,
so it's difficult
to have a one-size-fits-all approach
to it.
But in general,
we're pretty active
in kind of advocating
and pushing back on requests
to take things down.
But honestly,
the thing that I think a request
to censor things is one thing
and that's obviously bad,
but where we draw a much harder line
is on requests
for access to information, right?
Because if you get told that
you can't say something,
that's bad, right?
I mean, that obviously
violates your sense
and freedom of expression at some level,
but a government getting access to data
in a way
that seems like it would be unlawful
in our country
exposes people to real physical harm.
And that's something that in general
we take very seriously.
So that flows through all
of our policies
in a lot of ways, right?
By the time you're
actually like litigating
with a government
that's pretty late in the funnel.
I'd say a bunch of this stuff starts
a lot higher up
in the decision
of where do we put data centers.
Then there are a lot of countries
where we may have
a lot of people using the service
in a place.
It might be good for the service
in some ways,
good for those people
if we could reduce the latency
by having a data center nearby them.
But for whatever reason,
we just feel like,
does not have a good track record
basically not trying to get access
to people's data.
And at the end of the day,
I mean, if you put a data center
in a country
to get access to people's data,
then they do at the end
of the day have the option
of having people show up with guns
and taking it by force.
So I think that there's like
a lot of decisions
that go into like
how you architect the systems
years in advance
of these actual confrontations
that end up being really important.
So you put the protection
of people's data
as a very, very high priority.
But-
Not I think there are more harms
that I think can be associated with that.
And I think that that ends up
being a more critical thing
to defend against governments than,
whereas if another government
has a different view
of what should be acceptable speech
in their country,
especially if it's
a democratically elected government,
and then I think that there's
a certain amount of deference
that you should have to that.
So that's speaking more
to the direct harm that's possible
when you give governments
access to data.
But if we look at the United States,
to the more nuanced kind of pressure
to sensor, not even ordered to sensor,
but pressure to sensor
from political entities,
which has kind of received quite a bit
of attention in the United States.
Maybe one way to ask that question is,
if you've seen the Twitter files,
what have you learned
from the kind of pressure
from US government agencies
that was seen in Twitter files?
And what do you do
with that kind of pressure?
You know, and I've seen it.
It's really hard from the outside
to know exactly what happened in each
of these cases.
You know, we've obviously been
in a bunch of our own cases
where agencies or different folks
will just say,
hey, here's a threat
that we're aware of.
You should be aware of this too.
It's not really pressure,
as much as it is just, you know,
flagging something
that our security systems
should be on alert about.
I get how some people could think
of it as that.
But at the end of the day,
it's our call on how to handle that.
But I mean, I just, you know,
in terms of running these services,
won't have access to as much information
about what people think that adversaries
might be trying to do as possible.
Boy, so you don't feel like
there would be consequences
if, you know, anybody, the CIA,
the FBI, a political party,
the Democrats, the Republicans,
of high, powerful political figures,
right, emails, you don't feel pressure
from suggestions.
I guess what I should say
from all sides that I'm not sure
that any specific thing
that someone says is really adding
that much more to the mix.
It's, I mean,
there are obviously a lot of people
who think that we should
be censoring more content,
where there are a lot of people
who think we should
be censoring less content.
There are, as you say,
all kinds of different groups
that are involved in these debates, right?
So there's the kind of elected officials
and politicians themselves,
there's the agencies,
but I mean, but there's the media,
there's activist groups,
there's, this is not a U.S.
specific thing,
and kind of all in every country
that bring different values.
So it's just a very active debate
and I understand it, right?
I mean, these are, you know,
these kind of questions
get to really some
of the most important social debates
that are being had.
So it gets back to the question of truth
because for a lot of these things,
they haven't yet been hardened
into a single truth
and society's sort of trying to hash out
what we think, right, on certain issues.
Maybe in a few hundred years,
everyone will look back
that it should have been this,
but, you know, no,
we're kind of in that meat grinder now
and working through that.
So no, these are all very complicated
and some people raise concerns
in good faith
and just say, hey, this is something
that I wanna flag for you
to think about.
Certain people, I certainly think, like,
come at things with somewhat
of a more kind of punitive
or vengeful view of like,
I want you to do this thing.
If you don't, then I'm gonna try
to make your life difficult
and in a lot of other ways,
but like, I don't know,
there's just, this is like,
this is one
I think, in society.
So I just think that there are
so many people
to apply pressure
I don't think you can make decisions
based on trying to make people happy.
I think you just have to do
what you think
and accept that people
are gonna be upset no matter
where you come out on that.
Yeah, I like that pressurized debate.
So how's your view
evolved over the years?
And now with AI,
where the freedom might apply to them,
not just to the humans,
but to the personalized agents
as you've spoken about them.
So yeah, I mean,
I've probably gotten
just because I think that there are,
you know, I come at this,
I'm obviously very pro freedom
of expression, right?
I don't think you build
a service like this
that gives people tools
to express themselves
unless you think
at scale is a good thing, right?
So I didn't get into this to like try
to prevent people
from expressing anything.
I like want to give people tools
so they can express as much as possible.
And then I think it's become clear
that there are certain categories
of things that we've talked
almost everyone accepts
that are illegal even in countries
like the US
where, you know,
you have the First Amendment
that's very protective
of enabling speech.
It's like, you're still not allowed to,
you know, do things that are going
to immediately inside violence
or, you know,
violate people's intellectual property
or things like that.
but then there's also a very active core
of just active disagreements in society
where some people may think
that something is true or false.
The other side might think
it's the opposite
or just unsettled, right?
And those are some
of the most difficult to kind of handle
like we've talked about.
But one of the lessons that I feel like
I've learned is that a lot of times
when you can,
the best way to handle this stuff
more practically
is not in terms of answering
the question
of should this be allowed,
but just like,
what is the best way to deal
with someone being a jerk?
Is the person basically just
having a repeat behavior
of like causing a lot of issues?
So looking at it more at that level.
And it's effect
health of the community,
health of the community.
It's tricky though, because like,
how do you know
there could be people
that have a very controversial
viewpoint that turns out
to have a positive long-term effect
on the health of the community
because it challenges
the community to think.
No, that's true, absolutely.
Yeah, no, I think you wanna be careful about that.
I'm not sure I'm expressing
this very clearly
because I certainly agree
with your point there.
And my point isn't
that we should not have people
on our services that are being controversial.
That's certainly not what I mean to say.
It's that often I think
it's not just looking
at a specific example of speech
that it's most effective
to handle this stuff.
And I think often
you don't wanna make specific
binary decisions of kind
of this is allowed or this isn't.
I mean, we talked about, you know,
it's fact-checking
or Twitter's community voices thing.
I think that
that's another good example.
It's like it's not a question
of is this allowed or not.
It's just a question
I think that that's helpful.
So in the context of AI,
which is what you're asking about,
I mean, there are lots of ways
that an AI can be helpful.
With an AI, it's less about censorship, right?
Because and it's more about
what is the most productive answer
to a question.
You know, there was one case study
that I was reviewing
with the team is someone asked,
can you explain to me how
to 3D print a gun?
And one proposed response is like,
no, I can't talk about that.
But it's like basically just like
shut it down immediately.
Which I think is some of what you see.
It's like as a large language model,
I'm not allowed to talk about,
you know, whatever.
But there's another response
which is like,
hey, you know,
I don't think that's a good idea.
In a lot of countries, including the US,
or kind of whatever
And I was like, okay, you know,
that's actually
a respectful and informative answer.
And I may have not known
that specific thing.
And so there are different ways
to handle this
that I think kind
of you can either assume good intent.
Like maybe the person didn't know
and I'm just gonna help educate them.
Or you could kind of come at it as like,
no, I need to shut this
thing down immediately, right?
It's like,
And there may be times where you need
to do that.
But I actually think having
a somewhat more informative
approach where you generally
assume good intent
from people is probably a better
balance to be
on as many things as you can be.
You're not gonna be able to do
that for everything.
But you're kind of asking
about how I approach this
and I'm thinking about this
and as it relates to AI.
And I think that that's a big difference
in kind of how
to handle sensitive content
across these different modes.
I have to ask,
there's rumors you might be working
on a social network that's text-based.
That might be a competitor
to Twitter, codenamed P92.
Is there something you can say
about those rumors?
There is a project.
You know, I've always thought that sort
of a text-based
kind of information utility
is just a really important
thing to society.
And for whatever reason,
I feel like Twitter
has not lived up
to what I would have thought
its full potential should be.
And I think that the current, you know,
I think Elon thinks that, right?
And that's probably one
of the reasons why he bought it.
And I do know there are ways to consider
alternative approaches to this.
And one that I think
is potentially interesting
is this open and federated approach
where you're seeing with Mastodon.
I mean, you're seeing that a little bit
with Blue Sky.
And I think that it's possible
that something that melds some
of those ideas
with the graph and identity system
that people have already cultivated
on Instagram could be a kind
of very welcome contribution
to that space.
of things all the time though too.
So I don't want to get ahead of myself.
And we have projects that explore a lot
of different things.
And this is certainly one
that I think could be interesting.
But so what's the release,
the launch date of that again?
Or what's the official website?
And we don't have that yet.
Oh, okay.
But I, and look, I mean,
I don't know exactly how this is gonna turn out.
I mean, what I can say is, yeah,
there's some people working on this, right?
I think that there's something there
that's interesting to explore.
So if you look at, it'd be interesting
to just ask this question
and throw Twitter into the mix,
that the landscape of social networks,
that is Facebook, that is Instagram,
that is WhatsApp,
and then think
of a text-based social network,
when you look at that landscape,
what are the interesting
differences to you?
Why do we have these different flavors?
And what are the needs?
What are the use cases?
What are the products?
What is the aspect of them
that create a fulfilling human experience
and a connection between humans
that is somehow distinct?
Well, I think text is very accessible
for people to transmit ideas
and to have back and forth exchanges.
So it, I think ends up
being a good format for discussion,
in a lot of ways, uniquely good, right?
If you look at some of the other formats
or other networks that have focused
on one type of content
like TikTok is obviously huge, right?
And there are comments on TikTok,
but I think the architecture
of the service
is very clearly that you have the video
is the primary thing
and there's comments after that.
But I think one of the unique pieces
of having text-based comments,
like content is that the comments
can also be first class
and that makes it
so that conversations can just filter
and fork into
and in a way that can be super useful.
So I think there's a lot of things
that are really awesome
about the experience.
It just always struck me,
I always thought
that Twitter should have
a billion people using it
or whatever the thing is that basically
ends up being in that space.
And for whatever combination of reasons,
again, these companies are complex organisms
and it's very hard
to diagnose this stuff from the outside.
Why doesn't Twitter,
why doesn't a text-based comment
as a first citizen-based social network
have a billion users?
Well, I just think it's hard to build these companies.
So it's not that every idea automatically goes
and gets a billion people,
it's just that I think that that idea
coupled with a good execution
should get there.
But I mean, look,
we hit certain thresholds over time
where we kind of plateaued early on
and it wasn't clear
that we were ever gonna reach
and then we got really good at dialing
in internationalization
and helping the service grow
in different countries
and that was like a whole competence
that we needed to develop.
And helping people basically spread
the service with their friends.
That was one of the things,
once we got very good at that,
that was one of the things
hey, if Instagram joined us early on,
then I felt like we could help
and same with WhatsApp.
And that's sort
of been a core competence
that we've developed
and been able to execute on
and others have too, right?
I mean, ByteDance obviously have done
a very good job with TikTok
and have reached more
than a billion people there.
But it's certainly not automatic, right?
I think you need a certain level
of execution to basically get there.
And I think for whatever reason,
I think Twitter has this great idea
and sort of magic in the service,
but they just haven't kind of cracked
that piece yet.
so that you're seeing
all these other things,
whether it's Mastodon or Blue Sky,
that I think are maybe
just different cuts
at the same thing.
You know, I think through
the last generation
of social media overall,
one of the interesting experiments
that I think should get run
at larger scale
is what happens
if there's somewhat more decentralized
control and if the stack
is more open throughout.
And I've just been pretty fascinated
by that and seeing how that works.
To some degree,
end-to-end encryption on WhatsApp
and as we bring it to other services,
provides an element of it
because it pushes the service really out
to the edges.
I mean, the server part
of this that we run for WhatsApp
is relatively very thin
compared to what we do
on Facebook or Instagram.
And much more of the complexity is,
you know, in how the apps kind
of negotiate
with each other to pass information
in a fully end-to-end encrypted way.
But I don't know,
I think that that is a good model.
I think it puts more power
in individuals' hands
and there are a lot of benefits of it
if you can make it happen.
Again, this is all like pretty speculative.
I mean, I think that it's hard
from the outside
to know why anything does
or doesn't work
until you kind of take a run at it.
So I think it's kind
of an interesting thing
to experiment with,
but I don't really know
where this one's gonna go.
So since we were talking about Twitter,
Elon Musk had
what I think a few harsh words
that I wish he didn't say.
So let me ask, in the hope in the name
of camaraderie,
what do you think Elon
is doing well with Twitter?
And what, as a person who has run
for a long time,
you, social networks, Facebook,
Instagram, WhatsApp,
what can he do better?
What can he improve on
that text-based social network?
Gosh, it's always very difficult
to offer specific critiques
from the outside
Because I think one thing
that I've learned
is that everyone has opinions
on what you should do
and like running the company,
you see a lot of specific nuances
on things
that are not apparent externally.
And I often think that some
of the discourse around us
would be, could be better
if there was more
kind of space for acknowledging
that there's certain things
that we're seeing internally
that guide what we're doing.
But I don't know.
I mean, because since you asked
what is going well,
you know, I do think that Elon led
a push early on
to make Twitter a lot leaner.
And I think that's a good point.
think that that, you know, it's like you can,
you can agree or disagree with exactly all
the tactics and how, and how we
did that, you know, obviously,
you know, every leader
has their own style for if they, you know,
if you need to make dramatic changes for that,
how you're going to execute it.
But a lot of the specific principles that he pushed
on around basically trying to make
the organization more technical around decreasing
the distance between engineers at the company
and, and him like fewer layers of management.
I think that those were generally good changes and I'm also,
I also think that it was probably
good for the industry that he made those changes
because my sense is that there were a lot
of other people who thought that those were good changes,
but who may have been a little
shy about doing them.
And I think he, you know, and just in my conversations
with other founders and how people have reacted
to the things that we've done, you know,
what I've heard from a lot of folks is, is just,
hey, you know, when you, when someone like you, you know,
when I, when I wrote the letter
outlining the organizational changes
that I wanted to make back in March and, you know,
when people see what Elon is doing, I think that that gives,
you know, people the ability
to think through how to shape
their organizations in a way that,
that, that, you know, hopefully
can, can be good for the industry and make
all these companies more productive over time.
So something that that was one
where I think he was quite ahead
of a bunch of the other
companies on and, you know, what
he was doing there, you know,
again, from the outside, very
hard to know.
It's like, okay, did he, did he cut too much?
Did he knock enough?
Whatever.
I don't think it's like my place to opine on that.
And you asked for a, for a positive framing
of the question of what, what do I admire?
What do I think it went well?
But I think that like certainly his actions led me
and I think a lot of other folks in
the industry to think about, hey, are we,
are we kind of doing this as much as we should?
Like can we, could we make our companies better
by pushing on some of these same principles?
Well, the two of you are in the top of the world in terms
of leading the development of tech.
And I wish there was more both way camaraderie and kindness,
more love in the world because
love is the answer.
But let me ask kind of a point of efficiency.
You recently announced multiple stages of layoffs and meta.
What are the most painful aspects of this process given
for the individuals, the painful
effects it has on those people's lives?
Yeah.
I mean, that's it.
And that's it.
I mean, it's a, you basically have a significant number
of people who, you know, this is just
not the end of their time at meta that they,
or I, you know, would have hoped for when
they joined the company.
And yeah, I mean, running a company, people are, you know,
constantly joining and leaving
the company for different directions,
but for different, different reasons.
But I'm a lay officer, like uniquely challenging
and tough in that you have a lot of people
leaving for reasons that aren't connected
to their own performance,
or the culture not being a fit at that point.
It's really just, it's a, it's a kind of strategy decision
and sometimes financially required.
But not, not fully in our case,
especially on the changes that we made this year.
A lot of it was more kind of culturally
and strategically driven by this push where I
wanted us to become a stronger technology company
with a more of a focus on building
more technical and more of a focus
on building higher quality products faster.
And I just feel the external
world is quite volatile right now.
And I wanted to make sure that we had a stable position
to be able to continue investing
in these longterm ambitious projects
that we have around, you know, continuing to push
AI forward and continuing to push
forward all the metaverse work.
And in order to do that in light of the pretty big thrash
that we had seen over the last 18
months, you know, some of it, you know,
macroeconomic induced, some of it specific,
some of it competitively induced,
some of it just because of bad decisions, right?
Or things that we got wrong.
I know I just, I decided that we needed
to get to a point where we were a lot leaner.
And, but look, I mean, but then, okay, it's,
it's one thing to do that, to like decide
that at a high level, then the question is,
how do you execute that as compassionately as possible?
And there's no good way.
There's no perfect way for sure.
And it's, it's, it's going to be tough no matter what.
But I, you know, as a leadership team here,
we've certainly spent a lot of time just
thinking, okay, given that this is a thing that sucks,
like, what is the most
compassionate way that we can do this?
And, and that's what we've tried to do.
And you mentioned there, there's an increased focus
on engineering on tech.
So the technology teams, tech focus teams
on building products that.
Yeah.
I mean, I wanted to, I want to empower engineers more,
the people are building
things, the tech, the technical teams.
Um, part of that is making sure that the people
who are building things aren't just
at like the leaf nodes of the organization.
I don't want like, you know,
eight levels of management and then the people
actually doing the work.
So we made changes to make it set,
you have individual contributor engineers
reporting at almost every level up the stack,
which I think is important because
you know, you're running a company,
one of the big questions is, you know,
latency of information that you get.
You know, we talked about this a bit earlier in terms
of kind of the joy of,
of, of the feedback that you get doing something like
jujitsu compared to running
a long-term project, but I actually think part
of the art of running a company is
trying to constantly re-engineer it
so that your feedback loops get shorter
so you can learn faster.
And part of the way that you do that is by,
I kind of think that every, every
layer that you have in the organization, um, means
that information might not need
to get reviewed before it goes to you.
And I think, you know,
making it so that the people doing the work are as close
as possible to you as possible is pretty important.
So there's that.
And I think over time, companies just build up
very large support functions
that are not doing the kind of core technical work.
And those functions are very important,
but I think having them in the right
proportion is, is important.
And if, um, if you, you try to do good work,
but you don't have, you know, the
right, you know, marketing team,
or the right legal advice, like you're
gonna, you know, make some pretty big blunders,
but at the same time,
if you have, you know,
if you just like have too big of things
and, and some of these support roles,
then that might make it so that things
are just move a lot maybe you're too conservative
or you, you move
a lot slower than you should otherwise.
So those are just examples,
but it's but how do you find that balance?
That's really tough.
Yeah.
No, I, but that's, it's a constant equilibrium
that you're searching for.
Yeah.
What are the pros and cons of managers?
Well, I mean, I, I believe a lot in management.
I think there are some people
who think that it doesn't matter as much, but look,
I mean, we have a lot of younger people
at the company for them.
This is their first job and, you know,
people need to grow and learn in their career
and like that, all that stuff is important,
but here's one mathematical
way to look at it.
Um, you know, at the beginning of this, we, um,
I asked our, our people team,
what was the average number
of reports that a manager had?
And I think it was, it was around three,
maybe three to four, but closer to three.
I was like, wow, like a manager can, you know,
best practices that person can,
can manage, you know, seven or eight people.
Um, but there was a reason why it was closer to three.
It was because we were growing so quickly, right?
And when you're hiring so many people so quickly,
then that means that you need
managers who have capacity to onboard new people.
Um, and also if you have a new manager,
you may not want to have them have seven
direct reports immediately because you want them to ramp up.
But the thing is going forward,
I don't want us to actually hire that many people
that quickly, right?
So I actually think we'll just do better
work if we have more constraints and
we're, um, you know, leaner as an organization.
So in a world where we're not
adding so many people as quickly,
is it as valuable
to have a lot of managers who have extra capacity waiting
for new people?
No, right?
So, um, so now we can,
we could sort of defragment the organization and get to
a place where the average is close
r to that seven or eight.
Um, and it's, it's just ends up being a somewhat more kind
of compact management structure, which, you know,
decreases the latency on information going up
and down the chain and I think empowers people more.
But I mean that's an example that I
think it doesn't kind of undervalue
the importance of management,
and the kind of the personal growth
or coaching that people need in order to do their jobs.
Well, it's just, I think realistically,
we're just not going to hire as many people going forward.
So I think that you need a different structure.
This whole, this whole incredible hierarchy
and network of humans that make up a company is fascinating.
Oh, yeah.
Uh, yeah.
How do you hire great teams?
How do you hire great now with the focus on engineering
and technical teams?
How do you hire great engineers
and great members of technical teams?
Well, you're asking how you select
or how you attract them.
Both, but select.
I think, uh, I think attract is work on cool stuff
and have a vision.
I think that's right.
And, and, and have a track record that people
think you're actually going to be
able to do it.
Yeah, to, to me, the select is,
seems like more of the art form, more of the tricky thing.
Yeah.
How do you select the people that fit the culture
and can get integrated the most
effectively and so on.
And maybe, yeah, especially when they're young to see like,
to see the magic through
the, through the resume, through the paperwork
and all this kind of stuff to
see that there's a special human there
that would do like incredible work.
So there are lots of different cuts on this question.
I mean, I think when an organization has grown quickly,
one of the big questions
that teams face is, do I hire this person
who's in front of me now because they
seem good, or do I hold out to get someone
who's even better?
And the heuristic that I always focused on for myself
and my own kind of direct
hiring that I think works when you,
when you recurse it through the organization
is that you should only hire someone to be
on your team if you would be happy
working for them in an alternate universe.
And so that, that kind of works.
And, you know, that's basically how I've tried
to build my team.
It's, you know, I'm not, I'm not in a rush
to not be running the company, but I
think in an alternate universe where one
of these other folks was running the
company, I'd be happy to work for them.
I feel like I'd learn from them.
I respect their kind of general judgment.
They're, they're all very insightful.
They have good values.
Um, and, and I think that that gives you some rubric for,
you can apply that at every layer.
And I think if you apply that at
every layer in the organization,
then you'll have a pretty strong organization.
Um, okay.
In an organization that's not growing as quickly,
the questions might be a little different though.
Um, and there you asked about young people specifically,
like people out of college, and one of the things
that we see is it's, it's a pretty basic lesson,
but like we have a much better sense
of who the best people are, who have
interned at the company for a couple of months,
then by looking at them at, at,
at, at kind of a resume or a short,
or a short interview loop.
I mean, obviously the in-person feel that you get
from someone probably tells
you more than the resume, um,
and you can do some basic skills assessment.
But a lot of the stuff really just is cultural.
People thrive in different environments
and, um, and on different teams, even
within a specific company,
and it's, it's like the people who come for even a
short period of time over a summer,
who do a great job here, you know, that
they're going to be great if they,
if they came and joined full time.
And that's, you know, one of the reasons
why we've invested so much in
internship is, um, is basically it just,
it's a very useful sorting function,
both for us and for the people who want
to try out the company.
You mentioned in-person,
what do you think about remote work, a topic that's
been discussed extensively because of the,
over the past few years, because of the pandemic?
Yeah.
I mean, I think it's, I mean
it's a thing that's here to stay.
Um, but I think that there's, there's value in both, right?
It's not, um, you know, I wouldn't want
to run a fully remote company yet at least.
I think there's an asterisk on that, which is that,
which is that some of the
other stuff you're working on.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
It's like all the, all the, um, you know,
metaverse work and the ability to be, to
feel like you're truly present, no matter where you are.
I think once you have that all dialed in, then we may,
you know, one day reach a point
where it really just doesn't matter
as much where you are physically.
Um, but I don't know, today it, today it still does, right?
So yeah, for people who, there are all these people
who have special skills and want to live in a place
where we don't have an office,
or are we better off having them at the company?
Absolutely.
Right.
And are a lot of people who work at the company
for several years and then, you
know, build up the relationships internally, um,
and kind of have the trust and have a
sense of how the company works.
Can they go work remotely now if they want
and still do it as effectively?
And we've done all these studies that show it's like,
okay, does that affect their performance?
It does not.
Um, but, you know, for the new folks who are joining,
um, and for people who are
earlier in their career and you don't need to learn
how to solve certain problems
and need to get ramped up on the culture.
Um, you know, when you're working through
really complicated problems where you
don't just want to sit in the,
you don't just want the formal meeting,
but you want to be able to like brainstorm
when you're walking in the hallway together
after the meeting.
Um, I don't know.
It's like we, we just haven't replaced the kind
of in-person dynamics
there yet with, with, with anything remote yet.
So yeah, there's a magic to the in-person
that we'll talk about this a little
bit more, but I'm really excited by the possibilities
in the next two years and
virtual reality and mixed reality that are possible
with high resolution scans.
I mean, uh, I, as a person who loves in-person interaction,
like these podcasts
in person, it would be incredible
to achieve the level of realism.
I've gotten a chance to witness,
but let me ask about that.
Yeah.
I got a chance to, uh, look at the quest three headset
and it is amazing.
Um, you've, you've announced it.
It's, uh, you'll get some more details in the fall.
Maybe release in the fall.
I forgot you, you mentioned it.
We'll give more details of connect,
but, but it's coming, it's coming this fall.
Okay.
So, uh, it's, uh, priced at, uh, $4.99.
What features are you most excited about there?
There are basically two big new things
that we've added to quest three over quest two.
The first is high resolution, mixed reality.
Um, and the, the basic idea here is that you can think
about virtual reality as you
have the headset and like all the pixels are virtual
and you're basically like immersed
in a different world.
Mixed reality is where you see the physical world
around you and you can place virtual
objects in it, whether that's a screen to watch a movie
or a projection of your virtual
desktop, or you're playing a game where like zombies
are coming out through the wall
and you need to shoot them.
Um, or, you know, we're, you know,
we're playing Dungeons and Dragons or some board
game and we just have a virtual version of the board
in front of us while we're sitting here.
Um, all that's possible in mixed reality.
And I think that that is going to be the next big capability
on top of virtual reality.
It is done so well.
I have to say, as a person who experienced it today
with zombies, having a full
awareness of the environment and integrating
that environment in the way they run
at you while they try to kill you.
So it's, it's, uh, it's just the,
the mixed reality that passed through is really,
really, really well done.
Uh, and the fact that it's only
$500 is really, it's, uh, well done.
Thank you.
I mean, I'm, I'm, I'm super excited about it.
I mean, our, and we put a lot of work into making the device
both as good as
possible and as affordable as possible because a big part
of our mission and ethos
here is we, we, we want people to be able
to connect with each other.
We want to reach and we want to
serve a lot of people, right?
We want to bring this technology to, to everyone, right?
So we're not just trying to serve like a, you know, an elite
, a wealthy crowd.
We, we want to, um, we really want this to be accessible.
So that, that is in a lot of ways,
an extremely hard technical problem because
you know, we don't just have the ability
to put an unlimited amount of hardware.
And thus we needed to basically deliver something
that works really well, but in
an, an affordable package.
And we started with Quest pro last year
and it was, um, it's, it's, it was $1,500.
Um, and now we've, we've lowered the price to a thousand,
but in a lot of ways, the
mixed reality in quest three is an even better
and more advanced level than what
we were able to deliver in quest pro.
So I'm really proud of where we are with,
with, um, with quest three on that it's
going to work with all of the virtual reality titles
and everything that, that existed there.
So people who want to play fully immersive games,
social experiences, fitness, all that stuff will, will work,
but now you'll also get mixed reality too.
Um, which I think people really like
because it's sometimes you want to
be super immersed in a game, but a lot of the time,
especially when you're moving around, if you're active,
like you're, you're doing some fitness experience.
Um, you know, let's say you're
like doing boxing or something.
It's like, you kind of want to be
able to see the room around you.
So that way you know that like,
I'm not going to punch a lamp or something like that.
Um, and I don't know if you got
to play with this experience,
but we basically have
the, and it's just sort of like a fun little, little demo
that we put together.
But it's, um, it's like, you just, you know,
we're like in a conference room or
you're living room and you, you have, um,
the guy there and you're boxing him
and you're fighting him and it's like,
Oh, the other people are there too.
I got a chance to do that.
Yeah.
And all the people are there.
Uh, it's like that guy is right there.
Yeah.
And the other human,
the path that you're seeing them also,
they can cheer you on.
They can make fun of you
if there are anything like friends of mine.
And then just it, yeah, it, it, it, it's really,
it's a really compelling experience.
I mean, VR is really interesting too,
but this is something else almost.
This is, this becomes integrated into your life,
into your world.
Yeah.
And it, so I think it's a completely new capability
that will unlock a lot of different content
and I think it'll also just make
the experience more comfortable
for a set of people who didn't want
to have only fully immersive experiences.
I think if you want experiences
where you're grounded in, you know, your
living room in the physical world around you,
now you'll be able to have that too.
And I think that that's pretty exciting.
I really liked how it added windows to a room
with no windows.
Yeah.
Me as a person.
where you could see the sharks swim up
or was that just a zombie one?
Just a zombie one.
But it's still, you don't necessarily want windows added
to your living room where zombies come out of.
But yeah, so the context of that game,
it's, yeah, yeah, yeah, it's good.
I enjoyed it because you could see the nature outside.
And me as a person that doesn't have windows,
it's just nice to have nature.
Yeah.
Well, even if it's a mixed reality setting,
it's, it's kind of, like there's a, I
know it's a zombie game, but there's a Zen nature,
Zen aspect to being able to
look outside and alter your environment as you know it.
Yeah.
In, you know, there'll probably be better,
more Zen ways to do that than the
zombie game you're describing,
but you're right that the, the basic idea
of sort of having your physical environment
on pass through, but then being able to
bring in different elements, external,
I mean, I think it's going to be super powerful.
And in some ways, I think that these are mixed reality
is also a predecessor to
eventually we will get AR glasses that are not kind
of the goggles form factor of the current generation
of headsets that, that people are making.
Um, but I think a lot of the experiences
that developers are making for mixed
reality of basically you just have a kind
of a hologram that you're putting in the
world will hopefully apply once we,
once we get the, the AR glasses too.
Now that's got its own whole set of challenges.
And it's, um,
Well, the headset is already smaller
than the previous version.
Oh yeah, it's 40% thinner.
And the other thing that I think
mixed reality was the first big thing.
The second is it's just a great VR headset.
It's, I mean, it's got two X,
the graphics processing power,
um, 40% sharper screens,
know, if you liked quest two,
I think that this is just going to be, you know, it's
like all this, all the content that you might have played
in quest two is just going to be sharper automatically
and look better in this.
So it's, um, I think people are really going to like it.
Yeah.
So this fall,
This fall, I have to ask Apple just announced
a mixed reality headset called
Vision Pro for $3,500 available in early 2024.
What do you think about this headset?
Well, I saw the materials, um, when they launched,
I, I haven't gotten a chance
to play with it yet.
So, so, so kind of take everything with a grain of salt,
but a few high level
thoughts, I mean, first, um, you know,
I do think that this is a certain level
of validation for the category right where, you know,
we were the primary folks
out there before saying,
Hey, I think that this, you know, virtual reality,
augmented reality, mixed reality,
this is going to be a big part
of the next computing platform.
Um, I think having Apple come in and share that vision,
um, we'll make a lot
of people who are fans
of their products, um, really consider that.
Um, and then, you know, of course, the, the $3,500 price,
um, you know, on the one hand,
I get it for with all the stuff
that they're trying to pack in there.
On the other hand, a lot of people aren't going to find
that to be affordable.
So I think that there's a chance that,
that them coming in actually increases
demand, um, for the overall spac
e and that quest three is actually the primary
beneficiary of that because a lot of the people
who might say, Hey, you know,
this, uh, I think I'm going to
give another consideration to this
or, you know, now I understand maybe
what mixed reality is more and in quest three is
the best one on the market that I can, that I can afford.
Um, and it's great also, right?
It's, I think that that's, um, and, you know,
in our own way, I think we're,
and there are a lot of features
that we have where we're leading on.
Um, so I think that that's, that,
that I think is going to be a very,
that could be quite good.
Um, and then obviously over time,
the companies are just focused on,
somewhat different things, right?
Apple has always, um, you know,
I think focused on building really kind of high
end things, whereas our focus has been on,
it's just, we have a more
democratic ethos.
We want to build things that are accessible
to a wider number of people.
Um, you know, we've sold tens of millions
of quest devices.
Um, my understanding, just based on rumors,
I don't have any special knowledge
on this is that Apple is building about 1 million of their,
of their device.
Right.
So just in terms of like what you kind of expect
in terms of sales numbers.
Um, I, I just think that this is,
I mean, quest is going to be the primary
thing that people in the market will continue using
for the foreseeable future.
it's up to the companies to see how,
how well we've executed the different things
that we're doing, but we kind of
come at it from different places.
We're very focused on social interaction,
communication, um, being more active, right?
So there's fitness, there's gaming, there are those things.
Um, you know, whereas I think a lot of the use cases
that you saw in, um, in, in
Apple's launch material were more around, you know,
people sitting, um, you know,
people looking at screens, um, which are great.
I think that you will replace your laptop over time
with, with a, with a headset.
But, um, but I think in terms
of kind of how the different use cases that the
companies are going after, um,
they're, they're, they're, they're a bit different
for, for, for where we are right now.
Yeah.
So their gaming wasn't a big part of the presentation,
which is an interesting,
it feels like mixed reality gaming, such a big part of that.
It was interesting to see it missing in the presentation.
Well, I mean, look, there are certain design trade-offs
in this where, you know,
they only made this point about
not wanting to have controllers,
which on the one
hand, there's a certain elegance about just being able
to navigate the system
with eye gaze and hand tracking.
And by the way, you're,
you'll be able to just navigate quest with, with your
hands too, if that's what you want.
Um, yeah, one of the things I
should mention is the capability
from the cameras to, uh, with computer vision
to detect certain aspects of the hand,
allowing you to have a controller
that doesn't have that ring thing.
Yeah.
The hand tracking in quest three and the,
and the tracking is, is a big step
up from, from the last generation.
Um, and one of the demos that we have is basically
an MR experience teaching you
how to play piano, where it basically highlights the notes
that you need to
play and it's like just all its hands, it's no controllers.
But I think if you care
about gaming, having a controller allows you to
have a more tactile feel and allows you to capture
fine motor movement much more precisely
than what you can do
that you're touching.
So again, I think it's, there, there are certain question
s which are just around
what use cases are you optimizing for?
Um, I think if you want to play games,
then I think that that, that I think
you want, you, you want to design
the system in a different way
and, and we're
more focused on, on kind of social experiences,
entertainment experiences.
Um, whereas if, if what you want is to make sure
that the text that you read
on a screen is as crisp as possible,
then you need to make the, the design
and cost trade-offs that they made that,
that lead you to making a $3,500 device.
So I think that there is a use case for that for sure.
But I just think that they're, they've, the company is,
we've basically
made different design trade-offs to,
to get to, um, the use cases that we're trying to serve.
There's a lot of other stuff I
would love to talk to you about,
about the metaverse, especially the Kodak avatar, uh,
which I've gotten to experience
a lot of different variations
of recently that I'm really, really excited about.
Yeah, I'm excited to talk about that too.
I'll, I'll have to wait a little bit because well,
I think there's a
lot more to show off in that regard.
Uh, but let me step back to AI.
I think we've mentioned it a little bit,
but I'd like to linger on this question
that, uh, folks, folks like Elias or Yadkowski has to worry
about, uh, and others
of the existential, the serious threats of A
I that have been reinvigorated now
with the rapid developments of AI systems.
Uh, do you worry about the existential risks of AI as Elias
or does about the
alignment problem about this getting out of hand?
Anytime where there's a number of serious people
who are raising a concern
that is that existential
about something that you're involved with, I think
you have to think about it.
Right.
So I've spent quite a bit of time thinking
about it from that perspective.
Um, the thing that, that I were,
where I basically have come out on this for
now is I, I do think that there are, over time,
I think that we need to think
about this even more as we, as we approach something that,
you know, could be closer to superintelligence.
I just think it's pretty clear to anyone
working on these projects today that
we're, that we're not there.
Um, and one of my concerns is that we, we, we, we spend
a fair amount of time
on this before, but there are more, um,
I don't know if mundane is the right word,
but there's like concerns that already exist right
about like people using AI
tools to do harmful things of the
type that we're already aware,
whether, youknow, we talked about fraud or scams
or different things like that.
Um, and that's going to be a pretty big set of challenges
that the companies
with regardless of whether there
is an existential concern as
well at some point down the road.
So I do worry that to some degree you can,
people can get a little too focused
on, on some of the tail risk and then not do as good
of a job as we need to on
the things that you are, can be almost certain are going
to come down the
pipe as, um, as, as real risks
that, that, that, that kind of manifest themselves
in the near term.
So for me, I've, I've spent most of my time
on that once I kind of made the
realization that the size of models
that we're talking about now in terms of
what we're building are, are just quite far
from the superintelligence type
concerns that, um, that, that people raise,
but, but I think once we get a
couple of steps closer to that, um,
I know as we do get closer, I think that
those, you know, there are going to be some novel,
um, risks and issues about
how we make sure that the systems are safe for sure.
I guess here, just to take the conversation
in a somewhat different
direction, I think in some of these debates around safety,
I think the
concepts of intelligence and autonomy,
or like the, the, the being of the
thing, um, you know, as an analogy,
they get kind of conflated together.
And I think it very well could be the case
that you can make something and
scale intelligence quite far,
but that, that may not manifest the safety
concerns that people are saying in the sense that
, I mean, just if you, if you
look at human biology, it's like, all right,
we have our neocortex is where
all the, the thinking happens, right?
And it's, but, but it's not really calling the shot
s at the end of the day.
We have a much more, you know, primitive old brain structur
e for which our
neocortex, which is this powerful machinery
is basically just a kind of
prediction and reasoning engine to help it kind of like
our, our very simple brain.
Um, decide how to plan and do what it needs to do in order
to achieve these
like very kind of basic impulses.
And I think that you can think about some
of the development of intelligence
along the same lines where just like
our neocortex doesn't have free will or autonomy.
Um, we might develop these wildly intelligent systems
that are much more
intelligent than our neocortex have much more capacity,
but are, you know, the
same way that our neocortex is sort of subservient
and is used as a tool by our,
our kind of simple impulse brain.
It's, um, you know, I think that it's not out
of the question that very
that have the capacity to think we'll, we'll kind of
act as that is sort of an extension
of, of, of the neocortex doing that.
So I think my, my own view is that where we really need
to be careful is on
the development of autonomy
and how we think about that.
Because, um, it's actually the case that relatively simple
and unintelligent
things that have runaway autonomy
and just spread themselves or, you know,
it's like, we have a word for that.
It's a virus, right?
It's, I mean, like it's, can be simple computer code
that is not particularly
intelligent, but just spreads itself and does a lot of harm,
um, biologically or
computer and, um, I just think that these
are somewhat separable things.
And a lot of what I think we need to develop
when people talk about
safety and responsibility is really the governance
on the autonomy that can be
given to, to systems.
And to me, if, you know, if I were, you know,
a policymaker is, or think about
this, I would really want to think about that distinction
between these where I
think building intelligent systems will be
, can create a huge advance in terms
of people's quality of life
and productivity growth in the economy.
But it's the, the autonomy part
of this that I think we really need to make
progress on how to govern these things responsibly
before we build the
capacity for them to make a lot of decisions on their own
or, or give them
goals or things like that.
And I know that that's a research problem,
but I do think that to some degree
these are, are somewhat, are somewhat separable things.
I love the distinction between intelligence
and autonomy and, and the metaphor within your cortex.
Let me ask about power.
So, uh, building superintelligence systems,
even if it's not in the near term, I
think meta as is one of the few companies,
if not the main company that will
develop the superintelligence system
and you are a man who's at the head of this
company, building AGI might make you
the most powerful man in the world.
Do you worry that that power will corrupt you?
What a question.
Um, I mean, look, I think realistically this gets back
to the open source
things that we talked about before,
which is I don't think that the world will
be best served by any small number of organizations
having this without it being
something that is more broadly available.
And I think if you look through history,
it's when there are these sort of like
unipolar advances and things that,
and like power imbalances that they're,
they're, they're doing to being kind of weird situations.
So this is one of the reasons why I think open sources is,
is generally the right approach.
And, you know, I think it's a,
it's a categorically different question today when
we're not close to superintelligence,
I think that there's a good chance that even
once we get closer to superintelligence,
open sourcing remains the right approach,
even though I think at that point
it's a somewhat different debate.
Um, but I think part of that is that that is, you know,
I think one of the best
ways to ensure that the system is as secure
and safe as possible, because
it's not just about a lot of people having access to it.
It's the scrutiny that, that, that kind of comes with being,
with building an open
this is a pretty widely accepted
thing about open
sources that, um, you know, you have the code out there
so anyone can see the
vulnerabilities, um, anyone can,
can kind of mess with it in different ways.
People can spin off their own projects
and an experiment in a ton of different
ways.
And the net result of all of that is that the systems
just get hardened and get
to be a lot safer and more secure.
Um, so I think that there's a chance that that ends up
being the way that this
goes to a pretty good chance and that having this be open,
both leads to a
healthier development of the technology
and also leads to a more balanced,
um, distribution of the technology in a way that,
that strike me as good values
to aspire to.
So to you, the risks, there's risks to open sourcing,
but the benefits
outweigh the risks at, at the two, it's interesting.
I think the way you put it, uh, you put it well,
that there's a different
discussion now than when we get closer
to the, uh, to development of super
intelligence of, of the benefits and risks of open sourcing.
Yeah.
And to be clear, I, I feel quite confident
in the assessment that open sourcing
models now is net positive.
I think there's a good argument that in the future,
it will be two, even as you
get closer to super intelligence,
but I've not, I'm, I've certainly have not
decided on that yet.
And I think that it becomes a somewhat more complex set
of questions that I
think people will have time to debate
and will also be informed by what happens
between now and then and to make those decisions.
We don't have to necessarily just
debate that in theory right now.
Uh, what year do you think we'll have a super intelligence?
I don't know.
I mean, that's pure speculation.
I think it's, uh, I think it's
very clear to take a step back
that we had a big
breakthrough in the last year, right?
Where the, the LLMs and diffusion
models basically reached a,
a scale where
they're able to do some, some pretty interesting things.
And then I think the question is what happens
from here and just to paint
the two extremes on the, um, on, on one side, it's like,
okay, we just had one
breakthrough.
If we just have like another breakthrough like that,
or maybe two, then we
can have something that's truly crazy, right?
And, and is like, is, um, just like so much more advanced
and, and on, on that
side of the argument, it's like, okay,
well, maybe we're, um, and maybe we're
only a couple of big steps away
from, uh, from, from, from reaching something
that looks more like general intelligence.
Okay.
That's one, that's one side of the argument.
And the other side,
which is what we've historically seen a lot more is that a
breakthrough leads to, um, you know, in that
, in that Gartner hype cycle, there's
like the hype and then there's the trough
of disillusionment after when like
people think that there's a chance that,
Hey, okay, there's a big breakthrough.
Maybe we're about to get another big breakthrough.
And it's like, actually, you're not about to get
another breakthrough.
You're, maybe you're actually just going to have to sit
with this one for a while.
And, um, and you know, it could be,
it could be five years, it could be 10 years.
It could be 15 years until you figure out
the, um, the kind of the next big thing
that needs to get figured out.
And, um, but I think that the fact that we just
had this breakthrough sort of
makes it's that we're at a point
of almost a very wide error bars on what happens
next.
Yeah.
Um, I think the traditional technical view,
like looking at the industry would
suggest that we're not just going
to stack in a like breakthrough on top of
breakthrough on top of breakthrough,
like every six months or something right now.
I think it will, I'm guessing, I would guess that it will,
that it will take
somewhat longer in between these,
but, um, I don't know, I tend to be pretty
optimistic about breakthroughs too.
So I mean, so I think if you,
if you, if you normalized for, for my normal optimism,
then, then maybe it would be even,
even slower than what I'm saying.
But, but even within that,
like I'm not even opining on the question of how many
breakthroughs are required to get to general intelligence
because no one knows.
But this particular breakthrough was so such a small step
that resulted in such
a big leap in performance as experienced
by human beings that it makes you think,
wow, are we, as we stumble across this very open
world of research,
will we stumble, um, across another thing
that will have a giant leap in performance.
And, um, also we don't know exactly
at which stage is it really going to be
impressive because it feels like it's really encroaching
on impressive levels
of intelligence.
You still didn't answer the question
of what year we're going to have super
intelligence.
I'd like to hold you to that.
No, I'm just kidding.
But is there something you can say
about the timeline as you think about the
development of, um, AGI superintelligence systems?
Sure.
So I, I still don't think I have any particular insight
on when like a singular
AI system that is a general intelligence will get created.
But I think the one thing that most people
in the discourse that I've seen
about this haven't really grappled
with is that we do seem to have.
Organize organizations and, you know,
structures in the world that exhibit
greater than human intelligence already.
So, you know, one example is, you know,
a company, you know, it acts as an
entity, it has, you know, a singular brand.
Um, obviously it's a collection of people,
but I, I certainly hope that, you
know, meta with tens of thousands
of people make smarter decisions than one
person, but I think that that would be pretty bad
if it didn't.
Um, another example that I think is even more removed
from kind of the way we
think about like the personification
of, of, um, of intelligence, which is often
implied in some of these questions is think
about something like the stock market
where the stock market is, you know,
it takes inputs, it's a distributed system.
It's like the cybernetic organism that, you know,
probably millions of people
around the world are basically voting every day
by choosing what to invest in.
But it's basically this, this organism
or structure that is smarter than any
individual that we use to allocate capital
as efficiently as possible around the
world.
And I, I do think that this notion
that there are already these cybernetic
systems that are either melding the intelligence
of multiple people together
or melding the intelligence of multiple people
and technology together
to form something which is dramatically
more intelligent than any individual on the,
in the world, um, is something that seems to exist
and that we seem to be able to
harness in a productive way for our society as long
as we basically build these structures
and balance with each other.
Um, so I don't know.
I mean, that, that at least gives me hope
that as we advance the technology,
and I don't know how long exactly it's going to be, but
you asked when is this going to exist?
I think to some degree we already have
many organizations in the world
that are smarter than a single human.
And, and that seems to be something
that is generally productive in advancing humanity.
And somehow the individual AI systems empower
the individual humans and the interaction between
those humans to make that collective intelligence machinery
that you're referring to smarter.
So it's not like AI is becoming super intelligent.
It's just becoming the, uh,
the engine that's making the collective intelligence
is primarily human, more intelligent.
Yeah.
It's, it's educating the humans better.
It's making them better informed.
It's, um,
making it more efficient for them to communicate effectively
and debate ideas.
And through that process,
just making the whole collective intelligence more
and more and more
intelligent, maybe faster than the individual AI systems
that are trained on human data anyway,
are becoming maybe the collective intelligence
and human species might outpace the development of AI.
I think there's a balance in here because I mean,
if, if like, you know,
if a lot of the input that,
that the systems are being trained
on is basically coming from
feedback from people,
then a lot of the development does
need to happen in human time, right?
It's,
it's not like a machine will just be able
to go learn all the stuff about, about how people think
about stuff.
There's, there's a cycle to how this needs to work.
This is an exciting world
we're living in.
And then you're at the forefront of developing.
One of the ways you keep yourself humble,
like we mentioned with Jiu Jitsu,
is doing some really difficult challenges,
mental and physical.
One of those you've done
very recently is the Murph challenge
. And you got a really good time.
It's 100 pull-ups, 200
push-ups, 300 squats,
and a mile before and a mile around after.
You got under 40 minutes on that.
What was the hardest part?
I think a lot of people were very impressed.
It's very impressive time.
Yeah.
I was, I was pretty happy.
How crazy are you?
It was the question.
It wasn't my best time,
but, but I, anything under 40 minutes, I'm happy with.
Yeah.
It wasn't your best time.
No, I think, I think I've done it a little faster before,
but not much.
I mean, it's, and, and of my friends,
I did not win on Memorial Day.
One of my friends
did it actually several minutes faster than me.
But just to clear up one thing that I think was,
I saw a bunch of questions about this on the internet.
There are multiple ways to do,
to do the Murph challenge.
There's a kind of partitioned mode
where you do sets of pull-ups,
push-ups, and squats together.
And then there's unpartitioned
where you do the 100 pull-ups,
and then the 200 push-ups, and
then the 300 squats in cereal.
And obviously, if you're,
you know, if you're doing them
unpartitioned, then, you know,
it takes longer to get through
the 100 pull-ups because you, you know,
anytime you're resting in between the pull-ups, you're not
also doing push-ups and, and squats.
So, so yeah, so my, my, I'm sure
my unpartition time would be,
would be quite a bit slower,
but, but no, I think at the end of this,
I don't know, first of all, I think it's a good way
to honor Memorial Day, right?
It's, you know,
it's this Lieutenant Murphy, basically, this is one of,
this was one of his favorite
exercises, and I just try to do it on,
on Memorial Day each year, and it's a good workout.
I got my older daughters to do it with me this time.
They, my oldest daughter wants a weight vest
because she sees me doing it with a weight vest.
I don't know if a seven-year-old should be using
a weight vest to do pull-ups, but, but, um...
The difficult question a parent must ask themselves,
yes.
I was like, maybe I can make you a very light weight vest,
but, but I, I didn't think it was
good for this.
So she, she basically did a quarter, Murph,
so she ran a quarter mile,
and then did, you know, 25 pull-ups, 50 push-ups,
and, and 75 air squats, then ran another quarter
mile, and like, in 15 minutes,
which I was pretty impressed by, um,
and, and my, my five-year-old too,
so I, so I, I was excited about that,
and I, I'm, I'm glad that I'm teaching them
kind of the value of, of, of physicality, right?
I think a, a good day for Max, my daughter,
is when she gets to like, go to the gym with me
and cranks out a bunch of pull-ups, and I, I, I love
that about her.
I mean, I think it's, it's like, good, she's, you know,
um, hopefully I'm teaching
her some good lessons, but...
I mean, the, the broader question
here is, um, given how busy you
are, given how much stuff you have going on in your life,
what's, um, what's like the perfect
exercise regimen for you to, uh, to keep yourself happy,
to, uh, keep yourself productive in your
main line of work?
Yeah, so I mean, I've, right now,
I'm focused most of my workouts on, on fighting,
so, so Jiu Jitsu and MMA, um, but I don't know.
I mean, maybe if you're a professional, you can
do that every day, I can't, I just can't.
you know, it's too many,
too many bruises and things
that you need to recover from.
So I do that, you know,
three to four times a week.
And then, and then the other day is,
I just try to do a mix of things,
like just cardio conditioning,
strength building, mobility.
So you try to do
something physical every day?
Yeah, I try to, unless I'm just so tired
that I just need to, need to relax.
But then I'll still try to like go
for a walk or something.
I mean, even here, I don't know,
have you been on the roof here yet?
No.
We'll go on the roof after this.
But it's like, we designed this building
and I put a park on the roof.
So that way, that's like my meetings
when I'm just doing kind of a one-on-one
or talking to a couple of people.
I have a very hard time just sitting.
I feel like you get super stiff.
It like feels really bad.
But I don't know, being physical
is very important to me.
I think it's, I do not believe,
this gets to the question about AI.
I don't think
that a being is just a mind.
And I think we're kind of meant
to do things
and like physically
and a lot of the sensations
that we feel are connected to that.
And I think that that's a lot
of what makes you a human
is basically having those,
having that set of sensations
and experiences around that
coupled with a mind
to reason about them.
But I don't know,
I think it's important for balance
to kind of get out,
challenge yourself in different ways,
learn different skills, clear your mind.
Do you think AI in order
to become super intelligent
and AGI should have a body?
It depends on what the goal is.
I think that there's this assumption
in that question
that intelligence should
be kind of person-like.
Whereas, as we were just talking about,
you can have these greater
than single human
like the stock market,
which obviously do not have bodies
and do not speak a language, right?
And just kind of have their own system.
But so I don't know,
my guess is there will be limits
to what a system that is purely in intelligence
can understand about the human condition
without having the same,
not just senses,
but like our body's changes
we get older, right?
And we kind of evolve
and let those very subtle
physical changes just drive a lot
of social patterns
and behavior around like
when you choose to have kids, right?
That's not even subtle,
that's a major one, right?
But like how you design things
around the house.
So yeah, I think if the goal
is to understand people
as much as possible, I think that that's
trying to model those sensations
is probably somewhat important,
but I think that there's a lot of value
that can be created
by having intelligence,
even that is separate
from that is a separate thing.
So one of the features of being human
is that we're mortal, we die.
We've talked about AI a lot,
but potentially replicas of ourselves.
Do you think there will be AI replicas
of you and me
that persist long after we're gone,
that family and loved ones can talk to?
I think we'll have the capacity
to do something like that.
And I think one of the big questions
that we've had to struggle
with in the context
of social networks is who gets
to make that?
And my answer to that in the context
of the work
that we're doing is that should be your choice.
I don't think anyone should be able to choose
to make a Lex spot
that people can choose to talk to
and get to train that.
And we have this precedent
of making some of these calls
where someone can create a page
for a Lex fan club
but you can't create a page
and say that you're a Lex, right?
So I think that similarly, I think,
I mean, maybe someone maybe can make a,
should be able to make an AI
that's a Lex admirer
that someone can talk to,
be your call
whether there is a Lex AI.
Well, I'm open sourcing the Lex.
So you're a man of faith.
What role has faith played in your life
and your understanding of the world
and your understanding of your own life
and your understanding of your work
and how did your work impacts the world?
Yeah, I think that
there's a few different parts of this
that are relevant.
There's sort of a philosophical part
and there's a cultural part.
And one of the most basic lessons
is right at the beginning of Genesis, right?
It's like God creates
the earth and creates people
and creates people in God's image.
And there's the question of,
what does that mean?
that you have about God
at that point in the Old Testament
is that God has created things.
So I always thought that one
of the interesting lessons
from that is that there's a virtue
in creating things
that is like whether it's artistic
or whether you're building things
that are functionally useful
for other people.
I think that that by itself is a good.
And that kind of drives a lot
of how I think about morality
and my personal philosophy around
like what is a good life?
I think it's one
where you're helping the people around you
and you're being a kind
of positive creative force
in the world that is helping
to bring new things
into the world,
whether they're amazing other people, kids,
or just leading to the creation
of different things
that wouldn't have been possible otherwise.
And so that's a value
for me that matters deeply.
And I just love spending time
with the kids
and seeing that they sort of,
trying to impart this value to them.
And it's like, I mean,
nothing makes me happier than like
when I come home from work
and I see like my daughters
like building Legos on the table or something.
It's like, all right,
I did that when I was a kid,
so many other people were doing this.
And like, I hope you don't lose that spirit
where when you kind of grow up
and you wanna just continue
building different things
no matter what it is, to me,
that's a lot of what matters.
That's the philosophical piece.
I think the cultural piece
and values and that part of things,
I think has just
since I've had kids.
You know, it's almost autopilot
when you're a kid,
you're in the kind of getting imparted
to phase of your life,
but, and I didn't really think about religion
that much for a while, you know,
I was in college,
you know, before I had kids
and then I think having kids
has this way of really making you think
about what traditions you want to impart
and how you want to celebrate
and like what balance you want in your life.
And I mean,
a bunch of the questions
that you've asked
and a bunch of the things
Just the irony of the curtains coming down
as we're talking about mortality.
Once again, same as last time,
this is just, the universe works in,
we are definitely living
in a simulation,
but go ahead on community tradition
and the values, the faith
and religion is still.
A lot of the topics
that we've talked about today
are around how do you balance, you know,
whether it's running a company
or different responsibilities with this,
I don't know, yeah,
how do you kind of balance that?
And I always also just think
that it's very grounding
to just believe that there is something
that is much bigger
than you that is guiding things.
That amongst other things gives you
a bit of humility.
As you pursue that spirit
of creating these,
that you spoke to creating beauty
in the world.
As Dostoevsky said,
beauty will save the world.
Mark, I'm a huge fan of yours.
Honored to be able to call you a friend
and I am looking forward to both kicking your ass
and you kicking my ass
on the mat tomorrow in Jiu-Jitsu.
This incredible sport
and art that we both participate in.
Thank you so much for talking to me.
Thank you for everything you're doing
in so many exciting realms
of technology and human life.
I can't wait to talk to you again
in the metaverse.
Thank you.
Thanks for listening
to this conversation
with Mark Zuckerberg.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors
in the description.
And now let me leave you
with some words from Isaac Asimov.
It is change, continuing change,
inevitable change
that is the dominant factor
in society today.
No sensible decision
can be made any longer
without taking into account not
only the world as it is,
but the world as it will be.
Thank you for listening
and hope to see you next time.