i'm here with mr beast
the brilliant mastermind behind some of the most popular videos ever created
do you think you'll ever make a video that gets 1 billion views
i think maybe one of the videos we've already made might get a billion views
which one
do you think
probably like the the squid game video with enough time
i mean it's only a year old and it's already on 300 million
or some of the newer ones we've done have gotten like 100 million views in a month
um
so those four projected over 10 years
because youtube's not going anywhere
probably one of those
so over time they don't necessarily plateau
what's interesting
we're literally jumping right now
i love it
it's good
um
so i i'm a firm believer
that it's much easier to hypothetically get 10 million views on one video
than a hundred thousand on a hundred
and part of why it's much easier in my opinion
is like if you make a really good video
it's just so evergreen
and it never dies
because youtube
when you open up youtube and look at the videos
they're just serving you
whatever they think
you'll like the best you know
and so
if you just make a great video and it's constantly just above every other video
you know
even two years down the road
then they'll just keep serving it
never stop
you know
which is why it's much easier to make one great video than a bunch of mediocre
ones
what about 1 billion subscribers
you've uh
passed
pewdiepie's the most subscribed to youtube channel
uh
when do you think you get a billion
let me do some math real quick
so we're on 120
what do you think about this
no
i don't
honestly
i
because one thing you'll find if you want to gain subscribers
if you want to get views
if you want to make money and almost any metric in this
uh
video creation space
if you want something
it all comes back to
okay
well
then just make great videos
so
instead of like focusing on all these arbitrary vanity metrics
i just kind of focus on the one thing that gets me all that
which is make good videos
but and that
i do think we will when they hit a billion subscribers
i don't have a plan on going anywhere
even though we're only on 120 million right now
on the main channel
i think like we're doing around 10 million a month now
and um youtube
just yeah
i just don't see it going anywhere
and i don't see any reason why i'd ever get burnt out or quit
so i think
with enough time
yes
i wanted to ask you those family friendly questions before i go to the doc question
so now we have dark questions right now
but if you wanted to hook them
you would start off with the dark questions
that's how you get them
okay
well
let me ask you about the uh
a twitter poll
you posted a ten thousand dollar death poll
he tweeted if someone offered you ten thousand dollars
but if you take it
a random person on earth dies
would you take the ten thousand dollars and
uh
forty five percent of people said
yes
that's at least at the time
i checked 850 000 people committing murder for just 8. 5 billion dollars in total
so
uh
what do you learn about human nature from that
that's a a good question
um
honestly
this is like late at night when i threw that up too
i was just like
huh
this will be a funny thing
i assumed it'd be 90 known like 10
yes
but there are a lot of serious people
um
for you guys listening
i just did this random twitter poll i was like
would you take 10 grand if it meant someone random in the world died
and a lot of the replies on this week were like hell
yeah
why not
and i was just not expecting that
um
and so i don't really know
i mean i feel like your take would be better than mine
was it disturbing to you
surprising to you a little bit
yeah
but i
you know
obviously a lot of people were trolling
but i actually
you know
you read through those replies
i do think like 10 of them were like dead serious
well
i think sometimes the trolling
and the laws reveal a thing we're too embarrassed to admit about the darker aspects of our nature
so i don't know if you listen to dan carlin's hardcore history podcast
he has a episode on painful payment
which he describes
throughout history
how humans have been really attracted to watching the suffering of others
so
um
public executions
all that kind of stuff
and he believes that's in all of us
that
for example
if something like a youtube or a different platform
stream to public execution or streamed the torture of another human being
a lot of people would
uh
say that's deeply unethical
but they will still tune in and watch and that
where we're attracted to that drama and especially the most extreme versions of that drama
and so i think part of the laws reveals something that's actually true in that poll that
like your answer is so much better than mine
do you think about that
maybe even with the squid game like
so
i think
how many
how many views
does this game currently have 300
million
yeah
something like this
so just imagine a thought experiment
how many views that video would get if it was like real
yes
because i mean youtube was like
we'll turn the blind out
we won't take it down
yeah
i mean it
i've obviously i probably have billions of views
how do you think you will die and do you think you'll be during a video
probably doing something dumb
like going to space when i'm in the older
like trying to go to mars or something like that
i know
for a fact
it won't be on a video
every video we do with safety experts and stuff like that
so it's not really risk
but um
yeah
i could see myself
like you know
after a million people go to mars or something like that
i'd probably be like
you know what let's go and and something like that
maybe so
not in the name of a video
just no for the holiday
heck
no
are you open to taking risks when you shoot videos
you just went to antarctica
i mean like you're
you're putting yourself in the line a little bit right
of course
but you know
we
we've had that video in the works for three years and then we consult with tons of experts
radar the entire path we're gonna walk beforehand to see if there's crevasses
so we know there's no crevasses
we do training
we consult with experts and we have survival guides there with us and you know
monitor to the weather and everything
so it's like any variable that where we could get harmed
we just pre-planned for it
same thing with buried alive
like i had david blaine spent a week underground
and so i consulted with him and consulted with basically anyone who ever buried themselves alive
you know the coffin we used to bury me we did so many tests
like that
coffin was buried 10 times before i was
you know
for a little way longer than 50 hours
it tested the airflow and everything to the point
where i was safer in that coffin underground than i was above ground
like
so we just tend to just not leave anything up to chance
you know
another strange question
then
so you've recorded these videos to yourself
you know
five years
ten years from now
have you recorded a video that's to be released once you die
well
first off
i am just glad that not every one of your questions have to do with like views
or things like that
it's nice getting different questions so this is
this is good
um
no
seriously stuck
but it's fine
because a lot of people just be like
how much money do you make
you know
it's just something
i
just
everything's always about money
now
for when people talk to me
so it's nice
um
but for the videos i made
uh
for you guys
who probably don't follow me too closely
when i had 8 000 subscribers and i was a teenager
i filmed a bunch of videos and scheduled them years in the future
and i said i'd filmed one where i was like
hi me in a year and the video went up a year later
and it was just like hey
i think you'll have 100 000 subscribers
and then i did one where i was
like
hire me in five years
i was like
hey
in five years
i think you'll have a million
and then one that hasn't come out yet
but it comes out in two years
is
was high me in 10 years
and i try to predict 10 years later
how many subs i'd have
that's what he's referring to
and yes
there
there are some that are scheduled like 20 years in the future
and so if i don't die
i'll just move them up
and i remember
because i filmed these though
like seven years ago
but
uh
it was
i remember saying a line like you know
if i'm dead
then i'm currently just in a coffin and like
whatever
blah
because the only way the video go up is if i'm not alive and if i'm not alive
then i won't be able to push back to schedule upload date
so go public
automatically
yes
and so
yeah
i have a couple of those
uh
like
if i knew i was gonna die of like cancer or something
i had like three months to live
i would vlog every day
i'd film so many videos
and then i would just schedule upload a video a week for like the next five years
so it's like i'm still alive and i would completely act like i'm still alive and everything
and i think something like that would be cool
it's i don't know why
but i've fantasized
not fantasize
but i've dreamed about that
a lot
like
i don't know if
if i only had 30 days to live
what would i do
and for me i would try to make like a decades worth of content and schedule upload it
so they automatically go public in the future
and so it's just like i never died i'm just there
yeah
it's a kind of immortality
but it's also kind of troll on the concept of time
yeah
that you can die in the physical space but persist in the digital space
i actually i recorded a video like that
because i had some concerns and i just thought it's also a good exercise to do
a video would like to be released if i die
and it was actually a really interesting exercise
it's cool
like it shows like what you really care about
i guess it's like writing a will
but when you're younger
you don't think about that kind of stuff
but exactly mine was just dumb
yeah
like i'm bones in a coffin
yours is probably so serious
no
it's fun actually what you realize
it's like there's no point to be serious at this point
it's a weird thing
i guess you've done this
but it's a weird thing to address the world when you
the
physically
you
is no longer there
so
like you know
this would only be released if you're no longer there
exactly
that's a weird exercise
you know what's funny of all the people listening to this
yeah
you know
we're probably the only two people that have made videos for
when we die it's like such a niche thing
and the fact that we're bonding over
it's kind of funny
i think people should think about doing that
it's not just about youtube
it's also social media
because think about it like there's going to be a last tweet and the last
i don't know
facebook post
their last instagram post
and uh
yeah
i feel like there's some aspects that's meditative to just even considering making a post like that
and also it's a way for your
the people that love you to kind of like celebrate
do you think that would help them cope or not like
if someone randomly watching this did film a video
you know
for
if they accidentally died in some freak accident to be given to their family
do you think that would
and it was like a genuine
i think it would really help
i mean it depends
because like
how would you even intro that
like
hey
mom
if you're seeing this
you know
it means i'm probably dead
yeah
exactly
that's how you enjoy it
that's the opener
oh
i just want you to know
yeah
i guess
and i guess you could say in a kind of funny way
but um
and just talk about the things that you that mean a lot to you
because otherwise you're at the risk of the last post you have is like
like i don't know
talking shit about
like mcdonald's mcdonald's exactly
and then you're dead
that's it
100 years
i don't know this
i i do recommend it
it's uh
like the stoics
meditate on death every day
in the same way you kind of meditate in your death when you make a video like that
because it's actually not just even talking to yourself
it's talking to the world and it
like
for some reason
at least
for me
they made it very concrete that there's going to be an end and i'm like
it's almost
it's over for me
if i'm making the video
it's just an interesting thought experiment
i recommend people
um
uh
try it
okay
uh
from
are you afraid of death
by the way
yes
i i
it's hard because like what
if you just die and then you just see nothing forever
you know
yeah
the nothingness
it just fades the blackness
and you're just like that
for trillions upon trillions to billion squared years
and it's just
it's scary
but also before you're born
you don't remember those what x amount of years either
so
um
that gives me a little comfort
but no
it's definitely very scary
something i'd rather not think about until i'm like 80.
i'll deal with that problem
then
i i don't know if i told you this
but i'm kind of hopeful that someone like elon or one of these like freak
smart people will just like be like
you know what
screw it
i'm gonna figure out a way where we can slow down aging
get it where you know
we can live to be two
300 years old and just like set their sights on that
and then
just kind of save us
so it'd be really nice like it's
it's almost absurd to think
that in our lifetime they won't figure out a way to just even slightly slow down aging
where we could live to be like 120 or 130
and then that extra time
they won't figure out somewhere we could live to be 200.
like
obviously not immortal
but i don't
i don't see how in my lifetime
the life expectancy doesn't just expand
well
it also could be that the immortality is achieved in the digital realm
like it could be a long
be
long after you're gone
there's a mr beast
run by chad gbt type system
exactly
yeah
that consumes everything i ever said
everything i ever wrote and thought i don't want that
i want to live
what are you
smart people out there
figure it out
i'll keep you entertained
but i need you to figure out how to keep me alive
give me until 200. that will make me happy
well
that's
that's funny
who owns the identity of of mr beast wants
the physical body is gone
like
is it illegal to create another mr beast
that's chad gpt based
i don't know what the laws are on that
yeah
like
i mean
once i'm done i don't care
well
but you just said you did care
i mean there could be a ai
like many mr beasts that are created after after you're gone
yeah
i mean that would be cool to be able to like train up a model
and and let them loose
so my content lives on
i guess
yeah
but it somehow feels like it diminishes the video you contribute
it's an authentic
but it's also
there's
there's some aspect to the finiteness of the art being necessary for it
yeah
i want the second that thing starts spamming out videos
the videos lose all meaning and it's pointless
and it's a money grab
if you run youtube for
uh
how long should you run it for a year
how would you change it
how would you improve
it
it's hard because you know
obviously i'm biased because we're doing really well
but i feel like when i open up youtube on my television
i get the videos i want to watch
i don't
i don't know
i don't ever open it and wonder like what are these
what are these 10 videos on my home page
when i click on video messages
i don't ever wonder what these are
like
i
i and maybe
it's because i'm very adamant about
like the kind of videos i watch
and i try not to watch videos that i don't want to get recommended more
because i just that's how i think
but i'm very happy with how it is
at the moment
i think one thing though that i just hate with the passion is the comment section on youtube
it's just so bad
um
but that i know that's not something that's gonna 10x the growth of the platform
but if you think about it
you go to reddit to read comments and somehow like that
you know usually the top 20 posts
uh
on a popular reddit post are not spam
you know what i mean
like
have you ever clicked on something on the front page of reddit
and then most upvoted reply to it is like go check out my site right here
and it's like trying to escape me out of a thousand dollars
yeah
i can't even think of one instance i've ever had that happen
so
like reddit
it's so nice to click on post and just see what people have to say
and i almost wish
like you had that same feeling when you read the comments a youtube video
instead
it's like it's so many people just copy
and pasting so many bots that just grab the top comment from your previous video and paste it over
so top comments on every videos are the same
and the things
that break through
that are just scammers trying to get you to give them a thousand dollars for a free
uh
you know
fake ad
that comment section is one of the most lively on the internet
so be amazing if youtube invested in creating an actual community like
where people could do high effort comments and be rewarded for it
like on reddit
yeah
like
actually right out along
that would make me so happy
because like when i upload a video
i usually go to twitter to see feedback
like i read my comments and i'll flip through newest
but it's just i feel like to read it
and twitter just give me so much better filtered feedback
especially now that
with twitter
blue
because people pay eight dollars a month
um
any
i've noticed
like any tweets i get from verified users now they're usually not just garbage troll takes
like these are people paying eight dollars a month
like they're usually relatively sensible
and so it's been pretty nice
like
after i upload my video
just go on the verified tab on twitter and just see what people have to say
and yeah
anyways
i live for the day that youtube's like that
uh
what do you think about twitter
what do you think about all the fun activity happening recently since
uh
elon
yeah
bought twitter
i think you should make me ceo like i tweeted
well
i should
i should say
sort of we had with
just like a couple hours ago
had a conversation with elon
and
uh
you guys had an exchange of some excellent ideas
so
yeah
i
i legitimately think obviously you're exceptionally busy
but i legitimately think it would be awesome if you somehow participate in the future of twitter
yeah
it would be fun because there's so much possibility of different ideas
first in the sort of the
uh
the content like dissemination
hosting and all the different recommendations like the search and discovery
all the things that youtube does
well
i think the most exciting thing is he's
you know
willing to move fast
and so i think there's going to be a lot of interesting things that come out of it
because he's just moving quick
and a lot of these more mature platforms just take years to do the simplest stuff
and they're very bureaucratic
and um
so it's gonna
i mean it'll be interesting to see which way it goes
when you just kind of take a move
quick break things
whatever type approach to social media
i'm actually pretty curious to see what futures he rolls out
so what will be your first uh
act as twitter ceo
i can't spoil it
okay
i gotta get hired
what do you think about video on the platform
i mean
yeah
do you think that's an interesting
or is it like messing with the the medium
the nature of the platform
i think twitter will always be closer to tick tock than it is to youtube
but i gotta
at least in this current form
i
i don't
i don't see 20 minute
one hour long videos or whatever
you know
even 15 minute videos being watched over there
i see it more as like the short and snappy stuff
closer to tick tock
but at the same time
twitter is a really good comment section for the internet
i mean it's almost weird
why
like
why doesn't twitter allow you to embed youtube videos
why
why does that
you should just ask elon that
like
i don't know if that's a youtube thing
but when
uh
youtuber posts the video
why do they have to link to youtube
why can't they just embed it on twitter and just play it there
i mean
wouldn't that just solve a lot of problems
yeah
but then the two companies that have to agree to integrate each other's content
i don't know
but it seems like a win-win i mean
well
it's more of a win for twitter
because then people don't have to leave the platform
i mean that would be the the easiest
but who gets
like
when you watch the ads on a youtube video that's embedded in twitter
who gets the money
it would still be youtube
but at least then
right now people just post a link
and it takes you off twitter and it just kills your session time on twitter
that's really interesting
but that
yeah
because the twitter
whatever the
the dynamics of the comments
especially once the spam bots are taken care of
twitter just works
it's really
so
reddit is a nice comment section for the internet
it's like slower pace
more deliberate
like a higher effort
twitter's like this high paced
like ephemeral kind of stream
but there's the vote
the upvoting
the downvoting works much better because you can do retweeting right
because the social network is much stronger than it is on youtube
like the interconnectivity
yeah
on reddit
you're gonna get the
the top replies are going to be the most refined ones
whereas twitter stuff floats to the top
that's not super refined
but
like you're saying
it's more off the cuff stream of consciousness
which a lot of people prefer gets a little more personal
how do you think twitter compares to youtube in terms of how you see its future unroll in 2023.
i mean i think youtube's gonna be youtube
and not much is really going to change
but it's going to keep growing just
because you know that's just what it does and because it's owned by google
um
but twitter
i don't know
i mean it's one of those things like you
you can't predict if i
you know
a year from now
an economy is going to be in a recession or booming
and i think twitter's kind of the same thing
one thing
for certain
a lot of things are going to be rolled out
but who knows honestly
you responded to elon saying twitter's unlikely to be able to pay creators more money than youtube
um
what do you think that is
well
yeah
because i i think the tweet i responded to is one where he was saying
um
that they
you know
users will jump over if twitter could potentially pay more
uh
than other platforms
and i was just saying
obviously
because google has google adwords and i mean that's google's whole thing
it's putting ads on stuff they've been doing it better
than anywhere else in the world for a very long time
it's very unlikely in the next few years that twitter is going to magically or any platform
you know
give a creator the ability to make higher cpms than on youtube
uh
it's
it's kind of crazy like some creators in in december
you know q4
because ad rates are higher because of christmas and everything
some creators literally make like 30
40 per thousand views
that's after youtube's cut like
it's almost like hard to think about
like how high the rpms get
and even then
once you pull out a financing cars
the highest cfm niches and you move into just normal stuff
it's still just crazy
the sheer volume of creators and the fact that all of them get these multi-dollar cpms at scales
it's pretty beautiful
so you do
i don't know what you would call them
but like integrated ads in your videos
and you do
i would say
masterfully
it's like part of the video you're talking about brand deals
brand deals
is that what you would call that
yep
so it's a brand deal
it's part of the video
it's still really exciting to watch
and yet there's a plug for the brand in general
just brand deals
since you brought it up
uh
integrating them
well
i think that's something a lot of creators don't do like
they'll just do a brand deal
out of the blue
they'll just be filming a video and then around the three minute mark
just start talking about a random company
yeah
and you
i feel like if you don't want viewers to click away
and you want people to not get pissed off and call you to sell out
you got to find a way to integrate in the content
and ideally use the money in the video to make it better
like
is the easiest thing you do
when you do a brand deal is just tell people how you're using money from the brand deal to make your content better
and if you do that
like
no one cares now they're supporting you for it
and you go from being a sellout to like
oh
i'm doing this to make better videos for you guys
you know
i don't know if you can share
but with those brands
when you have discussions with them
are they strict about how long you need to be talking about it
or is it more about their leaving control to you
about the artistic element of it
the problem is the the ones who don't give us the artistic element
we just don't really work with anymore
because it's just
you know
we get 100 million views of video now
and i can confidently say
i know how to entertain them and convert them better than these random brands
so
uh
yeah
if they don't give us that freedom
i just won't work with them
so you have that leverage
but for smaller creators
it's a lot harder
yeah
and they're
they're gonna just say 45 seconds
here's what you say
take it or leave it
and it's like pretty brutal
because i think
just in general
if brands were more accommodating
to let creators tell their story onto brandon
talk about the brand in a way that felt a little more natural
i i think it'd be less cringe it
people would be less likely to go
and you know
tough times
tap skip
and
uh
obviously it would convert better
but they're just so afraid and they want this standardized thing
say these words and 45 seconds
right here at this three minute mark
yeah
i often think about how to resist that
you just don't do them
though
right
not
on youtube
right
i do an audio
i do ads in the very beginning and i say you can skip them if you want
um
but brandon loves that i don't like the point is they
so the funny thing about podcasts is different than youtube videos
podcast
people actually do listen to ads a lot
because they it's slower paced and they like the the creator voice
like talking about the thing
um
but in general i just don't believe you should be talking about a thing for a minute exactly
and that's going to be effective
i want to see the data for that
i think what's much more fact
it was the way you do ads
which is like integrate into the content
like put a lot of effort into making a part of that
like doing the brand deals
and i just it's difficult to have that conversation
it's like a very strenuous conversation you have to have with with brands
you have to each one at a time
and i just wish there was more of a culture to say
like the quality of the ad read matters a lot more than the uh
like the silly parameters
like the timing of it
like how long it is the placement of it
all that kind of stuff
what percentage of your viewers do you think have seen one of my videos before
what percentage of the viewers on youtube
right
yeah
that's your viewers of the viewers on youtube
though
yes
okay
sure
or all of them
it's just interesting because you're
you're speaking very specifically
like about my brand deal process
and so in my head i'm like
i wonder what percentage of these people even have any idea what he's talking about
that's interesting
i love the thinking about numbers the whole time we're having this conversation
it's all i could think about is like god damn it
he's
there's
probably like 50 of these people have no fucking clue what he's saying
and we're about to torture him for five minutes
yeah
probably
but that's something i can't turn off in my brain
less than 50 is that a good thing or a bad thing
is that exciting to you that that there's like 50 of people
don't
i've not watched the mr beast video
isn't that an opportunity like
yeah
i guess there's an opportunity to grow
i don't know
honestly
i was just kind of excited to hang out with you
yeah
me
too
i mean
who cares
yeah
so it's kind of like having a buddy to go along the journey
as i'm just kind of eating shit and doing my normal ride
it was like kind of fun and also you just say really wise stuff constantly
okay
so
honestly
no
i never even put any thought into
like that
demographics of what i could gain
it's just interesting
because
like my retention brain
when you talk about something i'm instantly like
hmm
what value are they gonna get
how many of them are going to be interested
what percentage of people do
i think we'll lose
and i'm like running all those calculations in the background and that whole conversation
like the law is anyway
it's just something i can't turn off my
like bells were like
this is bad
what are the different strategies for high retention for your videos in general
it's like
how do you cook good food
you know what i mean
that's like the same kind of question i see
so there's so many different ways that you
so it boils down to
i mean
uh
do you think it's at the level of a story
or do you think like literally watching five seconds at a time
am i gonna tune out here
am i going to tune out here
that's all of it
you need the overarching narrative and then you also need the micro
where every second you know needs to be entertaining
and you
basically
what's interesting is the longer people watch something
the more likely they are to keep watching
so you don't have to try as hard in the hypothetically back half of a video as you do in the front like
even right now we're so deep into this
where a lot of people listening are probably just going to keep listening relatively close to the endless
we just have a really boring part of this conversation because they're just they're saying it
they're
they're immersed
um
and so a big like to really boil it down to a simple level
you just want to get people
where they're immersed in the content and then just kind of hold them there
we had this discussion offline and by the way
i should mention that this is like late at night
it is what times
it's uh
nine o'clock and i
uh
i only slept one hour last night because i'm an idiot and i flew to the wrong location
well here we're like
hey
book your hotel on a flight
he's like
no
i got it
we're like you
sure
we can just do it
we always do this
he's like
no
i got it
he's gonna have to rub it in
i know
and then today i come to find out
he flew to the wrong airport
the airport with the uh
our city with a similar name to ours
the same name
same name in a different state
and i was like that's why you should let us book it
and so he saw one hour of sleep and he's literally been dying all day before this podcast
he downed like two things of coffee
we've been going all day hard
uh
yeah
i've been
uh
got to interact with you
i should say that this gave me an opportunity to
i gotta
uh
ride from a stranger and it was an incredible person that got to interact with them
so it's like there's so many kind people around here
just like this kind of southern energy
and then i got to go to a diner because i could you know
there's only one hour between me arriving and having to fly out
so i went to a diner
there's a really kind waitress that called me
uh
honey
so that's a beautiful moment
you know
i was so confused
you tweeted about that and like steel's like
like my assistant
uh
lex isn't here yet and i saw your tweet and i was like he's here
he was like
no
he's still flying
i was like four
like an hour ago
he just tweeted about a nice diner
yeah
it was a diner
it was a diner in a different state
and then you had to fly
over here
yeah
that was
and then i called you
you didn't answer
i was like something's not had enough
yeah
i feel like it's such an idiot because
um
apparently the world
uh
has cities like springfield
right
like there's like
every single state has a springfield
oh
really
but i think so
i think that's whatever
that's like a simpsons joke
right that
like
it's uh
the the city and and the simpsons of springfield
and i think every single state or most of them have a springfield
and the same is true for
like
uh
georgetown
i think the most part
i forget what the most popular one was
but there's like a list of these people get when they run out of ideas
they just keep us
if they're your achilles heel
anyway
i got to
i got to meet a bunch of people from
uh
from your team
it's just an incredible human being
so let me just ask on that topic
how do you hire a great team like
what have you learned about hiring for
um
everything for it for the main channel that you do
uh
for the
the
react again
uh
the the gaming channel to
mr beast burger to
uh
feastables
all that the big thing is especially in this content creation
because it's not like anything that's done on netflix or or different
uh
content
medians
i
i really need people who are coachable and like
really see the value in what i care about
because it's a very specific way of going about things
and it's a like a thing
there's no one like plug and play
like
if netflix wanted to hire someone to do a documentary
there's probably tens of thousands of people you could hire that have worked on documentaries before
but if you want to hire someone to make super viral youtube videos
you know
like we do
there's just no one you you can really pull from
like
sometimes i'll hire people from
uh
game shows right
they have all these preconceived notions about pacing and how a video should be
and you have to spend like the first year like breaking all these habits
and you know
and they think they're better than you
like
a lot of people in traditional think they're better
and they think their way is better than what we do
and so for me it's almost easier to hire people that are just hard workers that are obsessed
and really coachable and just train them how to like
be good at content creation production than to hire someone from like traditional
which is the only way to really do it
because there's not that many youtube channels that have scaled up
so it's not like there's a huge talent pool of people who've worked on youtube channels
um
so it's easier just to train someone than just pull them from traditional
because traditional people
just i don't know they have all these opinions
and things and they just think our way of going about things is dumb
yeah
so you want people who have the humility to have a beginner's mind
even if they have experience
see the value like actually
you'll still get it
it's so crazy
like especially some of my other friends that are skilling up their youtube channels
there's people that will come on and you'll ask them like
what do you want to be doing in five years
and instead of saying
oh
i want to be working on this channel
they'll be like
oh
i hope to be workout movies or this
and they see like working on a youtube channels
the launch pad to go into traditional and it's like
no
like you just don't get it
this is the future is the end goal
this is your career
um
and so i'm just so tired of having those kinds of conversations like
i feel like people really should be coming around
are there like recurring interview questions that you ask is there is there ways to get
yeah
the biggest thing is like what do you want to be doing in 10 years and their answer isn't
you know
making content on youtube
or you know if their answer is anything like movies or traditional stuff like that
it's like just a hell
no
like it just won't even remotely work
oh
so you really want people to believe in the vision of youtube
yeah
i mean
ideally
it's like
oh
working here
you know what i mean
so it's less about the medium and more about just being on a great team that's doing epic stuff
yeah
well
and yeah
the media as well
because those it's just it's hard to put into words
but there's
it's just two completely different ways of going about things you know
like our videos aren't scripted and you know it's a lot more run and gun and when we
if we hypothetically blow up a giant car or whatever
like
you only have one take
you know
i mean
so
um
and it's not scripted
and so you have to over film
overshoot things over compensate for
like the dumb way of going about it
a lot of traditional people would be like
well
just plan what you're gonna say and just playing the angles
you can cut the cameras in half you can save 50 grand
here
you can save
you know
editing this and that and it's like
yeah
but that's not authentic like that's
you know
but you
you get it
it's
it's almost so obvious that it hurts to have to like
constantly have these conversations
but so where we live in
but there's also detail like there's a taste
like i've watched a bunch of videos with you and it's clear to you that you've gotten really good
i don't know what the right word is
style or taste
to be able to know what's good
and not in terms of retention
in terms of
yeah
just stylistically
visually
i don't have to think
i can just watch a video and it just it just screams in my head like this is what
this is what should change
based on the you know million videos i've watched and all these viral videos are consumed
like this is
blah
what's optimal and things like that
it's almost like your brain's like a
you know
like a neural net
like if you consume enough viral videos and enough good content that you just kind of start to like
train your brain to like
see it and see these patterns that happen in all these viral videos
and so that
anytime i watch a video or a movie or anything
i just can't stop thinking about what is optimal
and so it's like it gives me a headache
sometimes when i watch something too slow or i don't think it's optimal
obviously my taste isn't the end-all feel
um
but that's something that kind of torments me
if that makes any sense
oh
you can't enjoy a slow moving
no
i can't movie and and that's not to say
there's attention on the godfather is horrible
yeah
no
exactly
i've tried to watch that movie like three times but and that's not to say
slow movies are bad
like there's an audience for it
it's just obviously not what i've trained my brain to like
and and social media and youtube
right now
like that's just not the meta and in general
like you said
in neural network
you're training your brain in part on actual data
right
so you're actually
it's data driven
so you're looking at like in terms of thumbnails and titles and different aspects of the first five
ten seconds and then throw out the video
the retention
all that you're looking at all that
uh
for your own videos
to understand how to do it better
so that's where the neural network is training
yeah
basically there are ways you can kind of see
like the most view videos on youtube every day
and stuff like that
and i just kind of consume those every single day
and i've been doing that for way too many years
and then you just start to notice patterns like the thumbnails on the most view videos
or videos that go super viral
tend to be clear
tend to not have much clutter
tend to be pretty simple
titles
tend to be less than 50 characters
intros tend to be this
stories tend to be this
and you just kind of like after you see those thousands and then tens of thousands of time
it just starts to click in your head like this is what it looks like
you know
so how are you able to transfer that taste that you've developed to the team
so for like
because you said like broad things
but i'm sure there's a million detailed things like what zoom to use on the face to use in the thumbnail
right
like the answer is
whatever makes the best video
because the problem is the more
which i have so many friends who are like this
they'll make like checklists for their editor or something like you know
uh
this be in this beat and you need to have
like a three part arc
and then this
but the
the problem is
that's how you
the
the more constraints you put on the team
the more repetitive and less innovation you get
and the more like you know
after 10 videos
people are gonna be like
all right
i've already seen this
so to me and i'm 24
and you know i'm probably
my mindset will change over the next 10 years
i just haven't been in this industry too long
but the only way to like
really make innovative content and keep things fresh
is to not put constraints on or put as little as possible
and so that's why i'm very hesitant on all that stuff
because the more i say
the more they're gonna be like
oh
then that's what we do
and then you know
i'll say one time like
oh
you know
ideally
there's a cut every three seconds and the next thing you know
every video
there's like cut every three seconds or whatever
so it's it's hard because i try to give uh
as little train
not training but as little
uh
facts or as possible
and more
just make suggestions
if that makes any
you mean publicly or to your team
to my team
yeah
what's so we talked about
sort of uh teaching your voice or your style
whatever we want to call it to other people on the team
so they can be kind of a mr beast replacement
so what's the process of teaching that
so you don't wanna
no
you're more talking about like
uh
what i would call almost like cloning right like
like tyler and other things like that
yeah
so
when we were hanging out today
i was showing him how we have multiple people and they come
it's
it's almost like talking to the cameras
yeah
it turns slowly to the camera
i was like
anyways
have
it is it weird to you to not be looking at the camera
this whole interview
i constantly have been turning towards the camera like
yeah
i'm talking to him
yes
it's a habit
uh
because my whole life i've just been talking to a camera
who are you thinking about when you're looking at the camera
do you like
imagine somebody
i'm fully thinking about
the person just sitting watching it
and i almost
it's weird
but i'm looking at the camera
i don't see a camera
i'm like in a haze
picturing what the viewer is seeing when they watch it
yeah
that makes sense
and that's where i'll be saying things and or doing something and then
like when i'm watching
i'm like
that's not what i want
and then i'll freeze up
it's very weird when i'm filming
and then for people who haven't worked with me too much
they'll think
like
i don't know
it's very weird
like the how i go about it
because i'll just be doing whatever
like lighting a firework
all right
this is a thousand dollar firework
i'll go to lighting and i'll like freeze
because in my head i'm like this
i don't know
i don't like how that float or how that shot looked
because i
it's weird
i can perfectly picture what i'm filming
by just looking at the camera and then putting myself through the lens of the camera while making content
and i can do it at the same time
so you're like real time editing in my video
yeah
that's something that didn't at the start
come natural to me
but in the last
probably like five years it's happened
and so i would say it's one of my greatest strengths
but i don't know how i developed it
but anytime i'm filming anything like
it's almost like the like right side of my brain i just can just look at it
and i see exactly what i'm filming and i can just picture it
well
there's probably recording the video being the talent for the video
and then watching the editing and like analyzing you careful and do that over and over again
you'll do that over and over you
ten thousand times
yeah
you do the editing more than the being in front of the camera
so
like you
you start to see yourself from that third person perspective
exactly
then
maybe that actually helps with the nerves of it
too
like you see it as creating a video versus performing
uh
right
yeah
i think
so
you know
i
it's weird i've never been nervous talking to a camera
it's it's harder for me to talk to a person that doesn't talk to a camera
which i feel like a lot of people say that
though that are whatever
make content right
interesting
i've heard that so many times
or maybe not
maybe i'm just awkward enough
maybe they're practiced
i
to me
it's
i mean both are terrifying
but being in front of the camera by yourself is so much easier
really
yeah
so much easier
i preferred a million times over [applause] but that's my whole life
you know
so it's just that's why it's interesting
like you've spent more of your time talking to people
yeah
it comes natural
and i talk to a piece of plastic
oh
yeah
i guess you're talking to a person too
they're just then on the other side of the camera
yeah
there's just a pixel on the screen
so so cloning
how do you
how do you achieve this
oh
yeah
that's right
that's all right
so i was showing him
that i have a lot of people in the company who are able to think like me
and
uh
basically make decisions like i would make if i was like
if you were asked
hey in this video
should we climb a mountain
or should we dig a hole right
and like you know
they would pick the same answer
i'd pick 90 plus percent of the times
and so one example is tyler who i was showing you
and he was pitching some content and you could see it like this
he was on point and
uh
basically
for just four or five years
we just spent an absurd amount of time together and worked on every single video together and we worked
uh
side by side
and same thing with
uh
my ceo
james
he literally lived with me for a couple years
i'm a big fan of
just like finding people who are super obsessed and all in and a players that you know
they really just want to be great and then just dumping everything
and
like you were saying
because i'd love to find that
uh
and develop that you're saying
you're basically
for a long time
just said everything you were thinking to them
exactly like
uh
james
the the guy who's basically my right handman right now
um
for two years he lived with me and we probably talk on average of those two years
seven hours a day
i mean
anytime i had a phone call
i'd throw it on speaker and i'd let him listen anything
i was reading any content i was consuming
like really just
training his brain to think like me
so that way
um
he could just do things without my input without me having to constantly watch over him
or give him advice
and
and that's where we've gotten like
so for the first six months he didn't do anything
he just studied me and studied everything i cared about and how i spoke
and blah
blah
and then the next six months he started taking on some responsibilities
and now he can just run the company
and you know i don't ever really have to check in on him like i
most
the decisions he makes are exactly what i would do
um
and so i i call that cloning i don't know what other people would
but it's just like finding people that are really obsessed
and they just kind of really want it and just being like giving them an avenue to like
get it
if that makes any sense
another way to see it is
you're converging towards a common vision
and that makes like brainstorming much more productive
yeah
it just makes it where i don't have to be so involved in everything
because i just have these people i know
will think like
i will
uh
at least relatively close to it
so i can kind of almost be in multiple places at once per se
and so these things that you know
i still approve every idea we film and you know everything before we film it all the creative
i approve it
but i don't have to like
be in the weeds and nuances and do all this minor stuff
i can just let them handle it
i can just do the more macro things
i got a chance to sit in to a lengthy brainstorming session with tyler and others
that was really cool
can you talk about the process of that of
uh
people pitching ideas and you pitching alternatives or shutting down ideas
and it's just going like plowing through ideas
very good
i mean you kind of just describe exactly what we did
yeah
i mean
but the ideas are really really good
it's just tossing out like different categories of ideas and then also fine-tuning them to see
like you know
i changed
like thinking about the titles and the stuff i worked so well off of inspiration
it's like that's a something like give
give me anywhere
i don't know space
yeah
like i went to space
you know what happens if you love a nuke in space
or i went to the moon
i went to mars
right
because you said that one word
it was able to inspire me to come up with four ideas
and so that's just it's for me if you the way to get 100 million views on videos
you need something original
creative
something people really need to see
ideally
never been done before all these like things
and so you need like
if you want to consistently go supervisor
you need just a constant stream of ideas
and the only way i've really found
that i can consistently come up with 100 million view videos is to intake inspiration
and then see what my brain outputs
and so that's kind of at its core foundation
what i'm doing there is just like in taking a lot of random inspiration to see what spawns in my mind
so i can output it
but the neural network of your brain is generating the video
the title
the thumbnail
all that jointly
exactly
and that only comes because i spent 10 years of my life just obsessively studying all that stuff
because you
i mean it seems like you would literally potentially shut down a video just
because you can't come up with a good title
yeah
or a thumbnail
i mean that's what happened to 70 of those in that pitch session
i was just like
oh
what was one of them genius versus 100 people or
yeah
like
maybe average intelligence versus genius
yeah
i was like
what the heck is the thumbnail
even if the title was good
yeah
i mean there's so many
but yeah
people don't click
they don't watch
that's so interesting
but you developed over time
the ability to kind of give it
what
what makes for a good title short
not just short
it's also
i mean if someone reads it
are they like
do they have to watch it
is it just so intrinsically interesting that it's just gonna fuck with them if they don't click on it
you know what i mean
so it doesn't have to be short
but it has to be like
you almost want to have a retention to word by word reading
ideally
it's a title also that
um
you know
because the titles don't live in a vacuum
right
so it has to lead into the content
so ideally
the title represents content that you would want to watch for 20 minutes
so if it's a 20 minute video and the title is
i stepped on a bug
it's not gonna
because it's all of it combined
it's the click-through rate is going to be much lower
and then
if it was like a five second video
people might click it
so you gotta like
even nuances of the length of the video
based against the title will affect whether people want to click it
because sometimes they just all add up
i mean it's that
yes
ideally
you want it below 50 characters
because above 50 characters
on certain devices
you run the chance of it going
dot
dot dot
so
like i took a light pole
and i saw how many dollar bills i could stack on top and they would just go dot dot
because it's too long and it can't finish it
and that's the worst thing
because then people don't even know what they're clicking on and so it's going to do even worse
um
short
simple
ideally
and just so freaking interesting
they have to click
and it is a good segue into the content and represents the length of the content
and there's probably stuff
it's hard to kind of convert into words for you
like i stepped on a bug versus stepping in a bug versus mr b stepped on the bus
well
i mean that bug stepping that up
so it's like
yes
the more extreme the opinion
typically
the higher the click-through rate
if you can
like
uh
pay it off in the content
then it just supercharges it
so like
oh so you have a kind of estimate of the experience
this water
right
if you're like fiji water sucks
yeah
that would do fine
but if you said fiji water is the worst water bottle or the worst water
i've ever drank in my life
yeah
way more extreme opinion would do way better
but you have to deliver
yeah
but then you have to deliver
because the more extreme you are
the more extreme you have to be in the video
yeah
that's almost inspiration for you to step up
but you can
you can be more extreme in a positive way
a lot of people
it's easier
though
pause it
uh
negative
clickbait is much easier than positive cliff
it just is
it's so much easier to get negative clicks
and so a lot of people are just in my opinion
you know
a little bit lazier and they just take the route like
oh
well this one gets the same amount of clicks and it's easier
less effort
the positive one is doing a large number of numbers of something
like i
i spent this number of hours doing this or whatever
if you just wanted to help people or right
it's just harder to get 10 million views on a video helping people
than it is to get 10 million views on a video tearing down a celebrity
you know what i mean or whatever negative video you want to insert there
well
that said
most of your videos are pretty positive
so what's
but not a lot of people do those kinds of videos because they're hard
yeah
they're hard
some of that is giving away money
right
yeah
um
what's the secret to that
what's how do you do do that
right
yeah
like give away money or in a video that made to make it compelling
um
is it
so there's a number that is better than another number
right
the higher number is always better than the other number
yeah
for the most part
and you know it's interesting
like some videos will give away a million dollars
some videos will give away half a million
there's not really
i guess
so i'm retracting what i just said
i was more joking with that
but there's no difference whether i put 500k or a million
it's probably not even really a difference between 100k a million
i haven't really looked into it
like some of our mostly videos are not us giving away a million dollars
and sometimes the million dollar videos just don't do as well as the other ones
so there there's a certain point
where a dollar amount is just a large dollar amount to an average human
and so i think that point is 100k
like anything above 100k
the average human's just like that's a lot of money
you know it
doesn't
it doesn't 100k a million like it doesn't really move the needle
if that makes sense
which that's a very nuanced piece of information that applies to very few people
but yeah
well
no
i think it applies
it's fascinating
human
our relationship with money is fascinating like
why is it so exciting to get
i mean i
you know
the times i found like 20 bucks in the ground are like incredible
really
i don't know why
right
why
why are you so happy
like
what exactly is so joyful about that
i mean it depends where you are in life
what the situation is
yeah
i don't know
there's also a gamified aspect to it it's exciting
yes
no
i get it
like why people want to see people win money
it's just interesting that past 100 grand
it's
it doesn't really seem to make a difference
like it's the same
basically
so you found
that to be true with all the money you've given away that i just didn't click through it
like obviously in terms of someone receiving it
yeah
a million dollars changes their life drastically
more
like
that's the difference
oh you
if you wanted to
you could really quit your job as opposed to 100k is like not really
you probably do
like a scientific study
like a formula giving away money to click-through rate
yeah
there could be some kind of digestion return
it definitely the
the returns level off dramatically after 100k
that's basically the premise
what about ten thousand
uh
no
there's ten
a hundred thousand
is that it's funny because this is such a small niche thing
but yeah
100 000 does it from what i see in our videos get more clicks than ten thousand
but the difference between a hundred thousand million is just so little
i just i think
big number
big number to a lot of people past that point
yeah
so for 100
you can like give an average salary
you could probably live for a year given give them a day out
average salaries in america
so that's like a big
that feels
yeah
i think it's also just more when they read the title
it's just like it's a lot of zeros
fuck loads of zeros
okay
click
yeah
oh man
that's fascinating
so on the thumbnail side again
that's going to be much harder to say
probably
um
but you know
offline
you know i got a chance to look at a bunch of thumbnails and it's fascinating
which ones do well
and which ones don't is there something you could say about what are the elements of a thumbnail
that work well
is this also deeply
well
that's where
yeah
it's the same thing like
how do you cook good food
but um
it's easier if you pull up a thumbnail
i could be like
that's why that's good
that's why that's bad
that's uh
like an example would be like one of my friends
i was
he just uploaded a video recently and i called him
i was like
what is this because he's a very
very smart guy
and then the thumbnail
he's
he's getting chased by cops
but the cops are wearing yellow vests
so they didn't look at cops
i was like
whoa
why are the cops in your thumbnail wearing yellow vests
it's like that makes it so much more boring
and he was like carrying a flag
but the poll and the color of the flag were the same color
so it's like it's a lot harder to see the flag
i was like
also
you're wearing like a shirt with like five different colors like
so it's like it's hard to tell what even what your outline is
and then in the background there were cars and i was like
oh
if you have cops chasing you
why not make the cars cop cars and you know and it's like
because in my head i'm like
dang
if he just did those
like four or five things
the video probably got
like seven next the views
how much iteration
because i also got a chance to see the number of iterations you do on a on
just it's a problem
now it's an addiction
is it
so you kind of
there's
a lot of the versions were really good
yeah
how do you know when to like
i love how you
when we pulled up that
uh
the burger one and we were flipping through them
you're like
that's really good
i was like
oh
that's version like one of like a thousand
but even the sketch
the idea was good
like already
even the original idea is strong
yeah
so we
one of our coming up videos
we made the world's largest plant-based burger
and the thumbnail we were thinking is like me standing beside the bird
because it's six feet tall
that's that's what he's talking about
so like
just picture a giant six foot tall burger super wide
thousands of pounds
and then i'm beside it
and then it's like eating the world's largest burger like you
that's just something you have to click like
so you were saying
like how would you describe a good thumbnail like that
you know what i mean like
but i think you said the one i noticed first that was good
where you were very small in it relative to the
and you didn't like that one
i needed to come forward a little bit
and also the photo we took was
uh
just my upper body
yeah
so they photo manipulating created my legs
photoshop
and that's why i said i didn't like it
because my right leg was a little like off
it was like bent the wrong way
does the physics and thumbnail have to even make sense
i mean you can just like exaggerate the head size and all that kind of yeah
yeah
things don't have to be relative
you can have a car in the background be three times the size
yeah
because
every one of my thumbnails
my face is in the you know
left side
very big
so brand recognition
so just people know
oh
especially because now that a lot of people copy our videos
it's just nice to like you know
everyone else might make thumbnails like this
but this is mine and obviously we usually over deliver and do bigger stuff
would you recommend to other creators that wanna that
wanna make it big to
and they see mr beast
and they look up to you to copy some elements of you or to really try to be unique
unique
you're not the next mr beast quote
feels weird saying that third person
but whatever is not gonna do what i'm doing better
they're gonna just invent their own lane
like you're just not going to do what i do
better than me
you know
i have so many
i literally have the best people in the world working here and i
i reinvest everything i make even to this day
you know what i mean
like
it's absurd
the amount of money i spent on content and i don't care
i'll just stop sleeping
and i'll just film every other day like you're just not gonna beat me at my own game
and that's fine
you shouldn't
like i didn't get where i am by just beating someone else out there again
i just found my own lane and innovated and adapted and so yeah
there's a lot of people that do copy me
and it's fine
whatever do it
but just know you're not gonna get to where i am doing that
um
and so i'd advise you
don't you give away a lot of the secrets
basically everything
yeah
about how you operate
is there
uh
i don't hold anything back
go for it
you know
how do you think about that
because that's also
that's pretty rare
i think
and this is a definitely not
uh
most people in my stance
i don't think would take this or my position would take this stance
but i see every other youtuber or so person on social media
even because we're also focused super heavily on youtube
but last year we're also the most followed tick tock creator in the world
as well
i actually remember most subscribed to youtube channel world and the most followed tick tock account in the world
um
but
uh
in general
i just see everyone else
as uh collaborators
not competitors
i
i don't think giving advice and helping other creators do well in any way harms me
and i think it only brings more value to my life
how is it jumping on tick tock and trying to understand that platform from scratch
yeah
so
from being a successful youtuber to understand a totally different algorithm
fundamentally different algorithm
it's interesting
well
not even just the algorithm
just the content
like i'm going from basically 15 minute short films to one sub
one minute
vertical content
at least a whole different
just ballpark
um
and so the first little while is doing tick tock
it was just kind of figuring out how what does mr beast look like in this short form content
but recently we've really started to catch our stride
and come up with some original concepts and figure out how to innovate over there
just like we did on youtube
because i don't want it
i didn't want it to just be shitty youtube videos
yeah
you know
and so
like an example is
um
we played the rock for 100k and rock paper scissors and the loser had to donate 100k to charity
we did
um
we went to random people on a campus and we offered them
so i said i'll give you a hundred dollars if you fly to paris
to give me a baguette
and then they said no
and i was like i'll give you 300 if a lot of hairs and give me a big hat
and i was expecting this person to say no and it go up to like 10 grand
he's like yes
and so he flew to paris
got a baguette and brought it back and gave it to me
and that across everything got like 450 million views
and because it's just really cool just to see this random guy get on a plane
spend a day in paris and we cut it up real nicely and bring it back
and so we're starting to find just tons of original content over there
but it seems like an epic video to make for one minute
exactly
no one on short forms doing it
that's the thing
it's like okay
it's just so funny
because like tick tock's been big for a while now years
and then
um
you know
as
as we started to really figure out things on the youtube channel and get it cranking
where i have some free time
we
we set our sights on tick tock and like okay
what are people not doing
how do we make it better
put in more effort
make it good
and we did the same thing we did at youtube
just different over on tick tock and it worked
and now we're the fastest growing or most followed tick tock account in 2022
and it's just funny that no one else did that
and you're not afraid to do epic stuff
which also during the brainstorming
some of the ideas you're like
that's better as a short
that's crazy
yeah
can you remember one
because i remember i said that a bunch
but i can't think of what
all i remember is that they were like epic videos
like
really
you're going to do that for a one minute video
yeah
that's crazy
so like
are you posting similar content to a youtube short
as a tick tock
yeah
those would just double up
it's just hard
you know
what's actually pretty fascinating in people who do social media
listening to this will probably find this pretty interesting
because the picture of like the content creation meta three years ago versus now
where you can make sub one minute
vertical content and it go viral on tick tock and go viral on youtube
shorts
go viral on instagram
reels
it goes viral on facebook
it goes reddit
you know you swipe through vertical content now and twitter
when you click on a video and you flip through it
so this is actually very weird
this is the first time in the history of
i guess western social media
that one form of content could actually go super viral on every single platform
it's never been like that before
so they're going viral individually
they're not like like something or whatever
i can post something on tick tock
they'll get 100 million views and then post it on shorts
and it'll get 200 million views and then post it on instagram
and i get 50 million views and then you know i haven't yet
but you know you can then turn around
and tweet it and get tens of millions of views and you can post it on reddit
get tons of interviews
and
and facebook and get tens of millions of views and that that just wasn't a thing three years ago
twitter didn't have when
because a lot of you probably don't even know this
but when you tap on a video now and you swipe down
it just turns into tick tock
that wasn't a thing even a year ago
reddit
that wasn't a thing a year ago
probably two years ago
that wasn't a thing on instagram
three years ago
that wasn't a thing on youtube
right with youtube shorts
so this is all new
and
uh
i don't
it's weird
i haven't heard a single person talk about it
but this is the first time
where content can actually go viral on every single platform
and you don't have to write or film a video for facebook film
a 12 minute video for youtube film
a sub 60 second video for tick tock
write a tweet for twitter and post this on reddit
you can just do the same thing on every platform
and the fact that your content has gone viral on multiple platforms regularly means that virality is not accidental
sometimes it can be
of course
but it's
it's just it can be engineered
it's
yeah
so many people say it's luck
and they're like you're just lucky or this or that
but what are we up to
probably like a thousand videos over 10 million views
like we don't ever have a dud like you can call it luck
but i think it could be trained
i
i counsel youtubers all the time
and show them how to go from getting a couple million views a month to 10 million views a month
very easily
if i'm even certain
ones
like just one of my friends
like he was just really struggling
and so i just started showing him basically everything i know and just doing like once every week
sometimes
once every two weeks
calls and it went from ten thousand dollars a month on youtube to over four hundred thousand
just doing these little counseling calls
and so i mean people can make excuses all they want
and say it's just luck or say you know
um
well
anyways
i don't even want to quote all the other stuff
but it's just it is
it is a teachable skill
it's a learnable skill
you can study your way to consistently make viral videos
no matter how small your channel is
even if you have zero subscribers
you could
if
if you actually studied hard enough and like
basically
if you knew what i knew
and some of these
so i don't sound so arrogant
also
like some of these other friends i have that i'd say are the smartest people in the world
when it comes to content creation online
if you had the knowledge that was in our heads
you could do it very easily
i see people do it all the time
um
and what's even more interesting is i go on podcasts and i say everything i know
and these people are also very open
some of them
i know it's all out there and a lot of people
instead of just studying that and trying to absorb and apply it in their own way
they're just like
no
it's just luck
you know
so you do lay it all out there
but i gotta push back to one interesting thing
i
i think a crucial component of your success is the idea stage
the idea generation
the brainstorm i heard today
but getting really good at generating idea is
so it's not
it's not just the uh
the selection of the thumbnail and the title
that creative process
it's also just the the engine of generating really good ideas
of course
and getting that
i mean
i i would say
that is probably the thing that needs to be trained the most for most creators
right that
they're
they just don't put enough ideas on paper
yes
but also a lot of creators also
just
don't
you know
which i didn't either
for the longest time
just didn't don't make good enough content
you know
content
that's worthy of getting 10 million views in the idea or the execution of the idea
both
i mean
like
think about how many people just make videos they film in under 20 minutes
and they don't really put any effort into it
and like you know
it's like my first 500 videos didn't deserve to get a million views
like there's a reason they did
they're terrible
you know
but at the time i thought they did right now i'm in the mindset of a lot of small youtubers
or i thought those videos deserved a million views
and i thought the algorithm hated me
but i watched them back now and i can tell you exactly why the videos was fucking horrible
you know what i mean
well
so what was the breakthrough for you to start realizing
to start having a self-awareness you know about these videos aren't good enough
you're probably still going through that you're probably still growing to see like
yeah
every six months
you should look back and hate your videos or at least see things you could improve and be like
oh
i could have done this better
that
better
if not
then you're not learning quick enough in my opinion
at least where's the source of that learning even for you now
uh
just look at it
i just got back from him
no
i'm
i just got back from a mastermind where i just got
like you know
10 of the smartest people i knew
and we just locked ourselves in a cabin and taught each other stuff constantly
every day
not every day
now
probably every other day
i go on a walk and i just call random people
i'll just say teach me something
and
uh
i mean it's just
you just have to have a never-ending thirst for learning link
that's very imperative
especially if you want
like
if you want to get on top and then stay on top
the only way to do it is just to constantly be learning
or someone who is learning is just gonna
you know
have a leg up on you in the knowledge game
and what kind of stuff
are you because you you've talked about offline that you just love learning of all kinds
it doesn't matter
but in terms of videos
are you studying
videos
are you studying recently
not as much
i'm more
because to get to the videos i want
i have to build this business
and scale up
and hire so one of my recent time has been like my teenage years were spent studying virality
and studying content creation
now i'm studying how to build a content company so i can actually produce the crazy ideas i want to produce
if that makes any sense
so
yeah
and that's the business side
uh
we talked about hiring
do you have trouble firing people
no
i'm pretty sure almost every person
yeah
actually every person i've ever heard
we just give them severance
and i like to see it more as it's no
ill
well
like
if there's like
if i fired you
if is
there's some other job
you want me to help you get
i'll dm them on twitter
like you know
if you want to go work for
i don't know
insert whatever mtv give me someone to dm
i'll dm
like you know
i i try to make it more like a transition
and do whatever we can to make it as easy as something
was just not working for you because you want people like you said
super passionate
because at the end of the day
if you hold someone that you
uh
onto someone that you don't see
being here in 10 years
you're just doing a disservice
you're just giving them more ingrained more and rooted and where where they are
um
and the sooner you do it and help them move on to their like new life
the better
given all the wisdom you have now
if you were to give advice to somebody or if you were to start over again
uh
you had no money
what would be the first 10 videos you tried to
uh
to make on a new channel
i guess that's advice for a new person and nobody knows you
yeah
and nobody knows me
like
hypothetically
i have a mask on
and you also
i guess don't have the wisdom
well
if i don't have what i have in my head
then i would say
just fail like just a lot of people get analysis paralysis
and they'll just sit there and they'll plan their first video for three months
and yeah
i'm any of you listening
if
if you
especially
if you have zero videos on your channel
your first video is not going to give views
period
it's not your first ten are not gonna give views
i can very confidently say that
so stop sitting there
and thinking for months
and months on end and just get to work and start uploading like all you need to do this
this applies to people who have not uploaded videos but have dreams of being a youtuber is make 100 videos
and improve something every time do that
and then on your 101st video
we'll start talking like
maybe you can get some views
but you know your first hundred are gonna
there are very freak cases like liza koshy or emma chamberlain
who have really good personalities and it doesn't take them
so
as many videos
and it's just like people who are seven foot five and making an nba like
yes
there are free cases you can find
but for the average person like us
you know
who don't have these exceptional personalities and you know backgrounds in filmmaking
just make 100 videos improve something each time
and then talk to me on your 101st video
well
the improve something
his time is the tricky one
how do you improve something each time
the second one
just i don't know
put more effort into the script
the third one try to learn a new editing trick
the fourth one try to figure out a way that you can have better inflections in your voice
the fifth one try to you know
study a new thumbnail tip and implement it
the sixth one try to figure out a new title
there's infinite ways
that's the beauty of content creation online
there's literally infinite ways from the coloring to the frame rate to the editing to the filming
to the production
to the jokes
to the pacing
to every little thing can be improved and they can never not be improved
there's no
there's literally no such thing as a perfect video
so if you knew everything
you know now
but no money
step one
would i just brainstorm like okay
i don't have money
what are some viral things like
i mean
the first thing that comes to my mind is something as simple as
when i count to a hundred thousand
which is what i did do and i i was poor
um
and like that worked
but like
what's something like that
i could do
that would be even more attention
yeah
you were as part of the brainstorm you would throw out a lot of ideas
and people throw out a bunch of ideas
and one of the questions is
is this even doable
right
yeah
first off
come up with ideas you think would do well and then ask yourself later if they're doable
yeah
because there's
there's different ways you can accomplish something
don't be cynical about the doability of stuff
yeah
because there really are so many different ways you can accomplish a goal like um
when we give away an island
like we give our 100 million subscribers island
yeah
you know
you can't find private islands that you know
don't look like shit for less than 10 million dollars so this isn't doable
right
all right
the idea doesn't exist
not doable exit off
but then you know
you dig into it and you
you know
find different alternatives and you find okay
what if we just buy a two million dollar island that sucks and then spend a million dollars
you know
importing some sand
let's build a beach
let's import 300 trees
let's put a little bit of canals
cut
some pass boom
now it's a really nice island
but it's actually affordable
because we don't have 10 million dollars to spend on video
but we can afford to spend three and a half and lose whatever a million dollars on that video
so
like
that's an example of like
yeah
if you just went off the gut test
you're like this isn't doable
you know
every island is 10 million dollars
we're screwed
like
if we go cheaper
it's just a terrible island
no
and so if you like
there are so many different ways you can achieve what you want
you've really got to push through notes
which not a lot of people do you have to have
like a more of a dominant personality and just a willingness to
um
when people tell you it's not possible
just actually go through all the variables and eliminate them all yourself
have a stubbornness and
uh
resilience to failure
maybe for what we do and creators online
it's very imperative that you have that
a no
isn't a no deal that you really have to like think and um
and just like we
we take a personality test and like
just having a dominant personality is a better indicator that when someone tells you
oh
there's no way you're going to build a brick wall for under 100 grand
you know you'll be like okay
and then still go check the next 10 vendors and you know
figure it out
yeah
uh
what advice would you give to an already established channel
like with one
two
three
four million subscribers
how to like 10x
it
like
increase it
um
without losing
maybe
yeah
that's where it's very specific
like channel by channel
you can't give general advice
okay
yeah
because if i do
millions of creators are gonna see this and then they're gonna do it and i'm gonna fuck them over
you know
oh
i see
so let's say i had like two million subscribers on this podcast
yeah
like
how would you 10x that without sacrificing what it is
10x is
your stuff
does it matter
so we you've talked about with success
yeah
it's different for everyone like is 10xing your definition of success
no
well
then it's gonna
right off the bat
it's hard because if you don't give a shit about 10x thing
it's even harder for 10x
um
he does this because he likes helping people
that's one thing i found throughout this day
every time i talk data
it's so funny with him because it's like you know you could do this to get more views
and he'll just be like blank
i'll be like that
doesn't register anything
he's just like
doesn't care
which is
it's really
i'm really nervous about that
i'm really nervous about the numbers affecting
because it's so fun
oh yeah
it's so fun to focus on the numbers and i'm
i'm really worried about that
but at the same time
you should be cognizant of that
because you've created not just some of the most watched videos but some of the most amazing videos ever
so it's
there's a strong correlation
there
it's not like you're selling your soul to make a highly viewed video
it's actually
if you look at the metrics
it helps you understand what is compelling and not
and so i feel like i am
uh
i feel like there's some value to investigate what work when people tune on and when
not to be more data driven
even on podcasts
but i'm really afraid
on the flip side
i think part of the appeal is that you don't care about that kind of stuff
but there there could be stuff that doesn't have to do anything with that
it has to do with stylistic choices of lighting and cameras
or maybe with
uh
um
for example
topics
yeah
you know
like
even what you've asked me here is like different than what most people ask me
yeah
so it could be
i mean
and it'd be nice to understand that
but yeah
again
i'm worried about polluting at the end of the day
it's
this is a true case of
it's your own intuition
like you know your viewers better than anyone else
it's whatever see
i'd like to push back on that
i really don't you do
who else
name one person who knows your viewers better than you
uh
somebody that looks at numbers of podcasts
no
you know your viewers
you know you're the only
how many episodes have you done
uh
350.
exactly
but i'm not paying it
you're the only one who's watched every second of all 350 of them
probably
that's just
that's just not no
you haven't
but the okay
well
because you did it
so you do know what's in all of them
sure
your content is you people
i'm telling you you do
and this is just one of those moments
where you're an intelligent guy and you just have to trust your like instincts like
just think what is the typical x viewer and what do they want
i don't think like that
my tip
but that's all you would have to do
and whatever your gut tells you
that would be the best guess
you don't know what the typical viewer is
though
i don't
i know
because to investigate that would be very
very difficult
and then you have to start looking at the numbers
you have to start to like
consider demographics
the only way i know that anybody even watches it is because i'll sometimes run into people
like when i run along the river and they'd be like
i love you
lex
it's like okay
well
that
that's
that's the data point and they're like cool people
but you know
i don't know any
like
i don't have any other
it's difficult man
it's difficult to know
it's difficult to know who listens to boxes
the difficult
do you have a sense of who's
i mean
like you're so huge that everybody watches
yeah
uh
but no
i still do
i would say
if you were to just put a gun to my head and you're
you're like
all right
we're gonna pick a random person that watched your last video and you have to like
roughly guess what they are
and if you're not close
we'll kill you
i would say
probably like a teenager that plays video games
like some
something like that would be probably the typical one
and then there are people that are
maybe a little bit younger
a lot of people are are older as well
but in a ramble random sample size
yeah
it's probably like i'm a male boy that plays video games like
that's the best way i would describing it
but i don't try to pertain to them
i just make whatever i think is interesting and good content
um
and this is what we were talking about before
even though
hypothetically 35 to 40 of my audience is
uh
women
which is
you know less than a majority
if we get 100 million views of video
that's still 30 to 40 million females that watch every video
which is probably the largest
uh
you know views per video for women on the whole platform
which you wouldn't think that
you know
uh
like
i can't think of a single other creator that gets more women to watch their videos than that
um
and so it's just anything
even like people above the age of 30
even if it's only like three or four percent
that's still three to four percent of 100 million views
there's a lot of people that age
so we we hit a large group of uh
of kind of every demographic
if that makes any sense
so what if we look at other
maybe more challenging kinds of channels or not
but if we look at educational
for example
like lectures
or if we look
yeah
educational
it could be short videos
like
how would you 10x that like
uh
something on robotics and biology
on science
on engineering
on all of that
that's more educational focused
we would honestly just have to pull the
because it's the same way
if you went to gordon ramsay
you said how would a new cook cook better
you know it's like
even then
that's not even specific
you have to go channel by channel
you really do
or i'm
i'm giving horrible advice
because if there was these
just school rules
everyone would do it
you know what i mean
like
if there's these magical little principles
how quickly when you look at a channel
can you kind of give advice
yeah
it's
it's like surface love at the start
and then the more
if we watch 10 videos
i feel like i'd have a good profile and i could tell you
in my opinion
you know one
especially once i look at the analytics and i get more ingrained in
like
okay
the typical viewers
this
they're from here
here's how they're feeling
you know
because there are people who make videos for rednecks and like the rednecks
taste of content is just so much different than obviously women watching makeup videos
which are so much different than you know
teenage boys watching a minecraft video
they're just all different
so the biggest thing you have to do is put
put your head
your head in the headspace of the viewer and see the content how they would
because if you just try to only give your taste
which is what a lot of people do and things from your perspective
it's very biased and it's just not going to work for everyone
and that's actually how you do more harm than good
which is something i'm very careful of
yeah
but at the same time just generating a lot of ideas
i think the first time
i've talked to you
was on clubhouse
actually
yeah
i mentioned something about robots and like almost immediately went to generating a bunch of ideas around audiobooks
uh
it's just 100 robots versus a hundred humans
yeah
how far can a robot throw a potato
i think your idea
like
i think the first idea was because you just said so many ideas
i never even thought of
but it's
it's
it shows the value of
uh
basically brainstorming with people that think differently
but at the end of the day
my ideas are probably
you know
might lean towards some people a little bit younger than your audience
like some of the stuff
yeah
but there's still the ideas
like
i think
the first one you said because we're talking about
uh
quadruped
like a robot dogs
you said to replace a biological dog with a robot dog and see if the owner notices something
you're just quickly brainstorming different ideas of like how this was years ago
i remember that
yeah
which is just i mean it's like
oh yeah
i never really thought about that kind of
so it's the basic
the tension between what does it take for a robot and our ai system to replace the biological systems
that we
the biological creatures that we that we love in our lives
yeah
and
but like that was like the um
the pace of idea generation was the thing that struck me today
and in general
it's like that's how you get at good videos
is you keep keep things
it's much easier to make a video around a good idea obviously than a bad one
you're just setting yourself up for success
okay
so that's for
uh
10x thing already popular
um
channel
what's the hardest number
you said
uh
the numbers that matters
click-through rate
average view duration and and
uh
surveys
what's the hardest number to
uh
optimize for probably surveys
you know
do you have any
do you have an insight into the surveys at all
no
not really
but if you just click on a bunch of random videos online
you'll eventually get a survey
what's this video
transformative
heartwarming
inspiring what people rate does make a difference
um
and it's like you can get people to click a video
you can get them to watch it
but you can't really fake whether or not they're satisfied
like they don't lie
the service
you know
um
maybe one person here
they're my troll
but once you're aggregate enough
it's a pretty clear telltale of the video
so either you're making a great video
or you're not
what is it
uh
minimizing the non regrettability
yeah
i think elon tweeted
that's what he's trying to do on twitter
twitter
and that's interesting
that's
that's basically the survey metric
how happy you are that you've been using the platform
yeah
you know
untreated
we want to limit the amount of regrettable minutes people spend on twitter
and
uh
the first thing i thought
it's like that's something youtube already has
a lot
like their whole survey system
when feedback loop
how tough is it to take on youtube
you think like um
for twitter
yeah for twitter for anybody else
um
i mean it's gonna be basically impossible
i mean youtube's not going anywhere
and i mean i don't know
i
don't
i don't think anyone's gonna do what youtube does better than them
uh
at least not in the next 10 years you asked on twitter
would you rather have 10 million dollars or 10 million subscribers on youtube
uh
what would your own answer be at various stages in your career
if
uh
if i had nothing
i would say 10 million dollars
so
because with 10 million dollars you can hire some people
and pump out content with like a million or two
get 10 million subscribers
and then keep the other 8 million
so that's if you believe in your ability to grow a channel
if you
uh
well
if you
yeah
if you don't believe in your ability to grow channel
then you shouldn't take the 10 million subscribers
because you're just gonna kill the channel
so the 10 million is definitely a better question would be
would you rather have a million dollars or 10 million subscribers
that's where it gets a little tricky
because now it's like
hmm
you know a million dollars
life-changing amount of money
uh
but you know
if you sim
i know what you're doing
you probably make a million dollars off a 10 million subscriber channel
but it is a little bit
a million dollars might not be enough to to build a strong team
because you don't know how to do it
so you might waste all that money
yeah
or they just keep it and retire
okay
that's true
yeah
because 10 million's just so high
it's like just never work again
who cares for the average human
that's so much money
it's interesting to me
also do the value of the subscriber versus the value of the dollar
um
i suppose how valuable is a subscriber for
uh
like
what percentage of the videos
how
active
are the subscribers and watching the video
um
for you
that's hard
i don't know
i was actually thinking more about the subscriber to dollar
like
if someone has 10 million subscribers
have they made 10 million dollars
i don't know why that that kind of popped in my head
it's an interesting thought
uh
do you ever
when you analyze
uh
videos
do you ever analyze videos like we've talked about offline of other videos across the youtube in general
just to understand
trying to understand social behavior
all your
not all
but a lot of questions are analytics based
yeah
it's so
because i love it
uh
i mean
it's just a giant social experiment
right like what people like to watch what people share
yeah
it's like a fascinating
so i hate that
so
like i said before
what percentage of your audience do you think care about this kind of stuff like this
deeply about youtube analytics
i think a large amount care about
uh
curiosity and exploration of interesting ideas
so in that sense
yeah
this would
this was fitted
i love it
this is funny
this isn't me like trying to like
i
i love you and i actually i love future magnus one and i
um
and even your hikaru one was really good
a bunch of other ones
but i think we're getting to the point now
where only analytics junkies would want to keep hearing more analytics talk
and the normie is probably like they've had their dose of youtube talk for the next three years
maybe i'm wrong
hey comment
if i'm wrong
i could be
i don't know your audience
see
this is where you would tell me
shut up
i know my audience
you dumbass
and i don't at all
i actually
i just follow the threat of curiosity
and i think there's just a lot of curious humans in the world and and to me it's like
so the question about analytics is the question of basically stepping away
stepping outside of yourself and thinking
why the hell do i like tick tock so much
why do i like twitter so much
why do i like youtube so much and getting
even if you're not a creator
getting an insight into that is really interesting
it's like what
uh
because
because all these platforms are fundamentally changing the nature of content
people are reading books less
they're probably going to be watching movies less and less
they're probably going to be watching netflix
less and less
do you ever think about the the sort of the darker side of youtube and um
with shadow banning and censorship and all that kind of topics
especially if you see it in other platforms like twitter
that
yeah
uh
elon
recently highlighted the shadow banning that was happening and in general
the censorship that was happening on those platforms
do you think about the role of centralized control
which information isn't or isn't made available through search and discovery
i'll be honest
i never really think about it
so
uh
you just you just try to make fun videos
that
yeah
more
i'm kind of more in my own lane
but it's not like that
i don't just specifically think about
i just like a lot of stuff in general
like i'm just kind of in my own lane
thinking about my own stuff
uh
but you know
now you asked
i'm curious
what are your thoughts on on youtube and that kind of stuff
well
i'm generally against centralized
um censorship or shadow banning
shadow banning is the worst one
because not that the goal of creating a healthy platform where you're having great conversations
and
uh
videos that are not spreading misinformation
that sounds like an admirable goal
but that's too difficult of a job for a centralized entity
that's too big of a yeah
and then there's the mis information stuff
and then there's also
just like the videos where they do something that causes
uh
what what happened back in the the
where
uh
adpocalypse
you know
and a lot of creators
revenue plummets because people are are doing videos that advertisers don't deem acceptable
and then now all these big advertisers are pulling and the little guys are getting hit
and
because adverage drop
by 30 and the person who just quit his job to go full-time consecration now can't sustain it
so it's also
it's like a lot of different variables as well
that makes it so complicated
well
i think the big thing is transparency
especially around shadow banning for for people i agree on shadow banning
uh
you should be transparent
you should let people know it
it
you know
obviously there has to be some type of controls
people can't just post whatever
and so if you're pulling those levers
they should at least know
yeah
so they know how
uh
how to improve their content
they can understand it
they can
exactly
uh
if it's a wrong shadow
banning
like
it's a society that we should not shadow ban this kind of content
that means exactly
you should be publicly discussing it
because if not
and if it's not known
then it's just kind of like
well
then who's pulling the strings and like how
do we know they're not just manipulating things to get whatever message they want out there
and silence other ones
yeah
and there could be sort of in the background government influence
which is
where actual freedom of speech comes into play that the government should not have any control
or be able to put pressure on censorship of speech
and it gets weird if none of that is being
there's no transparency around it
yeah
let's see
but to be fair
that's a huge responsibility
the amount of content that youtube is uploaded on youtube
that is shared by youtube
viewed by you
but even more of a reason why it
it would probably makes sense to be transparent
yeah because then people can help fact check it
that's right
but that that requires building a platform that makes that easy right
like uh to
to make fact checking easy to make the like
twitter now has like being able to share context and all that kind of stuff that crowdsource
it
crowdsources
the way wikipedia crowdsource it
i mean there's
it's right
and then you open a random wikipedia article
but like you know
people criticize wikipedia because there is a political lean to the editors of wikipedia
and then they get
there's some articles that definitely have a bias to them
and all that kind of stuff
it's a difficult problem
it's a difficult problem to solve that
ultimately
as much as possible
it would be nice for the viewer to have control of that versus the the entity that's hosting it
so for the viewer to decide
yeah
i'm just going to make fun cool videos
you know
let's go to antarctica again
how was that
how was going to you just came back from antarctica
that was
i watched the video
that was fun
that was a really fun video
thank you
um
there's
i mean there's a lot of things i can comment about that
but what was that
what was the hardest part of making that video the hardest part was just getting out there
it's just so remote
and you know you land the plane on just this ice runway
and it's so sketchy and then once the plane takes off
you're just there and you're the most remote place in the planet
and it's
it's just
it's very breathtaking
i don't
if you have the chance to ever go to antarctica
i would recommend it
it was probably like the in the video
we climbed a mountain
um
that wasn't named
so we can name it
and like standing on top of that mountain and just seeing kindling nothing
and because
once you get outside the outskirts and you get deep in antarctica
there's no penguins
nothing lives there at all
um
and so there's just nothing in every direction
it's just snow and these crazy beautiful mountains and some of them sticking to the clouds
and it was in the um
if you go during summer time
the sun never goes down
so the sun's up
and it's just like spinning in circles at the top of the planet or whatever
it looks like the top
um
yeah
you guys come with it several times
how beautiful
yes
and so it's just
yeah
it's just very beautiful
what about shooting itself like the technical aspects of shooting it
oh
i mean
well
so somehow we lucked out
one of the days
it was like the warmest day in like forever
that's been in antarctica
it's like it was positive
uh
degrees
but at certain parts
there's also like negative 20
negative 30
and that's where the cameras
you constantly have to be switching out the batteries
and heating them up and like putting them basically in like your pants
or they'll just get way too cold
and
uh
we were prepared for much worse
but it ended up being much better than we thought so for that video
but in general
maybe some other challenging videos
how does how do you go from the idea stage to the actual execution to the final video
what's can you take me through
like a full process of
like
we're talking about some crazy wild ideas today
how do you go from that to a final video where you click publish
well
i mean obviously
first things
first
you gotta figure out the idea and then it just depends
i mean pick any video you can think of on my channel
i can take you through it
uh
well
what about the
in a circle you have to stay in a circle for uh
400 days
yeah
so for that one step
one
one of the most popular
yeah
that video did really well
so we
um
problem is
uh
we have to
this is where you get really into the nuances of the company
because we have a lot of videos going out
you can't just in a vacuum be like
all right
we're not doing anything for 100 days
we're only filming this
so step one is we had to build an independent crew that could actually do that for 100 days
that way everyone else could keep working on the normal videos and not just screw everything up
yeah
um
so
step one
you build that team
okay
we got the team
now
what do we need
well to do this
we need probably like 10 cameras
at least rolling at all times
so
uh
we're probably gonna need to get a trailer and hook up a bunch of storage and stuff
so to just carry the sheer volume of footage we're gonna have and so get a trailer set up
the cameras go on the field
paint a circle
now we need a house
go buy a house
bring it out there
uh
and then it's like
oh wait
i think it'd be funny if i brought the house in on the intro for
yeah
you know
find a crane that can lift up a house so i can drive it in
and drop it in the intro
and that's like an iterative process where you're like
okay
this would be funnier
so this is not all up front
yeah
it's like your
ideally
it would be
but as you kind of see things
you get inspired and then you think of more and more
uh
and then this would be better with a crane
yeah
it'd be better if i dropped out of the house
that was crazy that you decided to do that
uh
so fearless in the kind of crazy stuff
you're willing to do
exactly what i'm a broken record
but whatever makes the best video possible
yeah
that's
that's all you
you focus on
okay
so
uh
what about the delegation of like
who
gets to what are the cameraman
like the people operating the cameras
what
uh
who's responsible for different things
this is like a distributed process like
well
that's where whoever the lead cam would be on that video would just decided that one
because we shot over 100 days
we didn't a lot of it was just sean and the guy who was in the circle just vlogging
i'm just gave him a camera
yeah
and he figured it out
and then we'd have like for him
just set hours each day that i can't remember would come
so if he had any content
he needed extra hands instead of just having someone on standby 24
7. it made more sense to do set hours nice
um
and uh
yeah
it was
it was hard
but you know it's funny and hindsight
it sounds so simple
you know
and i i guess
like the more
because that one is relatively simple
i guess
because it's a low number of people
yeah
the hard part about that is just the time right
like you know
i checked in on them so many different days
and it's like an hour here
two hours or two hours there
over a hundred days adds up to be a ton of time
and
and even then
like you know
if you have a 10 person crew
you know paying them daily rates for 100 days
it just all that adds up
what about
like the 100 versus 100
uh
adults versus the other kids
was
uh
bringing that to life
that seems like exceptionally challenging
yeah
basically the thought process was we did 100 kids or sorry
100 boys
100 girls
yeah
people loved it
honestly
i didn't think they'd like it as much as they did
video did really really well
so the second i saw that video was crushing
i was like all right
we're doing it again
but last time we did it
we did in our studio
so we built a
a giant room
put 100 girls in
it sounds bad
when i explain it like this
and then a gyrant put 100 boys
yeah
and we're like after 100 hours
which everyone has the most people give them half a million dollars
so did well
so we're like
all right
we're gonna do it again
so we threw out all these different ideas
it was like 100 football players versus 100 cheerleaders
100 this 100 that
and
uh
100 prisoners versus 100 cops
just craziest ideas
and we settled on 100 kids versus 100 adults
um
and then the next step was like
how do we make it better
the kids versus adults are the sorry
the boys versus girls
the first one we did was inside and the problem was every time it was night
when we did these long time lapses
you couldn't see the sun go up and down
so we're like
okay
this time
i want to do it outside
that's why the cubes are outside
um
and instead of doing circles
we want to make them cubes
and then you know
as figuring out
do we want that
yeah
there's just those videos came up at least today as ones that are like
really complicated in terms of the audio
in terms of how
yeah
film
it
yeah
that's the problem
we had a lot of audio issues because
uh
in the first one we didn't have a roof on it
the second one
there was a roof
so there's a lot of reverb
which then
in editing made it brutal
like half the shots weren't usable
and it really screwed us over
so we had to do a lot of frankensteining in the editing to make up for basically my ignorance
so you mentioned that you were surprised
how well that that one did
a lot of creators talk about getting depressed when
um
the videos don't do as well as they kind of expect it
there's the kind of feeling you can get really worn out by that dude
yeah
um
you do your yourself feel that and also do you have advice
for others that feel this
um
yeah
it's weird because i am a numbers guy
but also it
it used to
very much
especially when i was like betting everything i had on a video
when it did bad
i was devastating
i'd cry and i'd be depressed for days and it really would have a severe impact on my mood
but i don't know
now
it doesn't really matter
it's uh
if a video that's bad
i just look at it and i'm like
oh
why'd this video do bad
uh
probably
oh
there's a little retention dip there
i don't think people like the thumbnail
maybe we should switch it
i just look at it
objectively unemotional
and then just move on and i feel like that's a much healthier way of going about it
so if a creator is listening like that is the ideal way to um
respond to a video that's doing bad
just remove emotion from the equation
and just look at it and figure out how you can search the next one
is there tricks to detect
being able to detach yourself from the from that
because
because i
in your case
i mean that's true for creators
but in your case
there's like a lot of money on the
line
yeah
well
there's videos
yeah
so much time
but no
i mean you
just
i mean
i don't know
the only real answer is
it's just the conscious effort
you just have to unemotionally look at the video
determine the problems and then move on like there's there is no secret
you know what i mean
it's just that's
it's that
and if you really can't bring yourself to do it
then you're just screwed
honestly
maybe you're not meant for this game
okay
so that's part of the development as the creator is like being able to be a different longevity
yes
yeah
you have to unemotionally be able to look at videos that flop and figure it out
uh
because
if not just getting you can
not every video can be a one out of ten
and so when a video does bad
you know that that just stress and depression
it's just gonna eventually get to you in the long run
so you said you've uh
failed in a bunch of videos
uh
sort of taking them to completion
so what are some of the biggest fails
yeah
weirdly
enough
as we've matured and we've done this more
we don't have that problem as much
especially that we're getting into the multi-million dollar budgets per video
it's like failure is not really an option anymore
so i'm a little more particular about what i do
but back in the day
yeah
like we would do a video where we spent 24 hours on a desert island
and
uh
we filmed
it did it all
and i just i didn't like it after the edit
so i just grabbed the voice
and we went back to the deserted island and spent another 24 hours there and refilmed it
um
or
uh
could that have been caught and prevented at the idea stage
like where
like
no
it's a good idea
it was just poor execution to be honest
when we were out there
it was hot
we were
we're just like we all
at one point just kind of wanted to die
it was just miserable
so how do we
how do you avoid that these days
uh
well
i just thought it was a little cooler to be honest
and then we had literally the amount of fun we had in the video was like 10 times higher
oh interesting
so you like
there's some practical details that you just learned
yeah
i don't know what it takes
videos that where it's very hot or or it's on water
because i get super seasick
it's like a kind of like 10 things that
if they have these variables
i'm down to do it
but my fun meter is not as high as normal
uh
like we tried to sp
um
anytime we do anything on a boat
like when we spent 24 hours of beer in a triangle or when i tried to spend
like
which i didn't get up
but i try to spend like 100 hours at sea or whatever
just like on a raft
it's just like i
it makes me want to throw up and i get so seasick
i can't even see straight
but there are just some videos that require me to be on a boat
so i just suck it up
um
so
when you spend months in creating a video
i know this is probably stressful to some creators
uh
like
how much stress
how do you feel when you have to click
publish
uh
video
no
not much you're able to detach yourself
yeah
again
in old me tons
i mean i'd be like scratching and nervous and like my hands would be sweating like to the point
where i'm almost about to puke
i'm like
i really hope people like this
but you know
i don't know
i think that's just part of maturing it
there's different
and as a content creator
there's different phases
and
uh
you just like
once you get over the
the fear that you're just gonna wake up one day and be irrelevant
you know
and you
just
you know
accept that
like you believe in yourself and you believe in your content and that you can continue to be relevant
then you don't
i don't know
you
kind of
it's a little bit easier to attach yourself
i guess
and that's i
it's a much healthier place to be
you can't do this for 10 years
if every little thing just causes these huge emotional reactions
it's like
that's why a lot of creators go a little
you know
mentally
insane you know you have to get out of that that game
right
because it really messes with you
we've talked about this a little bit
but how do you define
and how do you suggest others define success
some people success is retiring
their mom is inspiring people and educating them
and you know
whatever they're peaking
their curiosity
um
for other people
it's just quitting their job
so you have to self-reflect on what your definition of success is
because i think a lot of creators kind of don't really think
don't introspect like they kind of want to keep getting more and more subscribers
kind of thing
and yeah
but subscribers is just a vanity metric
you know
it doesn't
subscribers don't correlate to views sure or views what
yeah
i know
but that's more
that was a drag to you
that was more direct to people listening
because
uh
a lot of people do really care about subscribers or even followers
like on tick tock
but if you look like your view
if on youtube
very
few
percent
if even a percent of your views come from the sub feed
right
you know
they're almost all home features
suggested
what's the last time you clicked on your sub feed to watch a video
oh almost never
yeah
maybe five years ago it used to be a thing
it's not anymore
no one does
um
and it's getting harder and harder to find
i subscribe to way too many channels
i think
yeah
that's what everyone does and you subscribe to 10 channels
they're great
but two years later your taste evolves and it's like it's a mess and so um
subscribers don't really matter
followers on tick tock don't really matter
um
so anyways
it
really
they really are the definition of a vanity metric
and but what about views they do
obviously
because if people are showing up time and time again
that's what matters
okay
so that that's a good thing to
uh
define a success
i just feel like
um
that too can be a problem
because
uh
i would say
you know
if i wanted to be successful
like it's a young creator
i might start copying mr beast or something like that
right
yeah
like
there's
you start trying to take shortcuts as opposed to find your your own unique voice
right
so
like chasing views is a problem too
it feels like or no
um
it's as long as you detach yourself from them
i mean if you're lazy
yeah
and you just want to copy someone else and not experiment and find your own way but yeah
i mean you can't make that excuse for them
and someone just isn't coming up with original stuff and putting in the effort
you can't just say
oh
it's because they're chasing views
we need some different metric from the chase
no
they just need to find their own way
well
it just feels like unique type of content will often lead to sacrifice in the number of views in the short term
by the long term
you win
okay
or if you do win you
you win more
i guess would be a better way putting it
do you think you will ipo
miss mr beast burger or feastables in the next five
ten years beast burger or feasible snow
i
i kind of think they're something actually
you know what
i just realized that this is our first time talking about those
we're like an hour and a half in
that's so funny
we started talking about what
uh
my retention brain kicked in
um
i wonder if you have retention brain for
like life itself
i do every time i'm talking to someone i can
i'm like
okay
what about
like loved ones
like spending time with loved ones thinking like we could be doing something much better right now
yes
no
that is a serious problem
uh
with
well
so we'll pause the b square
question
yes
but that's why
uh
my current girlfriend
which i was telling you before when we were talking about this is
she has a genuine love for learning
and that's something i have
like
i always feel like i need to be learning something to justify the time i'm spending
and so that's why it's such a nice trait
because i feel like that time is being used optimally
because whether we're watching a documentary or we're going in in
you know
taking an iq tests or reading about
whatever
just why modern art is the thing
i don't know
whatever weird thing we decided to do
i'm always learning and improving
so it justifies the time
so
to maximize retention in your relationship
yeah
you want to spend time with that time learning as much as possible
which conveniently i don't have to force right or i want to be recharging
so i
when i do work
i can
you know
hit the ground harder
and luckily we're into a lot of the same things which you know happen to be learning
sometimes it's not learning
like maybe watching an anime or something like that
um
but i'm a big believer and you're either
if you
well
if your goal is to be like a super successful entrepreneur
you need to either be working or you need to be doing something that decompresses and recharges you
so you can work again
if your goal is to be like a really kick-ass entrepreneur
obviously we're boiling this down to like a very basic thing
and so the the things you're doing
your down time when you're not working
if it doesn't recharge
you
you're screwed
you're just a ticking time
but i'm waiting to implode
um
and so you gotta like heavily recharge and like
so like watching for me
anime or whatever it is
playing a board game
like that is actually kind of crucial to my success
which takes a lot of maturing to come to that conclusion
because i used to be the kind of guy that wanted to work every hour of the day
and i would try to train myself to not need that stuff
and i
you know
and i almost resented like that
i i have to do these kinds of things and it would piss me off because it's not optimal
and you know
i just really want to make content and entertain people
but yeah
as someone who's gone down that road
and you know
you just work every day for two
three months straight
and you know every hour of the day
and then you just a bomb waiting to explode and lose your mind
and the only real sustainable thing is to just like
give yourself time to recharge in between working
so there's a kind of balance you have to find
you have to even
and i hate it more than anyone else
because i
you know
you hate not working
yes
because it's just not optimal for time like it's
it's
as a human
i do need to occasionally watch a mindless show and play a board game
yeah
and it took me a very long time to like
come to peace with that and not
i would have like borderline panic
attacks when i do it
because i just
what am i doing right now
why am i doing this
i should be
you know
like what if
one day i have to lay off an employee because we're not doing so well
like
how could i justify watching this this show or whatever i'm doing right now
you know
it's like there's a lot of things like
that that go on in your head but it's necessary before we return to
uh
mr beast burger
what is like
is this one on the topic
what is a perfect day in the life
perfectly productive day in the life of mr beast look like
oh boy
well
i mean or like a stand
i mean the perfectly productive day as we filmed my main channel video
because those get 100 million a pop
i mean it doesn't really get any better than that
what about
like the average day when you're not on the set
yeah
and you're like
because you're running a lot of things
right
yeah
so right now we have our snack brand feastables
we have a restaurant chain piece burger and then we
basically
which
we haven't even really launched any products yet
but we have the the data company that i was showing you
where we're gonna roll out some tools for creators
and then we have the reacts channel
the gaming channel
the main channel
and then we have my charity
which also has a channel
um
and so kind of how i've structured my life right now
uh
is
whatever
i have free time
we just kind of go
hey
guys
jimmy's got an hour from 2pm to 3 p. m
and it's everyone's just like i need this
i need this and this channel's like
i need this thing filmed
or you know
whatever
the guy who runs my tick tocks like i need this tick tock filmder
um
you know
beast burger is
like
i need this menu item approved
do we need to talk about this marketing thing
and then we kind of just look at what everyone needs and we're like that
one looks like the most important we'll do that
and then
so it's just kind of like
you know
if i just did that for every company in a day
then that's optimal
if i just kind of like an optimal day for me
would be going down the eight companies and just whatever they're like
two to three biggest pain points or things to need from me
and just doing those based on priority and then trying to keep it as short as possible
yeah
to just the things that you're needed on
it doesn't get more optimal than that
if i clear the bottlenecks or some bottlenecks for all my companies
then it's yes
that's a perfect day
yeah
i mean even just me
because you're like you're showing me around and you're being a great and gracious host
but on top of that
you're just doing all these meetings
you
basically
i felt bad at some points
i was like
oh
i just tricked him into going to meetings with me
he's like my little meeting buddy
yeah
i mean it was
it was fun
it's fun to see it
it was fun to see how effectively you've delegated
you basically trust the team to do a really good job on the various things
and there's just a strong team that's able to carry the five on all the different tasks
yeah
from the
from the brainstorming and the main channel to the reacts
and so on
yeah
it's really interesting
i mean it's
it's really interesting what it takes to build a team like that
because you very quickly build the very large team
that's that's able to scale
which is very scary
because it's my first
you know
i i'm 24. you know
and i think i was telling you this earlier it's funny
because six years ago i had to raise my hand to go use the bathroom
and now i'm in charge of hundreds of people and entertain hundreds of millions of people
and so it is crazy
just how quick it comes up
and i wish i was a little bit older
so i could have ran a couple companies
and failed a few companies in the past and like learn from those and apply those here
because i know for a fact when i'm 34
i'm 24 now when i'm 34.
i'll
i'll know so much more about running a business
and scaling and hiring and and how to lead people and
better
effectively communicate
and all these different skill sets that will make them a better leader that
uh
that's the only thing that sucks is
i just don't have those
because i just haven't been through the lessons
and i just have such a lucrative thing on my plate right now
and it just sucks that i have to learn the lessons with the lucrative thing
you know what i mean
yeah
because you
you already have so much influence
so much impact
but you have effectively scaled
what
what lessons do you draw from that
how to effectively scale as a 24 year old
like
yeah
that's something i feel like i actually could give a lot of value to to young people who are doing it
like older people who've built five companies or whatever they do
um
i probably couldn't
you know they're gonna be like
oh
this is so obvious
but
um
for uh
younger first-time business owners
you kind of just experiment to be honest
and
uh
but for us like
it's just a new space
no one had really ever skilled up a 100 person team to build make content on youtube
so there wasn't no
uh
i spent all this time
like i hired one person from disney to at one point to come in and help
and obviously that was a dumb idea
looking back on it but you know i thought
oh
they make great stuff
people want to watch
and they come over here and help me build a team
and you know they build it more the traditional way and not like how it should be online
and and so then it's like okay
and now i'm not trying to trash people
like they all tried their best
but then i try hire this one person who does this different type of uh media
and runs a 100 person team
and then you come in here and they try to build it that way
they don't really listen to you or value or or see the difference
and i i tried basically for building this company with like four
or five different people who worked in different veins of media
and you know every single time it
just like they just don't get it and they like they don't understand my world
and the
the eventual solution was just like throw up my sleeves and do it myself
you know
with
like james
where i hit man and just like no no one's ever done this
and like no one's gonna just give us a golden carrot and tell us how to build this company
we got to figure the fuck out ourselves and you have to kind of build up people from scratch
then
yeah
exactly all the stuff i was talking about earlier and all the the lessons i learned along the way
um
and sophie
for me
that was a big part of like
and try to stop trying to have someone build this company for me and just do it myself
because it's scary like my whole life studying youtube videos of virality
not business building
but fuck i was like
i guess we just got to do it ourselves
and
um
and that's where things really start to click and we got the exponential growth
we started getting the right people and training them the right way
and you know
just throwing conventional stuff out the door and focusing on what's actually practical for youtube
which is just completely different than traditional media
so you train people and then those people train people and and so on
yeah
i mean it's just even like
you know how you do the lighting on sets or like
how you do the audio or
or
um
you know
not writing scripts
so you know
we're just not as efficient with our filming
like sometimes i have to have 30 cameras running
why
because it's not scripted
i don't
i don't know what chris is gonna do when we start filming
he might run over there
but guess what we got to have it planned
because there's only one shot
i can't
you know
tell them not to do that
yeah
that's the shooting
but then there's also the editing
yeah
and then the editing as well
and not having guardrails
and kind of
you know
i
at the end of the day
it's whatever i want the video
their job is to make a video that they think i'll like
because it's my channel
but you know you can achieve that kind of
however
and um
and so it's just everything's just different
you know it's much more
i guess
like a startup as opposed to um
are you often surprised like with the result
like you think
a certain
like
we watched the video today
that was really nice
those different than you would have potentially edited
yeah
are you sometimes surprised by
like a decision editor makes
it's like okay
that's not the way i would have done it
but it's actually this is a cool idea
yeah
of course
now
um
the thing my biggest fear is i don't ever want to get trapped in like a bubble of
you know
because we are getting 100 million views of video on the main channel
like
but i don't want to get in this feedback loop of just my ideas are great
or or not feedback loop
but stop learning and improving
because it is easy sometimes to be like what we're doing is working
we need to just keep doing it
i want to keep learning and trying new things
and i guess one way i'd put is like you don't when
when you're on a a come up or you're growing
you don't want to
uh
test new things once
you start to plateau or have a downtrend
because if you're like
you know you
you're skyrocketing
right
you're up up and then you level off
you start to go down and you're like
oh
this isn't working anymore
let's start experimenting
well
if you have a bad experiment now you're in like a tailspin
you're nose diving and you have one more bad experiment
you're like screwed
kind of i'm oversimplify
you want to test things while you're still growing to keep the growing from happening
because once you like
have you know again
very oversimplifying that
like you know
kind of level off
you do a couple tests that go wrong
am i
you're like screwed
you know you're already out the door
now you're just confirming that you're out the door
an online entertainment
so that's kind of how i see it
so i think it's very imperative that you're constantly always experimenting and trying things
even if you're getting crazy
unheard of growth
and so that
outside of the thing that brought you to the dance
you just dived right into
uh
mr beast burger and feastables
this is a whole nother industry
like
what was that like
well
so beast burger
we kind of it was supposed to be like just a pop-up like we just partnered with someone who had 300 restaurants
and we're just like you know
um
let's let's just
uh
sell beast burgers for a day or two
let's let's see what happens
we didn't really think it would be as big as it was
but those first like that first day
you know
we do six figures in sales and they all sell out and they're running to local walmarts
they can't keep up with the demand
and it's like okay
well
maybe let's just leave it open a week
whatever
um
and we're just doing crazy revenue and it's like okay
well
let's add some more restaurants
and let's just leave them open for a month and we're just still doing six figures a day
and it kind of just went from this thing that was
i don't know it wasn't really
i don't really plan on running a restaurant chain
but here i am
but didn't that in some sense also open your mind to something like festivals
feasible
is something i've always wanted to do
because i i think
just in general
uh
american snacks are just full of so much horrible ingredients
to be honest
and they're not
i don't know
i feel like there also just hasn't been any innovation in american snacks in quite a while
um
and so that's just something i've always been pretty passionate about
the thing
we built that from scratch
so we hired the ceo and built a team around them
and we
we spent probably over two and a half years before we even launched
just like building the right team
figuring things out and making sure it was actually ran the way i wanted
um
which feasible has just been crushing
it's
it's very interesting
uh
this is something i've never talked about publicly
but having products in retail
it's like before feastables
everything i had done was online
so if you wanted to
you know anything from the cocoa peace brand
you'd have to buy it online and ship it to you
but feastfuls
now that you know
because our first product
chocolate bars
we started putting that in retail locations
so
like
for example
walmart
it's
it's crazy
like
it's just
it doesn't make sense
how if you're which
i guess it does for
because we get 100 million views of videos
so a lot of people know us
if i go stand in walmart
those people recognize me and ask for photos
like if i still don't enough
i could take 150 photos today in walmart 200
whatever it is
so obviously it makes sense those people go find feastfuls
but then you just multiply that by every walmart in america
and it just gets so crazy
and i didn't think we'd be doing the kind of revenue we are
and we're about to launch in some other
i don't know if i'm allowed to say so whatever
but other big retail
you know
locations and convenience stores
and like
by the end of next year we could be in like 40
fifty thousand locations
and the numbers just don't make sense
so you know
what are some interesting challenges about scaling there
that surprised you
the biggest problem
which i didn't think would be was just keeping the shelves and walmart stock
to be honest
like it would have to supply
it was supply chain
it was brutal
well
even then
sometimes
like you know
you get them the stuff
and they're like
it takes them like a day or two to put it out in that specific location
and i i had to stop promoting it
because every time i'd mention it
like 40 of people would just be like it's not there
it's not in walmart or i can't buy it
and so there's like a three ish month period where i just didn't promote festivals
because i was scared that someone would go by
and this is not there
and so like
it took us a very long time to catch up to the demand
and also
it's not like we have unlimited money
so but now we're relatively caught up in um
keeping up
but it's gonna be interesting
because now this year in 2023
we're gonna
basically
you know
10x the amount of locations they're in
so
or
and we're gonna try to launch new products
so we're in for an interesting ride
but yeah
i just hate
i hate when i tell people you know like
hey
go try this product and then they go in their local walmart and eventually other places
and it's not there
it's just so brutal
you know they made that whole journey out there and they didn't get it
and so that that was
really it
um
besides that
no
it's
it's been doing way better than i ever thought
uh
you've talked to a couple places about maybe doing mobile games or computer games in the future
yeah
is that something you're still considering
yes
um
because
uh
you know
do you normally talk with people as much as we talked beforehand
is that
no
that that was the pro who spent all day today
look in my head
everything you asked me is stuff we already talked about
not really well
no
not everything
i take it back
but sorry
the last two questions
yes
and so it's just funny
because what
no
i tried it's okay
there's a different style of asking those questions because i
i
on purpose
didn't dig further with you
uh
i could tell
yeah
so i can tell you
okay
this is
by the way
okay
all right
well
this is the first time i've ever talked to somebody as much as i did with you beforehand
yeah
well
on the same day
i know we're not even saying okay
together
one hour
yeah
literally
it's funny
um
this is a hilarious and awesome social experiment
i think i picked this hotel and i just like harassed him all day to hang out with me
and then
great
here we are
now
i love it
um
i was secretly recording the whole time
just
you know
i'm just kidding
anyway
so what was the question
yeah
so the interesting thing is
uh
with beast burger and feastables that
um
there's physical goods
as opposed to like making mobile games or pc game
whichever one we end up doing
which is software
and i actually have a giant international audience
like
um
most of my audience is obviously outside of america
and so the problem we're running into is it just takes time to build up the supply chain
and get feastables in southeast asia
get festivals in india
get festivals in brazil and mexico and all these other places
where we have giant pockets of our audience and same thing with peaceful
it's just it's going to take probably years
uh
unless we partner with someone who already has the distribution
which we're figuring out
but the udf software is
i can make a hypothetical game or whatever we end up doing
and all my fans
can you know
use it tomorrow the day i mentioned it
and so if i promote something in a video to 100 million people and it's like
uh
you know
basically like a game
they can all download it
so there you know
um
but if i promote a feast rules bar right now
it's only in america because we're struggling just to keep up with american demand
we haven't even gotten the chance to go outside america
so i i alienate
i'm uh
a majority of my audience
and it feels so shitty to just from
you know
mention something that most of them can't buy
but on the flip side you can't just spawn this crazy infrastructure
and just have tens of millions of bars
and all your products in every single store across the world before you promote it
so you can't put the egg before the chicken
and so
um
it's like that
that's
that's what i'm excited about
i want to get into less physical stuff and more stuff that everyone matters can actually use
this is the thought process
especially if there's a social element to the gaming too
because it's not unlike feastables
like that's a product you consume
you missed it
when you're setting it for this
we were
uh
doing some
basically just laying out every everything that we're planning for
so our interfaces where we want to start hiring the team to build it
and we're kind of just laying out the game
and i was actually really curious to get your thoughts
but i can't say it
because whatever i say
someone's just gonna take it and run with it
but you're pretty good idea about the kind of games you're thinking about
yeah
i mean i can imagine we also talked a little bit about it
it's super awesome
good one
i did so much good talk
all right
the juicy talks having you
she's like
i gotta go set up
well
you know i
i already heard a lot awesome
i mean
but that is a different kind of team you would need to hire
yeah
is that a little
uh
nerve-wracking like going into a new field and trying to a little bit
but then i remind myself like
like steve jobs didn't know how to code right
and you know he just he just knew what a good product was
and i feel like as someone who wasted so much of his lives playing video games
i have a good sense of it
and that might be ignorance
well
that's really important
right
it's not about coding
it's about what makes for a good game
exactly
and again
that might genuinely be ignorant
so maybe i end up
you know
getting bit in the butt because of what i'm saying now
but i think
just like with youtube
i just want to obsess over making a great product and things that i think my audience will love
and i think
as long as i keep that as my north star will do
well
uh
what is the path to being worth 100 billion look like
doesn't have to be worth 100 billion look like
i don't know
because okay
okay
let me just like
pause here
24 and there's so much awesome scaling so many great ideas
you
you think about different trajectories
yeah
uh
what those possible trajectives might look like
yeah
i mean if the goal was to just be worth 100 billion dollars
yes
i'm my goal of a broken record
so make the best view impossible
because i know whatever else i want will come
obviously
the video is the foundation
yeah
exactly so to pat to 100 billion dollars just keep getting 100 million views of video
you know what i mean
um
but or more
oh yeah
or more
exactly if we can keep growing
but you know
if we can keep feasibles
growing right
and we eventually spend international
and one day we're in 100 000 retail locations
and we're selling the same amount of excuse or units per skews
like we're currently doing
uh
i mean that would crush
and then
obviously
ideally
one day we open up hundreds of beast burgers
we get it where we turn out
you know
like supercell
a couple hit games
i don't want to make dozens or hundreds of games
i just want to make games that are just great
and you know
we rarely drop them while we do
they're bangers
um
and just
you know
whatever other stuff
we end up doing all that combined
i mean it's just interesting
because like what
what's a show that's pulled 100 million views per episode
basically
that's like we're doing like
you know
i mean
like the super bowl gets praised because they get 100 million viewers
but i can't think of a show
um
maybe in reruns or something
so there's also a show that's has
uh
has a singular kind of figure
yeah
that you can now use as a
like
i don't have a network tell me what to do
i don't have anyone like
i can do whatever i want
so it's a very interesting position
because i put out content and 100 million people show up and then i also have a gaming channel
i put out content
15 million people show up in a reaction
10 million people show up and have a tick tock and i put out content and on average
20 million people show up and like
and i
so
as long as i can keep that going
and then we build these businesses
it's like
it's honestly pretty scary to see what will happen
you know
uh
over the years
because feastables launched
you know
last year 2022
so it's a relatively new thing and beast burger
we just started scaling up the physical side and we haven't obviously even launched any mobile games yet
so i think i'm at the antithesis of it
i don't see a world where my youtube channels are relevant in the next couple of years
i just this is what i live for
and so if i can keep that going
and then really start to expand these businesses that leverage off of it
then
yeah
i mean
hopefully there's the day one where i could give away a billion dollars in a video
honestly
that that
yeah
that would be one hell of a video
um
let me ask you the ridiculous question
since you went from being broke to being
uh
rich
although you keep
uh
spending all your money
um
but
uh
does money buy happiness
how has money changed
sort of your
your happiness in life
it's money by happiness
um
no
not
i mean to a point
yes
once you can take care of your health
you can take care of
like any immediate dangers and you can take care of your family
relatively
no
it doesn't like
but those things do like
when i first came into money
one of the first things i did was retire my mom and like that brought me tons of happiness
you know what i mean
and like
you know
if my brother had a medical emergency and and we couldn't afford it
and i made money to afford it
that would bring tons of happiness
you know
so
once you take care of those basic necessities
so we'll say makeover hypothetically a million dollars
no
it
it really doesn't like adding an extra zero going from 10 million to 100 million or whatever it is
makes no difference
so you're given that or just fearless and spending the money
yeah
well
let me reframe
i guess it could for some people
if
if you really i don't know you spent your whole life obsessing over cars
it probably would bring you a little bit of joy to buy a nice lamborghini
i
i'm coming more from the frame of mind of of an entrepreneur
someone who's really obsessed with business ability for me and a lot of my friends and people
i hang around
what brings us
happiness is winning and building companies
and do you know
changing the world like that
that is fun
it's a complex problem
you can wake up every day and it gives you something to obsess over and devote your life to
where it's just having money
doesn't you know
well
one interesting question for you psychologically
so
because you have become wealthy and because you give
like
part of your work is giving away a lot of money
um
do you find it hard to find people you can trust is do people see you basically as a source of money as opposed to another human being
it's weird because you would think
yes
but i i feel like i also know the right places to look
um
but yeah
if i just walked into target and try to make friends with 10 random people
of course
um
you gotta
uh
so you can kind of sense
oh
yeah
that's the right thing
that's
yeah
it's so obvious
so i don't even want to go into descriptions
but honestly
a lot of my friends are like
uh
chandler
i i played literally with him
um
and tyler
the guy
i mean i went to school with him
chris
he was my first subscriber
um
carl was here after we got big
but whatever
he's friends with the boys
and it is a lot of my closer friends
even like my youtube friends
i i knew before i was big
so maybe there is some mirror to that
maybe it is
i
i don't know
i've never really put too much thought into it
maybe there's a reason i hang around a lot of these people i knew before i got paid
because it's much easier and they help you keep
like
uh
your radar sharp of who can and can't be trusted
because you know you can trust them
yeah
it's difficult when you become richer and richer and more powerful
well
one day
one time when you get rich
oh yeah
not even richer
but more fan
one thing i thought is
as i climbed this like ladder of youtube and got bigger
i thought there would be tons of people like me
people
how to like that
takes
like the kamikaze approach to building a business
you just throw all your money in it
you throw all your time
you throw all your energy throw everything
yeah
you're just like
fuck it
this is this
i'm dead
yeah
i thought there would be hundreds of these
and and there isn't there is
i mean there's like maybe one or two and i talked to those motherfuckers every single day
i'm sick and tired of talking to them
but i love them
um
but it's just so interesting
because like every level i got up like i get a million subscribers
like all right
where's all these guys in the million subscribers that are fucking psychopaths
and then you know
you know
there are people become like conservative as they get
like
they get more
especially as they get bigger
yeah
and you know
20 million subscribers
30. it's like every step of the way
it's like i just got more and more lonely
to be honest
since you
you know it sounds cliche and you hear that kind of shit in movies and you're like
that's not how it works
but it is like there's
there's just not many people that just want to give up everything
go all in and obsess over making the greatest goddamn videos every single day of their life
like they're really hard to find and be able to sacrifice everything for that video
yeah
like
basically you put all the money right back in
yeah
or the people doing it
they're on just a small scale
and if i talk to them
it's just 99. 9 of the time i'm teaching them things
and it's like
so it's lonely
because there's not too many people especially in the creative space that are as crazy as you
yeah
it is 100
it's
so
it's not what i
i was expecting
i was expecting there'd be a lot of people like me
but well
i guess the guy would talk to elon musk
is a bit like you in
that sense
yeah
just in a different domain
exactly
just willingness to put it all back in right
and that's why i found right now
a lot of the people i relate to don't even make youtube videos like they're just like i'm viewing more
and more away from fellow content creators and more to just
you know
i'm just looking for those other people who just share a little bit of it
so i don't feel so fucking crazy all the time
like you know what i mean
um
and
like people
i feel normal around and they tend to just be doing the randomest things
but you know
loving it well i think that's really inspiring
it's
uh
it's like the bukowski line to find what you love and let it kill you is really put everything
put everything into the thing you love
that
that's like the way to really create special stuff
but it's also the way to
yeah
you have to be careful
given this advice
because they're like
they're like bodybuilders who'll be like
just go to the gym
be disciplined
i'm disciplined
go to gym
but i would argue for those people
it's like it's not even discipline
they just enjoy weightlifting right
because there are people who are jacked
but they don't make much money or run a business
right
if they're that disciplined
they would
they would be hitting every area of their life
they just really like business
and there's people like me who just to an extreme level
love building companies
right
it's not even discipline for me
it's just in my blood
it's what i wake up
i don't think about it
i don't push myself
i don't need to watch a fucking motivational video to go work
i just do it
it's programmed in me at this point and i couldn't imagine a world
where i don't wake up and do it every day
um
but i think that a little bit of it is genetics
and just how you're hardwired
uh
not that it can't be trained or taught
and not that you know
and obviously the friend group you're in influences these things
and over time i think can change it
but someone's just not gonna be able to flip a switch
and then just start doing a kamikaze approach to building a business
just like a lot of people try to flip a switch and start bodybuilding and quit
majority of the time
you know
that's just not innate to them
but i think a lot of us have the capacity to do that in some domain
yeah
i think
if you went about strategically
if you surrounded yourself with fellow like-minded people and you know
slowly over time
switched it
uh
but if you just try to like hardcore
do it
you're just going to lose your mind
do you ever worry about your mental health
did you take step to protect it to
uh
yeah
to like for the long run
to make sure you have the mental strength to go on
yes
weirdly
enough
the best thing for my mental health was giving in to my innate nature to work
and the most depressed i get is when i try to restrict it and like i don't work weekends
so i don't work this day
what's best for me is just to work when i feel like working
and then just not work when i don't like and just have no constraints
because there are just some nights where i don't want to sleep
and for whatever reason i feel compelled to go all night
whatever like
just do it
you know
do
whatever you want
it's what i tell my like working brain
um
and i just give in to it and i feel that's where i feel the happiest
and and then
um
you know
it's typically like when i'm really in the grind mode
it'll be like seven or eight days
it's just non-stop going going
and then it's like
oh
i'll realize like
i need some recharge time and then go fucking binge a season of anime
yeah
but listen here
but that's the thing
like people will tell you don't work weekends or don't do this or don't work past this or blah
blah
give you all these constraints
but for me
and it's unconventional
i just give into it
i think there's something really to be said for that
i i try to surround myself with people that
like what i don't
when i pull an all-nighter they don't go
like you should get more sleep
there's a reason i pulled that all-nighter like
if i'm really passionate about something
they say
they basically encourage it because i i have no problem getting sleep and getting rest
um
what i need in my life is people that encourage you to kind of keep going
keep going with the thoughts that you're passionate about normal people
they don't want that life and they probably shouldn't
it's not good for you
um
but yeah
is
if you hang around people like just whatever
different people you're gonna feel crazy and it's gonna wear on you
whereas
if you're around similar people
it just it's so much easier
like if you
you know
um
i've started weightlifting more
and like
one thing that's helped is just having jack people around me because they naturally just eat healthier
they do
like
they naturally just have freaking grilled chicken and all this shit and high protein meals
and it's just like easier for me to just piggyback and be like
oh
can you just order me whatever you're getting
uh
and they're like
i gotta go to the gym and i'll be like
oh shit
i'll just join you
you know
and it's like
it's just it's cheat codes
you know
i mean
just surround yourself with people that you want to be
and it makes it like 70
easier
in my opinion
it's like that is the cheat code to life
um
and i wish i
obviously
your audience is definitely a lot older
but you know
to the older people listening like
if you have
are in a place of mentorship for someone younger or have influence over younger people
you should really try to drill
that in their heads like the people are there around 100 dictates the outcome
i would not be on 120 million subscribers
if i didn't find
uh
when i was around a million
i had a couple friends that were just also psychopaths
you know
i outgrew them
but at the time it was great
and i wouldn't be where i am today if it wasn't for them
um
and just all along the way
the friends that i hung out with had such a dramatic impact on wearing them
like
i'd probably have 80 million less subscribers
you know
if it was
if i wasn't so strategic about hanging out with people that i add value to
and they also add value to me
so the advice for young people would be to be very selective about the people you saw yourself
so selective
it's
it's crazy
like chris
you know he's i
i
he's really funny and that's why he's great for the videos
and part of why he's so funny is he consumes copious amounts of cartoons and just funny content
and so i'll find
like
when i spend more time with chris
i'll start just quoting these weird cartoons and shows
and like my speech will literally change
and just after like a week of spending more time with them
it has
like
it's like that quick enough effect
you know
now
picture that over the course of years
i mean
yeah
it has such a huge influence
like pluck one of their friends out and hypothetically put me in there
and yeah
you know
there's no doubt if they're trying to become a content creator
there are odds of success is 10x
right
obviously you can't do that
but you got to find your closest version of it and just be selective
yeah
but this also applies not just to younger
to older people to agree
but they
it's
it's even more
i like when i was a teenager
i just
you know
i couldn't relate to many people
i just i was like a fucking freaking nature
because no one was obsessed with building businesses or any of this kind of stuff
and so like
back then
you know that advice would have been helpful
maybe not that particular
but just knowing that there are
you know
it's not that you're a freaking nature
you just haven't found people that have the same interests
so the task is not to feel sorry for yourself or somehow change yourself
it's more to finally find people you fit in with
yeah
assuming which you know
you're not getting comproment
uh
like
assume
it's not something bad
right
like
if your hobby is shooting things you know or shooting things
you shouldn't be shooting
you know
don't find people that encourage that
but outside of that
for sure
uh
actually
as an answer to what is the best advice someone ever gave you
you said you're crazy until you're successful
then you're a genius 100
all along the way
people gave me so much
you know advice on why i shouldn't be doing it
why i'm crazy
every step of the way
people wanted to tell me why i shouldn't be doing this and should get alive
should stop being too obsessed
everything
everything under the book
um
and then
once i'm successful
those same people are like tank
you're a genius
wow
you
really
you pulled that off
those are probably the same people that will give you advice
now you're the most successful video creator of all time
stick to that anytime you want to do something new
right
yeah
uh
they'll
they'll like pressure you not to do the um
you know
feastables or or mobile gaming or whatever lays beyond
yeah
it's funny how people don't well
honestly
they're the type of people i just don't talk to anymore
i don't even know what they have to say now
so most people on the team are like yes
and they're like whatever
the idea you got
they
they're with it
no
it's weird
we actually have a
my team pushes back on me pretty hardcore
which i want
i don't want yes man
and yeah
they're
they're like
uh
they're james
you know
the ceo who helped me build all this
um
he's very adamant
like we're not yes men and and he trains people to really think for themselves and even
when i give them orders like really think like
is this optimal
is there context
or information jimmy could be missing that i can provide that could help him make a more updated decision
like i'm not
um
god
you know
what
i mean
like i'm human
i make errors and so don't take what i say
that's the bible
so even
like in the brainstorming
and so on
they can
they can push back
yeah
you can see it
like tyler
anytime i said something
he would give me feedback and push back
which is what i want
i don't want him just to be like
yes
you're fucking genius
good job
jimmy
you know i don't need that
you know
i need negatives
uh
you talked about being in a relationship
what role
jimmy does love playing the human condition
i think
well
roll this
the big thing is love can be scary
because this is
you know
the human you're gonna spend the most amount of time with in your life
and so
for projected over 50 years
they can be a liability or an asset
i love the magic tricks
you know
i love
no
but seriously
it's got to be someone that makes you better for me
i can't truly love someone that doesn't make me better
because
yeah
in the long run
across
because
if not
then it's like it's a negative
you know
to everything i've spent my life building
yeah
um
but luckily i'm very happy with the
the partner i haven't like we were talking about before
i do think she makes me better
there's a lot of actually positives
i've noticed
even things as simple as
like
you know
i struggle to turn off my brain at night
because i'm just thinking about all the businesses
and how we could do better or whatever weird thing i have on my mind
but you know
just chatting with her
and hanging out with her helps me like basically just shut my brain off and like mellow out
and even
like there's just a ton of little things like that that i've noticed are positives
especially when you really look for them that are easy to gloss over
if you're not
um
and so for me
yeah
i have someone who i think it's very beautiful
very intelligent
makes me better
it's constantly pushing me
okay with me working hard
makes me smarter
and just all these different things that i think for me love just makes me a better person
you know what i mean
which makes me love her even more
does that make sense
absolutely
what advice would you give on
uh
finding somebody like that
um
just really don't give up until you
you find someone that you know
there's so many people on the planet
i mean there really is there
there's billions of the odds are in your favor of yeah
like
just don't settle and find someone that you know makes you happy
yeah
just like you said
surround yourself with people that make you a better person
in the same case
surround yourself with that one special person that really makes you a better person and for
and maybe that's just an entrepreneurial brain
looking at it
not everyone's to hyper optimize their life like me
but for me to like
truly love someone
they have to make me a better person in every way
yeah
well
what do you hope you're 24. we thought we started talking about death
let's let's finish talking about death what do you hope your legacy is
when you
when we look a hundred years from now
and
yeah
alien
the ai has completely taken over and the aliens visit and discuss with the ai
what this last of special humans that existed on earth was like
what
what do you hope they say about you
um
it's a deep one
as probably just that
because it's hard
right
like i said before elon is over double my age
i could live every second i've lived up to this point in my life and still have elon's age
so i have so much time
i just hope whatever it is that it's a net positive on the world
and it impacts billions of people in a positive way that makes lasting change
so you admire people like steve jobs
and elon musk for having sort of reached for that goal as well
yeah
of course
to help to help millions
i mean the iphone's the most successful product ever invented
it's hard not to admire what he created
you know
um
the same with
sort of
as johnny ive talks about
like the
the passion the effort they put into the designing the iphone that
like little bit of love is transferred to the whole world
like they get to experience the joy of that from the designer
it's what a beautiful thing to do
you know
i mean i couldn't think of anything better
to create something that
even after you're dead for decades
just has such a profound impact on basically half the human population
yeah
it's wild
brings joy to people
yeah
um
well
i hope you do just that man
you've already done it for millions and millions and millions and millions of people
and i hope you keep doing it
i'm ex
i can't like
it's so exciting to see what happens this year and next year
i know
like this is the limit
yeah
i can't
i mean
uh
the videos
but ever all the other businesses
you're in and you
as a human being
as you grow
i can tell
i know
as everyone knows
you have a kind heart and the fact that you're really damn good at
uh
actually using that kind of heart to help a lot of people
it's awesome to see man
i appreciate it
more importantly
before we go
yeah
are we gonna play dune tonight
it's important
i'm gonna play dude
i have to
i have
you don't want one hour
you don't want to play board games with me
i wanna
i'll play
i'll play four games
if if only i wasn't an idiot and actually flew to the right airport
yeah
i do more games with me
they're gonna dislike the video
thanks for listening to this conversation with mr beast to support this podcast
please check out our sponsors in the description
and now let me leave you with some words from the poet and philosopher
rabindranath
tagore
reach high for stars
lie hidden in you
thank you for listening and hope to see you next time