the following is a conversation with neil ferguson
one of the great historians of our time at times controversial
and always brilliant
whether you agree with him or not
he's an author of 16 books
on topics
covering
the history of money power
war pandemics
and empire
previously at harvard currently at stanford and today
launching a new university here in austin texas called the university of austin a new institution
built from the ground up to encourage open inquiry and discourse
by both thinkers and doers from philosophers and historians
to scientists and engineers
embracing debate dissent and self-examination
free to speak to disagree to think to explore truly novel ideas
the advisory board includes stephen pinker jonathan height and many other amazing people with one exception
me
i was graciously invited to be on the advisory board which i accepted
in the hope of doing my small part in helping build the future of education
and open discourse
especially in the fields of artificial intelligence robotics and computing
we spend the first hour of this conversation talking about this new university
before switching to
talking about some of the darkest moments in human history
and what they reveal
about human nature
this is the lex friedman podcast
to support it please check out our sponsors in the description
and now here's my conversation with neil ferguson
you are one of the great historians of our time respected sometimes controversial
you've flourished in some of the best universities in the world from nyu
to london school of economics to harvard
and now to hoover institution at stanford
before we talk about the history of money war and power
let us talk about a new university
you're part of launching
here in austin texas
it is called university of austin
uatx
what is its mission its goals its plan
i think it's pretty obvious
to a lot of people in higher education that there's a problem
and that problem manifests itself in a great many different ways
but i would sum up the problem as being
a drastic
chilling of the atmosphere
that constrains free speech free exchange even free thought
and i had never anticipated
that this would happen in my lifetime my academic career began in oxford in the 1980s
when
anything went one sensed that a university was a place where one could risk
saying the unsayable and debate the undebatable
so the fact that in a relatively short space of time
a variety
of ideas
critical race theory or wokeism
whatever you want to call a variety of ideas have come along
that seek to limit and quite drastically limit what we can talk about
strikes me as deeply unhealthy
and i'm not
sure
and i've thought about this for a long time you can fix
it with the existing
institutions
i think you need to create a new one and so after much deliberation
we decided to do it and i think it's a hugely timely opportunity
to
do what people used to do in this country which was to create new institutions
i mean that used to be the default setting of america
we sort of stopped doing that i mean i look back and i thought why why
why are there no new universities
or at least if there are why do they have so little impact
it seems like we have the billionaires
we have the need let's do it so you still believe
in institutions in the university in the ideal of the university
i believe passionately in that ideal
there's a reason they've been around for nearly a millennium
there is a a unique thing that happens
on a university
campus when it's done right and that is the transfer of knowledge between generations
that is a very sacred activity and it seems to
withstand
major changes in technology so this form that we call the university predates the printing press
survive the printing press
continue to function through the scientific revolution the enlightenment
the industrial revolution
to this day and i think it's because
maybe because of evolutionary psychology we need to be together
in one relatively confined
space
when we're in our late teens and early 20s
for the knowledge transfer between the generations to happen
that's my feeling about this but in order for it to work well
there need to be very few constraints
there needs to be a sense that one can take intellectual risk remember
people in their late teens and early 20s are adults but they're inexperienced adults
and if i look back on my own time as an undergraduate
saying stupid things was my mo
my way to finding
good ideas was through a minefield
of bad ideas
i feel so sorry
for my
for people like me today people age 18 19 20 today
who are
intellectually
very curious ambitious but inexperienced
because the minefields today
are absolutely lethal and you know one wrong food
and it's cancellation i said this to peter thiel the other day
imagine being asked now i mean we were obnoxious
undergraduates
there's nothing
that peter did at stanford that andrew sullivan and i were not doing at oxford
and perhaps we were even worse
but it was so so not career ending to be to be an absolutely insufferable
obnoxious
undergraduate then
today if we if we
if people like us exist today they must live in a state of of constant anxiety
that they're going to be
outed for some heretical
statement that they made five years ago on social media so
part of what motivates me is that it's the desire to give
the means of today a shot at free thinking and really i i'd call it
aggressive learning learning where you're really pushed
and i just think that stopped happening
on the the major campuses
because whether at harvard where i used to teach at stanford where i'm now based i
i sense a kind of suffocating
atmosphere of self-censorship
that that means people are afraid
to take even minimal risk in in class i mean just just take for example
a survey that was published
earlier this year that revealed
this is of undergraduates in four-year programs in the us
85 percent of self-described liberal students said they would report a professor to the university administration
if he or she said something they considered offensive
and something like 75 said said they do it to a fellow undergraduate
that's the kind of culture that's evolved in our universities
so we need a new university in which none of that is true
in which you can speak your mind
say stupid things get it completely wrong
and live to
to tell the tale there's a lot more going on i think because
when you start thinking about what's wrong with a modern university
many many more things suggest themselves
and i think there's an opportunity
here to build something that's radically new in in some ways and radically traditional
in other ways for example i have a strong preference for
the tutorial system that you see at oxford and cambridge which is small group teaching
and and highly socratic in its structure
i think it'd be great to bring that to the united states where it doesn't really
exist but at the same time i think we should be doing
some very 21st century things
making sure that while people are reading and studying classic works
they're also going to be immersed in the real world
of technological innovation a world that you know very well
and i'd love to get a synthesis
of the ancient and classical which we're gradually letting fade away with the novel
and technological so we we want to produce people who can simultaneously talk intelligently
about adam smith or for that matter shakespeare or proust and
have a conversation with you about where a.i is going
and how long it will be before i can get driven
here by
a self-driving
vehicle allowing me to have my lunch and prepare rather than
focus on
the other crazy people on the road so
that's the dream that we can create something which is
you know partly classical and partly 21st century
and we look around
and we we don't see it if you if you don't see an institution
that you really think should exist
i think you have a more responsibility to create it
so you're thinking including
something bigger than just liberal education also including science engineering and technology i should also comment
that
you know i mostly stay out of politics and out of some of these
aspects of liberal education that kind of been the most controversial and difficult within the university
but there is a kind of ripple effect of fear within that space
into science and engineering and technology that i think
has
has a nature that's difficult to describe
it doesn't have a controversial nature it just has a nature of fear where you're not
you know you're not just saying stupid stuff as a young 20 year old
you know
for example
deep learning
machine learning is really popular
in the computer science now as an approach for creating artificial intelligence systems
it's
it is controversial in that space to say that
anything against machine learning saying
sort of exploring ideas that saying this is going to lead to a dead end
um now that that takes some guts to do as a young 20 year old within
within a classroom
to think like that to raise that question in a machine learning course it sounds ridiculous
because it's like who's going to
complain about this but the the fear that starts
in
in a course on history
or
on the some course that covers society the fear ripples
and affects those students they're asking big out of the box questions about engineering
about computer science
and there's a lot you know there's like linear algebra that's not going to change
but then there's like applied
linear algebra which is machine learning and that's when
robots and
real systems touch human beings and that's when you have to
ask yourself these difficult questions about
about humanity
even in engineering and science and technology courses and these are not
separate worlds in two senses
i've just
taken delivery of my copy of the book that eric schmidt and henry kissinger have
co-authored
on artificial intelligence the central
question of which is what does this mean for us broadly
but they're not separate worlds
you know in cp snow's
sense of you know the the chasm between science and arts because on a university campus
everything is contagious from a novel coronavirus to the behaviors that are occurring
in the english department
those behaviors if denunciation
becomes a norm
you know undergraduate denounces
professor teaching assistant denounces undergraduate those behaviors are contagious and will spread inexorably
first to social science and then to natural sciences and i think that's
that's part of the reason why
when this started to happen when we started to get the origins of
disinvitation and cancel culture
it was not just
a few conservative
professors in the humanities who had to worry everybody
had to worry because eventually
it was going to come even to the most apparently
hard stem
part of the the campus
it's it's contagious this is something nicholas christakis should look at because he's
very good at looking at the way in which
social networks like the ones that exist in a university can spread
everything
but i think when when we look back and ask why did wokism
spread so rapidly
and rapidly out of humanities into other parts of universities and why did it spread
across the country and d beyond the united states to the other english-speaking
universities it's because it's a contagion
and and these behaviors are contagious
the president of a university
i won't name said to me that he receives
every day at least one denunciation
one call for somebody or other to be fired for something that they
said
that's the crazy kind of totalitarianism
light
that now exists in our our universities
and of course the people who want to downplay
this say oh well there only have been 100 and something in dis invitations
or oh there really aren't that many cases but the point is that
the famous events the events that get the attention
are responsible for a general chilling
that as you say spreads to every part of the university
and creates a
very familiar culture
in which people are afraid to say what they think self-censorship
look at the heterodox academy data on this
grows and grows so now a majority
of students will say this is clear from the latest heterodox
academy surveys
we are scared to say what we think in case
we get denounced in case we get cancelled
but that's just not the correct atmosphere
for a university in a free society
to me what's really
creepy
is how many of the behaviors i see
on university campuses today are reminiscent
of the way that people used to behave in the soviet union
or in the soviet bloc or in maui's china
the sort of totalitarianism
light that i think we're we're contending with here which manifests itself as denunciations
people informing on superiors some people using it for career advantage
other people reduced to hapless desperate apology to try to exonerate themselves people disappearing
metaphorically if not literally all of this is so reminiscent
of the totalitarian
regimes that i studied earlier in my career that it makes me feel
sick
and what makes me really feel sick is that
the people
doing this stuff the people who write the letters of denunciation
are apparently
unaware that they're behaving exactly like people in stalin's soviet union they don't know that
so they clearly have there's been a massive educational failure
if somebody can write an anonymous or non-anonymous letter of denunciation
and not feel shame
i mean you should feel morally completely contaminated
as you are doing that but but people haven't been taught the realities of totalitarianism
for all these reasons i think
you need to
try at least to create a new institution
where those pathologies will be
structurally excluded
so
maybe a difficult question maybe you'll push back on this
but you're widely seen politically as a conservative
hoover institution is politically conservative
what is the role of politics at the university of austin because some of the ideas
people listening to this when they hear the ideas you're expressing
they may think there's a lien to these ideas
there's a conservative
lean to these ideas is there such a lien
there will certainly be people who say that because the standard
mode of trying to discredit any new initiative is to say oh this is a sinister
conservative
plot but one of our co-founders heather heing is definitely not a conservative
she's as committed to the idea of academic freedom
as i am
but i think on political issues we probably agree on almost nothing
and at least i i would guess
but but politics
max weber made this point a long time ago
the politics really should stop at the threshold of the
the classroom
of the lecture
hall
and in my career
i've always
tried to make sure that when i'm teaching
it's not
clear where i stand politically
though of course undergraduates
and insatiably
curiously
want to know but it shouldn't be clear from what i say because indoctrination
on a political basis
is
an abuse of the power of the professor
as weber rightly said
so i think one of the key principles
of of the university of austin will be that barbarian principle
that politics is not
an appropriate
subject for the lecture hall for the classroom and we should pursue truth
and enshrine
liberty of thought
if that's a political issue then i can't help you i mean if you're against
freedom of thought then we don't really have much of a discussion to have
and clearly there are some people who politically
seem quite hostile
to it but my sense is that there are plenty
of people on the left in academia
i think of
that interesting partnership between cornell west
and robbie george
which has been institutionalized
in the academic freedom alliance it's bipartisan
this issue it really really is after all
50 years ago it was the left that was in favor of free speech
the right still has an anti-free speech
element to it look how quickly they're out to
ban critical race theory critical race theory won't be banned at the university of texas
wokism won't be banned
everything will be up for discussion
but the rules of engagement will be clear chicago principles
those will be enforced
and if you have to give a lecture on well let's just take a recent example
the dorian abbott case if you're giving a lecture on astrophysics
but it turns out that in some different venue
you express skepticism
about a formative action
well it doesn't matter it's irrelevant
we want to know what your thoughts are on astrophysics because that's
what you're supposed to be doing a lecture on that used to be understood
i mean at the oxford of the 1980s
there were communists
and there were ultratories
at cambridge there were people who were so reactionary
that they celebrated franco's birthday
but they were also out and out communists
down the road at king's college
the understanding was that that kind of intellectual diversity
was part and parcel of
university
life and frankly for undergraduate
it was great fun to cross the road and go from
you know outright conservatism
ultra
tourism to communism one learns a lot that way
but the issue is when you're promoting or hiring or tenuring people
their politics is not relevant it really isn't
and when it started to become relevant
and i remember this coming up at the harvard history department late in my time there
felt deeply deeply uneasy
that we were having conversations
that amounted to well we can't heart x person despite their obvious academic qualifications because
of some political issue that that's not what should happen at a healthy university
some practical questions
will university of austin be a physical in person university or virtual university what are some
in that aspect where the classroom is it will be a real space institution
there may be an online
dimension to it because there clearly are a lot of things that you can do
via the internet but the core activity
of of teaching and learning i think requires
real space and i've
thought about this a long time debated
sebastian
throne about this many many years ago when he was a complete
believer in
let's call it the metaversity
to go with the metaverse i mean the metaversity
was going to happen wasn't it but i never really believed in the metaversity
i didn't do moocs because i just didn't think you'd a be able to retain
the attention b be able to cope with the scale
scaled
grading that was involved
i think
there's a reason universities have been around and that they're formed for about a millennium
you kind of need to all be in the same place
so i think answer to that question definitely
a campus in the austin area that's where we'll start
and if we can
allow some of our content to be available online great we'll certainly do that
another question is what kind of courses and programming
will it offer is that something you can speak to what's your vision here
we think that we need to begin
more like a startup than
like a full service university
from day one so our vision is that we start with a summer school
which will offer provocatively the forbidden courses we we want i think to begin by giving
a platform
to the professors who've been most
subject to council culture and also to give an opportunity
to students
who want to hear them to come so we'll start with the summer
school that will be
somewhat in the tradition of
of those institutions
in the interwar period that were havens for refugees
so we're we are dealing here with the internal refugees
of
of the work era
we'll start there it'll be an opportunity to test out some
some content see what students will come
and spend time in austin to hear so that's part a that's the sort of
if if you like the launch product and then we go straight to a masters
program i don't think you can go to undergraduate education right away
because the established brands in undergraduate education are offering
something it's impossible to compete with initially because they have the brand harvard yale stanford
and they offer also this peer network
which is part of the reason people want
so badly to go to those places not really the professors
it's the
classmates
so we don't want to compete there initially
where there is i think room for new entrants is in
a masters program
and the first one will be in entrepreneurship and leadership
because i think there's a huge hunger
amongst people who want to get into particularly the technology world
to learn about those things and they know they're not really
going to learn about
them at business
schools
the people who are not going to teach them leadership and entrepreneurship
are professors
so we want to create something that will
be a little like
the very successful
schwarzman
program
in china which was come and spend a year in china and find out about china
we'll be doing the same
essentially saying come and spend a year and find out about technology
and there'll be a mix of academic content
we want people to understand
some of the first principles of what they're studying
there are first principles of entrepreneurship
and leadership but we also want them to spend time with
people like one of our co-founders
joe lonsdale who's been a hugely
successful venture capitalist and and learned directly from people
like him so
that's the kind of initial
offering i think there are other masters
programs
that we will look to roll out quite quickly
i have a particular passion
for a masters in applied history or politics and applied history
i'm a historian driven crazy by the tendency of academic historians
to drift away from
what seemed to me the important questions
and certainly to drift away from addressing
policy relevant questions so i would love to be involved in
in in a masters in applied history
and we'll we'll build some programs like that before we get to the full liberal arts
experience that we envisage for an undergraduate program
and that undergraduate
program is an exciting one because i think we can be innovative there too i
i would say two years
would be spent
doing some very classical
and difficult classical things
those old divides between arts and sciences
but then there would also be in the second
in the second half in the junior and senior years
something somewhat more of an apprenticeship
where we'll have centers including a center for technology engineering mathematics
that will be designed to to help people make that transition
from the theoretical to the the practical
so that's the vision
and i think like any like any early stage
idea
we'll doubtless tweak it as we go along
we'll find things that work and things that don't work
but i have a very clear
sense in my own mind of how this
should look five years from now
and i don't know about you i mean i i'm unusual
as an academic because i quite like starting new institutions
and i've done a bit of it
in my career
you got to kind of know what it should look like
after
the first
four or five
years
to
get out of bed in the morning
and put up with all the kind of
hassles of doing it not not least the inevitable
flack that we we're bound to take from the educational
establishment
and i was graciously invited to be an advisor to this
university of austin and one the reason i would
love to help in whatever way i can
is several so one i would love to see austin the physical location flourish intellectually
and especially
in the space of science and engineering that's really exciting to me
another reason is i am still a research scientist at mit i still love mit
and i see this effort
that you're launching as a as a
beacon
that leads the way to the other elite institutions in the world
i think too many of my colleagues and especially in robotics
kind of see
don't see robotics as a humanities problem but to me
robotics and ai will define much of our world in the next century
and for not to consider
all the deep psychological sociological
human problems associated with that
to have real open conversations to say stupid things to challenge
the ideas that
of how companies are being run for example
that is the safe space it's very difficult to talk about the difficult questions about technology
when you're employed by facebook or google and so on
the university
is the place to have those conversations
that's right we're hugely excited
that you want to be one of our advisors
we we need a
a broad
and an eclectic
group of people
and i'm excited by the way that group has
has has developed
it has some of the some of my favorite intellectuals are there steve pinker for example
but but we're also you know making sure that we have people with experience in
academic leadership
and so it's a it's a happy coalition of the willing
looking to try to build something new which as you say will be complementary
to
the existing and established institutions
i think of the academic world as a as a network
i've moved from some major hubs
in the network
to others but i've always felt that we do our best work
not in a silo
called oxford but
in a silo that
that is really a hub connected
to stanford
connected
to
harvard
connected to mit
one of the reasons
i moved to the united
states was that i sensed
that there was
more
intellectual
action in my original field of expertise
financial history and
that was right it was it was a good move i think i'd have stagnated
if i'd stayed
at oxford
but at the same time i i haven't lost connection
with oxford i recently went and gave a lecture there
in honour of sir roger scrutin one of the great conservative philosophers
and the burden of my lecture was
the idea of the anglo-sphere which appealed a lot to roger will go horribly wrong if
illiberal ideas that inhibit academic freedom spread all over the anglo-sphere
and this network gets infected with
these i think deeply
deeply damaging notions so yeah i think we're creating a new node
i hope it's a node that makes the network overall
more resilient
and
right now there's an urgent need for it i mean there are people
whose academic careers have been terminated
i'll name two who are involved peter bogosian who was harassed out of portland state
for the reason that he was one of those
intrepid figures who carried out the grievance studies
hoaxes
exposing the utter charlatan ray going on in many supposedly academic journals by getting phony
gender studies articles published was genius and of course
so put the noses out of joints of the academic establishment
that he began to be subject to disciplinary
actions
so peter is going to be involved and in a recent
shocking british case
the philosopher kathleen stock has essentially been run off the campus of sussex university
in england
for trans
for violating the the increasingly complex rules about discussing
transgender
issues and
women's rights
she will be
one of our advisors and i think also one of our founding
fellows actually teaching
for us in our in our first iteration so
i think we're creating a node that's badly needed
those people i mean i remember saying this to
the the other founders when we first began to talk about this idea
to barry weiss
and to panic and losses pano canelos as well as to heather heing
we need to do this urgently
because there are people whose livelihoods are in fact being destroyed
by these extraordinarily
illiberal campaigns
against them and so
there's no time to hang around and come up with the perfect design
this this is an urgently needed lifeboat
and let's start with that and then we can build something spectacular
taking advantage of the fact that all of these people have
well they now have very
real skin in the game they they need to make this a success
and and i'm sure they will help us make it a success
so you mentioned some interesting names like heather heing barry weiss and so on
stephen
pinker somebody i really admire
he too was under a lot of quite a lot of fire
many reasons i admire him one because of his optimism about the future and two
how little of a dam he seems to give
about the
like walking
through the fire
there's nobody
more zen
about
walking
through the fire
than stephen
pinker
but
anyway you mentioned a lot of interesting names jonathan height is also interesting there
um who is involved with this venture at this early days
well
one of the
one of the things that that i'm excited
about is
is that we're getting people from
inside and outside the academic world so we've got
arthur brooks who for many years ran the american enterprise very s enterprise institute very successfully
has a harvard role now teaching
and and so he's somebody who brings i think a different perspective
there's obviously a a need to get experienced
academic leaders involved
which is why i was talking to larry summers about
whether he would join our board of advisors
the chicago principals owe a debt to the former president of chicago and he's
graciously
agreed to be in the board of advisors
i could go on it would become a long and tedious list but
my goal in in trying to get this happy band to form has been
to signal that it's a bipartisan
endeavor it is not
a conservative institution that we're trying to build it's an institution that's committed to academic freedom
and the pursuit of truth
that will mean it when it takes
robert zimmer's chicago principles and enshrines them in its its founding charter and will make those
something other than honored in the breach which they seem to be at some institutions
so the idea here is is to grow this organically
we need
rather like the academic freedom alliance that robbie george created earlier this year we need breadth
and we need to show that this is not some kind of
institutionalization of the intellectual dark web though we welcome founding members of that
that
nebulous body it's really something designed for all of academia
to provide a kind of reboot that i i think we all agree is is needed
is there a george washington
type figure who is is there a president
elected yet or is is
who's going to lead this institution hannah canelos
the former president of st john's
is the president of university of austin
and so he is our george washington
i don't know who alexander hamilton is i'll lead you to guess
it's funny you mentioned idw intellectual dark web have you
talked to your friend sam harris about but any others he
um
he is another person i really admire and i've talked to online and offline
quite a bit for
not belonging to any tribe he stands boldly on his convictions
when he knows they're not going to be popular
with like he based
he basically gets canceled by every group he sort of he doesn't shy away from controversy
and not for the sake of controversy itself he is
one of the best examples to me of a person who thinks freely
i disagree with him on a few quite a few things
but
i deeply admire
that he is he he is what it looks like to think freely by himself
it feels to me like he represents
a lot of the ideals of this kind of effort yes he would be a natural
fit sam if you're listening i hope you're in
i think in in the course of his recent intellectual
quests
he did collide with one of our founders heather hying so
we'll have to model civil disagreements
at the university of austin it's extremely
important that we should all disagree about many things but do it
amicably
one of the things that has been lost
sight of perhaps
it's all the fault of twitter or maybe it's something more profound
is that
it is possible to disagree
in a civil way and
and still be friends i certainly had
friends at oxford who were
far to the left of me politically
and
they are still among my best friends so
the university of austin has to be a place where we can
disagree
we can disagree vehemently
but we can then go and have a beer afterwards
that's that's in my mind a really important part of university life learning
the difference between the political
and the
and the personal
so sam
is a
i think a a
good example
as a you
of
a certain kind of intellectual
hero
who has been willing to go into the cyber
sphere the metaverse and carve out an intellectual
space
the podcast and debate everything fearlessly his
essay was really an essay on black lives matter and the question of police
racism
was a masterpiece of 2020
and
and so he i think is a a model of what we believe in
but we can't save the world with podcasts good though
yours is
because there's a kind of
solo element
to this form of public intellectual activities
it's also there in substance where all our best writers
now seem to be including our founder barry weiss
the danger with this
approach is ultimately
your subscribers are the people who already agree with you and we are all therefore
in danger of preaching
to the choir
i think what makes an institution
like university of austin so attractive
is that we get everybody
together
at least part of the year and we do that informal interaction at lunch at dinner
that allows
in my experience the best ideas to form
intellectual activity isn't really a solo voyage
historians often make it seem that way but i've realized over time that
i do my best work in a collaborative
way and scientists have been better at this than people in the humanities
but what really matters what what's magical about a good university is that interdisciplinary
serendipitous
conversation that happens on campus
tom sergeant the great nobel prize-winning economist and i used to have these
kind of random conversations in elevators at nyu or in corridors at stanford
and sometimes they'd be quite short conversations
but in that short serendipitous exchange
i would have
more intellectual stimulus than in in many a seminar lasting an hour and a half so
i think we want to get the sam harris's and and lex friedman's
out of their darkened rooms
and give them a chance to interact in a much less structured
way than we've got got used to again
it's that it's that sense that sometimes you need some free willing
unstructured
debate to get the really good ideas
i mean to talk anecdotally for a moment i look back on my oxford
undergraduate
experience and i wrote a lot of essays and attended a lot of classes but
intellectually the most important thing i did
was to write an essay on the viennese satirist carl krause
for a an undergraduate
discussion group called the cannon club
and i probably put more work into that paper
than i put into anything else except maybe my final examinations
even although
there was only really one senior member present
the
historian
jeremy cato i was really just trying to impress my contemporaries
and that's the kind of thing we want the great intellectuals
the great intellectual leaps forward occurred
often in somewhat unstructured settings
i'm from scotland you can tell from my accent a little at least
the enlightenment happened in late 18th century scotland in a very interesting
interplay between the universities which were very important glasgow edinburgh st andrews and
the coffee houses and and pubs of
the scottish cities where
a lot of unstructured discussion often
fueled by copious amounts of wine to place
that's what i've missed
over the last few years
let's let's just think about how hard academic
social life has become
that we've reached the point
that amy chua
becomes the object of a full-blown investigation
and media storm for inviting to yale law school students over to her house
to talk
i mean when i was at oxford it was regarded as a tremendous
honor to be asked to go to one of our tutors homes
the social life of oxford and cambridge is one of their great strengths
there's a sort of requirement
to
sip unpleasant
sherry
with
the dons
and we've kind of killed all that
we've killed all that in the us because nobody
dares
have a social interaction with an undergraduate
or
exchange
an informal
email in case the whole thing ends up on the front page of the local
or student newspaper so that that's what we need to kind of restore
the
the social life of academia so there's magic we didn't really address it sort of explicitly
but there's magic to the interaction between students there's magic in the interaction between
faculty
the people that teach and there's the magic and the interaction
between the students and the faculty
and it's
it's an iterative process that changes everybody involved
so it's like world experts in a particular discipline are changed
as much as the students as the 20 year olds with the with the wild ideas
each are changed and that's the magic of it that applies in liberal education
that applies in this in the sciences too
that's probably maybe you can speak to this why so much
scientific innovation has happened in universities
there's something about the youthful energy of like young minds
graduate students undergraduate
students that inspire
some of the world experts to do some of the best work of their lives
yeah well the human brain
we know is at its most dynamic
when people are pretty young
you know this with your background in math
people don't get better at math after the age of 30.
and
this is important when you think about the intergenerational character of university
the older
people the professors have the experience
but they're fading intellectually
from much earlier than anybody really wants to admit and so you get this intellectual
shot in the arm
from hanging out with people who are circa 20
don't know shit
but the brains are kind of like cooking yeah
i look back on
the career i've had in teaching which is over 25 years where cambridge oxford
nyu harvard and
i have extremely strong relationships with with students from those institutions
because
they would show up whether it was at office hours or in tutorials
and disagree with me and for me it's always been about encouraging
some active intellectual rebellion
telling people
i don't want your essay
to echo my views
if you can find something wrong with what i wrote
great or if you can find something i missed that's new
fantastic
so there is definitely as you said a magic in that interaction across the generations
and it's extraordinarily
difficult i think for an intellectual to make the same progress
in a project in isolation
compared with the progress that can be made in these very very special communities
what does a university do amongst other things
it creates a somewhat artificial environment
of of abnormal job security that's the whole idea of giving people tenure
and then a relatively high turnover new faces each year and an institutionalization
of thought experiments and actual experiments
and then you get everybody living in the same kind of vicinity
so that it can spill over into 3 a.m conversation
well that that always seems to me to be
a pretty potent combination
let's ask ourselves a counterfactual
question next let's imagine let's imagine that
the the world wars happen
but but there are no universities
i mean how does the manhattan project happen with with no academia
to take just one of many examples in truth
how does britain even stay in the war without bletchley park without
be being able to crack the german
cipher the academics are unsung partly sung heroes of these conflicts
the same is true in the soviet union the soviet union was a terribly
evil and repressive system but it was good at science and that kept it
in the game not only in
in world war ii kept it in the cold war so
it's clear that universities are incredibly powerful intellectual force multipliers
and our our history without them
would look very different
sure some innovations would have happened without them that's clear the industrial revolution
didn't need universities in fact they played a very marginal role
in the key technological breakthroughs of the industrial revolution
in its first phase
but by the second industrial revolution in the late 19th century
german industry would not have leapt ahead of british industry if the universities
had not been superior
and it was the fact that the germans institutionalized
scientific research in the way that they did that really produced a powerful powerful advantage
the problem was that
this is a really interesting point
that friedrich meinecker makes in d deutsche catestor for the german catastrophe
the german intellectuals became technocrats
homo faber he says they knew a great deal about their speciality
but they were alienated
from broadly speaking humanism
and that is his explanation one of his explanations for why this very scientifically advanced germany
goes down the path of hell led by hitler
so when i come back and ask myself
what is it that we want to do with
a new university
we want to make sure that we we don't fall into that that german
pit where very high levels of technical and scientific expertise
are decoupled from the fundamental
foundations of of a free society
so liberal arts are there i think to stop the scientists
making fausty impacts and that that's why it's really important that people working on ai
read shakespeare i think you
said the academics are unsung heroes of the 20th century
i think there's kind of an intellectual
a lazy intellectual desire to kind of
destroy the academics that the academics are the source of all problems in the world
and i personally believe that exactly as you said we need to recognize that
the university
is probably
where
the ideas that will protect us from the catastrophes
that are looming
ahead of us
is that's where those ideas are going to come from people who who work on economics
can argue back and forth about john main arcanes
but i think it's pretty clear that he was the most important economist
and certainly the most influential economist
of the 20th century and i think his ideas are looking
better
today in the wake of the financial crisis than they
have at any time since the 1970s
but imagine
imagine john maynard keynes without cambridge you can't because someone like that doesn't actually
doesn't actually exist without the incredible hot house
that a place like cambridge wars in keynes's
life he was a product
of a kind of hereditary
intellectual
elite
it had its vices
but you can't help but admire
the sheer power of the mind i've spent a lot of my career reading
keynes and i i revere
that intellect it's so so powerful
but you can't have people like that if you're not prepared to have
king's college cambridge
and and it comes with redundancy
i think that's the point there are lots and lots of things
that are very annoying about academic life
that you just have to
you have to deal with they're they're made fun of in that recent netflix
series the chair
and it is easy to make fun of academic life
tom sharpe's porterhouse blue did it it's it's an inherently comical
subject professors at least used to be amusingly eccentric
but we've sort of killed off that side of academia by turning it into an increasingly
doctrinaire place
where eccentricity
is not tolerated
i'll give you an illustration of this i had a call
this morning from a british academic
who said can you can you give me some advice because they're trying to decolonize
the curriculum
this is coming from the
diversity equity and inclusion officers
and it
seems to me that what they're requiring of us is a fundamental
violation of academic freedom because it is
determining ex-ante what we should study and teach
that's what's going on and
that's the thing that we really
really have to resist
because that kills the university that's that's the moment that it stops being
the magical place of intellectual creativity
and simply becomes an adjunct of the ministry of propaganda
i've loved
the time we spent talking about this because
it's such a hopeful message for the future of the university
that
i still share with you
the love of the ideal of the university so very practical question you mentioned summer
which summer are we talking about so when
i know we don't want to put hard dates
here but
what year
are we thinking about when is this thing launching
what are your thoughts on this we are moving as fast
as
our resources
allow
the goal is to offer the first of the forbidden courses next summer summer of 2022
and we hope to be able to launch an initial
albeit relatively small scale masters program
in the fall of next year that's that's as fast as is humanly possible
so yeah we're
really we're really keen to get going and i think the the approach we're taking is
somewhat imported from silicon valley think of this as a startup
don't think of this as something that has to exist as a full service university
on on day one
we don't have the results
of that you
need billions
and billions of dollars
to build a university
sort of as a as a facsimile
of an existing university but that's not what we want to do i mean copying
copying and pasting harvard or year or stanford would be a futile thing to do
they would probably you very quickly end up with the same pathologies
so we do have to come up with a different design and
one way of doing that is to grow it organically
from something quite small
elon musk
mentioned in his usual humorous way on twitter
that he wants to launch the texas institute of technology and science
tits some people thought this was sexist because of the acronym tits
so first of all i understand their viewpoint
but i also think there needs to be a place for humor on the internet
even from ceo
so on this podcast i've gotten a chance to
talk to quite a few ceos
and what i love to see is authenticity
and humor is often a sign of authenticity the
the quirkiness
that you mentioned is such a beautiful characteristic
of professors and faculty and great universities
is also beautiful to see as ceos especially founding ceo so anyway
the deeper
point he was making is showing an excitement
for the university
as a place for big ideas in
science technology engineering so to me
if there's some kind of way
if there is a serious thought that he had behind this tweet
not to analyze elon musk's twitter like it's shakespeare but if there's a serious thought
um i would love to see him supporting
the the flourishing of austin as a place for science technology
for these kinds of intellectual developments that
that that we're talking about like make make a place for free inquiry civil disagreements
coupled with great education
and conversations about artificial intelligence about technology about engineering so i'm actually gonna
i hope there's a serious idea behind that tweet and i'm gonna
i'm gonna chat with him about it i do too i do too i
most of the
biggest
storms and teacups of my academic career have been caused by bad jokes that i've made
these days if you want to make bad jokes being a billionaire is a great idea
i'm not here to defend elon's
twitter style or sense of humor
he's not gonna be remembered for his
tweets i think he's gonna be remembered for the astonishing
companies that he's built and his his contributions
in a whole range of of fields from spacex to tesla
and solar energy and i very much hope that we can
interest elon in this project we need
not only elon but a whole range of his peers
because
this takes resources universities are not cheap things to run especially
if as i hope we can make as much of
the the tuition
covered by scholarships and bursaries we we want to attract the best
intellectual talent to this institution
the best intellectual talent is somewhat randomly distributed through society
and some of it is in the bottom quintile of the income distribution
and that makes it hard to get to elite education so this will take resources
the last generation of
super wealthy plutocrats
the generation of the gilded age of the late 19th century
did a pretty good job of founding universities
chicago wouldn't exist but for the money of that era
and so my message to not only to elon but to all of
the peers all of those people who made their billions
out of technology
over the last couple of decades is
this is your time i mean and this is your opportunity to create something new
i can't really understand
why
the wealthy of our time are content to hand their money
i mean think of the vast
sums mike bloomberg
recently
gave to johns hopkins
to his established
institutions
when
on close inspection those institutions don't seem to spend the money terribly well
and in fact
one of the mysteries of our time is the lack of due diligence
that hard-nosed
billionaires seem to do when it comes to philanthropy
so
i think there's an opportunity here for this generation of very talented wealthy people to
to do what their
their counterparts
did in the late 90s and early 20th century and and create some new institutions
and they don't need to
put their names on the buildings
they just need to do what what the
founders of
of chicago university of chicago did create something new that will that will endure
yeah mit is launching a college of computing and
um
steven schwartzman has
given quite a large sum of money i think in total a billion dollars
and as somebody who loves computing and somebody who loves mit i want some accountability
for mit becoming a better institution
and
this is once again why i'm excited about university
of austin because it serves as a beacon
look you can create something new
and this is what the great institutions of the future should look like
and steve schwartzman
is also uh an innovator the idea of creating a college on the tsinghua campus
and creating a kind of rhodes program
for students
from the western world to come study in china was
was steve's idea
and and i was somewhat involved did some visiting
professing there
it taught me that you can create something new
in that area of graduate education and quite quickly attract really strong
applicants because the people who finish their four years at harvard or stanford know
that they don't know a lot and i having taught a lot of people
in that group know how intellectually dissatisfied
they often are at the end of four years
i mean they may have beautifully gained the system to graduate
sumo or magna cum laude but they kind of know
they they'll confess
it after a drink or two they know that they gained the system and that intellectually
it wasn't
the fulfilling experience they wanted and they also know that an mba
from a comparable institution would not be a massive intellectual step forward
so i think what we want to say
is here's something really novel exciting
that will
be intellectually very challenging i i do think the university of austin has to be difficult
yeah
um i'd like it to feel a little bit like surviving
navy seal training to come through this program because it will be intellectually
demanding
and that i think should be a magnet so yeah steve if you're listening
please join elon in in supporting this and and
and peter thiel if you're listening i know how skeptical
you are about the idea of creating a new university because
heaven
knows peter and i have been discussing
this idea for years and he's always
said well no we thought about this and it just isn't going to work but i
really think we've got a we got a responsibility
to to do this well steve's been on this podcast before we've
spoken
a few times so i'll send this to him i hope he does
actually get behind
it as well
so i'm i'm super
excited
by
the ideas that we've been talking about that this
effort represents
and
what ripple effect it has on the rest of society
so thank you that was a time
beautifully spent and i'm really grateful for the
the fortune
of getting a chance to talk to you at this moment in history
because i've been a big fan of your work
and the reason i wanted to talk to you today
is
about all the excellent books you've written about various aspects of history through money war
power pandemics all of that but i'm glad that
this
we got a chance to talk about this which is
not looking at history it's looking at the future
this is a beautiful little
fortuitous
moment i appreciate you talking about it
in the book ascent of money
you give a history of the world through the lens of money
if the financial system is evolutionary
nature
much like life on earth what is the origin
of money on earth
the origin of money
predates coins
most people kind of assume i'll talk about coins but coins are relatively late developments
back in ancient mesopotamia so i don't know 5 000 years ago there were
relations between creditors and debtors there there are even in the simplest economy
because of the way in which agriculture works
hey i need i need to
plant these seeds but i'm not going to have crops for x months
so we have clay tablets in which
simple debt transactions are inscribed
i remember looking at great numbers of these in the british museum when i was
writing the ascent of money and that's really
the beginning of money the minute you start recording
a relationship between a creditor and a debtor you have something that is quasi money
and that is probably what these
um clay tablets mostly denoted
from that point on
there's a great evolutionary experiment to see what the most convenient way is
to record
relations between creditors and debtors and what emerges
in the time of the ancient greeks are coins metal tokens
sometimes
a valuable metal sometimes not usually bearing the imprint of a state or a monarch
and
that's the sort of more familiar
form of of money that we still use today
for very very small
transactions
i expect coins will
all be gone by the time
my youngest
son is my age but but they're a last remnant of a very very old way
of of doing
of doing simple transactions and when you say coins you mean physical coins
i'm talking about coins has been
rebranded
into digital space yeah not coin based coins
actual
coin
coins
you know the ones that jangle
in your
in your pocket
and you
kind of
don't know quite what to do with once you have some
so
that that became an incredibly
pervasive
form of of of paying for things money's just a it's just a crystallization
of a relationship between a debtor and a creditor and coins are just very fungible
you know whereas a clay tablet relates to a specific transaction
coins are generic and fungible they can be used in in any transaction
so that was an important evolutionary
advance
if you think of financial history and this was the point of the ascent of money
as an evolutionary
story there are punctuated equilibria
people get by with coins for a long time
despite their defects as a means of payment
such as that they can be debased
they can be clipped it's very hard to avoid
fake or debased money entering the system
but coinage is still kind of the basis of payments all the way
through the roman empire out the other end into the so-called
dark ages it's still how most things are settled
in cash transactions in the early 1300s
you don't get a big shift until after the black death
when there is such
a need to monetize
the economy because of chronic labor shortages
and feudalism
begins to unravel
that you you just don't have a sufficient
amount of coinage and so you get bills of exchange and i'm
really into bills of exchange
because and this i hope will capture your listeners and viewers imaginations
when they start using bills of exchange
which which are really just pieces of paper saying you know
i owe you over a three month period while goods are in transit from
florence to london
you get the first
peer-to-peer
payment system which is network verified
because they're
they're not coins they don't have a king's head on them they're just pieces of paper
and the verification comes in the form of signatures
and you you need ultimately some kind of guarantee if
i write an iou
to you build change i mean you don't really know
me that well we only just met
so you might want to get endorsed
by
i don't know somebody really credit worthy like elon
and so we we actually
can see in the late 14th century in northern italy in
england and elsewhere
the evolution of
a peer-to-peer network system of of payment
and that's actually how world trade grows because you just couldn't settle
long oceanic transactions with coinage it just wasn't practical
all those
treasure chests full of doubloons which were
part of the way in which the spanish empire worked really inefficient
so bills of exchange are an exciting
part of the story and they illustrate
something i should have made more clear of the ascent of money
that not everything used in payment needs to be money
classically economists will tell you oh well money money has three different functions
it's you've heard this a zillion times right it's a unit of account
it's a store of value and it's a medium of exchange
now there are three
or four things that are worth saying about this and i'll just say two one
it may be that those three things are a trilemma
and it's very difficult
for anything
to be all of them
this point was made by my
hoover
colleague manny rincon
cruz
last year and i still
wish he would write this up as a paper
because it's a great insight
the second thing that's really interesting to me is that
payments don't need to be money
and
if we go around as economists
love to do saying well bitcoin's not money because it doesn't fulfill these criteria
we're missing the point that you could build a system of payments
which i think is how we should think about crypto that is
isn't money doesn't need to be money it's like bills of exchange it's network-based
verification
peer-to-peer transactions without without third-party verification
when it hit me the other day that we actually had this precedent
for crypto
i got quite excited
and thought
i wish i had written that in the ascent of money
can you sort of from a first principles like almost like a physics perspective
or maybe a human perspective
describe where does the value of money come from like where is it actually
where is it so it's a sheet of paper or it's coins
but
it feels like in a platonic
sense
there's some kind of thing that's actually
storing
the value
as us a bunch of ants are dancing around and so on
i come from a family of physicists
i'm the black sheep of the family my mother's a physicist my sister is
and so when you ask me to explain something in physics terms i
i get a kind of little part of me dies because i know i'll fail
but in in truth it doesn't really matter what we decide
money is going to be and anything can record
crystallize the the relationship between the the creditor and the debtor
it could be a piece of paper it can be a piece of metal
it can be nothing can just be a digital
entry
it's
trust that we're really talking about here
we are not just trusting one another we may not but we are trusting the money
so whatever we use to represent
the credited debtor relationship whether it's a banknote or a coin or whatever
it does depend on us both trusting it
and that doesn't always pertain
what we see in episodes of inflation
especially episodes of hyperinflation
is a crisis of trust a crisis of confidence in
the means of payments
and this is very traumatic for the societies to which it happens
by and large human beings particularly once you have a rule of law
system of the sort that evolved in the west and then became generalized
are predisposed to trust one another
and the default setting is to trust money
even when it depreciates a quite steady rate as the us dollar has done
pretty much uninterruptedly since the 1960s
it takes quite a big disruption for money to lose that trust
but i think essentially what money should be thought of as
is a series
of tokens that can take any form we like
and can be purely digital
which represent our transactions as as creditors and debtors
and the whole thing depends on our collective trust to work
i had to explain this to stephen colbert once in the
call burster the old old show that was actually funny and
when he said
um
so so so neil could i be money and i said yes you know we could
we could settle
a debt with a human being that was quite common
in much of history but but it's not the most convenient
form of money
money has to be convenient
that's why when they worked out how to make payments with cell phones the chinese
simply
went straight there from bank accounts
they skipped out credit cards you won't see credit cards in china
except in the hands of naive tourists
how much can this trust
bear
in terms of
us humans with our human nature testing it
it seems that i guess the surprising thing is the thing works
a bunch of self-interested ants running around
trading in trust
and it seems to work except for
a bunch of moments in human history when there's hyperinflation like you mentioned and it's just
it's just kind of amazing
it's kind of amazing that us humans if i were to be optimistic
and sort of hopeful about human nature
it gives me a sense that
people want to lean on each other they want to trust
that certainly
i would say probably now a widely shared view amongst evolutionary psychologists
network scientists it's one of nicholas christakis's argument in a recent book
and i think economic history broadly bears this out but you have to be
cautious
the cases where the system works
are familiar to us
because those are the those are the
the states and the eras that produce a lot of written records
but when
the system of trust collapses
and the monetary system collapses with it there's generally quite a paucity
of of records i found that when i was
writing
doom and so we slightly are biased in favor of the periods when trust
prevailed and the system functioned
it's very easy to point to a great many episodes
of very very intense monetary chaos even in the relatively recent past
in the wake of the first world war
multiple currencies not just the german currency multiple currencies
were completely destroyed the russian currency the polish currency
there were currency disasters all over
central and eastern europe in the early 1920s
and that was partly because
over the course of the 19th century a system had evolved in which trust
was based
on gold
and rules that were supposedly
applied by central banks
that system
which produced relative price stability over the the 19th century
fell apart
as a result of the first world war and
and as soon as it was gone
as soon as there was no longer a
clear link between
those
banknotes and coins and gold the whole thing went completely haywire
and i think we should remember that the extent of the monetary chaos from certainly 1918
all the way through to the late 1940s
i mean the german currency was destroyed not once but twice
in that period and that was one of the most advanced economies in the world
in the united states there were periods of intensely
deep deflation prices fell by a third
in the great depression and then very serious price volatility
in the immediate post-world war ii period so
it's a bit of an illusion
maybe it's an illusion
for people who've spent most of their lives in the last 20 years
we've had a period of exceptional price stability
since this century began
in which a regime of central bank independence and inflation targeting appeared to generate
steady below 2
inflation
in much of the developed world was a bit too low for the central bankers liking
and that became a problem in the financial crisis
but we've avoided
major price
instability
for
the better
part
of 20 years
in most of the world there haven't really been that many
very high inflation episodes and hardly any hyperinflationary
episodes venezuela is one of the very few zimbabwes another
but if you take a hundred year view or a 200
year view or if you want to take a 500
year view
you realize that
quite often the system doesn't work
if you go back to the 17th century there were multiple competing
systems of coinage there had been a great inflation that had begun the previous century
the price revolution caused mainly by the arrival of new world silver
i think financial history is a bit messier than one might think and
the more one studies it the more one realizes that the need for the evolution
the reason bills of exchange came along was because the coinage systems had stopped working
the reason that banknotes
started to become
used
more generally
first in
the american
colonies
in the 17th
century
then more widely
in the 18th century
was just that they were
more convenient
than
any other way of of paying for things we had to invent the bond market
in the 18th
century
to cope with the problem
of public
debt
which
up until
that point had been a recurrent
source
of
instability
and then we invented equity finance
because bonds were not enough
so i would prefer to think of
of the financial history as a series of crises really that are resolved by innovations
and in the most recent episode very exciting episode of financial history something called bitcoin
initiated a new financial or monetary revolution in response i think to the growing
crisis of the fiat money system can you speak to that so
what do you think about bitcoin
what do you think it is the response
to what are the growing problems of the fiat system
what is this moment in human history
that is full of challenges that bitcoin and cryptocurrency is trying to overcome
i don't think bitcoin
was devised by satoshi whoever he was for fear of
a breakdown of the fiat currencies
if it was it was a very far-sighted enterprise because certainly in 2008
when the first bitcoin paper appeared it wasn't very likely that
a wave of inflation was coming if anything
there was more reason to fear deflation at that point i think
it would be more accurate to say
that with the advent of the internet
there was a need for a means of payment native to the internet
typing your credit card number into a random website it's not the way
to pay for things on the internet
and i'd rather think of bitcoin as the first iteration
the first attempt to solve the problem of how do we pay for things in
what we must learn to call the metaverse
but
let's just call it the internet for old times sake
and ever since that initial
innovation the realization that you could use computing power and cryptography to create
peer-to-peer payments without third-party verification
a revolution has been gathering momentum
that poses a very profound
threat to the existing legacy system of banks and and fiat currencies
most money in the world today is made by banks not central banks banks
that's what most money is it's entries in bank accounts
and
what bitcoin represents is an alternative mode of payment that really ought to render banks obsolete
i think this financial revolution
has
got past the point at which it can be killed
it was vulnerable in the early years
but it now has sufficient adoption
and has generated sufficient
additional layers
i mean ethereum
was in many ways the more important
innovation because you can build a whole
system of of payments and ultimately smart contracts on top of ether
i think we've now reached the point that it's
pretty hard to imagine it all being killed
and it's just survived an amazing thing which was the chinese
shutting down mining and shutting down everything and still here we are
in fact crypto's thriving
what we don't know is how much damage
ill-judged
regulatory interventions are going to do to this financial revolution
left to its own devices i think decentralized finance provides the native
monitoring financial system for the internet
and
the more time we spend in
the metaverse
the more
use
we
will make of it
the next
things
that will happen
i think will be that
tokens in game spaces like roblox will become fungible
as my nine-year-old spends a lot more time playing on
computer games than i ever did i can see the entertainment
is becoming
a game-driven phenomenon and in the game space you need skins for your avatar
the economics of the internet
it's evolving very fast and in parallel you can see this payments
revolution happening i think that all
that all goes naturally
very well and generates an enormous amount of wealth in the process
the the problem is
there are people in washington with an overwhelming urge to intervene and and disrupt this evolutionary
process
partly i think
out of a muddled sense that there must be a lot of nefarious things going on
if we don't step in many more will go on this i think greatly exaggerates
how much
criminal activity is in fact going on in the space
but there's also the vested interests at work it was odd to me
maybe not odd
perhaps it wasn't surprising but the bank for international settlements earlier this year published
a report
one chapter of which said this must all go let's all stop
it's all got to be shut down
and it's got to be replaced by central bank digital currency
and martin wolf in the financial times read this and said i agree with this
and one suddenly realized that the the banks are clever they had they'd achieved the intellectual
counter-attack
with almost no fingerprints on the weapon
i think central bank digital currency is a terrible idea
i can't imagine why we would want to copy a chinese
model that essentially takes all transactions
and puts them directly under the surveillance of a central government institution but
that suddenly is a serious counterproposal
so on the one side we have a relatively decentralized
technologically
innovative
internet native
system of payments that has the possibility to evolve to produce a full set of
of smart contracts
reducing enormously
the transaction
costs
that we currently
encounter
in the financial
world because it gets rid of all those middlemen
who take their cut every time
you take out a mortgage or whatever it is that's one
alternative
on the other side we have a highly centralized
system in which transactions
will by default be under the surveillance of the central bank
seems like an easy choice to me but hey i have this thing about personal liberty
so that's where we are i don't think that the regulators can can kill
web 3 i think we're supposed to call it web 3 because crypto
is now an obsolescent
term
they can't kill it but they can definitely make it difficult
and
throw a lot of sand into the machine
and i think worst of all they can spoil the evolutionary story by
by creating central bank digital currency that i don't think we really need or
we certainly don't need it in the chinese form
but do you think bitcoin has a strong chance to take over the world so
become the primary you mentioned the three things that make money money
become the primary methodology by which we store wealth we exchange no
no i think what bitcoin is
this was a phrase that i i got from my friend matt mclennan
first eagle an option on digital gold so it's the gold of the system
but currently it behaves like an option
that's why it's quite volatile because we don't really know if this brave new world of
crypto is gonna work
but if it does work then bitcoin is the gold because of the finite supply
what role
we need gold to play in the metaverse isn't quite
clear
i love that you're using the term metaverse this is great
well i i just like the metaversity
as a kind of yeah
as the antithesis of what we're trying to do in in austin but
i love it but can you imagine i'm using it sarcastically
i come from glasgow where all novel words have to be used sarcastically so the metaverse
sarcastic but see the beauty about humor and sarcasm is that the joke becomes reality
i mean it's like using
the word big bang to describe the origins of the universe
it becomes like that
it will
after a while it's in the textbooks
yeah and nobody's laughing
yeah well that's exactly right so sticky
yeah
um i'm on the side of humor but it is a it is a dangerous
activity
these days
anyway
i think bitcoin is is the option of digital gold
the
the role it plays is probably
not so much storage value
right now it's just nicely not very correlated
asset in your portfolio
when i updated the ascent of money which was in 2018
10 years after it came out
i wrote a new chapter in which i said
bitcoin which had just sold off after its 2017 bubble will rise again through adoption
because if every millionaire in the world
has point two percent of his or her wealth
in bitcoin
the price
should be fifteen thousand dollars and if it's one percent it's seventy five thousand dollars
and it
might not even stay at one percent because i mean look at its recent performance
if you
if your exposure to stocks global stocks had been hedged with a significant
crypto holding you would have aced the last few months
so i think the non-correlation [music]
property is very very important in driving
adoption and the volatility also drives adoption if you're a sophisticated investor
so i think the adoption drives
bitcoin up
because it's the option of digital gold but it's also just this nicely not very correlated
asset that you want to hold
in
in a world where
the hell i mean
the bank central bank is going to tighten we've come through this massively disruptive
episode of the pandemic
public debt soared
money printing sword
you could hang around with your bonds and wait for the euthanasia
of the rontier
you can hang on to your tech stocks and just hope there isn't a massive correction
or
dot dot dot well and
it seems like a fairly obvious strategy
to make sure that you have at least some crypto
for the coming year given what we likely have to face
i think what's really interesting is that on top of ethereum
a more elaborate
financial system is being built
stable coins are the interesting
puzzle for me because we need off-ramps
you and i have to pay taxes in u.s dollars
and
there's no getting away from that
the irs is going to let us hold crypto as long as we pay our taxes
and the only question in my mind is what's the optimal off-ramp
to make those taxes make those tax payments
probably it shouldn't be a currency invented by facebook
never struck me as the best solution to this problem
maybe it's some kind of fed coin
or maybe one of the the existing algorithmic
stable coins does the job but we clearly need some stable off-ramp
so you don't think it's possible for the irs
within the next decade to be accepting bitcoin as tax payments
i doubt that
having dealt with the irs now since when did i first come here 2002
it's hard to think of an institution less likely to leap into the
21st century when it comes to to payments no i think i think we'll we'll be
we'll be tolerated
crypto world will be tolerated
as long as we pay our taxes
that's the and it's important
that we're already at that point
and then the next question becomes well
does gary gensler define everything as a security and do we then have to go through
endless regulatory contortions to satisfy the sec
there's a whole bunch of of uncertainties
that the administrative
state excels at creating because you know that's just how that's how the administrative
state works you'll do something new hmm
i'll decide whether that's a security
but don't expect me to define
it for you i'll decide
in an arbitrary
way and then you'll owe me money
so all of this is going to be very annoying
and you know for people who are trying to run
exchanges
or
innovate in the space these these regulations
will be annoying but the problem with fintech is it's it's different from tech broadly defined
you know when tech got into
e-commerce with amazon when it got into social networking with facebook
there wasn't a huge regulatory jungle to navigate
but welcome to the world of finance which has always been
a jungle of regulation because the regulation is is there to you know basically
entrench the incumbents that's what it's for
so it'll be a much tougher fight than the fights we've we've seen over
other aspects of the tech revolution because because the incumbents are are there and they see
the threat
and in the end
satoshi said it very explicitly
it's peer-to-peer payment without third party verification and all the third parties are going wait what
we're the third parties
so there is a connection between power and money
you've mentioned world war one from the perspective of money so power money war authoritarian regimes
from the perspective of money do you have hope that cryptocurrency
can help resist war can help
resist the negative effects of authoritarian regimes
or is that a silly hope
wars happen because the people who have the power to command armed forces
miscalculate that's generally what happens
and we will have a big war in the near future if
both the chinese government and the us government miscalculates
and they unleash lethal lethal force on one another and there's nothing that any financial institution
can do to stop that
any more than the rothschilds could rothschilds could stop world war one
and they were then the biggest bank in the world by far with massive
international financial influence
so let's accept that war is is in a different domain
war
would impact the financial world massively
if it were a war between the united states and china because
there's still a huge china trade on wall street is long china europe is long china
so the conflict that i could foresee in the future is one that's highly financially disruptive
where does crypto fit in crypto's obvious
utility in the short run
is as a store of wealth of transferable wealth for people who live
in dangerous places
with
failing not just failing money but failing rule of law
that's why in latin america
there's so much
interest
in crypto
because latin
americans
have a lot of monetary
history
to look back on and not much of it is
so i think that the short run problem that crypto solves
is and this goes back to the the digital gold point
if you are in a dangerous place with weak rule of law and weak property rights
here's a new and better way to have portable wealth
i think the next
question to ask is would you want to be long crypto
in the event of world war three
what's interesting about that question is that world war three would likely have a significant
cyber dimension to it
and i don't want to be a hundred percent in crypto if they crash the internet
which between them china and russia might be able to do
that's a fascinating question whether you want to be holding
physical gold or digital gold
in the event of world war iii
the smart person who studied history
definitely
wants
better both
and
so let's imagine world war iii has a very very severe
cyber component to it with high levels of disruption
yeah you'd be glad of the old the old shiny stuff at that point so
diversification still seems like the most important
truth
of a financial history
yeah and and what is crypto it's just this wonderful new source of diversification
but you'd be nuts to be a hundred percent in bitcoin
i mean i i i have
some friends who are
probably
quite close to that close to 100
i i'd marr the i'd mar the bowls of steel
yeah in whatever way that balls of steel takes to takes form
you mentioned smart contracts what are your thoughts about
in the context of the history of money about ethereum about smart contracts about kind of
more systematic at scale formalization of agreements between humans i think
it must be the case that a lot of the complexity in a mortgage is redundant
that when we are confronted with pages and pages and pages and pages of small prints
we're seeing some manifestation of of the late stage regulatory state
the transaction itself is quite simple
and most of the verbage is just ass covering by regulators
so i think the smart contract
although
i'm sure lawyers will
email me and tell me i'm wrong
can deal with a lot of the plain vanilla and maybe not so plain transactions
that we want to do
and eliminate
yet more intermediaries
that's my my kind of working assumption and
given that a lot of of financial transactions
have the potential at least to be to be simplified automated
turned into smart contracts that that's probably where the future goes
i can't see an obvious reason why my
range of different financial
needs let's think about insurance for example will continue to be met
with instruments that in some ways are 100 years old
so i think we're still
an early stage of a financial revolution that will greatly streamline
how we take care of all those financial needs that we have
mortgages and insurance leave leap to mind you know most households are are penalized
for being financially poorly educated and confronted with oligopolistic
financial services providers so you kind of leave college already in debt so you start
in debt servitude
and then
you gotta somehow
leave her up to buy a
home if you can because everybody's kind of telling you you should do that so
so you and your spouse
you are getting even more leveraged
and you're
you're long one asset class called real estate which is super illiquid
i mean already i'm i'm crying inside at the thought of
describing
so many households
financial
predicament
in that way and i'm not done with them yet because oh by the way
there's all this insurance you have to take out
and here are the providers
that are willing to insure you and here are the premiums
you're going to be paying
which are kind of presented
to you that's your that's your car insurance
that's your home insurance
and if you're here it's the earthquake
insurance and
pretty soon you're just bleeding
money
in a bunch of monthly payments to the mortgage
lender to the insurer
to all the other people that lent you money
and let's look at your balance sheet it sucks
you know
there's this great big chunk
of real estate
and what else have you really got on there
and the other side is a bunch of debt which is probably paying too high interest
the typical household in the median
kind of range is is at the mercy of
oligopolistic financial services providers go down further in the social
scale and people are outside the financial system altogether
and those poor folks have to rely on
banknotes and informal lending with huge punitive rates
we have to do better than this this has to be
this has to be improved upon
and i think what's exciting about our time is that technology
now exists that didn't exist when i wrote the ascent of money
to solve these problems when i wrote this under money which was in 2008
you couldn't really solve the problem i've just described
certainly you couldn't solve it with something like microfinance that was obviously not viable the
interest rates were high the transaction costs were crazy
but now we have solutions
and the solutions are extremely
exciting so fintech is this great force for good that
brings people into the financial system
and reduces transaction costs
crypto is part of it but it's just part of it there's a much broader
story of fintech going on here where
you get suddenly you get financial services
on your phone
don't cost nearly as much as they
they did when there had to be a bricks and mortar
building
on main street
that you kind of went
humbly
and beseeched
to lend you money i'm excited about that because it seems to me very socially transformative
i'll give you one other example of what's great
the people who really get sculpt in our financial system are senders and receivers of remittances
which are often amongst the poorest families in the world the people who are
like my wife's family in east africa really kind of hand to mouth
and if you send money to east africa or
the philippines
or central america
it's it's the transaction
costs are awful
i'm talking to you western union
we're gonna solve that problem
so ten years from now the transaction cost will just be negligible
and the money will go to the people who need it rather than to
rent seeking financial
institutions
so i'm on the side of the revolution
with this because
i think the incumbent financial institutions globally
are doing a pretty terrible job
and
middle class and lower class families lose out and
thankfully technology
technology allows us to fix this yeah so fintech can remove a lot of inefficiencies
in the system
i'm super excited myself maybe as a machine learning person in the data oracles
so converting a lot of our physical world into data
so
and have smart contracts on top of that so
that no longer is there's this fuzziness
about
what is the concrete nature of the agreements
you can tie your agreement to weather you can tie your agreement to
the behavior of
certain kinds of financial
systems you can tie your behavior to i don't know
i mean all kinds of things you can connect it to the body
in terms of human
um sensory information
like
you can make an agreement that if you don't lose five pounds in the next month
you're going to pay me a thousand dollars or something like that i don't know
it's a stupid example
but it's not
because like you can create all kinds of services
on top of that you can
you can just create
all kinds of interesting applications
that completely revolutionize
how humans transact
i think
of course we don't want to create a world of chinese style social credit
in which our behavior
becomes so transparent
to providers of financial services particularly insurers that
when i try to go into the pub i'm i'm stopped from doing so
every time you take a drink your insurance goes up
right or my credit card won't work
in certain restaurants because they serve
you know ribeye steak
i fear that world because i see it being built in china and
we we must at all costs make sure that the western world has something
distinctive to offer
it can't just be oh it's the same as in china only the data go to
to five tech companies rather than to
xi jinping so i think the the way we need to steer this world is
in the way that our data
are by default vaulted on our devices
and we choose
when to release the data yes
rather than the default setting being that the data are available
that's important i think because it was one of the biggest mistakes
of
the evolution of the internet that
that in a way the default was to let our our data be plundered
it's hard to undo that but i think we can we can at least
create a new regime
that in future makes privacy default rather than open access default
in the book doom the politics of catastrophe
your newest book you describe wars pandemics and the terrible disasters in human history
which stands out to you as the worst in terms of how much
it shook the world and the human spirit
i am glad i was not around
in the mid 14th century when the bubonic plague swept across eurasia
as far as we can see that was history's worst pandemic
maybe there was a comparably bad one in the reign of the emperor justinian but
there's some reason to think it wasn't as bad
and the more we learn about
the 14th century with the more we realized that it really was across eurasia
and the the mortality
was
in some places 50
in some places higher there were whole towns that were just emptied
and when one reads about the black death it's an unimaginable
nightmare of of death and
madness in the death with flagellate orders wandering from town to town
seeking to ward off divine retribution by flogging themselves
people turning on the local jewish communities as if it's somehow their fault
that must have been a nightmarish
time
if you ask me
for an an also ran a runner-up it would be it would be world war ii
in eastern europe and in many ways
it might have been worse because for a medieval
peasant the sense of being on the wrong side of divine retribution must have been overpowering
in the mid-20th century
you knew that this was man-made
murder on a massive industrial scale
if only if one reads grossman's life and fate just to take one example
one enters a a hellscape
that it's extremely hard
to imagine oneself in
so these are two of the great disasters of of human history and
if we did have a time machine if one really were able to transport
people back and
and give them a glimpse of these
times
i think the post-traumatic
stress would be enormous
people would come back from those those trips even if it was a
one-day excursion
with guaranteed survival
in a state of of utter shock
you often explore counterfactual
hypothetical
history this which is a fascinating thing to do
sometimes to a controversial degree
and again you walk through that fire gracefully
so let me ask maybe about
world war ii or in general or what key moments in history of the 20th century
do you think
if something else happened at those moments we could have avoided some of the big atrocities
stalin's holomore hitler's holocaust miles great chinese famine
the great turning point in in world history is is august the 2nd 1914
when the british cabinet decides to intervene
and what would have been a european war
becomes a world war
and with british intervention it becomes a massively larger and more protracted conflict
so very early in my career i became very preoccupied with the deliberations on that day
and the surprising
decision that a liberal cabinet took to to go to war
which you might not have bet on that morning because
there seemed to be a majority of cabinet members who would be disinclined
and only a minority including winston church
who wanted to go to war so that's one turning point i often wish i could
get my time machine working and go back and say wait stop
just think about what you're going to do and by the way
let me show you a video of europe
in 1918 so that's one can we linger on that one
that one
a lot of people push back on you on in the because it's so difficult
so the idea is if i could try to summarize
and
you're the first person that made me think about this very uncomfortable
thought which is
the ideas in world war one
it would be a better world if britain stayed out of the war
and germany won right
thinking now in retrospect that the whole story of the 20th century thinking about
stalin's rule of 30 years thinking about hitler's rise to power and
the atrocities of the holocaust but also like you said on the eastern front
the death of tens of millions of people
through the war
and also sort of the political
prisoners and the suffering connected to communism connected to fascism all those kinds of things
well that's one
that's one heck of an example of why you're just like fearless in this
particular style of exploring counterfactual history so can you elaborate on that
idea and maybe why this was such an important day in human history
this argument
was central
to my book the pity
of war
i
i also
did an essay
in virtual
history
about
this
and it's always
amused
me that
from around that time i began to be called a conservative
historian
because it's actually a very left-wing argument
the people in 1914
who thought britain should stay at the war were the left of the labour party
who split to become the independent labour party
what would have happened well first of all britain was not ready for war in 1914
there had not been conscription the army was tiny
so britain had failed to deter germany the germans took the decision that they could risk
going through belgium
using the schlieffen plan to fight their two-front war
they they calculated that britain's intervention would either not happen or not matter
if britain had been strategically
committed
to preventing
germany winning a war in europe they should have introduced conscription 10 years before
had a
meaningful land army and that would have deterred the germans
so the liberal government
provided the worst of both worlds a commitment that was more or less secret to intervene
that the public didn't know about
in fact much of the liberal party didn't know about
but without really the means
to make that intervention
effective a tiny army with just a few divisions
so it's perfectly reasonable to argue as a number of people did in
on august the 2nd 1914 that britain should not intervene
after britain had not immediately intervened against the french revolutionary armies
back in the 1790s
it had played an offshore role ultimately intervening but not immediately intervening
if britain had stayed out
i don't think that france would have collapsed immediately as it had in 1870
the french held up remarkably well to catastrophic
casualties in the first six months of the first world war
but by 1916 i don't see how
france could have kept going if britain had not joined the war
and i think the war would have been over perhaps at some point in 1916.
we know that germany's aims would have been significantly
limited
because
they would have needed to keep britain out if they'd succeeded
in keeping britain out they'd have had to keep britain out
and the way to keep britain out was obviously
not to make any
annexation
of belgium to limit german war aims
particularly to limit them to eastern europe
and from britain's point of view what was not to like
so the russian empire is defeated along with france
what does that really change
if the germans are sensible
and we can see what this might have looked like they focus on eastern europe
they take chunks of the russian empire perhaps they create as they did in the
in the piece of brest-litovsk
an independent or quasi-independent
poland
in no way does that pose a threat to the british empire in fact
it's a good thing
britain never had had a particularly good relationship with the russian empire after all
the key point here is that the germany that emerges from victory in 1916
has a kind of european union it's the dominant part of an enlarged
germany with a significant missile europa
whatever you want to call it customs union type arrangement with neighboring countries
including one suspects austria-hungary
that is a very different world
from the world of 1917-18 the protraction of the war for a further two years
its globalization which britain's intervention made inevitable
as philip zeliko showed in his recent book on the failure to make peace in 1916
woodrow wilson tried and failed to intervene and broker a piece in 1916
so i'm not the only
counterfactualist
here the extension of the war for a further two years with escalating
slaughter the death toll rose because the industrial capacity of the armies grew greater
that's what condemns us to the bolshevik revolution
and it's what condemns us ultimately to nazism
because it's out of
the experience of defeat in 1918
as hitler makes clear in mind camp that he becomes radicalized and enters the political realm
take out those additional years of war and hitler's just a failed artist
it's the it's the end of the war
that turns him into
the demagogue
you asked what are the things that evolve avoid the totalitarian states
as i've said british
intervention for me is the most plausible
and it takes out all of that malignant history that follows from the bolshevik revolution
it's very hard for me to see how lenin gets anywhere if the war is over
that looks like the opportunity for the the constitutional
elements the liberal elements in in russia
there are other moments at which you can imagine history taking a different path
if the provisional government in russia had been more ruthless
it was very lenient towards the bolsheviks
but if it had just rounded them up and shot the bolshevik leadership
that would have certainly
cut the bolshevik revolution off
one looks back on the
conduct of the the russian liberals with the kind of despair
at their
their failure to see the scale of the threat that they face and the ruthlessness
that the bolshevik leadership would evince
there's a counterfactual in germany which is interesting
i think the weimar republic destroyed itself in two disastrous economic
calamities the inflation and then the deflation
it's difficult for me to imagine hitler getting to be
reich chancellor without those huge economic disasters
so another part of my early work explored alternative
policy options that the german republic the weimar republic might have pursued
there are other contingencies
that that spring to mind in 1936
or 38 i think more plausibly 38
britain should have gone to war the great mistake was munich
hitler was in an extremely vulnerable position in 1938
because remember he didn't have russia squared away as he would in 1939.
chamberlain's mistake was to fold instead of
of going for going for war as church or rightly saw
and and that there was a magical opportunity
there
that would have played into the hands of the german military opposition and conservatives
to to snuff hitler out
over czechoslovakia
i could go on the point is that the history is not some inexorable narrative
which can only end one way it's a garden of forking paths and at
many many junctions in the road
there were choices
that could have averted the
calamities of the mid-20th century i have to ask you about this moment
before you said i could go on this moment of chamberlain and hitler snuff hitler out
in terms of czechoslovakia
and
we'll return to
the book doom
on this point what does it take to be a great
leader
in the room with hitler or
in the same time and space as hitler
to snuff him out to make the right decisions
what what
is
so it sounds like you put quite a bit of the blame
on the man
chamberlain and give credit
to somebody like a churchill so what is the difference where's that line you've also
written a book about henry kissinger who's an interesting sort of person that's been through
throughout many difficult
decisions in the games of power
so what does it take to be a great leader in that moment
that particular
moment sorry to keep talking
is fascinating
to me because it feels like it's man on man conversations
that define history well hitler was bluffing
he really wasn't ready for war in 1938
the german economy was clearly not ready for war in 1938
and and chamberlain made a fundamental
miscalculation along with his advisors because it wasn't all chamberlain he was in many ways articulating
the establishment
view
and i tried to show in a book called war of the world how that establishment
worked it extended
through the bbc into the aristocracy
to oxford there was an establishment view chamberlain personified it churchill was seen as a warmonger
he was at his lowest point of popularity in 1938
but what is what is it that chamberlain gets wrong because it's conceptual
chamberlain
is persuaded
that britain has to play for time because britain is not ready for war in 1938.
he fails to see that the time that he gets
that he buys at munich is also available to hitler
everybody gets the time
and hitler's able to do much more with it because hitler strikes the pact with
with stalin
that guarantees that germany can fight a war on one front in 1939.
what does chamberlain do builds some more aircraft
so the great mistake of the strategy of appeasement
was to play for time
i mean they knew all was coming but they were playing for time not realizing
that
hitler got the time too
and after he partitioned czechoslovakia
he was in a much stronger position not least because of all the resources that
they were able to plunder
from czechoslovakia
so that was the conceptual mistake churchill played an heroic role in pointing out
this mistake and predicting accurately that it would lead to war on worse terms
what does it take it takes a distinct courage
to be unpopular
and churchill was deeply unpopular
at that point people would listen to him
in the house of commons
in silence
on one occasion
lady astor shouted rubbish
so he went through a period of being hated on
the other thing that made churchill
a formidable leader was that he always applied history to the problem
and that's why he gets it right he he sees the historical
problem much more clearly than than chamberlain
so i think
if you go back to 1938
there's no realistic counterfactual in which churchill's in government in 1938
you have to france collapse for churchill to come into government
but you can certainly imagine
a tory elite
that's thinking more clearly about the likely dynamics
they haven't seen this
i guess problem of conjecture to take a phrase from kissinger
which is that whatever they're doing in postponing
the war has the potential to create a worse starting point for the war
it would have been risky in 1938
but it was a way better situation than they ended up with in 1939
a year later
you asked about kissinger and i've learnt a lot from reading kissinger
and talking to kissinger since i embarked on writing his biography
a great many years ago
i think one of the most important things i've learned
is that
you can apply history to contemporary problems it may be the most important
tool that we have in that kind of decision making
you have to do it quite ruthlessly and rigorously
and in the moment of crisis you have to take risk so
kissinger often says
in his early work
the temptation of the bureaucrat is to wait for more data
but ultimately the decision making that we do under uncertainty can't be based on data
the problem of conjecture is that you could take an action now and incur some cost
an avert disaster
but you'll get no thanks for it because nobody is grateful for an averted disaster
and nobody goes around saying wasn't it wonderful how we didn't have another 911
on the other hand you can do nothing
incur no upfront costs and hope for the best
and you might get lucky the disaster might not happen
that's in a democratic system the much easier path to take
and i think the the essence of leadership is to be ready
to take that upfront cost avert the disaster and accept that you won't get gratitude
if i may make a comment
an aside about henry kissinger so he i think at 98 years old currently
has still got it yeah he's brilliant
it's very very impressive i
can only hope that my brain has the same
durability
that his his does because it's a formidable intellect and it's still in
in as sharp form as it it was 50 years ago
so you mentioned eric schmidt's
in his book
they reached out to me didn't want to do this podcast
and i'm i'm
i know eric schmidt i've spoken to him before i like him a lot obviously
um so they said
we could do a podcast for 40 minutes with eric
40 minutes with eric and henry together
and 40 minutes with henry so those are three different conversations
and i had to like i had to do some soul searching
because i said fine 40 minutes with eric we'll probably talk many times again
fine let's talk about this ai book together for 40 minutes
but i said what i wrote to them said i would hate myself
if i only have 40 minutes to talk to henry kissinger
as i had to hold my ground went back and forth and in the end decided
to part ways over this and i sometimes think about this kind of
difficult decision
um in the podcasting space of when do you walk away because
um there's a particular world leader
that i've mentioned in the past where the conversation is very likely to happen
and
as as it happens
those conversations can often be
you know unfortunately
this person only has 30 minutes now i know we agreed for three hours but unfortunately
and you have to decide
do i stand my ground on this
on this point i suppose that's the thing that journalists
have to think about right like um
do i hold on to my integrity
in whatever form that takes and do i stay in my ground even if i
lose a fascinating opportunity
anyway it's something i thought i thought about and
something i think about and with henry kissinger
i mean
he's had a million amazing conversations
in your biography
so it's not like something is lost but it was still nevertheless
to me some soul searching they had to do as a as a kind of practice
for
what to me is a higher stakes conversation i'll just mention is vladimir putin
i can have a conversation with him unlike any conversation he's ever had
partially because i'm a fluent russian speaker
partially
because
i'm messed
up in the head in certain kind of ways that make for an interesting
dynamic
because we're both judo people we both are
certain kinds of human beings that can have a much deeper apolitical conversation
i have to ask to stay on the topic of leadership
you've in your book doom have talked about wars pandemics throughout human history
and in some sense saying that all of these disasters are man-made
so humans have a role in terms of the magnitude
of the effect that they have on human civilization
without taking cheap political shots can we talk about covid19
how will
history remember the coven 19 pandemic what were the successes with what were the failures
of leadership
of of man of humans
doom was a book
that i was
planning to write before
yes the pandemic struck
as a history of of the future based in large measure on science fiction
it had occurred to me in 2019
that i had spent too long not reading science fiction and so i decided i would
liven up my my intake
by getting off history for a bit and reading science fiction
because history is great at telling you about the perennial problems of power
putin is always interesting on history
he's become something of a historian recently with his essays and lectures
but what history is bad at telling you is well what will the effects of this
discontinuity
of technology be
and so i thought i need some science fiction
to think more about
this
because i'm
i'm
tending
to miss
the importance of technological discontinuity
if you read a lot of science fiction you read a lot of plague books because
science fiction writers are really quite fond of the plague scenario
so the world ends in many ways in science fiction but one of the most popular
is the lethal pandemic
so when
when the first
email
came to me i think it was on january the third from my medical
friend justin stebing
funny pneumonia and wuhan
my antennae
began
to tingle because it was just like
one of those science fiction books that begins in just that way
in a pandemic
as larry brilliant the epidemiologist said many years ago the key
is early detection and early action that's how you deal with a novel pathogen
and almost no western country did that
we know it was doable because the time and ease and the south koreans
did it
and they did it very well
but really no western country got this right
some were unlucky because super spreader events happened earlier
than in other countries italy was hit very hard very early
for other countries the real disaster came quite late russia which has only relatively
recently had a really bad experience
the lesson for me is quite different from the one that most journalists
thought they were learning last year most journalists last year thought
trump is a terrible president
he's saying a lot of crazy things
it's his fault that we have high excess mortality in the united states
the same argument was being made by journalists in britain boris johnson dot dot dot brazil
bolsonaro dot dot dot even india narendra modi
the same argument
and i think this argument
is wrong in a few ways it's true that the populist leaders said many crazy things
and broadly speaking gave poor guidance to their their populations
but i don't think it's true to say
that with different leaders these countries would have done significantly
better if joe biden had magically been president
a year earlier
i don't think the us
would have done much
better
because
the things
that caused
excess mortality
last year weren't presidential
decisions
they were
utter failure of cdc to provide testing that definitely wasn't trump's fault
scott gottlieb's book makes that very clear it's just been published recently
we utterly failed to use technology for contact tracing which the koreans did very well
we didn't really quarantine anybody seriously
there was no enforcement of quarantine
and we exposed the elderly
to the virus
as quickly as possible
in elderly
care homes
and
these things have very little to do with presidential incompetence
so i think leadership
is of somewhat
marginal
importance
in a crisis like this because what you really need is your public health bureaucracy
to get it right and very few western public health bureaucracies
got it right
could the president have given better leadership yes
his correct strategy however was
to learn from barack obama's playbook with the opioid epidemic
the opioid epidemic killed as many people on obama's watch as covert did on trump's watch
and it was worse in the sense because it only happened in the u.s
and each year it killed more people than the year before over eight years
nobody to my knowledge has ever seriously blamed obama for the opioid epidemic
trump's mistake was to put himself front and center of the response
to claim that he had some unique insight
into the pandemic and to say
with every passing week more and more foolish things until even
a significant
portion of people who'd voted for him in 2016
realized that he'd blown it which is why he lost the election
the correct strategy was actually to make mike pence
the pandemic tsar and get the hell out the way
that's what my advice to trump would have been in fact it was in february
of last year
so the mistake was
to to try to lead
but actually
leadership in a pandemic's
almost a contradiction in terms what you really need is your public health bureaucracy
not to fuck it up
and they really
really fucked it up and that was then all blamed on trump
yes
you know jim fallows writes a piece in the atlantic that says
well being the president's like flying a light aircraft
it's pilot error
and i
i read that piece and i thought does he really
after
all the years he's spent
writing
think that being president is like flying a light aircraft
i mean
it's really nothing like flying a light aircraft
being president is you sit on top of a vast bureaucracy
with how many different agencies 60 70 we've all lost count
and you're surrounded by advisers
at least a quarter of whom are saying this is a disaster
we have to close the borders and the others are saying
no no we have to keep the economy going that's what you're running on in november
so being a president in a pandemic is a very unenviable position
because you actually can't
you can't really determine whether your public health bureaucracy
will get it right or not
you don't think to push back on that
just like being churchill in a war is difficult
so leaving trump abiding aside what i would love to see from a president is somebody
who makes great speeches and arouses the public to push the bureaucracy the public health bureaucracy
to get their shit together
to fire
certain kinds of people to do i mean i'm
sorry
but i'm a big fan of
powerful speeches
especially in the modern age with the internet
it can really move people
instead
the lack of speeches
resulted in certain kinds of forces
amplifying division
over whether wear masks or not or all
it's like it's almost like the public pick some random topic over which to divide themselves
and there was like a complete indecision which is really what it was fear
of the of uncertainty materializing itself in some kind of division
and then you almost like busy yourself with the red versus blue politics
as opposed to some i don't know fdr type character
just stands and say
fuck all this bullshit that we're hearing we're going to manufacture
5 billion tests
this is what america is great at we're going to build the greatest testing infrastructure
ever built or
something
or even with the vaccine development
but that was what i was about to interject yes
in a pandemic the most important thing is the vaccine
if you get that right then you should be forgiven for much else
and that was the one thing the trump administration
got right because
they went around the bureaucracy with operation warp speed and achieved a really major success
so i think the paradox of of the the 2020
story in the united states is that the one thing that mattered most the trump administration
got right
and it got so much else wrong that was sort of marginal
that we were left with the impression
that trump had been to blame for the whole disaster which wasn't really quite right
sure it would have been great if we did operation warp speed for testing
but ultimately vaccines are more important than tests and
this brings me to the question that that you raised there of polarization
and why that happened
now
in a book called the square in the tower i argued
that it would be very costly
for the united states
to allow
the public sphere to continue
to be dominated
by a handful of big tech companies
that this ultimately
would have
more adverse effects than simply
contested elections and i think we saw
over the past 18 months just how bad this could be because
the odd thing about this
country is that we came up with vaccines with 90 plus percent efficacy
and about 20 of people refuse to get them and still do refuse
for reasons that seem best explained
in terms of the anti-vaxx
network which has been embedded on the internet for a long time predating the pandemic
reni diresta wrote about this pre-2020
and this this anti-vax
network has turned out to kill maybe 200 000 americans who could have been vaccinated
but were persuaded
through magical thinking that the vaccine was riskier
than the virus whereas
you don't need to be in epidemiology
you don't need to be a medical scientist to know that the virus
is about two orders of magnitude
riskier
than the vaccine
so again leadership
could definitely have been better but the politicization of everything
was not trump's doing alone it
happened because
our public sphere has been dominated by a handful of platforms whose business model
inherently promotes polarization
inherently promotes
fake news and extreme views because those are the things that get
the eyeballs
on the screens and sell the ads
i mean this is now a common place
but when one thinks about the cost of allowing this
kind of thing to happen it's now a very high human cost
and we were foolish to leave uncorrected
these structural problems in the public sphere that were already very clearly visible in 2016.
and he described that
like you mentioned that there's these networks they're almost like laying dormant
waiting
for their time in the sun and they stepped forward in this case
and that those network effects
just
the service catalyst for whatever
the bad parts of human nature
i do hope that there's kinds of networks that emphasize
the the better angels of our nature to to to quote steven pinker
it's just
clearly
and we know this from all the revelations
of the facebook whistleblower
there is clearly a very clear tension
between the business model of a company like facebook
and the public good
and they know that i just talked to the founder of instagram i i yes that's
the case but it's not from a technology perspective
like absolutely
true of any kind of social network i think it's possible to build
actually i think it's
not just possible i think it's pretty
easy if you set that as the goal to build social networks
that don't have these negative effects
right but if the business model is we sell ads
and the way you sell ads is to maximize user engagement
then the algorithm
is biased in favor
of fake news and extreme
views but it's not it's so it's not the ads a lot of people
blame
the ads
the
the problem i think is the engagement
and the engagement is just the easiest the dumbest way to solve the ads
i think there's much different
metrics that could be used to make a lot more money than the engagement
in the long term it has more to do with planning for the long term so
optimizing the selling of ads
to make people happy
with themselves in the long term
as opposed to some kind of addicted
like dopamine feeling
and so that's
to me that has to do with metrics and measuring things correctly and sort of
also creating a culture with what's valued
to have difficult conversation
about what we're doing with society
all those kinds of things and i i think once you have those conversations
this takes us back to the university of austin kind of
once you have those difficult human conversations
you can design the technology that will actually make
for
help people grow
become the best version of themselves help them be happy in the long term
what gives you hope about the future
as somebody who studied some of the darker moments of human history what gives you hope
a couple of things
first of all the united states has a very unique operating system
which was very well designed
by the founders who thought a lot about history and and
realized it would take quite a
a novel design
to prevent the republic
going the way of all republics
because republics
tend to end up as tyrannies for reasons that were well established
by the time of the renaissance
and it gives me hope that this design has worked very well
and with student enormous stress test stress test in the last
in the last year i became an american in 2018
i think
one of the most important
features of this operating system is that it is the magnet for talent
here we sit
part of the immigration story
in you know in a darkened room with funny accents talking to russians
walk into a recording studio and talk about america it's it's very much like a joke
and elon's a south african and so on and thiel is a german and we're
we're extraordinarily fortunate that the natives let us come and play
and and play in a way that we could not in our countries of birth
and as long as the united states continues
to exploit that superpower that it is the talent magnet
then it should out innovate the totalitarian competition
every time so that's
that's one reason for being an optimist
another reason and it's quite a historical reason as you would expect from me
another reason that i'm
optimistic
is
that my kids
give me a great deal of hope they range in age from 27 down to four
but each of them in their different way
seems to be finding a way through this crazy time of ours without losing contact with
that culture and civilization
that i hold dear i don't want to live in the metaverse as mark zuckerberg
imagines it to me that's a kind of ghastly hell
i think western civilization is the best civilization
and i think that almost all the truths about the human condition can be found
in western literature
art and music
and i think also that the the civilization that produced the scientific revolution
has produced the great problem-solving
tool that eluded the other civilizations that never really cracked science
and what gives me hope is that despite
all the temptations
and distractions
that their generation
[music]
had to contend with my children in their different ways have found the found their way
to literature and to art and to music
and and they are civilized
and i i don't i don't claim
much of the credit for that i've done my best but i think it's
deeply encouraging that
that that they found their way to the things that i think
are indispensable for a happy life a fulfilled life nobody i think can be truly fulfilled
if they're cut off from the great body of western literature for example i've thought
a lot about
elon's argument that we might be in a simulation
no no there is a simulation it's cold literature
and we just have to decide whether or not to enter it
i'm currently in the midst of the later stages of of proust's great
allah and
observation of human relationships is perhaps more meticulous than that of any other writer
and it's impossible not to find yourself
identifying with marcel and his obsessive jealous relationships particularly with alberti
it's the simulation and you you decide i think
as a sentient being how far to in your own life
reenact these more profound
experiences that others have written down one of my earliest literary simulations
was to reenact jack kerouac tripping on the road when i was 17
culminating and getting very wasted in the hanging gardens of zochimilco
not to be not to be missed and
it hit me just just as i was reading proof
that's really
how to live a rich life
that one lives life but one lives it
juxtaposing one's own experience
against the more refined experiences of the great the great writers
so it gives me hope that my children do that a bit
do you include the the russian authors very much in the canon
yes i don't read russian
um
but i was entirely obsessed with russian literature as a schoolboy
i read my way through dostoyevsky
tolstoy turganyev i check off i think
um
of all of those writers
tolstoy
had the biggest impact
because at the end of war and peace there's this great essay on historical
determinism
which i think was the reason i became a historian
but i'm i'm really temperamentally a kind of togenyev person
oddly enough
i i think if you if you haven't read those novelists
i mean you can't really
be a complete human being if you haven't
if you haven't read the brothers karamazov you will not really
you're not grown up
and so i think i think in many ways those are the greatest
the greatest novels raskolnikov's remember raskolnikov's nightmare at the end of crime and punishment
in which he imagines
in his dream a world
in which a terrible virus spreads
do you remember this and this virus has the effect of making every individual think
that what he believes is right
and in this
self-righteousness
people fall on one another and commit appalling violence
that's raskolnikov's nightmare and it's a prophecy it's a terrible prophecy of of russia's future
yeah it's
and coupled with that is probably the i also like the french the existentialist
all that that the full
spectrum
and germans hermann has said and just that
range of human thought has expressed the literature it's fascinating i really
love your idea that
the simulation
like
one way to to live life is to kind of
explore these other worlds and borrow from them yes
wisdom
that you then just
map onto your own lives you almost like
stitched together your life with these kind of pieces from literature
the highly educated
person is constantly
struck
by illusion
everything is an allusion to something that one has read and that
is the simulation that's what
the real metaverse is it's the imaginary world that we enter when we read
empathize and then recognize in our daily lives
some scrap of the shared experience that literature gives us
yeah i think i've aspired to be the idiot from prince mishkin from dostoevsky
and in aspiring to be that i have become
the idiot i feel at least in part
um
what you mentioned the human condition
does love have to do what role does it play in the human condition friendship love
love is the drug
kind is this was a great roxy music line
that brian ferry wrote and love is
the most powerful and and dangerous of all the drugs
the um
the driving force that overrides our reason
and of course it is the it is the primal it's the primal urge so
what a civilized society has to do is to prevent that drug that primal force from
creating mayhem so there have to be rules
like monogamy
and
rituals like like marriage that that reign love in and make the the addicts
at least
more or less
under control and i i think that's that's part of why i'm i'm a romantic
rather than a you know steve pinker
enlightenment rationalist because the romantics realized that that love was the drug it's like
the difference in sensibility
between
handel and wagner
and i i had a vagnerian phase when i was an undergraduate i still remember thinking
that in in
as old as libra's toad
that wagner had got the closest to sex that anybody had ever got
in in music or perhaps to love
i'm i'm lucky that i love my wife and that
that we were by the time we met you know smart enough to understand
that that love is a drug that you have to kind of take
in in in certain careful ways
and that it works best in the context of a of a stable family
that's that's the key thing that one has to sort of
take the drug and then submit to the
the the conventions of of of marriage and family life i
i think in that respect
i'm a kind of tamed romantic
contain romantic
that's how i would like to think about it and that's the degree
to which
your romanticism
is tamed
can be then channeled into productive
work that's why you're a historian
and a writer
is the breast is that love is channeled
through the writing
so if you're going to be addicted
to anything
be addicted
to work
i mean we're all addictive but yeah the thing about workaholism
is that it is the most productive addiction
and
and rather that than
drugs or booze so i i'm i'm yes i'm always trying to channel my anxieties
in into work
i learnt that at a relatively early age it's a sort of massively
productive way of coping with the inner demons
and again we should teach kids that because
let's come back to our earlier conversation about universities
part of what happens at university
is that adolescents
have to overcome all the inner demons and these include deep insecurity
about one's appearance about one's intellect
and then
madly raging hormones
that cause you to behave like a complete fool with
the people to whom you're sexually attracted all of this is going on in the university
how can it be a safe space it's a completely dangerous space by definition
yeah so so yeah teaching young people how to manage these storms
you know
that's part of the job and and we've
we're really not allowed to do that anymore
because we can't talk about these things for fear of the title
nine
officers
kicking
down the door
and dragging
us off in chains
and like you said hard work and something you call work ethic
in civilization
is
um is a pretty is a pretty effective way to
achieve i think a kind of happiness in a world that's full of anxiety
or at least exhaustion so sleep well
well there is there's a beauty to the exhaustion too that's why running this manual work
that some some part of us is built for that right i mean we are
products of of evolution and
our adaptation to a technological world is a very imperfect one so
hence the kind of masochistic urge to to run
i i'd like
outdoor exercise i don't really like gyms
so i'll go for long punishing
runs in in woodland
hike up hills i like swimming in lakes and in the sea
because there just has to be that physical
activity in order to do the good mental work and so
it's all about trying to do the best work
that's my sense that we we have
some random allocation of talent you kind of figure out what it is that you're relatively
good at and you
try to do that well i think my father
encouraged me to think that way
and
you don't mind about being average at the other stuff
the
kind of sick
thing is to try to be brilliant
to everything
i hate those people
you should really not worry too much if you're just
an average double bass player which i am or kind of average skier which i definitely
am
doing those things okay is is part of leading a rich and fulfilling life
i was not a good actor but i got a lot out of
acting as an undergraduate
turned out after three years of experimentation
oxford that i was
broadly speaking better at writing
history essays than
my peers
and that was my edge that was my comparative
advantage
and so i've just tried to make a living
from
from that slight edge
yeah
that's a beautiful way to describe a life
is there a meaning to this thing
is there a meaning to life what is the meaning of life
i was brought up by a physicist
and a physician
they were more or less committed atheists who had left the church of scotland
as a protest against sectarianism in glasgow
and so my sister and i were told from an early age life was a cosmic
accident
and that was it there was no great meaning to it
and i i can't really get past that
isn't there beauty
to being an accident at a cosmic scale
yes i wasn't taught to to feel negative about that and if anything
it was a frivolous
a frivolous insight the whole thing was a kind of joke
um and and i think that
atheism isn't really a basis for ordering a society but it's it's
been all right for me
i don't have a kind of sense of of a missing religious
faith
for me however there's clearly some embedded
christian ethics in the way my parents lived and so we were kind of atheist calvinists
who had kind of deposed
god but carried on behaving as if we were members of the elect
in in a moral universe
so
that's kind of
um the state of mind that i was left in and i i think that
we aren't really around long enough to claim that our individual lives have meaning
but what
edmund burke said is true the real social contract is between the generations
between the dead the living and the unborn
and the meaning of life is
for me at least
to live in a way that honors the dead
seeks to learn from their accumulated wisdom because they do still outnumber us they outnumber the
the living by quite a significant margin and then
to be mindful of the unborn and our
our
responsibility
to them writing books is a way of communicating with the unborn
it may or may not succeed
and probably won't succeed if my books are never assigned by work professors
in the future
so what we have to do is more than just write books and record podcasts
there have to be institutions
i'm 57 now i realized recently
that succession planning had to be the main focus of the next 20 years because
there are things that i really care about
that i want future generations to have access to
and so the meaning of life i do regard as being intergenerational transfer of wisdom
ultimately the species will go extinct at some point
even if we do colonize mars one senses that
physics will catch up with this particular organism but it's in the pretty far distant future
and so
the meaning of life is to make sure that
for as long as there are
human beings
they are able to live the kind of fulfilled lives
ethically fulfilled intellectually fulfilled
emotionally fulfilled lives that civilization has made possible
it would be easy for us to revert
to the uncivilized world there's a fantastic book
that i'm going to misremember milos is the captive soul the captive mind rather
which has a fantastic passage here he was a polish
intellectual who says americans can never imagine what it's like
for civilization to be completely destroyed
as it was in poland
at the end of by the end of world war ii
to have
no
rule of law
to have no security
of
even person never mind property rights
they can't imagine what that's like and what it will lead you to do
so one reason for teaching history is to remind the lucky
generation z members of california that
that civilization is a thin film and it can be destroyed remarkably easily
and to preserve civilization is a tremendous
responsibility that we have it's a huge responsibility
and we must we must not destroy ourselves
whether it's in the name of of wokism
or the pursuit of the metaverse
preserving civilization
and making it available not just to our kids but to people we'll never know
generations ahead that's the meaning
and
do so by studying the lessons of history
right not only studying them but then acting on them
for me the biggest problem is how do we apply history more effectively
it seems as if our institutions including government are very very bad at applying history
lessons of history are learnt poorly if at all
analogies
are drawn crudely
often the wrong inferences are drawn
one of the big intellectual challenges for me is how to make history more
useful
and this was the kind of thing that
professors used to hate but really practically useful so that
policymakers
and citizens
can think about the decisions that they face with a more historically informed
body of knowledge
whether it's a pandemic the challenge of climate change what to do about taiwan
i can't think of a better set of
of things to know
before you make decisions about those things than
the the
things that history has to offer well i love the discipline of applied
history
basically
going to history
and saying
what
are the
key principles
here that are applicable
to the problems of today
right and how can we solve that great philosopher of history r.g collingwood
said in his autobiography which was published in 1939
that the purpose of history was to reconstitute
past thought from whatever surviving remnants there were and then to juxtapose it
with our own predicament and that's that juxtaposition
of past experience with present experience that is so important
we don't do that well
and indeed we've we've flipped
it so that academic historians
now think their mission is to travel back
to the past with the value system of 2021
and castigate
the the dead for their racism and sexism and transphobia
and whatnot
and that's exactly wrong
our mission is to go back and try to understand
what it was like to live in the 18th century
not to go back and condescend to the
the people of the past
and once we've had a
better understanding once we've seen into their lives read their words tried to reconstitute
their experience to come back
and understand our own time better
that's what we should really be doing but academic history has gone completely haywire
and it does almost the exact opposite of what i think it should do
and by studying history
walk beautifully
gracefully through the simulation
as you described by mapping the lessons of history into the world of today
we have virtual reality already in our heads we do not need oculus
in the metaverse
this was an incredible hopeful conversation
in in many ways that did not expect i thought our conversation
would be much more about history than about the future
and it turned out to be the opposite
thank you so much for talking today
it's a huge
honor to finally
meet you to talk to you thank you for your valuable
time
thank you lex and good luck with putin
thanks for listening to this conversation with neil ferguson
to support this podcast
please check out our sponsors in the description
and now let me leave you with some words from neil ferguson himself no civilization
no matter how mighty it may appear to itself is indestructible
thank you for listening and hope to see you next time