um,
so we're here for um
oral history of avi tavanian
and it is febian
tanian
already started with thank you. uh
avitanian
and it's february 21st and i'm john maroff
and hansen
sue is to my left
and david brock is to my right
and on we go.
so can we start by um
having you tell us
uh
where and when you were born.
sure.
i was born in portland, maine back east in 1961.
okay.
and um
can you tell us something about your family and how your family came to to maine
and
um
you know a little bit of their origin?
so
uh
i'm 100 % armenian. both of my parents are armenian and both of their parents
all of my grandparents came over in the early 1900s from armenia.
um
as part of the um
you know war with the turks. um
i should know more about that than i actually do.
uh
certainly heard a lot of stories about that when i was younger and mostly forgotten them. um
so anyway, my grandparents came across literally on the boat.
um
they had children.
uh
my
dad
my dad's family went to portland, maine. my mom's family went to worcester, massachusetts. somewhere along the way
they met each other. don't know how that happened.
um
they got married and i was her oldest son.
and was armenian spoken in the household when you were growing up? it was a little bit
uh
my parents were both fluent in armenia. armenian.
they would usually use it when they didn't want us kids to know what they were saying. um
but we knew a few of the words ourselves.
not enough to converse with them, but we could usually figure out what they were saying. yeah.
yeah.
and what did your parents do?
so my mom was some kind of bookkeeper before she was married.
when she got married, i think she gave up that career, just became a full-time mom.
i came pretty early on after they got married and she had four boys
so we kept her busy.
um
my dad started out
basically
uh
well
when he was very young
like 10, 11, 12,
very poor family
obviously coming from armenia
in portland
and
uh
he worked when he was very young and tried to also go to school. so he would
in portland
he'd go down to the warf in the morning like 3 : 00 a.
m.
4 : 00 a.
when the fishing boats were coming in.
he'd buy the fish from them, take them to the supermarkets and try to make some money doing that.
then he go do a paper route and just anything that he could
um
while still going to school.
uh
he then went into the army for world war ii. he was a machinist.
he was always good with his hands.
uh
he was literally in the action, not on the front lines, but right behind as a machinist.
he would go and fix tanks when they broke down or whatever else.
then he came back and he was basically
um
you know
he did jobs where he could use his hands for a while working in machine shops,
worked in a christmas ornament factory for a while
if i recall correctly
and then he basically became an entrepreneur in the late 50s
um
which of course is before i was born.
he saw an opportunity
or he saw a movement of drive-in theaters
and so he bought some land just outside of portland and built a drive-in theater
which exists today and is still a family business.
oh wow.
um
he
then
in the 60s
um
while also operating the um drive-in theater
bought a bowling alley out of bankruptcy and rebuilt that business and turned it around.
i spent many hours working in that bowling alley myself. um,
and then as my younger brothers were getting to the age
where they would go out
and get jobs
and stuff, he built a business beside the bowling alley, which was at
that time a retail boat business, which then got morphed into other fun toys like snowmobiles, motorcycles, things like
that,
which a couple my brothers still run. your dad's sort of entrepreneurial gene. um, it's interesting.
he started sort of as bluecollar worker. yes.
and but going back, do you know if there was an entrepreneurial history in the in the family in armenia? i mean, what pushed him toward business? um,
you know,
i i really don't know.
um,
i mean, it's
it was so long ago
and we lost him about 30 years ago, so it's been a while since i've heard any of the stories.
um
he
you know
he grew up in the age himself
where you had to work hard just to put food on the table
and he was helping put food on his family's table by doing that
and so i think you learned a lot from being in the army
especially in world war ii
and he was just always looking for ways to better his family's life and so i think
when he got to a certain point of um
affluence
if you will
i mean by the time i was born and growing up
we were definitely middle class.
um,
you know,
by working hard for many years, earning a salary, and i'm sure saving it like crazy.
um,
i think he thought he could take a little more risk, which was, you know,
building the drive-in theater to get beyond just having the regular 9-to-five type job. but he was
he was
he was not just a typical,
even though he started out as a blueco collar worker, he was not typical.
i remember
when i was younger, he taught me about how the stock market worked, which i thought was, you know,
even back then,
not many people even invested in the stock market. you had the wall street journal with the, you know,
the quotes in the back of the paper every single day.
it was only you got stock quotes, but he was into that and he'd show it to me.
so, he was interested in these other things beyond just the blue, the blue collar type stuff.
yeah. um, could you say a little bit about your brothers?
um, and what did they go in a technical direction
just sort of general? so, i'm completely different than my brothers.
um, they all went into the hands-on type businesses themselves.
the, in fact, the three i have three younger brothers.
they all went into the family business focusing on what would again start out as the boat business.
now, my father actually died shortly after that was set up and operating,
and he had always intended that that was something they could do with their lives,
and they ended up doing that
because he wasn't there to run anymore.
so they kind of learned trial by fire on some of that.
i had one brother who worked building yachts for a while up at a place in maine
and doing some other things like that.
but two of them still do that today. okay. and sort of characterize what the household was like
grow,
you know,
your home was like growing up. were dinner table conversations lively? sort of stylistically.
what was the family like? yeah, it was kind of crazy with four of us boys. uh
you know
in retrospect
um
in some sense it was a traditional armenian family in that
you know
my mom was just a great cook making traditional armenian foods
and so you know nothing
i would have appreciated at the time
of course
it was just dinner right
but
um
it was
it was something that i think was just really good for our upbringing
we always saw our dad as a hard worker
going in early in the morning
coming back late at night
um
when we were old enough to know he
when he was rebuilding the bowling alley.
um,
my brothers and i were all close.
we'd do things together all the time.
we lived in a neighborhood that was friendly.
doors were always unlocked.
we knew all the neighborhood kids.
we'd go outside on the street, play kickball.
we'd go down the street and find a big field and play baseball.
all those kinds of things. but this was
this was typical of the, you know,
60s and early 70s.
um
you know
many evenings we'd all stay home and watch tv around the the one
family tv like again
like everybody did with
sometimes with our tv dinners.
i became a huge star trek fan then
right when it came out.
and so if your brothers went into the family business
was there something
why did you go in a different direction? i was always the different one.
so when i was very young
they knew that i had an aptitude for math
is what it turned out
to be.
and so we'd all be in our station station station wagon driving along, the six of us, two parents
and four kids,
and my dad would be
th
would be shouting out math problems for me to solve.
and it would be, you know,
multiplication tables or things things like that.
but um
you know,
i was always the one that got good grades in school and homework was easy
and it was
it was more challenging for my brother.
so it was always new.
it was always informally known that i was kind of going to be the one to go off
and do something different.
yeah.
did you say you were the first? i was the oldest. yes.
okay. yes.
and any idea what where the aptitude for math came from? um,
you know,
i i think both my parents were pretty smart.
i can't say that either one of them was particularly good at math.
and i'm pretty sure that
by the time i got to high school, i was doing more advanced math than they knew about
cuz they never helped me with homework.
and i'm not sure they could have at the time.
um
it's just i just got that gene from somewhere. yeah.
and and i had a love for it.
and i think maybe that's part of the genetics, too. yeah.
and in that period in the 60s
when you're growing up, religion and politics in your household, were there? um
the
the religion was minimal. uh
my mom was somewhat religious from massachusetts. she was a regular churchgoer and but we'd all worn her down
and the extent of her religion at
that point was to try to get us to go to church for christmas
or easter,
something like that. um
minimal politics.
um
my dad leaned republican as a businessman. um
he did run once for some city alderman position
and he didn't know what he was doing and he didn't win
but he only did that once. yeah.
was your mother orthodox? um
so i don't even know.
my mother
i don't
i don't know.
there was an armenian church though. there was an armenian church. uh
well
it was
that was a big deal in worcester where she came from.
um,
in portland
there was an armenian community
which i think went to an armenian church or an armenian dominated church. i'm not sure
because that was not my thing. yeah.
and portland, maine in the 60s and 70s.
um,
it was big enough
that we wouldn't call it a small town, right? how would you describe portland in in
you know your community in portland when you were growing up? was it suburban or urban or?
so i grew up, we lived in portland
when i was born and we moved from portland to a neighboring town, westbrook,
when i was in second grade.
so i was maybe six or seven years old
and westbrook was definitely the suburbs even though it was only four miles away.
um, so i i consider myself as growing up in the suburbs.
and
when we got old enough, we had dirt bikes
and we literally drove the dirt bikes a quarter of a mile down the road to
where the trails were
and there were trails there. and and uh
it's
it's probably worth mentioning.
i mean, my brothers and i, i mean, me being more of an academic type person
had this exposure to all these things that academics normally don't get exposed to.
like we'd go dirt bike riding all the time over huge jumps,
you know,
doing crazy things. we look back, we don't know how we possibly survived.
with my brothers, we literally built a boat.
and it was a high-speed boat that went 90 to 100 miles an hour called a drag boat.
quartermile drag boat. and we
we
what the time would have been called mailordered a small fiberglass hull from somewhere in california
that got shipped out.
um
actually
that was our second boat. our first boat
we literally got plywood, we bought frames, plywooded it, and fiberglassed it ourselves.
that boat probably went 70 miles an hour
and my brother
and i were driving in it at one time
and i looked over the side and i it was blue.
i see this blue flap
and it was fiberglass starting to come off my motion.
i said we better go back quickly. when we got back it had all ripped off on the bottom
just the plywood.
so it was interesting growing up in a family like that
because of all these other experiences
that i think most of the people i know today never had anything like it.
yeah.
um
and somehow we all survived it. and um
in in your school in
i guess
in in the in the suburban in westbrook, you know,
science and technology,
did you get exposed to besides sort of math, was there,
you know,
would you call
i
i guess i would call it
um
sort of fallout from sputnik? did
did you have a science education in
yeah,
we had a science education and a math education.
you know, we're talking rural maine now
or semi not way out in the boonies, but we're near portland, so we've got good teachers.
we've got money for the schools. we've got good schools. um,
and to to me it was a good exposure.
westbrook had a very good school system. um,
and you know, it it today you go to a lot of schools
and there's all these different lanes and different tracks and you're on the advanced lane
where you're learning calculus as a junior or even earlier
sometimes
and the low lanes where you're kind of struggling to get algebra done.
we had one lane with some honors classes
and that was it
and that was only in math.
we we had that in some science too. but i feel i got good solid exposure to the sciences
which i liked and to math which i liked.
and i think
um
maybe
more importantly, i think i was lucky in that
the school
when i went to high school, actually in 8th grade,
as i was preparing to go to high school, the school knew that i had some good math aptitude.
and so they kind of singled me out
maybe along with a few other kids to show us a few extra things and give us extra stuff.
so, i remember so vividly
when i was in 8th grade at the or high school orientation, they pulled me in
and they said, " and we have a computer.
" and i didn't even know what a computer was.
okay? i didn't know what a calculator was, nothing like that.
but they had a pdp8e and i didn't know what it did.
it was just this box that had some flashing lights and i just fell in love with it.
i'm like, " high school is going to be so cool. " uh,
and it was.
and so, you know,
i had a a teacher.
i had the same math teacher for three years, mr.
small, sophomore, junior, and and senior years. he had an advanced
uh
honors
math class, which i was in.
and he would do other things after school that would enrich us even more.
so, while i mean, we did most of our pdp programming after school, kind of come in
and use it, right, for as much as you want, and there only half of us ever wanted to.
um, but he would do other things like offer a special class, learn how to programming.
we had an oliveti cash register that could be programmed in some way i can't even remember now.
and and so i would get access to all these sort of extracurricular things.
so this is by now we're in the early 70s
or is this well,
now you're mid to late 70s.
late 70s. okay. so was the pdpa connected to the outside world with a modem or anything
or was it just a standalone? it was a standalone computer with two
asr33 teletypes, which is where the normal
the computer quote
computer science class, there was no computer science class.
there was a math class
where you learned a little bit about programming it and you always used just the asr33s, right? um,
but again, they would let me go after school and load up different things into the computer.
so, everyone's using basic. i would learn focal.
i would learn how to program from the switches on the front.
um,
and i would write
and
and obviously my regular basic programs, but i could just do all these other things just to learn extra stuff
that weren't wasn't even being taught in class.
focal was lower level
or what kind of a program? it was another programming language.
i i can't even remember any details, but it was basic like i think
but what what really excited me was programming at the switches. yeah.
you know,
you select the address, you select the data in,
load
and that was it
and then run when you're done.
so is that
even
is that machine or assembler?
what would you machine code?
machine code.
yeah, you wrote out the bits. you can go
each switch was a bit.
yeah, that was
that was
i thought that was the best.
that's great. that that's great. and so would you call it was mr. small?
what did you think of him as a mentor? did he take you under his wing kind of?
yeah, i think he did. yeah.
and it was the computer stuff,
you know,
he sponsored our math team.
i became the captain of the math team.
had tremendous fun with that. he gave us all this extra stuff to do outside of class.
um
yeah,
and interestingly through all this i thought i was going to become a statistician because i was told
um by they
they would have career people come in for career advice and they say
oh
you
you guys that are really good in math
you're going to become statistitians
and now that would be a perfect career choice
because you could have gone right into machine learning and be set.
yes.
well, what actually what happened was
i think it was either my junior year or senior year,
we got some new fangled data
general computer that had memory and our our programs could be stored on it.
and this was a whole new paradigm for us programming
and it had a much more advanced basic and other ways to interact with it
and you could
we could like
like write
like real games and stuff on it. and i remember
um
you know
when i got to the school
the pdp was already installed up and running
but for the data general
it took like a week for some technicians to come in
and set it up and test it and do whatever they did.
and i at that point i said that's what i'm going to be
that's going to be my job. one of those people. and did it
when you talk about
did it come with games
like was adventure on it
or were there
and were you taken with games at all or were you more interested just in this was before adventure.
um
there was some game on it.
i think it was a very basic game that would have been a teletype type game.
i don't remember what it was
but i did
i did love it. yeah,
i did love it. and did math take over your life? i mean were you a math geek
or were you were there other subjects in school that caught your interest? so,
um
i guess i was probably a math geek then
because the computer science part of it was very minor.
although i liked working with the computers much more, right? i also enjoyed some of the scientists.
i really liked physics for some reason. something about that really really resonated with me. um
but when i went to college then it wasn't about math. it was about computers
and i went to university of rochester
which didn't offer computer science program
knowing i wanted to do computers.
so i was still sort of a quote unquote math geek
because i had to get a degree in math.
that's all they offered.
there was no computer science degree. but i spent all my time working on computers. yeah.
and before we leave high school, um
um
outside pursuits
like
like sports
and reading, were
were you a jock at all
or
um
so that that's an interesting question
because in middle school
of all things
it was all intramural sports
and i literally played every intramural sport that you could play
and i won an award for that in my eighth grade
like most intramural sports played something like that.
um,
but
by the time i got to high school, i wasn't good enough at any of the sports except for bowling
because we own the bowling alley.
very good bowler. probably could have become a professional galloping bowler. um,
but i wasn't really good enough at the other sports.
and i think it was more i wasn't big enough to play the other sports.
so, i didn't do them in high school other than recreationally, occasionally with friends.
i then got bigger in college for some reasons.
my i had a big growth spurt in college
and i'm actually much more athletic now than i was in high school.
so never get into sports per se.
that having been said,
my family spent every summer on a lake nearby where we had a summer place.
and so i became a very good water skier
and you know
to some people riding dirt bikes and things like that is very much a sport
in that it takes a lot out of you
when you're out on trails and it's bouncing around and you're hitting jumps and doing corners and everything else.
yeah. so there was that aspect of it. did your dad's background as a machinist
carry over? did you get into tinkering
or was there a machine shop at the house? did he had a machine shop at the bowling alley?
and we'd always joke it was behind the machines.
you the front of the house and then you've got behind the machines
and usually the only time you go behind the machines is to fix them.
he would go behind the machines to build things
and so he would buy equipment, lathes or what you know
massive drill presses, whatever.
and during the day
when he's supposed to be working up front, he would have someone else work up front
and go back and just build things.
on the weekends, he'd sometimes bring us in and show us how to do things.
but i personally had no aptitude for that.
um
that was my brother's when we built that boat.
we built an engine from scratch.
we went down to a chevrolet dealer
and ordered a bare block from and they're like, " what? " yeah.
well, okay.
we'll order it for you.
and they shipped it to our house and we bought all the other parts and built the motor.
now, that was all my brothers
cuz they had much more aptitude for that than i did.
gotcha. but i got to see it all happen. yeah.
and um
in high school, did you have any like
did you have to
did you work in the family business or did you have jobs?
um
good question.
so
in high school, uh
on weekends
definitely work at the bowling alley, help out in the morning on saturdays and sundays
when it would get busy.
sometimes help out during the week
on the evening
when there's a big league night,
but not too much because we had school to worry about.
the first real paying job i had was after my senior year
just before college at a company paper mill called sd warren.
and um
i won if you can win a job, i won this job.
they gave this job to a couple students in recognition of some academic whatever.
um
they
they were the local company in westbrook
and so they gave a couple jobs and the job was outside crew.
and you may ask,
well, what's outside crew?
well, let me just say
when we didn't have our normal job to do, we would go and we would sweep parking lots.
so, so
uh
we would do things like you'd go on the daily run around the paper mill to empty the trash cans.
um
you would be called on occasion to clean out a sewer, which meant taking these massive hoses with these um water jets
that shot backwards, sticking them into the sewer, then firing it up
and just having it bore through the sewer.
and it's a paper mill. things
these things would get plugged a lot and you just do all these crazy things throughout the mill.
so that was my first real job, which was interesting
because the next summer i worked at the paper mill again, but i worked in the research department programming their computers.
cool.
and what kind of machines did you have? that was still in high school.
no, that was after one year of college. okay. after my my first my
after my freshman year.
and the corporate computers of that era, what what did you do
you remember what they were? they deck micomp computers
or um
we had
so this was interesting because it was in the research lab and it wasn't really programming the corporate computers.
we got to do research projects where
uh
for example
so they would make paper and then they would code it
and there's all these different codings you could do
and in the research lab
they had a smallcale prototype coder where they'd run experiments and they had a control system on it
that was unlike what was in the mill
because in the mill it just did one thing right
but we could fully program it to control the coder
and and mostly get readings off it to figure out temperatures and all kinds of other things
and i got to do the programming on that
which i think was probably controlled by digital equipment, probably pdp type stuff.
and i love that because i got to work on all these programs to control equipment.
i mean, control real equipment. i i could control digesttors that would cook the pulp as it's being prepared
um to turn into paper to control the temperatures and heat and everything else.
and i and i could control the computers to basically run and monitor this coder.
it was
it was very cool stuff. excellent.
and so in that period through high school, so personal computers were starting to show up in the world.
microcomputers were starting to show up in the world in 75, but it sounds like you sort of grew up on many computers.
and when you were in high school, did pcs show up at all in your um
you didn't see that issue of popular computing that had the mitsal tear on the
it wasn't popular computing, it was popular electronics that had mitsal out there on the cover
or have your own computer kind of thing.
that was not even on our radar screen.
the closest thing
that we had to
that was i had, you know, the top line top-of-the-line ti handheld pocket, not pocket, the big ti calculators back then.
programmable programmable.
they were programmable.
yes. yes.
so so
um
and then
in terms of of going to school, what determined where you went to to college? almost accidental.
um
so you know,
obviously neither of my parents had gone to college. um
they
they were not
they were smart. they were not highly educated.
um
which was not uncommon back then. um,
i had
i mean i was
i was literally going high school for me was day-to-day whatever,
right? i'm having fun on the math team.
i'm having fun programming computers and no long-term planning.
someone's telling me i'm going to be a statistician, but i'm thinking i'm going to be a computer technician
installing computers, whatever.
and i i realized at some point
that i was going to go to college, but i knew nothing about college.
i knew nothing even about the application process.
and then i started hearing in the fall of my senior year about some of my friends who had been getting some early acceptances at colleges.
i'm like, really? i didn't even know you're supposed to like apply now, right?
and so somehow i figured out
and i think my parents started helping me a little bit, probably mostly high school counselors.
yeah, you need to apply to college.
and i had won this award
um
called the bosch and lom science award
which was awarded by bosch and lom in rochester, new york
um
back in the day, right? and they or they
they gave this award to an outstanding science student in every high school in the country.
and one of the benefits of that was you got a free application to the university of rochester.
and this is a really
it's kind of a sad but funny story.
so i had heard of rochester institute of technology being a technology person
and i figured that was one of the schools i would apply to.
and so i'm given this free application from the university of rochester. i think they're basically the same thing.
it never occurred to me they were different.
and i'm like this is great.
i get to save 50 bucks.
i don't have to pay them for the for the admission fee.
so, i sent it in and i sent in a couple others. um,
and um
the ones i remember i applied to were rochester, um,
princeton, mit, and tufts.
um,
uh,
both princeton and mit said no.
um, mit said no because they didn't like my essay.
and i remember at the time i made a mistake of not having anyone help with my essay.
and i'm sure it was a disaster.
um,
which in retrospect i should have done differently. both tus
and um,
rochester accepted me
and so we figured i just go to tus because it's pretty close. and we
we drove down there one day. it seemed like a fine school. and so we went,
that was a fine trip.
but then a friend of our family said, you know, you should look at rochester before you make the final decision.
so my dad and i got on a plane.
first time ever getting on a plane.
we we had to take a connection to get to rochester, new york. okay.
and and i remember going there
and
um
they said
well
you know
we don't have a computer science program
and i think tus might have had a minimal computer science program
there was pretty rare
but they took me in
they had graduate students
graduate computer science students
they took me into the lab
where the
where the graduate students worked
and they had a xerox alto
and i didn't know what a xerox alto was
but they showed me
this computer with a spinning globe on it
so here i am coming from a pdp8
okay.
and i see a computer with a graphical display with spinning color earth graphics.
i was just blown away. i didn't see anything like that at tus. yeah. okay.
and i'm like, okay. even though this
even though these are graduate students
and and they said, " and by the way,
you know, we can probably get you in here and give you some access.
" i'm like, " i have to come here.
" so, i decided to go there. and so, what year
would
what
what year did you enter? um
79. 79. okay. okay. so, the alto was pretty mature at that point. it was
uh
relatively
it was rare, right? but it was relatively mature. do you know why they ended up at why rochester?
do you know? was there a faculty member? xerox.
oh, of course.
yeah.
of course.
yeah. right.
xerox was a big supporter of rochester.
that's right.
so, it was all accidental.
i thought i was applying to rit
and i i finally get to rochester. oh, that's actually a different school. but it's okay.
it worked out.
so, so before leaving high school, um, did either video games
or computer networks show up on your your radar at
all
in video games were out in the world. we had a pong.
okay. so, we had the first ataris that came out. oh, the bowling alley.
no, no, no.
on our tv at home. okay. and i loved those things. yeah. right.
the video games in the bowling alies came a little bit later, but remember you could get pong
and you could get the basic atari thing.
um, may maybe you could get the video games in in the bowling alleys then too.
i don't remember. but it was very cool. very cool to have it. p
you could get pong.
that's right.
pong was first.
and so i remember falling in love with all that stuff.
yeah.
but to me, the notion of being able to program those things myself was completely foreign, right?
that was something way beyond what i even thought possible.
yeah.
at least for myself. yeah.
but the the family had some one of the video game like an atari or something to play.
yeah.
yes.
and but you weren't programming that. you were programming real computers. well, i mean, you couldn't really pro
it was an atari game console, right? and you bought the pre-programmed games.
you couldn't program them yourself. it was a big deal to program them. yeah. yeah.
so, um
um
tell us about the university of rochester and sort of what showing up as a freshman.
what was it like? would you living in a dorm? and and living in a dorm, i remember it
it was very hard for me. um
because i'd never been away from home before,
completely isolated,
no internet to send emails to friends or family,
right? no unlimited cell phone plan to call home.
there's one phone in the dorm and you have to pay long distance charges which i couldn't afford.
so, i was isolated.
and to make matters worse, i go to my first orientation meeting with a bunch of other freshmen
and they're all saying, " what's that weird accent you have? "
and had a really thick man accent at the time.
and i'm like, " oh my god, i didn't even know i had an accent.
what are these guys talking about?
they're all from new york and everything else. " and so it was
it was very hard yet. um,
you know,
by those day standards, they had great computing facilities
and again no undergraduate computer science program as a degree, but they did offer some classes.
and so of course
first semester i signed up for intro to programming
whatever it was where we learned pascal or fortrren or whatever.
and so i got an account on the ibm 3070
or whatever whatever it was at the time the big computer punch cards
and everything else.
and so um
that was for classwork.
and so i started using that
and i found another friend in my dorm who was also in the computers.
he wasn't quite a good programmer as i
but i
i would be in my dorm writing my programs
and then taking them in to the punch cards and so remember
in those days you had an allocation of computer time right
and it was all normalized to dollars you had
so we had like say $ 100 for the semester
i used it all up in like two weeks
okay
just writing my own programs and experimenting
and i
one of the first programs i wrote even without any assignments
was a program that would print posters because we want to put posters on our walls in our dorm
in the hall
in the hallways of the dorms. we had no way to do that.
so i said, i can write a program.
so i designed a font and did it all,
you know,
i encoded it myself and then wrote a program.
you just put in the cards for what i was going to print out.
and i got in big trouble for that
because i had these huge printouts coming out
which, you know,
some guy would, you know,
cut it off
and bring it to you
and start yelling at you, why did you do this? so i got in trouble for huge printouts.
i got in trouble for using up all my money,
but that was a blessing in disguise
because within the first couple weeks of this class, i had to go visit my professor
because i had no computer time left to do my homework.
so, so i had to explain to him how i'd used up all my computer time
and i was in fear.
but in retrospect,
i realized he said, " okay, this guy has selfidentified as someone who is really interested in this.
" so, not only did he fix my problem with computer time,
he said, " i want to introduce you to our graduate computer lab.
" i see.
so, and so back to the alto.
so, i got back into the alto.
not not quite into the alto then, but i started getting jobs working for computer science faculty.
okay. working side by side with graduate students, getting, you know,
paid, you know,
a reasonable amount of money.
i wasn't expecting to get any money, but they were paying me now. so in evenings and weekends
i would go in there
and i would either do the work i was supposed to do for the professor
or teach myself how to program the alto
or a lot of the work i was a lot of the paperwork i was doing was on a vax at the time.
um
so i got to use all the different systems. so you
you moved to computing right from the what was the math scene like? did you stay in the math program
and was it competitive and how did you stack up against
when you got to college? you've been a math star.
were you still a math star?
okay.
so my ego is usually in check, but there's one thing i have to say, which is at orientation,
they had us all in a big auditorium.
all the freshmen are going to say, " okay, you guys, you're all one of the top students at your high school.
now you're just one of the normal people.
" that scared me, but i still had no trouble there.
and in the math stuff, i was able to stay ahead of everybody.
computer science stuff, clearly it was not
it was still not a problem.
so i felt good about that.
and the math stuff i had to do because it was my degree. um
the
um
the math was getting pretty abstract and pretty complicated. and um
certainly
in the later years with the really advanced classes, i was more in the mode of okay,
i'm just going to figure out how to get an a in this class as opposed to really learning it.
and that's what would start to h to happen.
and i know i've every once in a while i'll find some old document in a closet.
and i found one a few years ago
which was some old math notes i had
and i looked at them
i i didn't even know what they were about.
so you know
i i've learn
i've lost lost so much of the knowledge.
on the other hand, i remember
um
i was still into sciences
and so i took chemistry
and physics
and other classes almost for fun, which in retrospect was kind of crazy, but i remember i took a lot of advanced physics classes
and i remember even though i was in advanced math, um
we got to a point in physics
where the professor said, " okay,
and so now we're going to do some differential calculus that you guys haven't got to in math yet.
" and so just trust me, this is how it works.
and that's when i said, " okay, this physics is getting a little too complicated for me.
" some particle physics and quantum theory. and i stopped.
so i'd had enough of that.
and then i just focused on the math.
but my time was all about the computers. and it wasn't even about the
i mean i took some good classes in compiler theory and other things
where i learned how to build compilers and did interesting things there
but it was all about being able to work with faculty and doing actual research with them
where they were doing research projects and i got to contribute to it. yeah.
and and and doing fun things myself, right? i i mean i
i
you talk
you asked about games before. i started writing games on eltos. what were your
so
what were early games that you wrote on
i may have played some of your games. you probably have
um
i
i forget what order i wrote them in.
i think the first one i wrote was i did knockoff games
cuz i wasn't creative enough to do original games. the first one was a knockoff of missile command.
okay.
i think that's the first one i did
because it was relatively straightforward for the graphics capabilities of the alto at the time.
didn't require too much microode.
and then the second one that i did was defender.
and defender was tricky
because the graphics on that are very intense and i had to write most of the game in microode.
oh wow. were there highlight was
was there pascal? well, there was small talk, right? did you learn?
no. small tech.
small talk was useless for games.
yeah.
okay.
i wrote in microode and bcpl.
didn't spend any time really in small talk.
that was too abstract a language for me.
yeah.
and and how about i mean the alto was such a statement about interface at that point.
i mean you had been in this asr world
and all of a sudden you were in this human machine interactive world.
did how did that i mean
did that play a role in shaping your outlook about computing?
um
probably you have to remember
i was still doing a lot of programming on the vax too. so i had a normal
was it a vt50 something or other
you know
screen
that i'd spent probably almost as much time using
for
you know
i'm writing when i'm writing my compiler
i'm doing that.
i was doing some vssi design work, some design checkers.
i was using that with big data.
um, so i spent probably roughly equal amount of times
and and but i really loved the graphics part of the alto
and just i
i
what i really loved about the alto also was the fact that you could write microode
and you could get right in there
and it was literally the case
that
that your program could break the computer if you didn't have the right weight states in the right spots.
bad things would happen to the computer
and so i had to be really careful about that
and i there's something about that
i always like to be really close to the metal
did maze wars exist
i think so
and were they were
the altos connected
the altos were wereworked
and
uh
my adviser later on at carnegie melon
rick
rashid had written with jean baltre
which inspired me to do the other games
okay
so you saw it before you met
rick
or rick had already left
rick was a graduate student at rochester
just prior to my arrival there
and then he went off to be faculty at carnegie melon
and so i i was able to see track
which of course i loved.
yeah. right.
that was clearly one of the
that's probably one of the very first network games. yeah.
and were you already just in terms of your your studies and your interests
was there already an os direction in as an undergraduate? no,
because people didn't really talk about os's then. it was
i would say it was an interest in low-level software. so close to the mission.
was there an os on the alto?
yes.
did i care about it? no.
because i was writing to the bare metal.
and as soon as you launched the defender program, it took over everything.
i didn't use any of the ui elements that the os provided. none.
yeah.
um,
so that never really occurred to me.
and all the interesting to me, all the interesting games, trek, i was
i loved clint parker's pinball game. remember pinball?
that was awesome. these are things that motivated me and they completely took over the whole computer.
and did you have a view into park? did park show up on your world view as an undergraduate
where allen's group lrg or any of the other
not at all.
yeah.
it was so disconnected and well i should say if it did
i don't remember.
this is a long time ago. so it's entirely possible that it did.
it's just that i've kind of blanked it out. yeah. yeah.
and so at that point had personal computers begun to be accessible at rochester
or were you still a big computer guy? personal computers were accessible. the alto
there
there was an undergraduate lab
which fortunately i didn't have to use
which had
uh
was it the commodore pets
and then they had some apple 2. okay.
and so before i got to spend a lot of time in the in the graduate lab, i did spend some time there,
which again this was all outside of class,
but i would do silly things like i would create
um
so let's say there was um
eight of these computers. i can't remember whether whether it's the commodore or the apple,
i don't remember.
i would write a program that would play music
and i would have an instance running on each computer simultaneously
each playing a different part.
cool.
i would do stupid things like that. that's very cool. for the audience
in that case was you? it was me.
it was me just to show that i could do it.
i'have to figure out a way to get them all started at the same time. yeah.
but that would probably be by bringing in friends or something. yeah. that's a classic hacker behavior. yeah.
i mean, you were pushing the machine to its limits.
i would just try to think about what could i possibly make this thing do that's never done before.
interesting.
and um
how much of your life was computing during college? i mean, were you just sort of swept into the computing world?
and i was swept into it all my spare time.
okay. so, today it would be worse because today you're always connected. so, you know,
at least then
when i went home, i was disconnected. yeah.
but i would be connected a lot in the office or in in the lab for many many hours.
yeah. was rochester an arpa site? did you have connection to the arpanet
or was it something that you were aware of?
um
i don't think we were an arpa site at the time
because we did all of our external email with ucp in uset.
so we probably were not an arpa site at the time
or it may have just been barely coming in. yeah.
yeah.
and um
in terms of the people who were influential
um
the computer scientists at rochester as being very influential on your development
as as a young computer scientist? um
this again
this is a long time. i remember
um
first of all
i remember a lot of them were tall and i'm tall
and i wonder if there's some correlation there between tall and computer science.
i was thinking that at the time.
this is interesting. they're all 6 feet and above and i'm like 6'2, 63.
um,
so that was the first thing that i thought was an interesting correlation.
there were a bunch of guys there. i have a hard time remembering their names. um,
who are very influential.
one was i already mentioned
uh
clint parker
who he wasn't that active
when i he was
he was officially a graduate student
but he wasn't that active.
i think he'd been there for a while.
he had done the pinball game and he had done a lot of really low-level groundbreaking elto stuff.
i know i leveraged some of his stuff in some of my games. he would do like he would
he wrote the classic super fast multiply divide for the elto
and i lifted that and put it in.
and there a few other things that he had done that i i would just kind of take from.
i was inspired by the work rick and gene had done on track
even though i'd never met them. um
there were some people there who were starting to do some experimenting with networking
which i was just kind of learning about. i don't remember who they were.
yeah. but
um
it's
it's so long ago. i
i
i definitely had good relations with faculty. um
you know
the
the person i was working for for most of the time was a vssi per vssi design person.
and at that point in time, the the design tools for vlsi were very primitive.
and he hired me to write a design rule checker program, which had never been done before,
where you make sure it's actually probably going to work
and not, you know,
short circuit immediately, right? um
i did some um computer
uh
computer vision work, very early computer vision
where the hard
i mean you had to like figure out how to do an edge detector, right?
and now that's all given, right? uh
with
um
i think his name was chris brown
who's doing some early work in computer vision
which now seems so basic. um
and then i got
i had a good relationship with um
his name escapes me. it'll come to me
jerry.
it'll it'll come to me later. he was the department head
um
who helped me get into grad school as it turns out.
okay. and questions about your games.
first of all, if defender was graphic intensive, one of the innovations of alto
as i remember
it was bit blit.
and i wonder if bitblit was something that was which you used
or that you knew about in terms of its graphics capabilities.
um, i knew about biplit and bitlit was important for the games,
but defender had a unique
a unique sort of challenge,
which is it drew a landscape in real time at the bottom of the screen that was basically random.
no, not random,
but it was
it was like a squiggly line.
okay, it wasn't just a line from one point to another.
it was thousands of points.
yeah.
okay.
and it had to be drawn in real time.
and bipllet was useless for that. and so i had to code that by hand. there was
i coded one instruction which would draw the landscape
and another instruction which would erase the landscape.
and so as fast as it could, basically 60 times a second, it would erase and redraw.
er, erase and redraw and try and get display sync just right. yeah. there was
that was the only way to do it. and did did these um games
uh
give you a reputation? was there already a community of people who would, you know,
value
i never thought about that at the time,
but probably
um
there weren't a lot of things like that for the alto, right?
and i do know these games spread to the other of the other sites
that
as everything did
everything good that got got spread out.
so it did spread to other elto sites.
um, i can't say that i can look back
and say that caused me to meet more people or whatever.
um,
i just i just don't know.
yeah.
okay.
and
um,
so were you always
at this point
you
were
you were always
so i'm just wondering about high level languages and what the gestalt was
or the sort of at rochester at that point. was it a pascal world?
what was the sort of this high level language that was fashionable
and did you have to spend time with it? so
from an academic perspective, teaching the masses of undergrads was pascal. they offered some more advanced classes
um
where you could do more. you could learn more languages
and in particular
i remember there was a language class
part of which
well
i think there was a language class
and then there was a compiler class
and in the language class we learned a lot of languages.
i remember i remember doing homework.
there was one homework where you had to write a text editor in snowball of all things.
um
so i do remember learning a lot of languages at least at a peripheral level.
yeah.
um
enough to do a text command line based text editor. yeah. back at that time. um
but when you graduated
you still graduated with a math
not an applied math degree, a math degree. i had graduated with a ba in math. math.
yes.
yeah.
and tell us about the the
the
the sort of the path from from rochester to cmu and the help that you got from the chair.
it's jerry
and his name is jerry feldman.
oh my god. okay. you know jerry feldman?
i do know.
a lot of people know jerry feldman.
so jerry was the chair of the department at the time
and i got to work with him a little bit.
he got to know me.
so if you think back to what i said about high school, i was going to be a statistician, right? well, so i'm thinking as an undergraduate in um college now, i'm a pretty good programmer.
i've done a lot of work for the faculty writing code, not not research per se,
but you know, some good work under their direction.
okay.
well, i'm going to go get a reasonably good paying job at microsoft who does all the professional software, right? so,
that was my thinking certainly at least through junior year.
um, but jerry and others said, you know, avi, you should take a look at graduate school.
they thought i'd be a good candidate for graduate school. i'm like, i'm like, what are you talking about?
it's never even occurred to me. i'm lucky to have even finished college.
this is totally cool. first person in my family. um,
but i was working with researchers now. so, i saw what they did.
and somewhere along the way,
what what i did was this this um work i've been doing on the vssi design rule checker.
i had built a um
interesting piece of technology
which would do in using the c language
which would
um
it was a
it was a dynamic
uh
mark and sweep type garbage collector
to automatically manage data structures without having to write any code that no one had ever done before.
or it was kind of interesting.
i pre-processed the header files and i added to them and recompiled them
and there's all
there's all this other magic with a runtime library and could garbage collect in real time.
it was pretty cool for what it was especially for an undergrad
and i wrote a paper on it and i don't
i didn't even submit it for publication or anything
but i figured this would just be a cool thing
and and the faculty i knew was helping me with it
and and so so it's a bit of unusual research for an undergraduate to do. um
and
and so the faculty said, " look, you should at least look at a graduate program before you go off
and get a job.
" i said, " okay, i love working with you guys.
i love this research aspect of it.
why not? "
and so i said, " but i'm only going to do
that if i can go to either carnegie melon, stanford,
or mit.
" okay.
and if i can't get into one of those then, and they kind of agreed with me.
they're like, " yeah, absolutely. " and so, um, i applied to all three
and jerry wrote me letters of recommendation.
i had a research paper that i had written.
lo and behold, i got accepted at all three.
okay.
and so, i'm like, i guess destiny is that i go to grad school.
so, that's how that happened.
and how did you choose which of the three? that's a really interesting.
the way i choose these things seems strange.
i mean, you go back to the rochester thing. so, here's here's the way that works.
so, i get letters of acceptance from all three and um carnegie melon in their letter of acceptance
or maybe in a in a quick follow-up says in you know
we'd love to see
they're all saying we'd love to see you come right
because they don't accept everybody there
maybe a year at those places at the time. yeah.
and and they're like
come visit us
call us up. tell us when you can come down
we'll schedule you know
meetings and everything. we'll take care of everything. so i called him up and i went down.
it wasn't too far of a trip. it was easy drive down to pittsburgh and loved it. and so
um
i then
uh
tried to talk to both
like
i talked to both stanford and mit to try to do something similar. and so i called mit
uh
and they said, " oh, we don't do that.
we we expect people that we expect to come here. " yeah. i was like, " okay,
well
you turned me down once.
i'm going to have turned you down this time. " and then stanford said, " um,
yeah,
we can host you. we don't always do that. we'd love to see you come out,
but you know,
no,
we can't play pay for a plane ticket, and no, we can't give you a hotel or anything.
" i'm like, screw that.
yeah.
if i want to go to the west coast, i'll go there for a job after i graduate from carnegie melon.
so, so carnegie melon was very good about this.
and they weren't really, i mean, they weren't the name brand school, right? so i would talk to my uncles back in maine who had heard of stanford
and mit but never heard of carnegie melon
and they're like wait a minute
especially mit
when if you're in maine
mit is like it
you've been accepted at mit and you're not going like
trust me
this is the right thing
but when i visited carnegie melon
it was just
you know
i loved it
just like i loved rochester when i went there and
and they were very welcoming and they had a
from what i could tell
a great program.
it was a great program. yeah.
go ahead. was so you applied to those three because they were the three top programs
or they were the ones that you that the faculty recommended?
those were the three top programs. yeah. yeah. yeah.
and just there are some people who said, " why didn't you apply to berkeley? "
and i said, "
because berkeley was number four.
" sorry, berkeley fans. yeah. before we leave college,
outside of computing, social life, sports,
what
what was what did you do besides compute while you were?
so, what did i do besides compute?
um, nothing of interest that i remember.
um, so,
you know,
i still had, you know,
interesting summer jobs, but that's was still around computing.
although,
when i was in as an undergrad, i would still go back
and we'd go to our summer place on the lake.
and so that was a 9-to-f5 computing job.
you left it there because there was no way to commute compute remotely and everybody left at 5.
the place was shut down
and then i i'd come back to the lake
and go water skiing with my brothers or boating or whatever.
and we go dirt bike riding or you all those kinds of things, but there wasn't that much else.
yeah. yeah.
um
before we go into the the cmu section, um
could you tell us more about the the other research projects that you were working on at rochester
and some of the other programs that you wrote?
so the
the
the two research projects i remember at rochester were the vlsi design tool and the computer vision work.
i don't even remember the details of the computer vision work.
those are the only ones that i really remember
and frankly those are probably the two major ones that i did.
if there was anything else, i don't really remember what it was.
and then everything else was all my personal programming projects.
and and i always took some kind of computer science class every semester. there was all
there was plenty that were offered. i took them all. um
but probably the most time was spent on my own projects.
and then the big ones i think were definitely missile command and defender. those took a lot of time.
oh, go ahead.
and the lsi design,
was that because rochester had that connection to xerox?
was that coming straight out of xerox park?
um,
we had someone on faculty whose area was vssi design
and um
i don't know why we did,
but we had a diverse set of faculty.
did conway and meat exist by that time? that that text about blsi designer?
i think so.
yeah.
but that was a graduate level text probably not for you know
i remember taking a vlsi undergraduate class where we did
we built a basic circuit
sent it out for fab.
oh, so that was
but it was
it was
it was very basic. yeah.
and i think as i recollect
that helped me a little bit to at least understand what i was working on on the design rule checker.
yeah.
and while you were there, did the ibm pc emerge and did
did there become a culture of the ibm pc style computing, doss,
did that all happen while you were an undergraduate?
um,
jamie,
we can look at the calendar. yeah, it would have happened when i was an undergraduate
just based on the calendar,
but it never i was always doing much more interesting things. i mean, programming on a vax
was way more interesting
and programming on elto
was way more interesting yet again.
so why would you ever use an ibm computer?
and if i wanted to do anything, i could always go use the apple 2
or the the commodore pet,
which in many respects was even more interesting than ibm.
and did computing ever did
were you in
did you live in a dormatory the entire time you were at school
or did you move off campus
or so
uh
it was different every year. so my freshman year i was in the dorm.
sophomore year, i was in an off-campus school-managed uh
two-bedroom apartment with a friend.
junior year, i was back on campus in a suite with five friends.
and then senior year, i was in an off-campus uh apartment with a couple of friends
that was on the school shuttle. yeah. yeah.
and and did com
did you ever have a not home computer
but a computer that you know that was not a work computer. so, so did you
what did did that transition happen while you were in school? like in your dorm room
or in your
so, the first computer i had that was not that was like in my room was probably
i think about this for a second.
that was probably when i bought a mac for myself at carnegie melon in 1984.
yeah.
so, the mac happened after you left.
yeah, i was at carnegie melon. yeah.
was it a big deal to buy a mac at that point? oh yeah.
$ 2, 400
or whatever it was.
it was like it was a commitment student discount. that's right.
and did so you were around when you know the the mac team was on their tour.
did do you remember the mac did?
like
did steve come through while you were a graduate student?
um
if he did on a mac tour, i don't remember it. yeah.
do you remember the 3m machine? the concept of a dream. absolutely.
yeah.
absolutely.
but it was bubbling while you were a graduate student, didn't it? or maybe it was too early.
when did it start? 85.
well, so you know,
i mean, different people have different views of when the first 3m machine was, but like the um
the um
uh
the perk
um
what was the name of the company?
uh
perk
systems or something like that. yeah, it was.
uh
yeah,
perk.
they sort of had one of the first 3m machines
which
of course that was a carnegie melon spin out and it was moused driven.
i remember it was mouse driven. yeah.
yeah.
it was a forgotten perk entirely.
so tell us about coming to carnegie melon entering the program and what what it was like. yeah.
so
um
very different than being an undergrad. um
i was almost like a kid in a candy store. i mean they had everything.
they had altos
of course. they had the ibm machines
which i could care less about.
they had a deck 20
which was super hot, right? and i mean hot in temperature
was hot in temperature
but super hot as a computer, right? and and i could get on that if i wanted to.
uh
they had perks all over the place.
um
which was totally cool
cuz not only was it like an elto in the lab, but you could actually get a perk in your office
which was
i mean that was really cool. yeah.
um
so
from that perspective i was like a kid in a candy store. um
it was also different in that there were some academic requirements
but they were very minimal
you know
minimal theory class
minimal
i probably took four classes the whole time there
it was
it
was
this is one of the things i liked about it.
it was applied research.
everybody there, almost everybody was doing things
that was tangible
that you could see was going to have some real impact in three to five to 10 years.
so what was the process of pairing up with the project or the faculty
or you know
so
was it a
was it a recruiting scene
or did you volunteer? how did you find your way to the
to the project you you ended up
and
was it more than one?
you know, i don't know the way it exactly happened, but i think there was,
first of all,
i think rick may have sponsored my visit to go to go see the place
because they knew there was a connection there with him being a rochester grad
and i think i'd expressed some interest in os level stuff by then.
i'd certainly taken some os classes by then. um,
and so i don't know that they assigned us together.
they probably didn't.
um
other than maybe an informal temporary adviser, but we were sort of naturally drawn together
because his area of expertise and research was
um
oss and he was working on the perk systems
with the accent
operating system
and operating systems were an area of interest to me and we had the connection with rochester.
so he became my adviser.
um
and most other students who took on rick as an adviser
who or he took on as a student
um
prior to me
would go work on some aspect of accent
and there were plenty of things plenty of research to do there.
and i looked at that
i said i don't want to do that and um
i wanted to do something new
and accent was fairly mature. it was they were selling it
um through perk and i wanted to do something completely new
and i think it was
rick told me
he said
you know
we've got this other thing that we're looking at getting a darpa grant for
um
why don't you take a look at that
either he told me that
or someone else told me that
or i somehow i discovered that
and i looked into it
and it was this project to build um parallel computing
if you will.
it had been done a little bit at the time
but not really
and they wanted to do
they were
they were putting in a grant for it
and so i decided i wanted to do that
and so that was a clean slate project
which i could basically start with rick from scratch
and he was very supportive
and
and that's how it all started. yeah.
and what
when you so
parallel computing was on the horizon
what were the hot
risk was a very hot topic there
but that was probably more architectural
like in the software world
what else was there was
i think risk came a little bit after
just a little bit after that
soon after that
though
um
robotics was starting to get hot
not like it is today
right
very different levels
there was a lot of going on in theory
ai was very hot
okay
um
ai was sort of one of the newer things.
people didn't know it didn't work then.
at least they couldn't get it to work then with the resources they had then.
but they really were trying to make it work. that was a big one. yeah.
um
there was still stuff going on in computer vision. there was stuff going on with
uh
transaction technologies, database and transactions.
um
those are the ones that i remember off top of my head.
wasn't there a file system project at that was later
file systems came a little bit later.
okay.
yeah.
and so you know there was a community of people.
were there other faculty who you know were sort of alternative universe ways for you to go that
you know
paths not taken because there was
there
was
well,
i'm sure there was
but i never really considered them. um
i mean i could have gone to work for a on ai.
i mean, carnegie melon was really leading that
then
with some of the people that were there or robotics. they were leading a lot of the robotic
they had a whole separate robotics area
and um
you know
maybe robotics could have interested me a little bit because i like doing that kind of stuff
but some
it just didn't
it didn't click.
i just i think rick and i hit it off hit it off pretty well
and i just love this.
it was a ground floor thing that no one was working on at all.
it was a whole new project
which got me really excited too. did do you remember the name red whitaker?
he was the hot roboticist when you were there.
you didn't end up doing anything with him. i remember the name. that's about it.
yeah.
um
and there was
you're right.
the ai project stuff they had there was formidable. i mean it was simon alen newell.
yeah. they were the guys.
they were the guys. they were all there doing that. yeah.
so
um
the challenge
talk about getting into parallel computing and the challenges of
i mean
did you
i remember that time as parallelization was not working very well
i mean there were people didn't think parallel
there were all kinds of sort of threads
but it wasn't really
things were not parallelized that
at that point in the world
well
as far as i was concerned
and sometimes i have tunnel vision
this may have been one of the times
as far as i was concerned
we were the first ones doing
and we're
it was an unsolved problem and we were going to make it work.
okay. and it wasn't really going to be
i never thought of it as a hard problem. it's like oh
you've got
instead of one computer
you've got four.
you just got to coordinate things, right? and people knew some of the basic things like semaphors.
those were known concepts, right? and so to me it was like okay
we just got to do some hard work. um
so we got the grant. um
digital
uh
had been tapped to build the computer.
they were going to take a 780
and turn into a 784, which was four 780s all hooked in with an inter interconnected shared memory to turn into a 784,
which i love.
i love the 780.
i get to use four of them.
this is totally cool and it's all mine.
um, i get to build the os for it.
no one's there's no os for it.
that was just beautiful.
and as part of that, they had just come out with the microvax.
they gave me a microvax which i got to put in my office.
i had like the best computer in anyone's office in the whole school.
um,
and it was interesting. i got because i got to write
write the os for it. yeah.
and it was not so your
the sort of the
the architectural direction was not parallelizing unix. it was much more fundamental than that.
um, i want to say yes,
but it's not that simple. there was a very fundamental aspect of it
which was to start with
what are the concepts we need to build a parallel
an an os for a par parallel computer
and so from that perspective
we did look at important subsystems
that hadn't really been done in a way that we thought needed to be done
excuse me at the os level for threading
scheduling
virtual memory
management
some things like that
um
but as we got into it very early on
mostly
i think
at rick's urging
we also integrated unix
and the reason for that was building an os that's useful is hard
right
there are many many different layers that you need to build
and what we figured was there were a bunch of layers
that we didn't care about some of these issues that we wanted to have access to
like you
remember the programs a and said and grep
y
we just want those right
we don't want to build those from scratch for a parallel word
we just want them
and
uh
so we figured we could leverage unix
which was getting pretty popular in colleges
um
not only to get those things but to also have a way to get others to use our research
and so we pursued this strategy of building a whole new core os
which was mock
and then the mock kernel
and then grafting onto it
bsd unix.
the whole thing people generally refer to as mock.
now it occurs to me to ask
i
um
maybe i know
the answer is
where did the name mach come from?
how did you come to name this the project?
okay.
um
it's one of the things i remember. um
so there are a bunch of us working on the project. um
and it didn't have a name.
and one of the things about rochester is it rained a lot
or i mean um
pittsburgh is it rained a lot. um
and a bunch of us would go to lunch over at pit
which was right next door to carnegie melon.
there were lots of good restaurants there. so we go to lunch over at pit almost every day
and and so rick and me and a couple of the grad students
maybe a couple of the faculty members were were trying to figure out what name we should pick for this thing.
and the best we had come up with is
um
i can't remember what
the best we came up with,
but we're all walking along
and we're trying to find acronyms that have multiprocessor in them and computing in them
and things like that. and we're
we're failing.
and as we're walking over one of the bridges, we huge puddles of mud everywhere.
and we're like walking, look at all this muck. and someone said, " muk,
that should be the name,
right? multi-user communicating kernel,
something like that. and we're all just joking about it.
and so we get back after lunch
and we're joking with one of the other faculty members who i believe was italian.
and we're like, " the best we've come up with so far is muk.
" and he heard it as mock.
he's a great name, mock.
and so it stuck.
there was no star wars. i mean, star trek.
uh, no.
that's why i guess it's
i thought that was the answer.
no.
so, so
um
did the idea of the micro kernel exist at that point
or did
where were you guys in the sort of architectural approach
that that was based on separating things in that way? i i think the answer to that is yes,
if only because accent had already had an architecture sort of like that. um,
and i don't remember if it was a similar time frame, but there there was other work going on.
i think there's some work at stanford going on or should would go on soon with the v kernel.
um,
and there may have been other work going on a little bit later.
it so it wasn't brand new, but it wasn't old either.
right. right. and were you thinking i'm trying to remember
at a certain point
parallel languages began to emerge. the one i'm thinking of right now is linda,
but i think that was maybe in the late 80s. were you ahead of all the parallel?
were there any parallel languages to to design to?
as far as i can recall,
we were ahead of the parallel languages.
and again, we were
we were operating at a level below that anyway.
yeah.
and if anything,
we were trying to provide something that people doing parallel language development could take use of. yeah. yeah.
um
and and um
okay,
i guess one of the things we wanted to ask for is sort of a a definition for a general audience of what a micro kernel is
or how you thought about separating function in the in design.
the the simplest way to describe how i think about the separation is you have only the minimal functionality
that you require in the kernel
in the kernel.
everything else is out.
and so what that basically means is the basic functions to control the computer itself. um
which is resource management for the protected resources
um
the scheduling of the resources
which is both scheduling of processors and scheduling of memory
which is the virtual memory part.
and that's it from a conceptual perspective.
now then reality sets in, right? and you look at things from a performance perspective.
and so there's all these things
that are now conceptually outside of the micro kernel, file system, networking, even device drivers
that have logic in them.
um, but what you do is you colllocate them with the kernel for performance reasons
and that's what exists today.
okay. yeah.
did
i don't know if we we had talked about this at lunch and the performance issue in particular.
did did you have
oh, i was actually i was just going to ask sort of what
what was mach's major advance over accent?
so, accent had focused on what i would say
is two
two
one idea
that's almost the same thing
or two things
that almost one idea
message passing and virtual memory.
m
and so accented message passing in a certain style
that allowed you to decompose problems into multiple processes that communicate each with each other
and also introduced this notion of what's called copy and write
virtual memory
where you can send
you can send
um
this is important when you
when you have things
sharing two processes sharing a lot of data but don't actually have to use it all.
you could send like 10 megabytes of data in one message without actually sending it
and it goes copy on write.
so it only actually copies when the other process writes it.
and so that and the message passing and they
they kind of go hand in hand.
and we actually did a paper about the duality of virtual memory and message passing at one point. um
that was sort of one of the key things behind accent other than powering a 3m machine. um
and so we kept that paradigm
but the newer things that we added were the notion of the scheduling of multiple processors
and how you do that
and we learned a lot over the years on how to do that efficiently
based on different architectures
um
and how do you do a virtual memory system
that supports this copy on write notion in a multipprocessor system
which is much more difficult than a non multipprocessor system. um
and
and then we also did some work with more formalizing the notion of having services
that aren't in the kernel itself
even though for optimization reasons they are. those are the the big things. it
you know
in the grand scheme of things
it doesn't seem like a lot
but it's pretty profound stuff and important stuff. mhm.
and also to to follow up on sort of this the performance issue. um
so mach 2.
5 was sort of a hybrid micro kernel. so with some things were still in kernel space,
not everything was in user space
and then mach 3 tried to move everything into user space. um
but then you mentioned that
you know
later on
um
things kind of move back towards the hybrid model. um
yeah
so that's a good memory of the version numbers
i wouldn't have remembered that until you mentioned it.
so 2. 5
up until 2. 5
um
we had built everything into a monolithic kernel for performance reasons
and then the 3. 0 effort was an effort
which i think actually that happened after i left carnegie melon and was done in part by osf.
uh
that was an effort to formally have a micro kernel and have services outside.
to me that was more of just a research effort
and i don't know that that codebase ever made it into any product anywhere. yeah. okay.
tell us about the creating the team.
how big was the team and what your role was in the mock
the mock group. um
okay.
so you know that's one of those areas where my recollection differs from other people
because i know people have told me what they thought the team was and how it worked
and um
so this is your oral history. this is my oral history and i'll
i'll annotate it with what others have told me that that may that seem plausible. um
so i started the team being the first person on the project because i wanted something new
and rick suggested because we had this grant potential. um
and of course rick was involved as my adviser. um
but initially he was still mostly involved with accent
and then as other students started coming in
they started just joining the team.
but i think initially i was probably spending a little bit of my time on some of the classes i had to get done
and just kind of poking around on this
and doing a little bit of investigative work such
that we could get the grant to have the money um
and working with deck on getting the actual hardware things like that.
i know i was working on the microvax
doing a lot of prototyping before we even had a 78 784.
um,
so we had a few other students join the project. um,
i think
just because they thought it was interesting.
um,
being the person that started it, i sort of controlled the codebase.
now, i've been told i was a benevolent dictator
when it came to controlling the codebase
and would send pe things back saying it wasn't good enough or all kinds of evil things like that.
i have no recollection of that, so i can neither confirm nor deny.
um
it's partially believable. um
but you know
a few years in we had the
the project was getting large and a few years in we were hiring research staff
not even students to work on it to do a lot of things.
it was turning into a big project and i don't know the numbers. it's too long ago
but you know
we quickly had probably a dozen people on it
and then
um
we started deploying it internally to the department
where we had people in the department using the software. yeah.
and and do you remember what part of
so money came from darpa the first year you were around? you you got
you were up and running as a funded project pretty quickly.
i don't know that the money came in the first year.
i don't remember when it came in, but it came in relatively early. and from ipo,
do you remember what part of darpa
by any chance? i do not remember which part of darpa it came in from
or the was there a program manager who showed up
or it was
you just had money.
i remember we went to a meeting where there were arpa people there.
there may have been some military people there as well,
maybe even someone in a uniform,
but i it was too long. i don't remember remember the details of it. so
um
the thing about mock is it got
you know
i i out on the west coast as a bite editor
i knew about mock mach sort of established itself as a sort of
you know
future of computing kind of idea early on.
do you know
have any idea how that happened
how it sort of got out into the broader world?
so couple reasons.
the first reason is because we adopted bsd unix as our interface
and everybody wanted to use bsd unix already
at least in academia and we had a better bsd unix
because we took out some of the looked at people
we took out some of the pieces of bsd unix they didn't like
and put in parts that they now liked.
uh
and that's true even today.
if you use freebsd, it's basically the version that we did. we grafted mock stuff into it. um,
and so it was
it was easy for people to use it.
it was, you know, they could use a set and graph. it all worked just like they're used to.
and the other thing that we did was we wrote research papers
and went to eustix conferences and other conferences and talked about it.
um,
and not only did we talk about it in a research paper, we said, " and oh
by the way,
here's where you can get a copy of it.
" and everybody else with a research paper had the research paper
and oh by the way
that's all we have.
so that was a pretty big difference and it gets back to the whole carnegie melon at that time
doing everything was very applied.
you know we thought we were failing if we weren't doing something
that other people could actually not just read about but use.
yes.
that's an interesting culture. yeah. um
so maybe
um
we're about an hour and a half in
so
maybe one last question and then we could take a little break. does that does that
um
so your view of the significance and the legacy of mark?
i mean so sort of take it the next step
and how did it change the world? well
boy
that's a complicated question. um
i think it changed the world in this
this is
you know
lots of unintended consequences
perhaps in a good way
which is
it's not even about the technology
it's about the relationships that came.
so, you know,
as we were presenting at usnix one time, steve jobs sent some next employee, some next employees,
and they loved what they heard and they found they could play with it, and they did.
and so they called us up and said, " we want to make this part of the next computer.
" so that would have been circa 86
86 86 87
right after they formed next.
yeah.
so really i don't remember which conference they saw us at precisely, but they told us in'87. yeah.
and then you know
so
then that caused me and steve to have a great relationship.
we did everything with next that led to apple
and i mean the rest is all history.
so i mean it's almost a non-technical story in that regard.
so clearly
i mean we'll get to that
but there is that thread going into next and apple.
um
did rick take stuff of mock philosophy
and architecture into microsoft? did it also have an impact in that direction? i don't think so.
i think it went more the the directions it went in obviously were the next direction.
there was the osf direction
which was pretty significant.
there was the bsd direction where they took a little piece of it and then it kind of stagnated.
those were probably the primary directions.
there were other companies that used the osf version a little bit.
never never in any kind of meaningful volumes. um
and i think what rick took to microsoft was more his research philosophy just in general.
and he wasn't even necessarily doing os research. he was doing research. yeah. okay. so then um
in terms of the micro kernel, so so all the the major oss that use the mock
or a version of the micro kernel still use the hybrid model that you developed
and and not sort of the
the whole theoretical absolute separation between um
user
user space and kernel space programs.
at least practically like
practically
it's not performant
enough
right
so
as far as i know
today
the only commercial uses are what apple has today
which is still what i would call the monolithic kernel
although it is partitioned a little bit
um
and then the other example would be like freebsd a little bit
but i'm not really aware of anything that uses the mach 3. 0
i know a pure micro kernel structure today. interesting.
okay.
i think that was more just a research project that proved it could be done
and today people opt for performance.
yeah.
if i could just ask one quick question to make sure that i'm understanding the story correctly.
it it seems like at first the mock project was very tied to this new kind of experimental machine,
you know,
this ganging the four computers together with the shared memory.
but then it sounds like very quickly
uh
the operating system becomes
not particularly tuned to that parallel experimental machine
but could be used much
uh
more widely.
is that correct?
did it lose its particularity
or?
so that is a really good point.
okay.
and let me clarify.
so initially the project was targeting the va 784.
this cluster of four 780s. but before they could build that, they sent me a microvax
which was just a vax.
it was a 780 with a small one. little desk. it was, you know, not a desktop
but it was small.
and so i started programing.
it had only had one processor in it.
so i started building an os for one where for you know
n processors where n equal one
okay
um
and did work on the 784
later on
worked on other multipprocessors
and what we discovered was that what we quickly discovered
and this was a problem for bsd at the time
um was
bsd wasn't portable
and so we built something that was portable and so other companies were using other instruction sets
so, um, encore was using the mips instruction set.
i believe sequent was using maybe the intel instruction set. i can't
i can't remember exactly. um,
ibm wanted to do things with the rt,
which was the was that the uh pa risk instruction? no.
yeah,
it was pa risk. yeah.
no, that was hp.
no, no,
pa risk was was hp.
what was the ibm risk? a trivia power. power. power. yeah. power.
um
and so so we started building a portable os
in addition to a multipprocessor os
and and um
i remember
in really early days
i i was thinking
you know
i'm a graduate student
been there a couple years
i'm thinking where are all the places we can take this quote
unquote micro kernel
where we're not going to need all of this heavy functionality that you see in an os today
and i'm thinking like maybe someday we can put this in a refrigerator
okay
this is back in
you know
mid 80s
right. and i'm thinking to myself, okay,
is this interesting enough if we can sell it for 50 cents a unit?
right? thinking, nah,
never going to sell that many copies. but but that was the thinking back then. you know,
we were tuned for the 784 initially. um,
but we knew we were building something beyond that.
we were porting to these other systems. was reporting to the rt
that was a single processor system but had an inverted page table which no one had ever seen before.
um
but our vm architecture made it easy to support.
you know we ran on encores,
we ran on sequence,
we discovered they had different memory architectures where they were,
you know,
30 processors in them
and you had to know where the caches were to make things efficient.
so we were doing all of the above at that point in time
and
and we didn't just focus on the one thing
and maybe this is in part why we had so many people that started to work on it.
yeah, that was the era of mini supers,
wasn't it? did you become sort of the the
the
i mean they they needed
they
were
they were all parallel kinds of machines and did they all pick up
uh
mock?
i
you know
i think they all had projects with us going on. they all
they generally ship their own os
okay
to their customers
but they're all working with us and they would have people porting
i don't know that any of them
i'm some of them probably went commercial with it
but i'm not really sure yeah
which ones or if there were any meaningful volumes
but a lot was learned in those years. yeah.
um
can we start tell us a little bit about your dissertation
what you focused on and where
okay
let me remember
oh
yes
okay
long time ago. so for my dissertation, i remember
my plan was to do a dissertation on mock.
seemed to make perfect sense to me. rick said, " no, you can't do that.
that's way too broad. " but, you know, i i was one that was happy being broad. right.
um,
so i said, " no, you got to focus more.
" so, so what i did was i focused on the virtual memory system of of the os
and i focused on
um
what we had done was we had built the first both portable and parallel virtual memory system.
so that was the focus.
yeah. okay.
and how does that work? did in terms of when you left and when you got your dissertation
did you get your dissertation before you decamped
or did it come after you were at
well
um
you mean the chronology related to when i left carnegie melon.
so you have to have your dissertation done before you can leave.
okay.
and so the order of events was
um
you pick your topic
of course
well
in advance of this
and then you do the research specific to it
then you write it up.
it's a massive document
and then you defend it with your thesis committee and then there's more work to do.
they say
great,
good job.
now make these changes. takes you a few months.
you do those tweaks
and you're done.
yeah.
besides rick, was there anybody else of note or you a member on your committee?
yes.
um,
so rick was on my committee,
al spectre was on my committee, uh,
al was a another faculty member, and dennis richie was on my committee.
okay, that's gold standard. that's good. yeah. um
and and then there's a question here, but maybe in the sort of flip it. um
you're
you continued to to work on big systems.
there was this massive explosion of the personal computing world in the first half of the 80s, but i i get the sense aside from you having a macintosh
that you were in a different world.
you remained sort of in a high performance computing world as opposed to the pc world while you were in graduate school
or i
i
from a research perspective, i think that's fair.
um,
remember
i did have the microvax.
yeah.
which was
it wasn't as low-end as the macintosh, but it was a personal
it was essentially a personal computer, the personal workstation. yeah.
um,
you know,
it's hard to say why we didn't focus on even the lower level
more personal computer type stuff. um
there
may
maybe the hardware wasn't quite ready for what we were trying to do is one of the answers.
yeah. yeah.
but i'm not 100 % sure about that.
yeah.
and then one one more question.
um
so while you were there,
you know, a generation earlier,
darpa used to have these annual meetings at snowbird in which they'd have the faculty who were the researchers
and then the students would come too
and it really was a community building exercise.
had those stopped
by the time you were in on a darpa track? well, if they hadn't, i never got invited to snowbird.
maybe rick went. um, so i don't know.
i do remember going to darpa meetings in washington. yeah.
um,
to talk about what we were doing every once in a while.
okay. go ahead. one question also.
um, so why did you decide to get a macintosh rather than, you know, an ibm clone? was it
because of the alto?
and how did you like the mac compared to your alto or compared to your experiences with the alto?
so, that's a good question.
let me think about why that might have been the case.
um, i think it's simply that the the macintosh was i mean, we talked about the 3m machine before
and the macintosh was sort of in the vein of the 3m machine
and the pc was not.
and so this was now a 3m machine that with a student discount i could afford. um
and so it seemed to make sense to buy it.
and while you were doing this research on on on were you a aware of the other projects
that were going on at other campuses of the time.
mips x had started up at um stanford.
um
there was um
sun originally started with bealign and um basket at at stanford.
were those on your radar at all before they got out into the commercial world? um
i don't know that those were on our radar screen before they became commercial that much. we
were
you know
we were being funded to use the deck stuff. other people who were doing things like ibm
for example
were coming in and showing us their stuff with the rt.
um
i don't recall which of the others had come in. some of them may or may not.
we
were
we were definitely getting a lot more interest
and focusing more on the the bigger guys, the encore as a sequence with the bigger iron.
and then i was thinking west coast
and then there were
also
so you were you
you had perk right there
and then what was the name of the sun competitor in in uh
in cambridge that i'm forget in boston. apollo did
did they have much contact with with
uh
you guys?
no
i don't
i mean we were aware of apollo
um
but we never interacted with them. you know i'm trying to think.
we probably had a meeting or two with them.
i remember visiting their place maybe once. yeah.
um,
but nothing really happened all that much.
was data general still alive at that time? i'm trying to remember when they got in trouble.
i think they were irrelevant if they were alive. yeah. yeah. yeah.
um,
go ahead. were the the mac ports of miss soul command and defender
fairly straightforward and just something fun that you did at home? uh,
the mac ports of those games were mostly fun. um,
the mac,
the mac had reasonable computing power compared to the elto,
except when you program the elto microode,
that was hard to be comparable to the mac.
so, um, the ports were relatively straightforward, but i couldn't get around using the os. and uh
i remember
the one big problem i had was i wanted to have sound effects and music in the games. um
and in the mac
in those days when you turned on the uh sound processor
it consumed like 50 % or more of the cycles of the computer.
wow.
and so that put me over the edge where the games didn't work.
so, i had to override the mac sound driver with my own and then i got it to work.
were these freeware projects? i can't
i can't remember.
um, i had visions of selling both the mac and defender games. and in fact, you know,
this was sort of the beginnings of people selling software.
and i had a contract with a company in la that was a software publisher. um,
and they asked me to put some copy protection in, which basically read bad sectors on the disc.
uh,
and then they were going to ship it.
and for some, i think they went out of business before they shipped it. something something like that.
so, i gave it away as freeear.
um,
uh,
i had a little message. if you like this, send a check to whatever.
a few checks came in. i think i got
i think i almost paid for the mac. maybe not quite.
not quite.
oh, that's that's they come in, you know,
$ 5, $ 10 at a time. yeah.
but it didn't seduce you into an open source
i mean a a a program cottage programming lifestyle. shareware. shareware.
yeah. no.
no.
yeah.
so now here you are at your next juncture.
um
what was your thought process while you were sort of in the second half of your graduate student career about what you would do after after graduate school? okay.
so let's set the stage.
i'm a happy camper, happy graduate student at carnegie melon, loving what i'm doing. uh,
i mean, i've got all these computers to myself because i'm writing the os.
no one else can use them.
um,
i've got control over this os.
people come to me to check in things and whatever.
they look to me for advice on what to do. and we're getting, you know,
people are following what we're doing.
lots of companies want to use our stuff.
and i'm just having a grand old time.
and i'm almost falling into the trap of what happened to a lot of carnegie melon grad students, which is they can take six, seven, eight years to graduate.
um, and so i'm probably, let's see, it's probably 90 87 now.
so, i'm in my fourth year
and rick and i come out to the west coast for a meeting at berkeley
because we're it's berkeley unix conference
and we find out that steve jobs wants to meet with us on our trip.
um, this is probably this might be 86 actually.
um, so we we come in, we fly in my first time ever to san francisco.
fly into san francisco. rick and i are staying in a not so good hotel just off the airport.
um,
and we're
we're going to meet steve for dinner.
so, we go over to the next offices on deer creek road
and we're sitting down in the lobby waiting for steve
and
um,
so steve comes down all excited. hi guys, how you doing? and shake up
shake
shake his hand. oh, i've met you before. that's what he says to me. like, i don't
no,
you haven't met me before. yeah,
i've met you before.
like, no, you haven't met me before.
i'm like, " steve, you know, i'd know if we'd met before.
" he's like, " no, i know we've met before. " and like, " whatever.
" so, we go have dinner with some of his team
and they tell us, you know, we we had no re,
we had no understanding why they wanted to meet with us other
than we knew they were building a computer for education.
um,
and we thought they might be interested in what we're doing a little bit
and want to learn about what we're doing.
and he's like, " well, we want to put your os on our computer.
" i'm like, " what? really? are you kidding? so, he then leaves
and we still have more dinner with the other guys
and then we go off to our meeting at berkeley
and i'm thinking, " oh my god, i better finish up
because these guys want to use this stuff.
they're going to fail. i'm going to have to help them. " um,
etc.,
etc., etc.
and it's like the corporate world now needs me is the way i'm thinking.
so, i get things in order. i finish up the dissertation. and i have my
my
uh
my defense thesis defense with rick and al and dennis
and i start interviewing in the meantime
and
uh
and so you know
one thing kind of led to the other and ended up going to work for next.
when did rick go to to microsoft a little? uh
that was several years after i
oh,
he stayed.
oh, i see.
yeah,
he was at carnegie melon for several more years. did they try to recruit him as well as you?
um
rick expressed no interest in a corporate job.
i think they wanted to hire him as a consultant but he wanted to stay independent.
okay. and do you remember who in in the first dinner
um
do you remember who uh was like was like bud?
bud was there and was doing software at that at that point
in terms of bud was doing software.
yeah.
bud was doing software. bud was there
and i'm not sure who the other guys were that were there.
i mean, i could guess, but i'd probably be 50 % chance of being right in terms of who was actually there.
yeah. was like, did when did joanna show up on your radar? i don't think i ever met joanna.
really? if i did, i don't remember. was she was she gone by the time? i think so.
wow. wow. by the time you came.
yeah. i never met her that i know of.
but she was there.
wasn't she there in the early days? i don't know.
i don't think so.
am i? maybe in the very early days.
i think there some of the those retreats she shows up on those videos.
okay.
yeah. yeah. that all predated me. yeah. i may be confusing things. i got there in'88. yeah. okay. yeah.
um
was was michael holly still around? mike
yeah, mike was there.
yeah. well, he was kind of in and out. he was always in and out. yeah.
um
and were there other companies on your radar? yeah.
so,
um
obviously they're saying next is saying they want to use ros.
so obviously they're going to offer me a job if i want it, right? but i knew i had to do a little more diligence.
um
so i interviewed with microsoft, i interviewed with sun
and i think that's about it.
um
if there were other interviews, they might have just been phone calls from people who knew i was looking for a job.
and like i think apple tried to contact me, but i wasn't interested in interviewing there. yeah.
um
so those were the the three places that i considered. son was
kind of confused. i mean, i knew some of the people there
like,
you know,
james gosling was there.
we talked
and stuff like
that, but they never kind of got their act together about what they wanted me to do
or anything.
um
microsoft was very organized. they wanted to hire me. um
and nex wanted to hire me.
so, i had to decide between those two.
and if you'd gone to microsoft, would it have been
where was nt at
that point? had nt emerged in the world already? if i had gone to microsoft, nt probably would not have existed.
or would have been something different. interesting.
yeah,
because they basically hired cutler instead when i didn't go there. cutler came after i interviewed there. interesting.
and and you know,
my view of microsoft was
um
it was
it was interesting. um
you know,
it was
i had a great time talking with bill gates about technology and stuff. he was really into that
and it was non-traditional interview
where he he just wanted to know the work that i had done and the design decisions
and he was giving his inputs and stuff like that. um,
which i found very refreshing. um, i talked to steve balmer
who was a little more, you know, salesy,
right? didn't really know what i did.
just knew that other people thought they should hire me. and then i talked to
i talked to nathan
nathan mirvald who had all these visions of what was going to happen.
and i i talked to people who worked on doss
and i talked to people on os2.
and one of the things
that i learned as part of the interview process was there were kind of some waring factions
and wasn't clear if they were really committed to os2.
wasn't clear if they wanted me to go fix os2 or do something different.
a lot of these things going on and and it didn't quite gel with me.
so was this before ulen had showed up there too? was
i can't remember whether i don't remember. yeah. i don't remember.
so, it just it didn't feel
i mean next had a clear sort of path to putting your software out into the world.
was that kind of the the
the sort of if you had to
when you came down to making a decision? why i made the decision? couple things.
one is, you know, this was a chance from the technology perspective to take what i had worked on
and make it successful.
and it wasn't clear to me that that was going to be possible at microsoft.
at microsoft, it's more you're a good os guy, come help us to build oss.
okay, maybe something new or fix os2 or whatever kind of tbd.
um
there was the classic big company versus startup.
you know, it's like microsoft was a let's say one or two billion dollar market cap company.
then how big could it possibly get, right? who knew?
um
whereas next was a startup, right? it's gonna
it's going to grow from where it is. no, no question.
um
and then,
you know,
i really enjoyed both bill and steve and interviewing with them, but they were very different kinds of people.
and um
at the time
i kind of was more excited to work with someone like steve
because he had not only the technology passion but also you could see he's thinking about how to drive things into markets
and and stuff like that.
um
whereas
i love the conversation with bill
but there was very little about the markets and that and that kind of stuff.
not that it's bad.
i mean that's who he was.
yeah.
um
and and but you know of all those factors
i mean the fact that they were using my technology really made a big difference. yeah.
and then i guess you know
one last point is
and this was something easier for next to do than microsoft
you know
next being a small company
steve made it a point to personally try to recruit me. yeah. and he would
he would do the follow-up calls go over the offer letter and i just can't decide. he said
well
let me offer you this.
you know what i mean? whereas bill couldn't do that.
the company was too big for bill to do that.
and you know there there sort of legendary stories about steve walk taking people on recruiting walks.
did you guys
what was the sort of the dance with steve? did you ever like go on a walk with steve while he was
we did not do a recruiting walk
but that's because just i was in pittsburgh again and he was in paloalto. yeah.
but, you know, steve,
what steve did was somehow i think
that part of, oh, we've met before is part of the whole thing.
i don't
i don't think that was quite
i think he thought i was someone else.
um
but for example,
one of the things that he did was
when i think he identified me as someone he wanted to hire and someone that he knew.
subsequent to our first meeting in paloalto, he had had
he was on a visit at carnegie melon with again some of his team
and he
and his team took a bunch of us grad students out for dinner
and he was just being real nice to me and joking and remember
at the end of the dinner
he said send that guy the bill pointing at me and he would
just
you know
do things like that to be a little more familiar and a little more
earthy
if you will.
yeah.
um
so
uh
had had
um
by the time you joined
had
um
nex
left deer creek and gone over to redwood city. no.
so you got there while it was still at
we're still at deer creek. um
we didn't leave for
i think at least a year after that.
okay.
maybe maybe even longer. we
we launched the next product in october of 88 while we were in deer creek.
okay. and so that launch is a famous event. um
uh
what was your role in
did you develop software for the launch
uh
demo in itself?
okay. so well
there's the version in this in the jobs movie
which is not true. um
and i tried to explain the truth to aaron sorcin
but he obviously didn't listen. um
so the
i have a vivid memory of the leadup of a part of the leadup to that
which is
um
two or three days before the launch
we were working on the optical drive
and
um
so i was part of the os team
chief operating system scientist
something that gave me this fancy title as a way to entice me to go work there
smart
um
so i wasn't responsible for the optical driver. i was responsible for more the core of the os.
um,
and it was working pretty well, but the optical driver was unreliable. and um,
i remember the guy working on it, outstanding engineer,
his name is john seammons.
um,
he was, you know,
burning the midnight oil just trying to get this thing working.
and about three days before the intro, and this has got to work.
um, i'm like, " okay, i gotta roll up my sleeves and help john.
" so, i dive in with john, fresh eyes on the problem.
and it was just unreliable.
and i said, " okay, we got to do something.
we got to start building reliability tests for the file system so we can figure out
is it a driver problem? is it the file system?
" whatever.
and so, i built a very simple unix level test to read
and write files in a slightly random way and ran it and it failed immediately.
and i built in logging and stuff
so we could then figure out what was going on. we went
and we
and we tested
and and we looked at the logs. we figured out the bug.
great. we fixed it. good. we're all set to launch. let's let's take
but before we do that, let's take the testing to the next level.
and so he and i kept iterating on these test programs to the point where
um
we
we finally had a test program
which was basically issuing random file system instructions to the os completely random.
no program would ever do this just to get it to fail. and we would see these failure modes.
oh yeah, that's a bug.
and oh yeah, that's a bug
because even though it's random, it should still work, right? and so we finally got it all to work.
and we
i think the two of us worked almost continuously for 48 hours.
wow. to make that work. was it stressful? was that your
i
i don't remember it being stressful. i just remember being wow
this is so cool. it's like
i mean it's so hard.
but i mean these are the hardest kinds of bugs to find.
i mean i remember before i'd been trying to find bugs in the virtual memory system
where suddenly your memory isn't right
and that's all you know is the memory isn't right.
and this could be 5 seconds after it went bad that you discover this.
and how do you discover those bugs?
and we're working on hard problems like that, which is extremely satisfying.
but we finally got it to work. yeah.
and and i remember i learned a lesson from that, which is, you know,
all of us engineers think we can write code that works.
but what you really got to do to test your code is throw garbage at it
and then see what happens.
when you th throw things at it
that is what you expect. yes, it works.
but a lot of times developers throw things at it that you didn't expect. yeah.
but that
so that was the leadup to the to the um intro
from my perspective
just getting the basic stuff to work.
there's a lot of other stuff going on that i was still helping others with.
you know, all the demos. you were there. i assume i was.
and the demos were incredible. yeah. and they all worked. at the actual event at davies hall itself,
were you in the audience
or were you backstage? i was in the audience.
yeah. okay. now, there's a bit of legend that you can help me with. um, apocryphal.
i heard that, you know, there was an intermission.
it was such an an event.
i heard that the machine crashed during the intermission. it was rebooted and it worked
and nobody knew. do you know if that's true? that is possible.
i don't remember.
um, i believe there was a hot spare anyway.
we've always had hot spares for as long as i can remember. yeah.
yeah.
so that you could swap out.
oh, that was
it was supposed to be the luck of steve jobs
that it would happen backstage and no one would know about it.
you know, bill would always give demonstrations and it would crash during the right.
right. yeah.
it's it's possible. i don't remember.
yeah.
what was the just your going to next and working there
just sort of top level
this description about,
you know,
you came from an academic environment, all of a sudden you were thrown into a steve jobs world.
what what was the shift like? um, that's a good question.
let me think about that for a second.
so, for me, a lot of it seemed the same
because i was just always working hard, trying to make things work, right? um,
there was probably a little bit more of a feeling of being a part of a a whole team
that is doing more than just building this os.
i mean, we had people do
we have bu people building the hardware.
we had people worrying about how to sell it, how to market it. um
we had hr teams, you know,
we had this whole this whole thing. and we also had um
a different level of sort of frenzy in terms of it's actually going to work.
this is not research.
this is something people are going to pay for
and we actually have deadlines, right? so
when we announced that october 17 or something announcement, it was going to be announced
then we weren't going to change that. and so we had to work 24 by7 to make it work
at least well enough for the demo. there was a famous wall street journal story
um
which quoted a pr woman in the first paragraph.
kathy cook was an outside pr woman.
she was quoted as saying, " they're carrying them out in body bags to describe how hard you guys were working.
" do you remember that? and it created quite a stir outside the company.
i don't know what it was like inside the company.
there were no body bags. there were no beds inside. um
but i remember my personal work habit was to work as long as i could, go home
and sleep,
and then come back in and work as long as i could, no matter what the time was.
yeah.
and i remember there were many of us who would be working all night
and then we'd go to denny's at 3 : 00 a.
m. to get some food and then go back and work some more. yeah.
and then go home at 7 : 00 a. m.
8 a. m. sleep a little bit
then come back.
were you single at that point? of course.
and when you came out to the valley, where did you live initially? i
uh
i lived in mountain view. had a small apartment in mountain view. yeah.
so so it was
it was
uh
it was a hacker's existence basically. it was a hacker's existence and i loved it. yeah.
and so you came out with that title.
were you responsible for nextep? is that the right way to describe your your initial role? not initially.
initially i was responsible for the core os
which was in
well
initially
i was an engineer. okay. i was one engineer of several.
um
you know
they looked up to me because it was my code base. a lot of it was
um
but i was responsible basically for making sure
that what we had built at carnegie melon had been ported to the next computer.
it worked.
then you know
like a year later i took over the whole os group
which me meant only the compiler and a few other things
and then i ultimately took budge job.
yeah.
yeah. and architecturally
this was a 6840 6820
i can't remember.
uh
i think it was a 30
25 meghertz
and the perk had been a mini computer
or it had been a microprocessor
bas
i think the perk was
uh
custom architecture.
yeah.
so, this was your first real experience with the 68, 000 family
or oh, no.
you've been a mac programmer, so you you knew it pretty well.
i had been a mac programmer myself, but we had
never
i don't think we'd ever ported mach to the 68, 000 series. yeah.
but i was
i mean,
being a mac programmer meant i knew the instruction set.
that was probably an advantage. but i had never done os level stuff
and the mac didn't even have virtual memory in it.
yeah. so, we were working at a very different level. yeah.
and and did the
you know
steve had taken this team or a port
some version of this team through this drill before with the macintosh
um
they
he'd sort of run this drill once
well
several times before
but the
the
you know
the mac experience was this very sort of dramatic and well
doumented
was
there
did you feel like there was mac culture still in the next organization
or he built another kind of culture at that point
um
there was a little bit of matt culture
but i saw that more from the perspective of everyone who wasn't an engineer was using a mac.
so if they email
well
actually there wasn't much email back then
but they were doing desktop publishing on their macs
or whatever they did
they were doing pretty much on their macs.
only the engineers had the actual computers because they didn't quite work.
um
and so you know
you have to remember
i didn't know what the mac culture was back then anyway.
so i can't say for sure if it was
or it wasn't.
and i'm sure some things were similar, some things weren't. yeah. yeah.
and did you get involved in as as you got in on the project
and got more responsibility, did you have at any point responsibility for some of the higher levels of the stack, the app kit,
um,
interface builder, um,
next step layers
or was that?
yeah.
so, i don't remember what year it was,
but um, when i became vp of software, i had all that stuff.
yeah. and and um sort of just roughly scale
when you came
how many people were doing software
and as you sort of
how did it
how did it grow over time?
okay, so when i got there
the company was probably 70 people. um
i was employee 80some
and i assume a few people had left. um
and most of the people were in engineering
um
and they were probably roughly evenly split between hardware and software.
yeah.
exact numbers, who knows?
so, maybe 25 software, 25 hardware,
then everybody else in, you know,
finance and marketing and sales,
things like that. how big was the os team? um,
the os team was probably three or four people.
wow. yeah.
i have two very clear memories of steve giving me factory tours.
once i got a tour of the mac factory
and once i got a tour of the next factory
which was
both of them
actually were highly automated.
you know
this is 85 83 to 87
88.
did you involve yourself with the factory at all? not really.
um
we'd have meetings over there every once in a while
just you know i was part of the executive team.
um
so once a month
or so
we'd have our executive team meeting over there just to keep them connected
and so we were aware what was going on.
but i didn't work with them really. not really at all.
yeah. you
you
this was not hollywood, but this was sort of silicon valley's equivalent of
that world, but it was just intense interest at that time
sort of from when steve started
to
you know,
everybody wanted to know what was going on next.
did that affect you at all? it didn't affect me at all.
and you know,
it's probably because i was so focused on the work, right? and it dominated everything
and
um
it
just it
just,
you know,
it wasn't on my radar. now, yeah,
i mean, sometimes i'd be out at dinner and maybe i'd be with steve
and people would recognize us and ask us things that are going on or whatever,
but that was not necessarily the norm. that was just on occasion.
yeah.
so there were these kind of myths that drove silicon valley. um
um
you know
going all the way back to alan k's dynabook
um
sort of this notion
and
and you know
during the macintosh days
steve probably expressed it best when he referred to the personal computer as a bicycle for the mind
and then he was clearly doing that with next.
i mean it was clearly in line with that kind of you know tool to learn
and and do science and all of that stuff.
did did that capture you? um
i mean
were
were you sort of in that kind of worldview and yes and no.
but you know, i was an engineer, okay?
and i was like, let's i mean, i love the technology, but i'm like, let's get this to work.
and the other people can worry about these grand visions, okay? but i'm like, this is so cool.
i want to make this work. i remember the first time i got audio to work.
i had no grand vision of what was going to happen with audio
and computers, okay? but one day, the hardware guys gave me a board.
they said, " we think audio works on this board. can you make it work in the os?
so, i spent a couple days and did. i'm like, this is so cool. yeah.
and
and you know, i was always the type of person who was, okay, what's the task at hand? how do we get it done? how do we push
that envelope a little bit more? right.
and the grand vision will take care of itself.
interesting.
but then you
you moved
as you moved up and became a vice president, um
did you get
did you get involved in the strategy component of sort of where next was going as a company
much
or absolutely.
and and i would say
um
i had a chance to do that well before i became a vice president.
first of all,
we were a small company.
second of all, i had formed a good relationship with steve
and the rest of the management team early on
because of my role.
so, they didn't look at me as your run-of-the-mill engineer they hired to work on, you know,
piece of software x.
so, i always had really great access.
like i said, i was part of the executive team even though i wasn't a vp,
which is kind of unusual.
yeah.
so, i'd get to go in and listen to what was going on. and, you know,
to be honest,
in those early years, i was more in learn mode than anything else.
like, here's all these really great guys who know what they're talking about. i'm learning from them. yeah.
i have to tell you from the outside,
i always thought of you as one of the executive team.
i mean, i'm just thinking back on next.
if i think of who the key guys were next, you were
you were,
you know,
that's the way it looked from the outside.
well, and that's because i had an unusual role as an engineer.
i quickly did become a manager and a director.
and from day one, they used me externally to talk about things.
so when we would do a conference, i would be a speaker and i would talk about different things.
so, so i did have some of that role. yeah.
and then,
you know,
steve cultivated the higher education community deciduously before and then during.
did he use you in, you know,
going out outreach to the higher education community
and were you involved in that sort of dance that went on a little bit? um,
you know,
obviously computer science departments were a pretty good target for us.
and so when there'd be an interesting computer science department to visit, they would make use of me. um,
and even beyond education,
when we
when we diversified to more customers, the salesforce used me quite a bit. yeah.
and so just i'm trying to remember there were
there were bunch of interesting people who were part of the the next team
and one person who came down
um
from reed
was a physicist. i'm trying to remember
i'm blanking richard crannle. crannle did he very good friend of mine. did he work with you? so richard
so i don't know if you know
but richard died a few years ago. i do. i do.
um,
sadly,
richard was probably my best friend at next.
okay.
and and you know, so my best friends at next were were were richard and steve.
yeah.
and re this great story about richard. when i arrived at next
for my first day in paloalto in april of 88
and i flew in to san francisco. um
i think they put me up in a
they probably put me in a hotel for the night
and it was evening and i had nothing to do
so i said i'll go into the office.
so, it's like 10 o'clock, 11 o'clock at night
and i'm going into the office and i go in there and i find richard
and he was the only one there and we just hit it off
and
um
you know
from then on we were just like best friends. yeah.
and what kinds of things did he do inside next? i i always thought of him as sort of outward facing to the educational community.
did did he do design stuff too? so richard was our karajin. he would always find things wrong.
and that day, that night, i went in and met him for the very first time.
he's like, " who are you? what are you doing here? "
and i explained to him, " i'm brand new.
" he said, " oh, well, you should know everything's broken.
" and that was typical richard cranle.
and so what richard would do
is
um
he was an education ambassador. um
and so he would write educational apps. yeah.
and what he would do is he would force us to make sure everything below that worked.
so he would try to push the envelope.
and so his role from an engineering perspective was to say, " well, this doesn't work
and i need to use it.
" and he was a physicist by trade.
so he didn't always do things the way they were intended to be done.
so we'd find interesting things based on him trying to use things. um,
but then he did have a big outward role, too.
i mean, he was part of that first keynote demoing some of the apps that he had written. um
very smart guy, very interesting to be around.
so that you showed up in april of 88
and the computer was introduced in october of 88,
right? okay.
and at that point, i'm trying going back in history
now
when you launched
it was still an educational strategy and ed educational
you were
steve had found a way to carve out the space for himself where he wasn't directly competing
or you know
he said he wasn't directly competing against apple and sun and ibm, right? what did it look like?
what did it feel like inside the company in terms of
that strate market strategy? that's exactly what we thought too.
um
i mean we knew we were building a general computer, right? but we always thought of our primary market, maybe not only market, but our primary market is education.
yeah.
and are there sort of attributes of the
you know there
sort of those those little vignettes you gave of like meeting with
uh
meeting with rick or working around the clock? describe next culture.
um,
is there anything else that was sort of emblematic
of
i mean now we know google culture.
what was next culture like?
so we did have a little bit of
i mean there you
you
in retrospect
there was a bunch of us that worked in my mold
but we also had some people who were married and didn't work that way.
they worked the more nineto-five job
and there's a little bit
of
you know we didn't always get along or see eye on a lot of those things
just a little bit
but at the end we all pulled together and knew what we were doing
but you know
we believed we were on a mission and we were building
i mean this
what we built was incredible for the time
and we knew that
and we just knew we had to make it work
and
uh
we knew that we were
you know
setting the stage for everything to follow afterwards
and
and so we all knew we're on a mission
just in general
working really hard. now, it was also very stressful
because it was a lot to get done quickly
and a lot of new things that we were inventing, things that had never been done before.
it described the optical drive. you know,
no one had ever done that before
and it had some hard things
where you don't just write the optical drive, you erase it, you write it,
and then you verify it every time you write.
and that had never been done before.
and to take an existing os and make it work in that model efficiently was not trivial. yeah,
there was so much i remember when that was one of the points of skepticism about
you know there was a performance point of skepticism around optical
and what did i mean outside there you you
it was sort of show me and where
where did what did it look like inside from a sort of well
we were all worried about it too
um
no question
and but you know
when you're an engineer
you try and solve it right
and so okay
we know that writing is incred incredibly slow.
okay.
so, what are we going to do to minimize the rights and you just try and make it work?
yeah.
and in the end, it was a limitation and we put in a hard drive. yeah.
let's see. did it ever ship with the optical?
i can't remember at what point it did. it did.
it did ultimately. yeah, i think so.
yeah. yeah.
and did you was one of the tricks using cache to get around the low?
yeah.
i mean, they're all standard tricks, right? caching, having higher level software be aware of what it's doing.
did you realize that you're writing all this data? oh, no.
i didn't
i didn't need to do that.
yeah, it's things like that. do did you have much interaction? there was an early app developer, i think.
was it called lighthouse software that jonathan
um schwarz
was the lighthouse design?
lighthouse design.
that's right.
yes, lighthouse design.
i know
jonathan,
you brought them in early and and well, so i don't know.
i mean, they were in pittsburgh. they're
i think they're all carnegie bell people
and they loved the next
and they started building apps
and we took note of people building apps, especially good apps like they were building.
yeah. so, um
did you there
there was kind of a small talk like dynamic object-oriented lang language.
were you involved? did you get involved in the at the language level? was a little bit a little more so
when i became manager of the group
because i was part of the compiler.
you're talking about objective c. objective c. yeah.
um
it was basically the c language
with a little bit of small talk sprinkled in is the best way to think about it. yeah.
exists today. people use it. people still use it today for ios. yeah.
and is it it's still called objective c in yes.
yeah. yes.
yeah.
um
so one of the questions was that we had heard that at various points
c + + and even display postcript were considered for the development language of next step.
were there sort of steps along the way to so the
the language for the screen was was display postcript wasn't
that is what it was.
yeah. um
and that was also profound. yeah.
um
and and even today
on a mac or an iphone, it's basically pdf is what's going on.
it's a pdf-like thing. so postcript is still the pdf.
so that model still continues today. for the c + + issue, um
we never considered c + + as a development language for the os itself, for next step itself.
but at some point we had been so beat up
by people saying they wanted to use c + +.
we built a version of c + + we called objective c +
+
which let it coexist with objective c.
never got used very much.
it became more of a checklist item for certain customers who wanted it but it was never a mainstream language for next.
yeah.
um
at some point you ended up working with mr. stallman.
was richard in the loop
and what is it like to try to collaborate with richard stallman?
so we collaborated with richard stallman because we used
uh
his compiler gcc
and
um
so had dinner with him a few times. always an interesting experience. very smart guy, very non-traditional though.
yeah.
uh
very set in his ways.
um
and you know we were very appreciative of the work that he had done
and we wanted to be a good steward of what he had done.
working hand
inand
with him
giving back changes
we had made suggestions
and just that was
you know
we never
i never worked directly with him
but i helped to facilitate the relationship a little bit
we had some engineers who worked more closely with him and his team
is what i would say
also
you want
oh yeah
i was curious
as how did you decide to use objective c as the as the
the basis for all of the frameworks
so the decision to use objective c was done prior to me arriving at next
and the fundamental reason for it was the team wanted to use object or object-oriented programming
and there weren't a lot of choices.
so you could use small talk and never have a product that ships,
right? uh
or you could use c + + and not really have object-oriented programming. you would have object-oriented sugar syntax
and that was it.
so, objective c was the only real object-oriented programming that existed,
at least language for it.
yeah. yeah. okay.
um,
so ultimately you were able to build this hybrid of open and proprietary
which continued on into the into the apple
where you know you
you were leveraging
um
you were leveraging an an open-source community
and and you know sort of the best of both worlds in this hybrid way.
um
was that strategic? i mean did you set about to do that as a as a strategic direction?
yes
and no.
um
there was a feeling
that there were areas
that we would adding we would have just incredible added value for things
that were brand new that should be kept proprietary
and and unique.
but other areas you didn't need to do that. so,
you know,
networking,
why wouldn't you support tcp ip
and be open, right? there's no reason to have a whole new separate networking language, if you will.
and so, that was sort of the general thinking.
um, and the nature of our business was we had many things
where interoperability or reuse was more important than being proprietary
and other areas where you could do something where proprietary really wasn't going to hurt you
and it added a lot of value and had a lot of differentiation.
yeah.
very pragmatic then. it's very pragmatic. yeah. yeah.
i remember
um
sort of after you guys got os 10 up
and running, bud came to give a talk at berkeley once
and at some point
like half of the lines in the code of os 10 he said were open source.
i mean i was just struck
the number was that large. um
that does not surprise me. yeah.
and and it's because there's a very large unix core
um
that's basically these days all open source.
and actually we we open sourced our version of it as well. yeah.
um
and you
so i think you you've kind of answered
you have this practical view of open source. um
in terms of getting of shipping
next step
um
did it stay in beta after it was out in the world
when
when the next was shipping
the first cube was
so
i think the first cube we shipped had version 0. 8
which obviously was we didn't call it beta
we called it 0. 8 a um
and then we shipped a 0. 9 and then we shipped a 1. 0.
i don't remember the exact dates, but we realized that the first version we were shipping wasn't 1. 0.
yeah.
um
in brent shen schlender's book, he writes
that you wrote the music synthesis program that played during the keynote demo.
um
is there is
that is not correct.
um
i don't know if he wrote that or not,
but i know if he did, it's not correct.
correct.
um,
so what i wrote
i described a little while ago was the first test program to verify that sound actually worked.
the demo, at least one of the demos, the most interesting demo at that introduction
um
was when the computer played with the violinist
and that was done
um
from the dsp with synthesized instruments. and i did not write that.
yeah.
i worked with people that wrote that. i did not write that. yeah.
and um
i think you've
i mean
you know
if you look back at the nextstep project and and the challenges and getting it to the market initially
what
what do you remember as being
you know
the the hurdles
like hurdles that stick out in your mind
as as
um
well
so i talked about the optical drive
huge hurdle. um
most things were just good old engineering work
but the optical drive was definitely paradigm issues. um
we were
we were getting into new space
providing developer tools
um
at a
at a level never done before
and that required a certain level of ways to work with developers
which also required adoption.
and one of the challenges was, you know,
we're building a new platform and we couldn't build all the apps ourselves.
so we had to have other people who would build apps for us.
and that was a big challenge. you know, i mean, pricing, right?
and this wasn't really a software issue, but it was a hardware issue.
the the staggering cost of the hardware from a cost perspective,
and then you translate into what it what you have to charge for it, that was a huge hurdle.
yeah.
just going into the market with a new computer.
i mean, you'd be insane to do that today, right? yeah. yeah.
um,
jumping a little bit forward, there was a point where the company's strategy shifted from educational to business productivity.
what can you tell us about
that process from the from the inside? i remember how how it struck the the industry
or the
you know
the computer trade journalism industry is like a huge deal.
i know next was shifting gears. well, so i forget the exact timing, but the big deal there was
we signed a deal with businessland. i don't know if you remember that.
yeah, i do. i do.
but um
i don't know if that was in conjunction with our push into business
or sort of right along with it.
and um
they
i believe they committed to buying something like a hund00 million worth of product over some interesting period of time, maybe a year
or something.
um,
and i remember,
shortly after we did that deal, they invited me and steve to go down to some event
where ronald reagan was speaking of all people,
just,
you know,
to celebrate the fact that we had done that deal. um
and and so we were really jazzed about that
because business land was a real company that sold to businesses and they had basically produced, you know,
soft pos for $ 100 million worth of product
which is way more than we had ever sold. yeah.
so we're pretty jazzed about that.
uh
but then they went out of business. so yeah.
was that i'm trying to remember now
where that uh stood with the sort of the politics of os2
and what was going on in the broader industry.
were you were you
at some point
were you moving toward competing head-to-head with this new sort
of
there was a
there was a tren
a phase change in in the broader desktop industry as well. i remember our biggest competitor was always sun.
yeah.
we were more compared to the workstation market and um
we had
i remember
we had done some uh marketing programs specifically. uh
we did this one program
where we had two programmers, one programming with nextstep, one programming with the sun tool set side
by side on camera and the next guy obliterated the sun guy.
u
we did a little, you know, 15 20 minute video. it's probably on youtube. um
uh
and so we we really started competing at that level. yeah.
yeah.
and the the transition.
so then there came the transition to the intel hardware, moving away from 6848.
do do you remember why you chose to move away from the motorola architecture
and go with intel? well, the intel was not about using intel hardware ourselves.
it was about selling software on pcs. yeah.
uh
the thinking there being these guys building pcs can do it for zero profit margin, right?
and they're at scale and we're not.
simple as that.
yeah.
and but that that for you that that meant
then you had to take this operating system and move it to a new architecture.
how
how how hard was it to move next step?
that was our specialty. remember we had mock
which is already portable.
yeah.
so, you know, that was easy
and
and in fact we ended up porting it to the x86 to the pa risk to the power architecture to spark.
um, you know, we were turnurning them out, you know,
give us the funding or commit to go
and six months later we'd have a running.
yeah.
we
we ported to some processor that never shipped the 88k.
remember the 88k?
i do remember the 88k.
we had it running on 88k prototypes. yeah.
and the decision process inside was it was it
um
you know
did you debate inside about whether to you know to go from from one architecture to to a software base? of course.
um
do you remember who was on what side and what it was like? you know i don't remember
exactly
but obviously that kind of a decision is something that hardware people don't like. uh
and almost everybody else does just generally speaking. yeah.
yeah.
um,
and do you remember
where steve was? sometimes i know that steve has to be brought around on issues
and then he becomes a champion at a certain point.
do do you remember?
that's right.
and and usually
um,
you know,
to expand further on what you're saying, usually things have to get pretty bad before it gets brought around.
yeah.
not always,
but usually.
and i think that's what was starting to go on here, which is
i mean, this hardware business is a tough one.
not only are we not selling very much, but it's capital intensive and, you know,
risky and and still not working. yeah.
and and oh, by the way,
most people see the value in the software. yeah.
where was bud trible on on that issue
porting to intel? um, i do not remember.
and in fact, it may have been that bud had already gone to sun,
so i'm not sure.
yeah.
bud,
i mean there were,
you know,
there were people who had been so close to steve
um
who at various points left. do you remember that as being painful?
i mean, but leaving. yeah, absolutely.
yeah.
that's another one of those things i remember vividly.
for some reason, i was at home in my apartment not working. i get a phone call from steve
and he was practically in tears.
he said, " you're not going to believe this, but is leaving.
" and i said, " really? where's he going to say? you're not going to believe this.
he's going to sign.
" yeah. and he just could not believe it.
it was he's like, i don't understand how i could possibly do this. yeah.
and were you close to bud at all? did you get a view into that about what his personal
um,
i was pretty close to bud.
um, i'm sure i talked to him after this, but i don't really remember.
we talked about it was so long ago. i'm sure he gave me some good reasons about yeah.
why he was doing it, what the opportunity was, something like that, but i don't remember exactly.
do you remember?
oh, go ahead. i'm sorry. what was it like to work with bud?
i loved working with bud.
um,
you know,
bud,
one of the smartest people you'll ever meet,
very nice person. um,
always wants to do the right thing,
always, you can always have a great discussion with him. um,
never got very social with him. um, probably because he was married and i wasn't.
um,
but he was just a great guy to work for.
yeah. and did did dana leave before or after? dan
did i think dana left before? yeah. yeah. i think dana left pretty early. yeah.
yeah.
so, in terms of your career, your your your time at at nex going from engineering to management, did what was
that as as a learning experience
and sort of learning to be a manager? and it was trial
by fire.
um,
you know,
i became a manager like within a year of joining next,
i think.
wow.
um,
but we were small.
we all knew each other really well.
there wasn't much managing to do.
um, again, i'm coming from being thought of as
that benevolent dictator on the mock project, which is probably not a good management trait.
um,
and i'm sure i learned that along the way.
um
but again
as far as i was concerned
we were also heads down at that point in time
just trying to get things done. yeah.
you know
yeah
we did annual reviews
but as to standard hr practices
very little at least at that time.
so i was
you know
i was learning
trial by fire
learn what works
learn
what doesn't work.
yeah.
in terms of sort of picking a replacement for bud.
um
were there others who were in contention? do you remember any of it
how steve chose?
was it was it paul heaggerty was being considered as
well?
do you know if that was correct?
so i'm not sure who took over after, but it might have been paul
but i'm not sure. i don't remember.
okay.
but then ultimately
then ultimately i took over. yeah. yeah.
so
um
so in that period when you managed software
so what are the sort of milestones that that you accomplished?
well
so i think if you look at sort of the assume you're asking about sort of the big ticket items
things that got done.
so i mean obviously we had next steps starting with the intro making it into a real product.
i think we took it through like 3.
0 or something as a product.
we introduced some really innovative features in it like distributed objects, enterprise objects framework.
these are things that were just groundbreaking at the time.
we had it such that it could communicate with windows systems over the network through an object model.
um
we built this product called pdio, portable distributed objects, which was our distributed object technology running on any
that was part of the windows angle.
then we ported it as a whole os to all these different architectures. intel, hppa risk, um,
power architecture, um,
the 88000, um,
etc., etc.,
etc.
um,
and then we took, uh,
the higher levels of it
and turned it into openstep, which then ran on solaris
and windows, was going to run on aix at one point.
um,
that's right.
uh,
that was an andy heler deal. do you remember this? i remember the deal. i don't remember andy.
yeah.
he was the head of the of the rt business. okay. yeah. um
and then
um
so i mean these were all really great innovations through the years
and then we had this
what i thought was a revolutionary product
web objects
which was the very first server-based application service ever. ever.
what year would that have been roughly? would that have been 9495 by then?
uh
yeah,
maybe.
yeah, probably i think so.
the s1 says it shipped in 96.
okay.
so, a little bit later.
that's when it first could be somewhere in that range.
yeah. yeah. we would have been working on it before that.
so, maybe 95ish.
so, you know, we we haven't asked you about this, but you know, the web was built on next.
how much of it was
i mean, from being inside next, how much did you have a early sense
that the web was going to be a worldchanging architecture?
so i think we got that not because of the client being on nex,
but because we built web objects.
yeah.
okay.
and the client being on x was kind of cool, but all you had was static websites, which is interesting for researchers
and a few things like that.
but
when we built this first web server
and we started thinking about all the things that could now be done, you know,
we built demos of a car selector where you pick models and options and colors
and it's changing in real time. you know, you have to refresh the page back then, but it changes.
and we built the first system that ever tied into saber for booking tickets.
i mean, who would have ever thought?
and so, we just knew then that we had something. yeah. so just
and and yet next you know
you could
you could almost see a
you know a business strategy based on that insight
and yet you weren't able to to sort of take it to the to the scale
that the web became.
well, that's because we got bought by apple. yeah. right. and so i think
um you know, if we hadn't got bought by apple,
web objects would have become a huge business
because we know how big these web services businesses are today. and it could have been a very
very large business.
yeah.
and i don't see any reason why it wouldn't because we had a huge head start on on everybody.
you can't even
you can't even say head start on the competition
because there was no competition.
there's maybe one other guy out there, cold fusion, i think it was,
that was even doing anything that got bought
by adobe.
yeah. yeah. that's interesting. um,
who sort of in terms of that openstep licensing decision, do you remember who's how that came about
inside next was for ibm? uh,
no.
i was thinking about sun.
oh, openstep on solaris and openstep on solaris.
windows and windows
and well, so windows wasn't a licensing situation.
that was us just having a product to sell with solaris.
i'm trying to remember how far that got. um,
i was told that the source code for the app kit was actually licensed to sun. it was
and we sent some engineers over to help them port it.
i don't know that they ever shipped it. um, it was we
we probably had things in place that made it too hard
like it had to be done in a clean room so
that anyone from sun working on it couldn't work on other sun projects
or talk to them.
all these requirements
and maybe that had a little bit to do with slowing it down.
we had some next employees on site
and i think you know it's probably one of those things
where sun probably had some antibodies that didn't want it to succeed anyway.
that wouldn't surprise me. most companies of that size have that kind of a problem. yeah.
but it just it just never got out. and and
um
a little bit more about web objects
you know
is there more of a backstory
sort of what you know
what were the sort of threads coming into web objects or what drove it
or you know
well
i remember
so i know i was running
i was running the software group at the time one of the guys
and engineers came to me and said got this idea
we can have a server that you send info to and it does something and then sends html back
i'm like
what do you mean
and he showed me a little demo of a very simple script like that's pretty cool.
we can do something with that.
so i authorized him and a couple other guys to go spend some resources on it. said okay
go build this and come back and then show them when you've got something a little more real.
and i mean it's one of those things where the first time you see that demo
it's like
of course this is the way it should be. yeah.
oh
and web objects was built on top of enterprise objects framework.
um
i would say it a little bit differently. web objects was built on the side of enterprise objects framework.
so
uh
web objects didn't require enterprise objects framework. eof
is what we called it, but it benefited from it if you had a data source.
so you would use eof to access a database.
didn't have to, but it was the easiest way to do it. yeah.
and h
how did how did the eof project come about? the eof project came about much earlier. uh
its first instantiation was something we called dbkit, database kit. uh
we had kits for everything and we knew accessing databases was important
and so we built a kit that let you access databases
and then we discovered what people liked and didn't like about it and redid it as eof.
yeah.
okay.
um
i'd forgotten this
an attempted um
next ipo.
do you
yes.
when did that
i'm totally lost in history. so my history
so
um
attempted in the form
it wasn't actually attempted in that
there was a registration
but there was an s1 that was 95 % done.
i've donated it the an original copy to the museum. okay. um
and
uh
we were working on it. i i think the draft is dated november of 96. uh
which was the same time we began discussions with apple. ah
okay.
so apple basically preempted it. yeah. okay. so yeah. um
and at that point
um
talk a little bit about java and was there a next java strategy
and where did java fit in the in the puzzle? uh
there was no real next java strategy at the time.
java came later on mostly for compatibility reasons. yeah. yeah.
actually, so blaine gar told me
that he had actually um created the java bridge for web objects while still at next.
is that correct? that's entirely possible. yeah. i don't
i don't remember the exact details on those dates. okay. yeah.