i'm grant seever
uh
triced
the computer history museum here with dave cutler in his living room in belleview on a beautiful seattle day
uh
nice weather for a change
the winter may be ending
uh
toh
discuss with dave
his long career in the computer industry
and
um
so we'll
uh
we'll begin
so
uh
we were talking about
before this
your entry into computers
but let's roll back a bit into early childhood and living in michigan and
and
uh
being near the i guess oldsmobile factory and lancing
so tell us a little bit about
uh
your early days and getting high school
and so on
well
i was
um
i grew up in dwit michigan
uh
which is about 10 miles south of or i'm sorry north of lancing
where oos mobile is at
i went to dt high school
um
i was a um
primarily an athlete
not a student
although i had pretty good grades at dt
i was a 16l uh athlete
i played uh
football basketball baseball and ran track
um
and
uh
i'm a michigan state fan
michigan state's was right there in east lancing
so i grew up close to east lancing in michigan state
um
early on
i
um
was very interested in model airplanes and built a lot of model airplanes and wanted to be a pilot
when i grew up
but somehow that just went by the way
and later on i discovered i had motion sickness problems anyway
so that wasn't going to make it
um
so that's pretty much my early
so the model airplanes kind of k
kindled a technical interest in in aviation and flying and and how that worked
uh
well
i
i don't know how i got into model airplanes
there was a local shop that
um
uh
was like a hobby shop that sold model airplanes and i got interested in building them
and then
of course
you know
you keep
you build bigger ones and bigger ones and you try to build powered ones and
and i built the powered ones and and i mostly crashed them
so i don't know if it really fostered a technical interest
but um certainly was something that i was interested in for quite a while
but then kind of sports took over in high school and um
i became more interested in sports
so the sports led to an opportunity to go to do at college
uh
all of at college
i'm sorry
all of at college and u
uh
athletics were a big part of making that possible
weren't they
um
i
in fact i went to al college
um
they offered me
pretty much a full ride
i had an academic scholarship and i had uh scholarships
for
basketball
baseball and football
and i would probably not have went to college if i hadn't had a full ride
um
because i we couldn't afford it and i had applied a couple other places
i i really wanted to go to central michigan and um
they didn't accept me
um
and the the thing at olette worked out really well was close to home
and that's where i ended up and how did you decide on the course program
that you take all of it
uh
when i got there at allette
i didn't really know
um
i think
like most students
what i really wanted to
uh
study and
um
i
you
know
i
i don't know why i i decided on math
other than it was
it was a a very interesting challenging thing
and then after i got in decided math was my major
then it was natural for me to say
well
i ought to have a lot of physics
so i took a lot of physics and i really enjoyed math and physics
um
i didn't enjoy some of the other things
olette is a liberal arts school
so there was a lot of liberal arts requirements
um
it's also a religiously affiliated school
although really not tightly religiously affiliated
but there was a lot of stuff i had to take that was religious related
um
but i sort of gravitated towards the math and the physics
and
uh
it worked out
well
great
so that that you know you're
you're progressing through college and thinking about what's next
what where where the career might lead
where you might go to work
uh
how did that prog any jobs during college
by the way
uh
did i have any jobs during college
the answerers
no
i
i had
um
i was so busy playing sports and um
later on
i
you know
the first
the first two years of college
i played mostly sports and studied just enough to get by and keep my academic scholarship
and then the last two years
i really you might say applied myself and
uh
try to um
be a good student
what happened to me was
um
within a span of 18 months
i had my right knee operated on and they pulled out the medial miniscus
i broke my left leg
and then i had my left leg operated on and they pulled out the medial miniscus there
so i was pretty much done with sports at the end of two years
and during those two years
i think that i mainly thought about that
that
you know
i never thought that it was
it was really going to end that i was going to be
you know
i just thinking about
well
i'm just going to be playing sports forever
and then
after two years
it's sort of like
well
i'm not going to be playing sports forever
what do i really want to do
and so i'm really not sure what i really want to do
but i think i really like math and i like physics and i'm a uh
hands-on kind of person that likes to build things
so i really think that i would like to have some kind of an engineering job somewhere
so i was sort of aiming at
um
an engineering job
not going to an engineering school in
uh
a time era where it was possible that such a thing could happen
today
that would probably be kind of like
uh
pretty remote that somebody could do that
i mean if you had a math degree
you probably wouldn't step into a mechanical engineering job or something like that
um
of course
you could
you could step into a computer engineering job
computer engineers
um
a lot of different disciplines make good computer engineers
so
anyway
my
my goal
um
in the last few years was to finish my degree and find an engineering job
and and how did that go
i mean you
did you start interviewing companies
companies come to the campus
or
uh
in those days
um
the companies didn't come to the campuses
you
we're talking 1965 and uh
at least they didn't come to our campus and and i i just mainly applied to um
a lot of different companies
i applied to
uh
lock heat and and the aerospace companies
and i applied to general motors
and i
you know
i applied to dupont
uh
i don't know how i happened to apply to dupont
i i saw a ad somewhere probably or something
and
um
sort of waited for people to come back
and you know
say
hey
we want to interview you
it turned out that i
i ended up actually having three solid job offers
one was from chrysler in a soft trim plant
uh
which was um door panels and soft soft trim in a
in an automobile is basically the inside and i would be a
uh
they
the job
there was a time and studies
kind of operations research
kind of job
um
in a town that wasn't too far from where i lived
i had a a a firm offer from os mobile to work in their
uh
computer accounting department
you know
i had an offer from dupont to work there in a job that was supposedly engineering job
so i sort of decided i didn't want to work for o mobile
because i didn't want an accounting job
um
there was
no
you know
i didn't know anything about computer science at that time
and i computers were around and people used them for records keeping and accounting kind of things
and of course there were people at unity
i ities
um
that were using them for other things
but mostly when you talked about computers
the general public knowledge about computers was accounting and records keeping
and that's mostly what the ibm machines were was recordkeeping and accounting
so i decided i didn't want to work there either
and so i decided to to
uh
go to wilmington delaware and take the job with dupont
and was that job
what you expected
uh
was the job
what i expected
no
it was a
it was a life lesson and interviewing
and um
that when you interview and you decide you'd like to go to work for a company
you really really should pin them down about what you're going to be doing when you get there
because if you don't
you may not be doing that
and i thought i was going into an engineering job a little bit
um
undefined
but i ended up when i got there
uh
with a job that was a tech writer
writing
um
standard test methods for dupont elastomeric materials division
which were basically
uh
methods on how you stretch and pull and bounce
um
synthetic rubber
that's pretty far from computers
what
uh
what was the first step into computers
my first step into computing was
uh
with a group at the same lab
i was at
which was a sales service lab
which helped
uh
dupont
customers apply dupont prod products to their products
uh
dupont basically made um raw materials for other people to use in developing a project or product
for instance
uh
the elastomeric materials division made neoprene
and neoprene went into a lot of uh things like wet suits
and even went into tires for a long time
um
so there was another group there
which was a math
and sta group
and i'd interviewed with them and they were interested in me and after about a year here
they asked if i could
um be lent to that group for a for a
a short amount of time to develop
um
a
a model of a phone process for scott paper company
go
okay
so we were talking about
uh
a pham making process at dupont and some challenges in that
that led to a computing
so dupont was trying to help scott paper company with a new process that they had developed
uh
to make foam for gar
the garment industry
and
uh
the
the guy at the uh lab
dupont lab
that was in the
the
um manager of the math
and stat group wanted to build a model to help them schedule the production on this new machine
and so i
they asked if i could do that model
and i said
yeah
i do that because i was so bored to tear
trying to write these test methods that nobody seemed to like what i was writing
so they sent me off to uh school with ibm to to learn a language called gpss
gpss 3 was general general system simulator 3
general gpss
general purpose system simulator
general purpose system simulator 3
which was i their third
um
a
their third version of this
gpss is a language that's a a
um
an event driven block oriented language
where
uh
you have a number of of different uh blocks
or you could look at them as functions that perform a specific kind of thing like um
create
transaction was a block so you could create transactions into the
um
the system that you're trying to simulate these
all these all operated in parallel
too
right
it was a parallel event language
if i remember
right
yes
it is
i'm sorry
it is the language
uh
um
tried to simulate a
a realtime um process
a realtime um system and the
the
everything was running in parallel
but there was no
there was no
um need for synchronization
so you were kind of removed from the synchronization aspect of building this model
and i end up building a fairly large model and partway through the building of the model
i got really interested in in more about how the computer worked than how the the model worked
so i began to
uh
really dig in a lot about the computer architecture
the machine i was running on
the machine that we ran this model on was an ibm um
yeah
it's a 44
maybe
anyway
it was a
it was the precursor to the 7094
well
so maybe it was a 7
it was a 7044
that's what it was
yeah
it was a 36 bit machine
and um
this
this is
uh
the time that i
i really learned how fallible humans are
and
and learned a lot of humility about programming and the fact that computers only do exactly what you say
and not what you mean
and i i went up to the ibm data center
we had to go up to philadelphia to go to the imm ibm data center
and with my deck of 2000 cards with all kinds of time free time
this time
um
scheduled with the ibm representative and my boss and everything
and we're jolly going up there
and we're going to run this model
and we get there
and we spend all the time trying to take the the syntax er out of the program
and we we never got them out the first day
so that was a really humiliating experience
so the so the gpss project finally worked
and you delivered some weit
the gps
the gps project or gpss project
uh
ran for i think about a year
and
uh
we had somebody from scott paper assigned to work with me that actually was a
was a somebody similar to me
very little experience and a young guy
and he and i would go up to the data center and run this model and we would
we would feed information into it and try to get results out
and we
what we're trying to do was we were trying to figure out how
or what the best um schedule was for scheduling a
a
a number of different colors
and textures of foam on this machine to get the best productivity out out of the machine and we
you know
eventually they
we
we got the model to work and we said
okay
you know
give us a question to ask the model and they came up with a question about scheduling
and we ran that and we had
you know
a big presentation
and
uh
we handed over the model to them and said okay
here's the model
you know
all you have to do is go to the ibm data center
run this
and you have a guy that can run this
and i really don't know what they did after that
i suspect they did very little with it
but it was sort of a
um
a lot of it was public relations on dupont
having a a vested interest in seeing
that scott paper company had the best support they could possibly get to run their phone process
so this initial 4a into computers then leads to digging deeper into how computers really work
and how operating systems really work
so after after this project
uh
i sort of
you know
got more interested in computing
and decided that i would really like to stay in the math and stat group
so i stayed in the math and stat group and and worked on various things
we had a 1108
well
it was 11 : 07 to start with univac machine at the at the experimental station
which was
i don't know
20 miles away and there was a shuttle that ran back and forth every day and we could submit
uh programs to run on that computer and get the results back
so i started doing some of that stuff for the math and stat group
and i also got involved with um with procuring a
a cdc 1700
which is a 16-bit machine to automate the
um
the instron
machines
which was a tensil
that's a tensil
strength testing machine
um
for the lab
and so i got pretty interested in that
um
and this all lasted
i would say maybe about two years
and then i started to think about
i really wanted to be somewhere where i was working more on computing computers
uh
rather than working on computers as a tool to solve other problems
so i succeeded in negotiating a transfer to the engineering department
a dupont
which had lots of computing capability and there they're the ones had the 1107
which they upgraded
the 1108 and uh
i joined the online systems group there
so the
the
uh
the 1108 uh and 1107 had a product called exec
which
uh
was kind of notoriously flaky
well
the okay
so the
on
what what did i do in the online systems group
um
basically i was trying to help um
the engineering service division
which was part with the online system group within was trying to help
uh
the operating departments
the operating plants within the elastomer department
um
actually with the engineering department was a whole company
so there was 13 operating departments
so they're trying to help them with their computer
uh
process control needs within the company
but there were
there was a lot of downtime
because we were project oriented and we're trying to go out and sell our services to somebody
so there was a lot of time when there wasn't much to do
so i sort of had got interested in the 1107 1108
and i went to the system programming group
and asked them if there was anything i could do for them and they said
well
yeah
i could probably help them figure out why
exec 2
which was the operating system
the 1108 was crashing so often
so they said what we want you to do is figure this out
and every time this the 1108 crashes
we take a dump and a dump is about
um
well
four four inches of fanfold paper
um
which is a
i think octal dump and um
we want you to figure out why or what's wrong with the system
so at times i would have a stack of these dumps that was 6 feet high in my office
and looking
you know
trying to figure out what the pattern was for this and
and i i found
um
several problems that were our fault
our fault being dupons
because we made
uh
i would say about 2, 000 lines of modifications to exec two
um
but i never really did really figure out what was really wrong
and i guess an interesting side story is that later on
when i was working at um
at microsoft in the early 80 or the late
i guess the early 90s
somebody from the university of washington in st louis did a study on the timing of the 1108
and and came to the conclusion that it would go metastable every four hours
because of the synchronizers in the system
didn't synchronize all the clocks properly
so i guess that was the real answer to why it was so flaky
so this is kind of immersion by fire into what an operating system is
uh
it is it
and i
you know
i spent a lot of time on the i'm
i
i should say
let me say
um
this was trial by fire
i was at the end of trying to figure out why something didn't work
which made me figure out why how it worked all right
so i had to figure out how it worked
to find out why it didn't work
and i'd be in these dumps and you know i'd trace back in the dump
you know
maybe a thousand instructions
and then the
the trail would just poof
it's gone like it's just gone
so eventually they
they got to the point
where they trusted me enough
that that i actually actually became one of the main people that maintained the system
and made improvements to it
what we thought were improvements
and put in um dupont specific changes to to streamline the operation of the 1108
so this
this is now
i know something about operating systems and i want to take my career further in that direction
um operating systems really interested me
and you know
i don't know why i decided that boy
that was the way i wanted to go
but it was really the way i wanted to go
and maybe i didn't know it exactly at that point
but but i sure
some of the most satisfying time i had was on the 11 : 08
um
and then i
i
the online system
part of it actually kicked in at one point or a couple points
where we did get some big things to do
we got a a big job to to work on at the u experimental station
which was dupont's main research center
which is a fairly big site
it was 120 acres and all 13 operating departments had um offices there
um
so they decided that they would like to automate the analysis of um
some of their instrumentation instrument data
and we proposed a dual pdp10 system to do that
we spent
i don't know
maybe six months with various other vendors
ibm being a vendor
uh
sds
if you remember
sds scientific data systems being a vendor
that we looked at the sigma 5 um and we decided the pdp10 was the best alternative
so we we built or we bought a pdp10 a dual pdp10 system with shared memory
uh
special
built by computer
special systems at dupon or not dupon
uh
digital and um
then we wrote one of the
we wrote an operating system for one of them
which was really the front end
um
and it brought in all the data
and then when the data was complete
it submitted it through the shared memory directly to the tops 10 system
which then did the analysis of programs written in fortran and then we shipped the the uh results back
so i got quite a bit of experience on uh deck
pp10s
um
became pretty knowledgeable about p
uh
the
the top stand went to digital
to a school on top stand
um
which was run by dave plumber
which was u digital's number one
uh guy about
uh
running courses on um
the tops 10
so after that
i came back
uh to the engineering department
and they gave me another job that was on deck equipment
which was a pdp11 uh
gauge control system for cronar film
which was used in magnetic tape
and this system was
uh
a pdp 1120
and at that time there was no suitable operating system for from digital
not digital
yeah
digital
no suitable operating system from digital
that would actually do this
we were going to do this on a very small pb11
i think it probably only had 8k of memory
um
so i was given the the task of developing the
the little runtime
the little real-time runtime system
to to to
uh
do the
the cronar gauge control system
um
so
when i finished that
i sort of decided that maybe it was time for me to to move on
and and think about something else
um
in fact
what i was thinking about was i'd move from from using computers to solve problems
to actually working on computers themselves
but with not within a computer company
and i thought
well
if i really want to max maximize my value to a company
and i want to be in the operating system business
i ought to go to a company that builds computers
so i arranged an interview with digital in um
mater massachusetts
and lo and behold
they hired me
so off the digital
i went
uh
just backtrack
a little bit here
what did you
what did you think of dupont in the year you were there for six years and an interesting culture
what was i
i was at dupont for seven years and
uh
the culture at dupont was very
um
kind of like really foreign to me
because it was very
it was an old company dupont was founded
i think in the mid 1800s
um
they
they supplied um
black powder during the civil war
um
that's how they got their start was black powder
a very bureaucratic
company
um
very regimented
you didn't tend to do things like go talk to your boss's boss
um
so it was
you know
i would
i had a good time at dupont and it was great for my career
but
um
i didn't feel as comfortable there as i actually ended up feeling it at deck
which was a very different kind of company
so did you
did you have a sense of what the deck culture was like
when you decided it was time to move to there
uh
when i went to deck
i had absolutely no idea what the culture was
other than the fact that i had went to the pdp10 programming course
so i was
um
a little bit acclimated to the
the
uh
the facilities that we're all
the digital
was in a mill and the mill was old
it led back to the mid 1800s also
uh
but not not really anything about the culture
i i
you know
and i i never really thought about that
um
i think i thought more about the opportunity than i did about
you know
was the culture going to be the same or different
if the culture had been the same as it was at dupon
i still would have went because the col or the opportunity was better
so talk a little bit about the getting started at deck
you know who
who was your first boss and what was the direction of the
the task at hand
my first job
well
let's let's back up a little bit about what i was hired for at digital
this is a kind of like
maybe another instance of um
not knowing exactly what you'd end up doing
although i really had this one tied down and i was going to work on something called os 45
and os 45 was a dream of dave stones
who was the head of programming at at digital
and the 45 had some special solid state memory that you could buy
that was 300 nond memory
and this is in 1971
and the pdp10 was
at that time
i think the best pd
well
the pdp10 was a a a above microsc machine
so this was
this was a very fast machine
and dave stone had this vision that we were going to recreate tops 10 on the 45 and um
we were also going to incorporate realtime system pro or realtime capabilities
and batch capabilities in addition to the time sharing
and there was a group of people that was assembled
that was probably about eight people
and um
the leader and of the group
and my initial boss was um
peter van rokin
peter came from rca and he was responsible for the development of vmos vos
which was the virtual memory operating system that ran on the rca ibm compatible machines
and so i came to digital and i spent probably the first two or three months
um
thinking about all this stuff
and the group was thinking about all this stuff
and then all of a sudden
um
we weren't really making a lot of progress on this
because there was one little small problem
that dave stone hadn't really considered as much as he really should have
and that was that the address space the pdp1 was 65k bytes and 65k
bytes
uh
just wasn't going to cut it for an address space
and the memory management capabilities weren't that great either
uh
so we had an awful hard time really getting started
and getting up to speed on what we were going to really do with this os
so there was another project
that was going on over in the industrial products group develop a a uh process control system for uh
or process control os for the pdp11
it was called rsx1 c
and they had been working on that for a couple years
and it was going nowhere and they asked me if i would go work on that
and i said
well
yeah
sure
i guess i will go work on that
um
you know
we're not doing much on this other project
so the first project i worked on really as far as real work was the rsx1 c system
and the the rsx1 series
uh
ended up cdm or something like that
if our my recollection is correct
rx11 c was the kind of like the first in the series of the rsx systems
which were primarily sponsored by the industrial products group but were also
uh
sponsored by the laboratory data products group
also because they were in the real-time business and um
rs 61c
was
uh
really
um
kind of like
was a just a coreon
uh
system that supported a few peripherals
um addd converters
um
um terminal interfaces
that was about it
and so there was a real need for some more functional systems
and
and as we filled out the pdp11 line
um
course
the 45 was a pretty big machine
but we filled it out with a lot of other ones to the
the 1140 and 45
well
yeah
the 45
the 1170
um
there was um
a need for some more machines or more operating system capability
that supported a more rich programming and and capability
and so there were several rsx systems
there was rsx1 c
there was rsx1 b
which maybe that that one may have never
um
had any body really know much about it
but it was basically rs rsx1 c that could load doss 11 files off of the dis
so it was sort of like we can store programs on the dis and run them
but it's still a coreon system
and then rsx1 m and rsx1 d
um
the order in which we did these was rsx1 c was done first and then b
and when i did b
i said i will do b
but i want you to te
promise me that i don't have to work on this again
and they said okay
so at about that same time
rsx 11d was starting up
which was a an equivalent of rsx uh 15
which is the 18-bit real-time system that digital sold
and so i was um assigned to work on that
and there was a fellow named hank cree
which was the main designer of that
because he worked on the r615 and i agreed to do
uh
the overlay linker for it
so my involvement when rs r 611d was the overlay linker and when we finished that
um
that came out a little bit larger than we hoped
and a little bit slower
than we'hoped so i had had had this idea of about building a system with a really different architecture
the r 611d had an architecture where basically everything ran as a process
and doing that meant the drivers ran as processes
which meant that there was an ipc
an interprocess communication mechanism had to exist between the program that wanted the service of a driver
and the driver
which wasn't really
uh
conducive to the real-time performance we wanted to have
so i had this other idea of building a system that was a lot different
in fact
it's mostly like
um
the other systems that we built
or i've been involved with
um
so i i proposed building r611 m
and the industrial products group got pretty excited about it
and they gave me i guess about eight people to work on that
and we completed that in about a year and a half or two years
and that became the main real-time system for pdp 11s because it would run on all the pdp 11s
the ones that had memory management system
uh
memory management units
and the ones that didn't in fact it ran on
it ran on systems from 32k bytes up to two megabytes
um
a big span
so this is the first time that you're running a major software project
right
a major operating system development project
um
was this the first time that i was running a major project
probably you would consider that to be the first time of a major project
because this was something that we're actually going to sell
we're going to sell rsx 11m
we're going to have customers
we're going to have support issues
and so there's all of that and we're
we're going to have documentation to do
um
the pdp10 system was probably
not quite as big a project
but but i was the lead guy there
too
very inexperienced
um
i don't know how dupon ever had the faith they had in me to do that
but um
they did did
and i'm thankful they did
so
rs 611m was really the first
the first time that i did a project
um
and so i developed around r611 a lot of things about
you know i was
how are we going to do this
and
uh
what
are we going to do
and what do we have to do
and so you know
one of the first things i wanted to know is what is the scope of work
what are we going to do
uh
you can't just just say we're going to do an operating system
we ought to know
well
what capabilities it's going to have
what are its constraints
one of the constraints it had was it had to be subset compatible with r 611d
so it wasn't a blank sheet of paper where we could just go off and do a new system
it was
well
it has to be subset compatible
but it's it's source
level compatible
not binary compatible
so that was a big
um
a big caveat
because binary compatibility is much more hard or much harder to achieve
so
r 611m was really my first
um
real operating system
from scratch
i think it took about two years
um
it was delivered with
what i think was pretty good quality for the tools and everything we had at that time
um
my philosophy about quality was quality was number one
it's still my first thing is quality
number one
so the
the size is the gold rubber stamp
uh
played into that
or
um
the
the one of the big constraints with r611 m was
or one of the big problems with r611 d was it required so much memory
so with r611 m
we wanted to build a much smaller system
and
and i kind of figured out right off the bat
that the only way to do that was we give everybody a budget
so everybody had a budget about how much memory they could use
and you know
if somebody
so that was their target
so if somebody came back and said i can't possibly do that
and you know whatever the budget was
then we'd rethink that
but um
generally everybody meant their budget
and so to kind of reinforce that
every i had this rubber stamp made
that says size is the goal
and everything was stamped with size is the goal
in those days there was no email
so there was no electronic exchange of communication
so all communication was through memos
and every memo was stamped with size is the goal
size is the goal
so we ended up with
you know
in a 32k byte system
there was 16k bytes for the operating system
and 16k bytes for whatever the the user environment was or the application environment
there wasn't really user mode and there was user mode and kernel mode
but these were dedicated systems
you know it wasn't
it wasn't a system where
um
there were a lot of people going to use this in a general way it was like this system is dedicated to controlling something in a real-time way
and and whoever bought the system would write the software that would control their process
now this is
uh
where the first dave cutler kernel
the dck shows up
you go off and code a big part of the operating system yourself
uh
well
all the stuff that i worked on
i did a lot of it myself
i
i did
um
going back to pdb1 i did a lot of that myself
in fact
everything that i've done throughout my career
um
i've always been a very hands-on person
i can't just stand back and say
you know
this is what we're going to build
you guys go off and write the specs
um
and i'm going to manage you
i sort of become part of the team
and i look at myself as more a leader than a manager
and i want to lead the people to build the product
and that means i'm a part of that
and and
um
there's no job that i can't that i won't do
i like to have
i have this little saying
that the successful people of the world are the people that do the things that the unsuccessful ones won't
so i've always been this person that you know i i will build the system
i will fix the bugs
i will fix other people's bugs
i will fix bug
uh
bill breaks
it's all in part of of um of getting the job done
so
uh
the 11s running out of gas deck decides it's time to build a 32-bit computer
they're behind sds and seal and others in 32 bits
and a new operating system is needed and vms starts off
uh
about
um
i think it was 1975
digital
um realized that they needed to build a 32-bit computer
and so being a part of rs 61m and the 11 world
i
i kind of got um i got involved in that
we had several architecture groups
several levels of architecture group
there was
we decided to call this vax
and vax was a code name
which stood for virtual address extension
because the pdp11 had such a small virtual address space
um
and gordon bell was the the person that was behind this
it was his vision that we should build this computer
and vax a was the hardware architecture group and vax b was sort of a review group
and then i think there was another one called vxi
which was kind of like the rest of the company
and i was like a formal member of vax b
but an informal member of vax a
also
so i spent a lot of time on the vax
a
uh
group
um
discussing the computer and whatever
and we
bill strucker was involved in this in gordon bell
this is my first real involvement
gordon
um
he was definitely at the company all the time i was there
but this is the first time i was really involved with him and we would meet
um
almost every day and talk about this computer and the instruction set and what we should do
and one of the biggest goals of of vax was to be able to encode a program in the same amount of memory
that the pdb1 could encode it
so that sort of dictated it a a instruction set that was pretty dense
um
the other thing is
we definitely wanted to
uh
increase the virtual address space by quite a bit
and building a 32-bit computer would allow us to do that
and at that time
like going from 16 to 32 was like man
how could we ever run out of 32 bits of address space and we'll later on
we'll skip forward and we'll figure out why we did run out of 32 bits
uh
so the vax
um
the vax a and the architecture group
basically were
were
uh
defining the architecture
and there were
there were other software people involved
uh
there were some people from the pdp10 group that were involved
mainly peter conlan
and we hired a fellow from um zerox
who had worked at sds
who had worked on a system called cp5
which was
uh
um
one of the systems that ran on the sigma 5
it was the operating system of the sigma 5
his name was dick husett
this is dick
uh
was involved with vx a and the other person was involved with peter litman
you know there were some other people
but we basically developed the architecture and then the company said well
let's build it
and and so we sort of said
well
how long do you want this to be
and they said
well
two years seem reasonable
he said
oh my lord
we can never build this in two years
this is too complicated of an architecture to build in two years
so we had
uh
this off-site one week
come to jesus meeting about what we would do to the architecture to make this system buildable in two years
and that i think that was called the blue ribbon committee
and there was three software people and three software implementers and three hardware implementers plus some of the architects
and we hammered out the the final vax architecture
uh
which reduced the um
the complexity of the
the
the instruction set architecture quite a bit
i i suspect that people would still say that the instruction said architecture was overly complicated
but it was really complicated before that
and
and the other thing
that happened was the memory management was so complicated
that the only person that could actually explain it was richie larry
and everybody else was sort of like
yeah
that seems like it might work
but we're not really sure
and so we really simplified the memory management architecture so
that the hardware architects thought that they could build it efficiently
and the software people thought that we could build an operating system for it
and one of the the decisions we made with vax
in fact
we made two
a couple of decisions with va
that
that limited the life of vax one was the the encoding of the um instruction stream to be be equivalent to the pb1
which caused it a extremely difficult to um implement hardware system that was mainly in hardware
and not mainly in micro code
so the vaac instruction set mostly was executed in micr code and not in hardware
because it was so hard to to decode
and the other thing that was u kind of a mistake
a long-term mistake was the page size being 512 bytes versus something more reason able
like 1k bytes or 4k bytes
would have been a much better um solution
however
you know
we looked at it and the marketing people wanted wanted
they wanted to sell vac systems that were the size of pdp11 systems in memory
so they wanted to sell a system that was 128k bytes
well
the most complicated uh instruction in the vax architecture was adpack
six
that was an ad packed instruction decimal instruction with six operands that could touch 40 pages
so it became
if it has to touch 40 pages and you only have 128k bytes
then you don't want to get into a live loock situation
where the what's going on in the system is such
that you can never get all the pages in to to actually execute instruction
so we settled on the 512 byte instruction set
um
so after the architecture was kind of signed off on and we decided we really want to build it
we went through the blue ribbon committee
uh
published the final architectural spec
then we put together the software group
and we put together the hardware group to build the hardware and to build the software
and
um
i was the technical lead of the software group
and then we spent
we went off and spent
um
i would say six months
uh
trying to think about and understand and um
how to build the system
because we were
we were death afraid of building a paging system
there wasn't a lot of experience on paging systems in those days
the pdp10 did not have paging
it had swapping
um
bbnn
had built a modification to the pdp10 which had paging
but you know the sort of the the
the scuttle butt was
it didn't run real well
multic was a paging system and multic did not run well
i'm not sure that multics would run well on today's hardware
uh
it was a great system
it
it spawned a lot of creative ideas
but it was basically very slow
anybody that ran on that system
definitely was not concerned about productivity
so we spent a long time figuring out how we would build this system
so we thought we would have good performance
um
we would be able to build it in a couple years and um
we would have the quality that we wanted to have
and so after six months we we
we
um
authored a document called the i think the starlet um design and project plan
well
a scarlet project plan and from that we started out and we implemented
um
we implement
we built
we implemented
or well
see
we developed vms mainly on r 611m and um rsx1 m had a little bit
by that time it had a little bit of time sharing capability
so there was multi-use and we had a large um 1170
probably two two megabytes of memory on it
um
two megabytes
so we developed mainly on on r611 m
but then we ran it on a simulator
the the uh group that actually built the vax 11
uh
750 was the group that was assigned to build the
the emulator for the for vx
and we actually had an emulator run on
which was a hardware emulator
so we had
we didn't run on a simulator
we ran on emulator and um
uh
we developed it
i got it running there
and then the
when the hardware
the breadboard for the 1170 uh was available
we took the what we had and we went up stairs and um
it pretty
much ran it
uh
booted up and
at least we got to the point where i didn't crash
so
um
that's kind of how how we started
and then
from then on we they built a prototype
um
i think it was proto 4
and that was our develop machine
and everybody ran on the develop machine and we ran what we built
and that was the
this is the first instance of the dog food thing
mhm
where you run on what you're developing
and that gives you a big incentive to fix whatever's wrong
so we would
um
we're all sitting
and this was vms
is a time sharing system
so
we were all in our offices all close to the machine
and if it crashed
you know dick husett
and peter litman
and i would go out
and look to see why it crashed and we'd figure out why it crashed and we reboot
go back to our office and fix the problem and then go out and reboot a new system
and then everybody would be with a new system
so that's sort of how the development of vms occurred and the day we shipped vms
uh
we had zero known bugs
now it was zero known bugs
that didn't mean there was no bugs
but there were zero known bugs
and i know there was a bug right at the very end
where we had a race condition that was fixed
like in the 11th hour
um
in then
the
the final binaries were submitted to
uh
the manufacturing plant
so the vms and the 780 kind of launched deck into the super mini
bigger applications
more nudging into the commercial world
all kinds of new features and requirements coming
and that spawns a lot of evolution of vms
so you
you were with the vms team
well
all of that
no
i
when vms vms was
um
what i was my first very difficult project
where you know
there were some constraints placed on us that were very
um
very hard
we were the two years that we were given to eventually or effectively produce a system of the level
and caliber of ems was very short
um
and at that point i thought that at the i thought you know
maybe i should try some other things i'm interested in
and one of the other
one of the things i was very interested in was compilers
so
at the end of vms version one
i decided that i would um start a compiler group to produce a pl1 compiler
so i really didn't
uh
continue on with the
with the the uh
continuing versions of the ms
i
uh
split off at that point and started this group of consisting of i think four people
and i think we grew to about six people to do a pl1 compiler
and we
we bought a u a front end for the compiler from a company in um boston
and we produced the back end
which was the code generator
and i think that was another two-year project or so
so
and in part of that project also spawned a c compiler for vax also
and this was an example of really eating the dog food of writing the compiler in the compiler in pl1 actually pl1
um
as far as a dog food kind of thing
was an interesting way
we did the compiler
um
we had the front end of the compiler on that was delivered to us on multics and multic
the first we first thought that what we would do is we would
we would take the the multic compiler
and we would compile the pieces of the multic compiler
and we'd bring them over to vax and run them
eventually
we tried running the the remotely on the multic system
and we we couldn't get it to run in full duplex mode
and this is like got in 100
whatever is 50 miles to boston
it's 300 b
so we tried half duplex
it was a little bit at half duplex
so we just that wouldn't work either
so we decided what we would do is we'd hire a shuttle service
and
and the guy that was working on the front end would produce stuff on multics
put it on mag tape
give it to the shuttle service
bring it to deck and we take it off the mag tape
so the first thing we did was
um
we did
we
we bootstrapped the compiler backwards
so we were doing the code generator on our end
but our
the code generator was mostly written in assembler
um
so we got that working
and then we would bring back the phases of the compiler one by one backwards
until we got back to the beginning of the compiler
and then we could compile the whole thing at digital
so we really were eating our dog fu
because the whole compiler was written in pl1 except for the
the
the parts of the code generator that had to run line last
so you
now we're about 1981 at deck or so
or a little earlier
this is about
um
well
it's yeah
um
sometime during that year
maybe early in that year
so some circumstances conspire and dave says
is no longer for me
pardon
maynard was no longer for you
so what happened after the pl1 compiler was
um
you know
i sort of getting really a little bit fed up with the the growth of digital
when i started digital
there was 12, 000 people
and i don't know
in 8 881
there certainly wasn't 12, 000 anymore
there was 75 75, 000 or something
and so what started out to be this really engineering run engineering
um environment
um
suddenly became more of a management
marketing program
management environment
which i wasn't too happy with
and so i had expressed some things to gordon about um
maybe that i would like you know to be somewhere else
and he had offered to
uh
he said
well
anywhere you want to go
you know
maybe we can figure out how we can start engineering
uh
facility there
and i'said well
i don't know
maybe maybe i'll be okay here
and then this opportunity came up to start a company that was um going to um
commercialize a compiler
i'm sorry
a language that was
uh
funded by the government for real-time control
which is called praxis
and it was done for lawrence livermore
and it was actually done for the shiva noa project
which was a fusion energy project
um
so i kind of got enthused about doing that and we we being
uh
i guess about six people
three of us from deck
and a couple from or four of us from deck and a couple from lawrence livermore
you know
traveled around the
the
the bay area looking for money
and
uh
we sort of got to the point
where i think we figured out that maybe this wasn't the right thing to do
or at least i figured out this wasn't the right thing to do
and so i had
i
we
i told digital
i'm leaving
and so
um
you know
gez
we had a termination date and everything
and and then all of a sudden i think
oh
well
i'm not sure this is going to work out
you know
um
the president of the company was going to be a guy from the shiven noa project
and he seemed to be more interested in how he was going to spend all of our seed money
which we had put up ourselves on things like his color and his wife
uh
paying his wife for our stationary
so suddenly all our money that we'put together was gone
and i'm thinking
wow
i don't know if i want to go with this guy
so at the last moment i said
no
i'm not going to do it so effectively
all the other deck guys says
well
we're not doing it either
so then became the question about
well
gez
what are you going to do
and so i said
well
you know
i think i think it's really appropriate that i think about being somewhere else where i'm kind of isolated
a little bit from a little smaller environment
where we don't have all of the bureaucracy or we're developing a deck
so gordon says
well
geez that's sounds good to me
let's where would you like to go
and i said
well
can't be on the east coast
because that won't be far enough
you know
i really don't really like the southwest too much
so maybe you know
like arizona in new mexico
probably texas is not a good place
probably the west coast would be the best place
well
gordon says you know the west coast would be fine
but i want you to be somewhere where there's a a university that's got a good computer science program
uh
so that we can draw people from there
and maybe we can
we can actually collaborate with the
with the
the university
so the deck
um
real estate department arranged this trip
where we would fly to several different places on the west coast and look at
and we
we went to um
went to san francisco
we went to um sacramento
um
they were really hot on santa rosa
we went to portland and we came to seattle and i had spent a little time in portland
a little earlier
in fact
what had spawned the earlier
the earlier um offer by gordon to um
to um
establish a engineering facility for me
was that i had actually interview interviewed at intel in portland
and which is kind of an interesting
this is kind of a backtrack
but let me go back and talk about that
just for a second
this happened
and and i interviewed and they were building
uh
the 432 at that time
which was their 32-bit computer
um
which eventually never ever materialized
but
um
we had lost a couple people
dave best
who had been the program manager for the 750 went there
so i interviewed out there
and they got to the point of they were going to offer me a a job and they said
well
we can't really offer you a job because we're
we really cooperate a lot with digital
and you've got to tell gordon bell that you're going to
you're interested in this
so i said
no problem
so we're at spit book road
i call up gordon
i said gordon
i just i've been interviewing with intel and i don't really want their job
but i
you know
i want their offer because i want to figure out how much i'm worth
i said
okay
you
okay with that
he saysure
and i hung up and about 15 minutes later the phone rings and it's larry partners
admin said larry and gordon would like to come up to spit brook and have lunch with you
i said
oh
that's fine
when
today
will that be okay
and i said
sure
so they
they came to to spit brook and said we went to lunch and they basically said
well
why
why do you want to leave
and i said
well
i i don't want to leave
i just want to know what my value is in the market
they said
oh
well
maybe we can work something out
and then that's when gordon said
i said i really like portland
and gordon said
well
maybe we
we can think about this
and so you know
we did something about the the salary thing
and we did something about stock options and we thought about that a little bit
then i said
hey
i don't really want to do that
i
i'm
i'll stay here for a while and then this other company opportunity came up and then
when that fell through
it was really like
i really do want to move
so anyway
we're back to the west coast
we're going down the west coast and we go everywhere and we come to seattle and it's raining
but everything's green
and i said
gee boy
this is really a nice place and we visited the university
we we talked to
uh
the head of the computer
the chairman of the computer science department
i forget what his name was
um
he was really interested in his coming
and so we went back home and we thought about it for a while and and said you know
seattle's got to be the place that's got to be the place
so that's how we ended up in seattle
um
sort of we took the trip and looked at some different places
and
uh
decided we didn't really like sacramento very well
um
the barrier was a little bit too busy for us
and belleview was a pretty nice place to be
so that's where we ended up
so here you are
so a number of people decided to come with you
and then some other folks were hired here locally
you started up a lab
uh
it
we
we came here and
uh
we brought
um
i guess about eight people with us and we hired
you know
one of the things was
we would like to hire some people from the university of washington to to fir
uh
to firm up that that um connection of university of washington
we hired a couple people
um
from there
and
uh
started on a project to our our charter
by the way for this was to produce um again
going back to the real-time roots to produce some uh software for embedded
uh
chip-based back systems we were working on a chip set at that time called scorpio
which by today standards would have been huge because it was six chips
um
i think three of them were custom custom vsi chips
so it was a you
it was a big
would been big compared to today
but it was very small compared to what we had in those days
so our charter was to build um
this runtime system
our little real-time operating system
which was very easy to program
and
uh
which was very easy to um
implement real-time applications
and the name of the system was back salon and
um
it was our
it was my first entry or our first entry
into multi-threading we actually did multi-threading in back salon
which is about the same time that mach was doing multi-threading on um
at carnegie melon
just about the same time
so we got partway through this project and we start thinking about
well
scorpio has been going for quite a few years
now
we don't know when it's going to be delivered
um
we don't really have any suitable platform to run this on
uh
maybe we should think about
what we should do to to vax to maybe make vax a smaller architecture
so we started an effort
uh
within the company called microvax
and which was to trim down the architecture
and then
later on
after we had developed the architecture
we thought
well
we still don't have any platform to run this on
because we're going to have to produce a chip for this
and there was a micras chip
so maybe we should start a hardware group here too and we should produce a uh
an implementation of microa
that would not be one chip
but it would be a small system
maybe the size of a pp105
so we brought some more people out from deck east
um for the hardware project and
and they were mainly people from the east
but we also hired
we hired
uh
i
guess three people locally
um
because there was a lot of
there's a lot of going on in this area
um
with electronics
so it was easy to hire a few people and to produce a m theu microa r
we actually shipped
uh
velon and microa one together
and i got very interested in hardware at that time and i ended up working on vac salon
pretty much writing the kernel and the other people wrote the pieces
the file system and the pieces that went around it
but then i switched to the hardware group for the microx one and wrote all the micro code
and somewhere along the way
you hooked up with carver
me and took the team to learn
learn how to do that
the way that we
uh
implemented the microx one
uh system was
um
gordon thought it would be a good idea if we tried
uh
some new technology with respect to producing silicon chips and one of the new technologies that was being touted
by carver me from
uh
was he from caltech tech
um
and linn conway
was
um
some um
silicon piler tools
and there
the company that was founded actually called silicon compilers
that kid was a principal in and john hennessy was also
and we got together with them
and inspected a chip that they could build that would be the central processing unit of the system
and it would be on one chip
and so that's
they produced the chip
um
they designed the chip
uh
jointly with our specifications going back and forth
they didn't have the all the expert expertise
and then our hardware
guys designed all the hardware that went around that
uh
we had a an awful time getting the the chip built
we
we went to a company called ami to start with
which you know
in those days
um semiconductor companies were popping up like um dandel lines
there were lots of them
um
they'd pop up
they'd run through their vc funding
they'd lie over
roll over and play dead
ami never actually produced a chip for us that worked
they produced a chip and we got the chip
when we looked at it and they had done all the masks backwards
they were all the negative of what they should be
oops
so i don't know how that happened
so we went to another company called seik and seek actually produced the chip
um
i can't remember us
having any problems with the chip with respect to arata
um
you know
there may have been some things that we worked
i
i don't really
i don't really remember
i remember it being pretty much bug free
and we were um able to take that chip and we put it in a cubus based system
and that was microx one and we ran velan on it
but later on we also ran vi a mess on it
um
partway through the microvax um architecture discussion
we had trimmed the memory management capabilities of um vms
quite a bit
i'm not vms
the the ar
the memory management capabilities of v
way down
which meant that vms would not run with it
it would have to be big modification to vms to make it run
and so i was writing the micro code and i was thinking
geez
why don't we just do the full memory management
not much micro code
so i got bob sutnik to agree to that
he was the guy that was doing the micro code for the microx one chip
that we just do the whole thing
it was going to be less work to do that than not do it
and we get the ms to run
so we got vms to run almost at the same time
we got our our system to run
and um
i
i don't remember exactly the year
it was probably 86 or something
maybe 84
about 3 years
maybe three years in development for that system
um
so
uh
that was our first project at at deck west
and where did that lead to
well
that led
what
what did that lead to that led to problems that led to big problems
because here we are
we have
now we have this kind of seasoned operating system group
we have the seasoned hardware group
now
what are we going to do
and so the problem is to try to find something to do that's not being done
by another group at headquarters
and so we went through several proposals on building projects
uh
building systems
um
hardware was mainly hardware
uh
there were some people at deck west
that wanted to build um
a workstation
um
and then there were some people that that wanted to build a more capable system than the workstation
and
uh
we ended up not building the workstation and we ended up trying to build a bigger system
and
um
that led to big problems
because we were always over the top
we're always duplicating some function
that or some
uh
part of the the uh price performance space that somebody at at headquarters was already doing
so we went through several projects
um
trying to
uh
find the right vac to build
and we basically we would go
i would go back to mayard and try to negotiate
um
what we should build
and get some degree of buying
and come back and we work for six months and then mayard would decide
well
that wasn't what they want us to build
so we have to find something else to build
so this sort of led to us
um
thinking about risk was becoming very popular at that time
and it was kind of u getting to the point
where there's a lot of publicity about risk having better performance in vaac
and risk was the way to go
and so we got interested in risk and
um
there were several risk projects going on in the company
there was one going on in marlboro
uh
there was one going on down in the bay area at wrl
which was a western research lab and we were sort of working on one
so
um
jack smith
who was the uh
senior vice president of engineering
said
deck west
is respons responsible for the risk architecture
so there started the prism project
which was
um
a new risk architecture for deck
and i think we probably started that in about um
i think maybe 85
so
um
that's what happened after we
we were
we
very successful in being
i
me
just tremendously successful
you know
very low overhead
very few people
um
we got things done in just record speed record for record amount of money
engineering
nre costs were like zilo compared to the other projects
but then into a period of not being able to find the right thing to do
and then into the architecture
the new architecture
all right
so
um
i guess it was kind of a a risk war
that started to evolve that de between various parts of the company
well
the reason that the prism archit ecture actually got assigned to deck west
was
because there were so many uh projects going on in the company trying to develop risk projects
or risk architectures
and of course digital already had
we know
we had the 36-bit line
which is a pdp 10 and then the dex system 20
we had the vax line
we had the pdp1 line
um
i don't think we were probably making any nines and 15s
we may may have still been shipping a few eights by by then
but um so we really didn't need three or four new risk architectures
so the prism architecture started out much like the vax architecture
with representatives from um
vms
had a representative hudson
which was
the semiconductor branch
had a a representative
uh
marlboro had a representative
one of the guys that worked on that architecture was there
we had um um myself
and then we had a guy from the architecture group
and we then spent the next three years
um
just about three years
uh
going through a revision of this
and then taking it back to the senior technical community and they would look at it and say
oh
we don't like this and we would go back we went
we flipped from 64 to 32 to 64
back to 32 in the architecture
which it took a long time to sort through all that
and then
and then you know
the whole principle of risk was to produce a hard or a
a system architecture that was easy to implement
um
you didn't have to have
uh
brute brute force methods of doing things and massive
verification suites
um
and but then the the company kind of ran off the track and started adding all these things
the first thing that happened is we got to have vector arithmetic
so you have to
we have to compete with sear c
so we had to have a vector architecture
well
sear probably had
you know
he probably had eight vector instructions
well
we had to have 150 vector instructions
you know
so
and they had to be long vectors
they weren't short vectors
and so this went on and on and on
and you know
at the meantime
at deck west
we're sort of um gearing up
you think that we'd be in a holding pattern
but we're not
we're sort of gearing up for building one of these systems
and we have proposals for building these systems
and we took microx one and we actually converted it to be to run prism code
so people could actually develop software
and
um
we came to a point where
finally the company just said we're canceling prison and i went through
uh
several
we went through a lot of iterations
i'd go to
i'd go to maynard
try to try to get some consensus on what we should be doing
i'd come back home and invariably it was always something bigger
and we add we'd add people
so we kind of grew from you
like 20 people to 180 people
so we have this 180 people organization
and we're building kind of a nebulous project or nebulous product built based on this new architecture
at a time when the company was trying to build three of these machines
there was one in marlboro and one in um littleton and one seattle
so our machine got cancelled and our system got
can
our operating system which called micah got cancelled and i sort of got
i
i kind of went through the the stages of
um
you know
trying to find some ground where we could all agree on what we're going to build
come back
i'd sell the people on it and then they get disappointed
so i said i don't want to do this again
so i said what am i going to do
and i said
well
i guess i'll form a company
so i got three other guys and i together these are the same three guys we met with
i was talking earlier about bomber
which we'll get into later and we decided we were going to build
or we were going to form a company to build servers and
um
i formally quit
although i didn't leave right away
they gave me an office somewhere else until i had really subtle things
i spent a lot of time traveling back and forth to the the valley
uh
talking to the vc and what we're doing and whatever
and we actually got to the point where
um
we had the vc all lined up
we we had
um
we had 3 vc and myips
they were all going to put up some seed money
we're going to have a million dollars worth of seed money
which um was probably quite a bit of money in today's dollars
and this was
this would have been in 1988
so
um
somewhere during this period
quite a few of the people
when prison was canceled had decided that maybe they'd look across the street at microsoft and go to microsoft
and one of the people went over there
had
um been talking to
uh
bill bill gates about
the group at micro
or group at deck west and that we had a good operating system group
and maybe that would be something that that he might be interested in
so
um
there was an interview arranged
and i went over
and talked to bill about what they were interested in doing and what they wanted to do
and and um
see if i was interested
and and they
their
uh
basic concern was that intel was not bringing the the x86 architecture forward fast enough
and that risk processors were going to overtake them
and if risk processors overtake them
then all the pc software that they developed would be wouldn't be valuable anymore
and that they ought to have something going on in risk
and if they were going to have something going on in risk
then they needed a new operating system that wasn't written in assembler
that was written in a portable language so that they could run across several different architectures
and so i sort of listened to all of this
and and um was really interested in doing my own company
and so i kind of left the interview thinking well
i don't think i'm real real interested in this
and sort of you know
time
kind of
i don't know
over a couple months
we mold us all over the four of us
and
um
finally we got all the dc lined up and
we got
we got the commitment from for the money
and before we were
we got the commitment
um
boy
you listen to them talk
we were the greatest people in the world but as soon as we got the commitment
our
our value seemed to diminish a little bit and they were a little bit more vocal about
um
whether or not we could actually run a company or not
whether we'd be able to to develop a product
even though we had a good history of product development
so i think sort of got under my skin a little bit
and about the same time
steve bomber
who
uh
worked at microsoft and he
was the head of the finance department of microsoft called and said
uh
you know
how are
what are you thinking
and i said
well
i'm thinking that we're
you know
we're really close to doing this company and and we're probably going to turn down the
or
i'm probably going to turn down the microsoft offer
and he said
oh geez
uh
won't you give me a chance to to convince you otherwise
and i said
well
yeah
okay
he said
well
how about how about breakfast at denny's
you know
on saturday morning
at 7 o'clock or i don't
maybe it was a sunday morning
i mean
but it was early and i said
yeah
okay
so the four of us went to denny's and and sat down
and and steve is
is such an energetic guy and and um
a positive thinker and
so he starts the sales job
and
um
i guess
the best way thing you can say is he fleeced this
because
by the time we left
we're all ready to sign up and we did
we
we decided not to form our company
which i think was a great looking back on it
uh
we would have been just another server company
probably
unless
unless we could have
uh
developed some
in fact
we were
really
um
founding was a hardware company
and unless we would have had the foresight to convert that company quickly to a software company
we would have been in trouble
so
um
in fact we were an interesting thing you might find interesting here is we actually were going to run unix on on this box
because of the lead time that would take to actually produce something of your own
and the fact that it would be incompatible with everything
so obviously we couldn't produce something that's vx compatible
so the next best thing was unix
and we decided that mach was the best example le of unic systems
they're actually going to use mock on this server
but anyway bomber fleeces us and we all decide to sign up and go to work for microsoft
and so you know
i quit immediately
they're still working for for deak
and you know
i
like
i quit on friday and join microsoft on monday
and the following monday
these other three guys follow me and then from there
um
we
i
i want to say we recruited because we didn't really recruit people
but people ask us about opportunities
and of course we're forthcoming about opportunities
so we managed to bring over quite a few people
we
and part of the thing about going to microsoft was they wanted the portable operating system
but i liked the hardware part of it too
having that
so
uh
we convinced them
or i convinced them that that i should have a hardware group
and the software group and that we would produce the hardware
produce
hardware group would actually produce the first risk-based pc
that the software group would be producing the operating system for
so we were able to bring over
i'm sorry we weren't able to bring over
we were able to to
uh
satisfy the
i think the statute of limitations is long past the statute of limit
long past
we were able to bring over these people from from deck
that had been
you know
the top performers at at deck west
and and so we got the the top hardware guys
and we got the top software guys
and you know it was about 10 10 or something like that
and we we hired some more people
we hired
um
we had part of the thing about
uh
the the group was
we the hardware group
not not like the software group
the software group
um
microsoft wanted to make sure we had microsoft people in the software group
because otherwise we would just produce some something that was duck the duck cultural thing
right
so we had
um
actually
i think we have one one software guy and he was a pretty good
pretty good
um
or
he was a vocal microsoft guy and he had a lot of ideas
um
which actually dovetailed with ours
pretty well
um
about how to build an operating system
they
microsoft had been working with ibm on os2 for several years
by that time and that relationship was not going real well
and this guy had worked on that so he was very happy to join our group
so you parachute kind of into microsoft and after a short period of time
you look around
what did
what did you see
what did microsoft look like at that time
well
microsoft didn't look like deck
um
actually
i should say
um
microsoft was a very different company than deck deck was
the thing i liked about deck
and i think that i can honestly say that that i spent most of my best
the most enjoyable engineering years at deck between 1971 and in 1980
or maybe 82 or 83
was
deck was mainly an engineering company
it was run mainly by the engineers
um
the engineers proposed the products
they talked to customers um they tried to produce very high quality products and um
put them in the market
and then the marketing arm of deck was not
i would not say
during those years was really strong
uh
i think it became strong
after that
much stronger
because it
the
the focus of the company became much more marketing oriented than it was engineering oriented
but microsoft was very marketing oriented
microsoft was
um
they
well
they marketed the pc software doss to ibm
um
so they were very
more marketing oriented
which you know
i thought was
um
i like that
because i liked it and i didn't like it
i liked it
because it was going to be
i was going to have a a group of marketing people
that were really going to be out hawking the projects
or products
on the other hand
i i didn't like it
because they might have their fingers in what we were going to do
and it turned out that the original version of nt
um
was pretty much an engineering deriven thing
except for a couple of things
and that was that
um
the
in addition to being portable
microsoft wanted this system to be compatible with multiple operating environments
so that sort of let us to an architecture within uh nt
that would allow uh
different subsystem personalities
and so we had
we had to keep ibm happy and run os2
of course
we want to run dos
and then the other thing that was
um big was very popular
i big
it was popular was posix
these are the
uh
the standardized unix interfaces
so the personality of this thing was going to be this multifaceted thing
um
so
see
i'm trying to think
why hard did i go down this rout
well
it was kind of like you
you
oh
okay
we're dropped in
drop in and i
so
anyway
the microsoft people or microsoft sort of dedicated that level
but none of the rest of the level
the rest of the level was pretty engineering
uh
driven
and we set about um
designing windows nt
much in the same way that we had set about designing vms
except that in the
in terms of
uh
windows nt
we decided to produce a much more more detailed specification of the system and vms
we sort of had
we had this small group and we spent a lot of time talking about things
and we
we did do some specs
but they were pretty rudimentary specs for nt
we wrote a humongous spec
and i'd say it was over six months about how the whole system would work so
that people could pick up the spec new
as new people came in
they could pick up the spec
and understand understand it and read the code and actually kind of understand what was going to go on
our first projected um
uh
delivery date for the os was like two years
now
it actually took us five years to produce the first os
um
i could have never
if you'asked me
even today
if it would have taken five years back
then i would have said no
it's so we can do it in two years
but there was so much more to do
um
vms did not have a graphical user interface
we had to do
that we didn't have the subsystem problem in in vms we had are running multiple personalities
we had to run the pdp1 binaries
and we produced what was called the ame
which was the application migration executive
and we ran all the
in fact
that's how we got the vms software out was by running the 11 software
completely unconstrained architecture
in the in the in the io
and so in the pc
yeah
and so
um
we had a lot more to do and and we
we
you know
we started out with this
um
this idea that we're going to produce the first risk pc
and we're going to produce a software for it and we and we make this
well
i i can't say that we make
we make this mistake
this mistake has already been made for us
when we get there
is
is intel
at the time is producing the i860
and this is um
one of the fastest risk machines in certain applications
and those applications are mainly graphics
so microsoft wanted to to use
that is the microprocessor for our first reference implementation
we're going to build a reference implementation
we of the 860 and and we got one of the um
the oems
uh
which
which was aletti that signed up to build this
so we were going to build the reference system and they were going to take the design
um
make it manufacturable and manufacture it
we were in a build a software
uh
but then a partway through that
we
we found out that the 860 was pretty sick
it had a lot of arata
that would make it
um
pretty unusable
is an os based system
um
it had some quirks that were made it very nice for the graphics world
but not very well for the
for the operating system world
had it virtually tag cash
so basically
every time you switch context
you sweep the cash because it has all the virtual tags from the last address space you ran in
so anyway it took five years to do the first version
um
so there
i guess your original question was how different was the environment
well
the environment was a lot different
because deck was a engineer
ing run company and we're always based on engineering excellence
microsoft
i
i think
um
justifiably
i would say it's a marketing based company and they weren't um
based on engineering excellence
so there was sort of a a little clash between our culture
um
and the microsoft culture
but i think that we instilled a lot of that into the microsoft culture
but we still had a lot of things going on that were sort of out outside our our
um
our control that we within the microsoft culture
so
um
that made it made the project a lot longer
and the fire was very different somewhere along the word you said to me
you know there a lot of coders at microsoft
but no software engineering
and you had to bring the discipline of software engineering
microsoft
that
um
one of the things that we brought was the engineering discipline on building software
and i don't think that that microsoft had the engineering discipline that we had at that time
um
of course
it's
you know
that's 28 years ago
it's a long time and and um
the discipline at microsoft now is
is i would say
is excellent
um
there's
there's a lot of stuff in place
it's
it's not the same atmosphere that we had with the original nt team
because it was
our team was small
you know
we started out with 25 guys
um
the the end of version one were 150
at the end of version four
we're 400
which is
um
big
today is 4,
so now
along the way
uh
a lot of things get added to what nt is
i guess you had program managers or some
that was
i think the title that
um
as far as the the culture and environment
you know
at deck
we had program manager
but but program managers were sort of
um
sort of
they were quasi marketing people
in some sense
um
they didn't try to manage the engineering effort
the engineering effort was managed by the engineering people
so there was a big clash in the beginning
when between me and the the program managers of of microsoft over who did what
and i i wrote
i i wish i could find this piece of mail i wrote
but i wrote this big thing
big big piece of mail to our program manager about his job and mine
which laid out what i thought his job was and what my job was
and
uh
so that pretty much worked its way itself out
because we pretty much operated the way we did it
deck
but over time program managers at microsoft have taken a a more
uh
direct um involvement and control over what happens
so the you have this enormously complicated thing
multiple platforms
you're going to run on portability
um
keeping control of this and keeping everybody moving for five years gets to be quite a challenge
so the so
a little bit about the compa or the uh
the complexity of what we're building
now we talked about the 860 and the problems with the 860
well
partway down the road
you know we'd only went about a year
and we decided there's no way we can go with the 860
and so i said
well
what should we do
so he said
well
how about myips
myips is doing the r4000 that that's the platform that we ought to make the first one
so our hardware group switched to the r4000 and we started
uh
to
go in that direction
and now this just to make a lot of difference to the operating system
because the way the operating system is structured or was structured
was we
we sort of taking the the stuff that was absolutely portable and it was still portable
and then the stuff
that was hardware architecture specific was divided out so that you just had to to replace that
so the first thing that happened was deck got wind of what we're doing and says
well
gez
we're building an r3000 workstation why don't you support the r3000 to
so
i guess
foolishly
we said
okay
we'll support the 3, 000 too well
well
that put us into some difficulty now
because the 3, 000 is not entirely compatible with the 4, 000
so now we're building for two two platforms
so we have the r3000
the r4000 and not long after said
well
you know
it looks like it's going to be a little while longer than we thought
maybe we should add the 386 back into the mix
here
you know
intel's coming out with a
i think it's a 38625 25 megahertz um
let's add that in
so now we start
uh
we
don't
we aren't building any hardware because there's a
there is the industry infrastructure to build x86 based system
so we don't do anything there
and
um
so now we're building for b
basically three targets and three operating environments and the gooey stuff
and now along
comes deck back with alpha and says gez
we want to run windows on alpha too
and so we said
okay
so we started doing alpha
and then ibm says
well
geez
as long as you're doing all that
let's do the power pc
so we're doing actually four platforms
we're doing four platforms
if you only count myips one
if you count them
two
then we're doing five
in addition
what happened was somewhere in the in the early 90s we had
we had this thing on the 16
it ran on doss
that was a um a layer
it just it was a program that ran on top of doss
it was called windows
we did windows 1
the industry said hoam
we did industry or windows 2
the industry said ham
we did windows 3
the window
the industry said ham
we we did windows 3. 1
we sold 16 million copies in 6 months
it was like unbelievable
so bill says
hm
i guess our major
our main operating environment will not be os2 anymore
it will be windows
so we switched from our main operating environment being os2 with the program manager
which was their graphical univ interface to windows
and when we brought in windows
then we brought brought in also all the compatibility requirements with windows 16
so we're running on all these platforms
we're running these different environments
we're running a 16bit doss emulator
we're running a 16bit windows on windows emulator
we're running
uh
windows 32bit emulators on alpha power pc and myips
all those things to to get to the first release
now
the first release actually only supported myips and and um the x86
then i think
about six months later we did another project called daytona
which was another release
and that included alpha
which was 35
and then
about six months later we did the power pc
so that's kind of why it took five years
oh yeah
easy to understand
in retrospect
lots of things changed
so keeping the team going
you know
here's the the dave cutler
infamous management style at work
uh
talk about keeping the team going
well
you know i'i've um
i
i said earlier that i'm always consider myself as a leader
not a manager
so i've always tried to be a leader
that is part of the team versus somebody that is separated from the team
so i'm always a part of the team
if the team is stressed and up against the wall
then i'm stressed and up against the wall
so
um
i think we did
we didn't have any um problems with um
people burned out
you know
people pretty much
uh
stood the whole five years
although there were some ramification
i mean people got divorced
you know
there other things that happened and we had very little attrition
i mean just really small attrition
um
everybody believed in the product
and the other thing we did was we did
we
we did this
uh
every every friday night
we had a party
we called it the whim
and the whim was the weekly integration meeting
and it
it was
it was instigated by a guy named dave thompson
who was in the network group
because we pulled in
we eventually pulled in the network group
um
originally in the pc world
the network group was separate from the operating system group
and it was just an add-on you know
it was just
it's some other program
if you want to do network operations
you ran a program to do that
it wasn't building the operating system
and we had planned all along to build it into the operating system with the vms model
so we're growing pretty rapidly as we're pulling in some of these groups and we're growing from you know
20 people to 150 or or whatever
and so he said
well
why don't we have this
we'll have a meeting every friday afternoon and we'll get
you know
beer and pizza and chips and we'll meet
and
um
just everybody will get to know each other
so this grew into a huge thing
i mean i can imagine five years and every friday night that you're doing this
you know
we start out
we're in a room about this size
and we end up in a huge room and we start out that that i send the development managers
there's
there's like four development managers under me
um
i send them down to safeway to buy a few beers
and pick up some pizza and bring them back to the to the end
when where we have full catering from marriott
may marot's bring in everything
and and we go from
you know
like
um
uh
chips and salsa and beer and pizza to uh
shrimp
and you know all sorts of stuff that's catered kegs of beer
i mean it was
it
was
it was interesting
and then there were some things where you know
we always have
uh
something going on where
um
we try to
uh
to
get people to feel better about what's going on and how much stress they're in
i know there's some people that felt they were under a lot of stress and sometimes they break
but i think generally we held everything together pretty good