all right
uh
today is april 17th 2017
um
i am hansen
su
i'm john marov
david brock
ai tanan avan
great
so
um
this is the the
the apple chapter
if you will
and could
could we start
i'd like to start by asking what your role was in that transition period
are there things
that you remember about that really sort of jump out at you about the process of of going to
you know
next becoming part of apple
so you're talking about literally the transition right after the acquisition was done
well
even like the first things you remember about that process of the acquisition
and becoming part of becoming part of
okay
yeah
so i guess
maybe i'll start with
uh
um
the process to get acquired
which started
i think it was just before thanksgiving around that time frame of 1996
and
uh
we had been watching in the press
um
about how apple was talking to be about potentially buying the company to get their os
because they needed a new os at the time
and you know
to be honest at next
our focus was more against competition from companies like sun than from apple
more in the workstation space
and so we weren't really weren't really paying too much attention to apple
but we had
um
while we were still supporting next step
of course
an open step
we had become increasingly focused on web objects
and so apple was not at all in that space
but when
um
i remember
when i saw some of those articles
um
i talked to steve jobs and said you know if they're going to buy an os
i mean we've got the best one
it's pretty clear
and so he made some calls into gil gil amilio
and in parallel
some of our marketing folks were making calls into apple as well at various different levels
and very quickly we had meetings set up to do technical evaluation
technical diligence
things like that
and in basically under a month we had a signed deal to be acquired
um
right after being acquired right after signing the deal to be acquired
so now we're looking at
uh
late december
couple days before christmas
uh
as that quarter is coming to a close for apple
they had to pre-announce a major loss
and that kind of took us by surprise
we certainly didn't see that coming just because we weren't watching the company at all
um
we knew the company was struggling
but we didn't know that it was that bad off
um
but the deal went through
we actually started doing a little bit of integration
uh
in january
very little
because you can't really do the integration until the deals closed
which was in february
i think
february 6th or 7th of 97
but i remember
um
you know
some of the initial interactions
uh
were
helping gil to prepare a macor speech in early january
an ill-fated ma world speech went on for like three hours
the longest speech i've ever heard all of us
yeah
um
it was amazing to watch it
and i say that in a not good way for people just reading the transcript
were you in the audience
or were you back
i was in the audience
um
and our role
well
we had two roles
one
one role was ahead of time to help prepare gil
and his team for those parts of the keynote that would focus on the next acquisition
and that was only one small part of it
they had many many things to announce
yeah
um
and then our other role was
steve jobs did 10
15 minutes of his own
um
after gil talked about the the merger coming up
and and steve's part of course was very good
i think it's widely acknowledged that that was the case
um
so so that was one part of it
that was sort of the first thing
the real tangible thing that i remember
another tangible thing that i remember was
um
i started meeting with
uh
um
some folks who would either become my direct reports inside of apple
or were sort of key people at apple
that i would really need to get to know and and work with closely
if you will
beyond who are coming over from the next team
yeah
and you know that was a pretty eye-opening experience for me
because i got to see firsthand some of the things
that were causing apple to be in the state that it was in
yeah
so let me backwards and then go forwards
because talk a little bit about the management team at that juncture on the next side
um
were you part of a a small group of people who are making strategic decisions at next
yes
so you know that's an interesting question
um
in that i don't think a lot has really understood about what was going on
then
um
so i was part of the next executive team for many
many years
either informally or for normally
almost from when i started back in'88 um
but when we're looking in 96
um
you know the company had gone through some pretty big transitions
first
uh
getting out of the hardware business
huge transition and
then
uh
transitioning toward lot
similar
with the hardware business around that same time frame
running the software on multiple platforms
obviously there's no hardware
it's got to be software
but also then transitioning or adding
if you will the web objects business
which would have
i think
would have been very
very
huge at the time
um
and so we had a small management team
uh
i ran engineering
it was only software engineering
at the time
it was all of engineering
we had a cfo
we had someone running sales
i think we had someone running marketing
it was a somewhat traditional but small management team
but something interesting was going on
which was
as we transitioned out of hardware
and as we transition more toward selling a web solution on the server side
it was a more it was
it was an even more enterprise sale than it was before
and um
steve was getting fairly uninterested in that
and he was getting tired of it
and he had pixar going on on the side
and so what we were going to do
in fact
had we gone public and this is in the the draft
s1
we were going to form an office of the president
which would have been
um
me
i believe
uh
mitch mandich and who's our sales guy
and i believe dominique tro
who's our cfo
and and steve
i think we probably would have been part of that
he would have been ceo and chairman
but what we were really trying to do was also to take some of the load off him
so
and and frankly
you know
enterprise sales wasn't his expertise
so that was fine
and the rest of us we were all fully engaged and able to to take the business forward
so that's kind of what it looked like inside and then
was there a distinct board
and were there interesting board members that you remember
that were involved in that decision
that were separate from the management
so the office of the president
i mean the the office of the president decision
or the
the
i'm sorry
the merger decision
um
so i'm pretty sure ross was still on the board
i'm pretty sure canon had a representative
because
uh
they had done a $ 60 million loan
and if there was any other board members
i don't remember
obviously steve was a board member there may have been another
but it wasn't
it didn't show up as a separate decision making
pro
the
the key decisions were made at the management group level
the key decisions were made at the manag group
the management group level
the decision to sell was
you know
me and steve and a couple of others
and that was a no-brainer um
because we had a fair price
a good price
what i thought you know
similar to what
it would have been going public
with full liquidity at the time
and putting our our technology and people into a company that we thought could really magnify it
yeah
but this was taking
i mean
as i recall
i mean steve was coming back as kind of initially
he wasn't there as ceo
right it
it
it was
he was like a friend of the company
almost
so
now you're talking apple
so when we got to apple
we all got jobs at apple
but steve didn't and that was all by design
um
he didn't want one
and i mean what job is he going to have right
i mean
i guess they could have given him the ceo job
then he wouldn't have taken it
yeah
um
at least i don't think he would have
but that wasn't what the deal was and so
you know they knew apple knew that
um
and to gil's credit
gil knew that he needed steve to help
um
you know
gills criticized for a lot of things about what what he did with
rightly
so
but the one thing he got right was knowing that steve was going to be a positive um
and so steve basically signed on as an informal adviser
yeah
and do you remember
at steve's memorial
larry ellison told that what i thought was a really sweet story about them talking about how to
you know how to go back to apple and larry had a very sort of cutthroat
you know
steve could make billions of dollars of i don't quite remember the story
but it was larry wanted to make money
office
steve wanted to do it because it was the right thing to do
did
am i telling it right
no sort of
um
the the essence of the story and and the true source of course should be larry
yeah
but
uh
the essence of the story
which i've heard from larry at that point and and in other other cases is that
um
obviously larry wanted to make a lot of money turning apple
and he wanted to help his friend steve
and steve really wanted apple to be success
successful
because it was his baby
um
and so larry's sort of idea was he would fund the takeover and install steve as ceo
and then together they would make it successful again
and
steve
according to larry
steve didn't really want to do it in a hustle way
he didn't think that was going to work
he didn't think that was going to be good
and he was still dealing with next and dealing with pixar
so that was a non-star now
steve never mentioned that to me
so i don't know to what extent it's been embellished
or you know how it's changed as it's been repeated many times
yeah
did you go ahead
uh
i was interested in asking about the
the bake off that you had with be
talk a little bit about that
the bake
off
so there was a
there was allegedly a bake
off
i only saw one side of that or one part of that
um
but i've been told by people who were in the room that there was indeed a bake off
and so as we were
um
uh
nearing the end of 1996
we done a bunch of uh discussions with the company
and they decided they wanted to do a bake off
be versus next
um
so
uh
we both went in at separate times
stage
we wouldn't meet each other there to the garden court hotel in palo alto and um
i don't know if we went first or they went first
i'm not even sure
uh
they may have gone first
but i don't remember
um
so steve
and i had an hour hour and a half or so to present our case to the management team
and
and we had
we had the benefit of a product that was in the market that worked great
that had been around for many years and b didn't
and so i remember
steve did his uh general sort of sales pitch on the company
and and the product and and everything we've got invested in and everything they could do
and we did just an incredibly dazzling demo
i remember
we had um productivity apps
um
we had
uh games
we had um
quicktime movies
four of them
on the screen
3d models all going at the same time literally on the screen
this was back in 1996
you know today
that's nothing
but we're talking over 20 years ago
that was a huge deal and the management team
i mean these guys were apple
i mean why couldn't they do that themselves
yeah
is probably what they're asking themselves right
and
and so we just had this great presentation and demo that
uh
i mean again
i don't
i wasn't in the room when be presented
um
but i think
they thought that they just had the deal done and there was only so much they could show
anyway
their product wasn't nearly as mature
their technology wasn't nearly as good
and so
uh
that happened
when
uh
we finished
um
steve and i left the garden court hotel and we went for one of our
uh
you know
signature
steve jobs walks around palo alto
and as we're walking around one of the blocks
um
we happened to see someone who was in
that meeting from the management team who said you guys won easily
no problem
you have nothing to worry about
so that's how that happened
was nagel in the meeting too
was he still around at that point
or was nel gone
he
i think he was there
i don't think he was there
interesting and that that must be significant if he wasn't there
because wasn't he head of software
maybe he was gone by that time
so when i was there
excuse me just prior
the last real head of software that i knew of was ike
nassie
oh
ike
yeah
and i think ike had just left
and so they may have replaced him
but i don't
if there was someone that was there
it was it
just there was really no one there
ellen hancock
the woman had come from ibm
did
did she show up on your radar at all
um
ellen was in this meeting
i remember
she was in the meeting
ellen was the deao person in charge of software
she was in charge of all of technology
i believe all of products
so she was that de facto person
yeah
at at that point
um
you were more than a colleague of steve
when you
you were
you guys were friends
i mean talk a little bit about your relationship with steve at that point
wasn't it closer than being a business only relationship
trying to turn back the clock in my head and get the dates right
so when i joined next in 88
we quickly became good friends we hang out together
every once in a while
we go to dinner
a lot things like that
we
we were both of the the
we always like to work all the time
and so we could always we
we'd be outside of work
but we'd still be like talking about work and that was just great
and so
by the time this happened
um
he had married loren
i had married my wife
we both had kids
by then
from a friendship perspective
we started to drift apart a little bit because we were more with our families than with our friends
if you will
um
but we were still close
for sure
yeah
were you the best man at his
his wedding he had no best man
but i was at his wedding
okay
which was at um
in yuse
at valley
um
the
the wonderful lodge
yeah
that was a quite an event
um
so what can you say about
i mean
so what's always
you know
striking is sort of the outside image of steve jobs versus the the steve jobs i know through the people i know who work for him
okay
which is it
it doesn't connect often
i mean you know people on the outside sort of say he can be harsh and a tyrant
and you know all of that
and yet very few people left over a long period of time
i the people who walked away from steve jobs are on the
you know
they're just not
so there must be
there must be some disconnect
i mean
and i just wondered if i mean if you're aware of the sort of the of
that kind of outside versus inside image
yeah
and maybe if we just back up a second
you asked if i was the best man at his wedding
i wasn't
but maybe what you're thinking is i put together his bachelor party
that's what it was
which is normally something the best man would do
yeah
but you know someone had to do it
so i stepped up and did it anyway
so
um
you kind of asked a couple questions about him there
and i i think you know one thing i'll say is i i explicitly asked him one day
so what's it like being famous and you've got this persona of who you are
what people think you are versus who you really are
they're not necessarily the same
and his answer to me was very quick
and very straightforward and not like you had to think about it all
you kind of knew his answer well
that public
steve jobs is kind of like a brother
he's just some other person
he's not me
he looks like me
he sounds like me
but i'm a different person
my private person is a different person
it just a different person
so he kind of dealt with it that way
just
you know
that's the public view of who i am
and that's a role that i take on
it's like an actor
but a
but a brother
very
very close
yeah
and then
um
the other part of your question is
you know people
he was hard to work for
known to be hard to work for
yet people seem to stick around
um
yes
and no
um
he
certainly he was hard to work for much of the time
but he was also great to work for much of the time
um
if you
you needed to earn his respect
if you earn his respect in some form
and there are multiple ways to do that
in multiple forms it could take
then
um
he would generally be fair with you
he might be harsh
but he would generally be fair and because he had respect for you
um
you felt as though you could still work with them
even though you're getting criticized
and
and what usually it meant is
that you had thick enough skin that you were someone who could work for for him
and know that maybe he
if he's berating you today
he's not going to do that tomorrow because it'll change his mind
but the net of that was that people who couldn't do that
didn't last long
and so they would go away
but you'd kind of never really hear about it
just because it would just be one meeting and they're gone
okay
and and for them to even say they worked for him would almost be a lie
um
and and many people
the interesting
that i find is you find all these people who say they worked for him but never really did
they were like
maybe in a meeting with him one time
okay
and suddenly that's elevated to
i worked with steve jobs
and there are hundreds of if not thousands of people in the valley and beyond that
now say that which is
you know
yeah
if someone says they work for steve jobs
i like say
i don't even know that person is
they probably didn't okay
and that's usually the case
as opposed to the opposite where they really did work for him and work with him
um
on a substantial basis
people have told me that he would often reject ideas
but if you were forceful and stuck with your idea and didn't sort of back off
he would ultimately adopt things that would
would
you know
he would internalize them
they become his ideas at a certain point
absolutely true
and not
i mean not always
but
but it was possible
and the strategy was to get him to adopt your idea
yeah
right
because then he would go out and sell it and
um
you know
one day black could be the most important color in the world
and then the next year
and anyone who thought white was was an idiot
but then the next year it could be the opposite
white is it
and anyone who thinks black is
it is just wrong
okay
and it's not because the trend change
it's because they're just wrong
and
and so i don't want to say most of the time
but frequently he would push back on things just to see what was going to happen right
so if you're
if you present an idea to him and he says he doesn't like it
then what he's really saying is well
i don't really know if i like your idea or not defend it
okay
and if you could
then defend it
and it might take a while
okay
if you can defend it
then
uh
he'll go for it
and i have a great example of this
um
which i won't wait for you to ask about it
because it's a great example
and it's something that i didn't even remember or even realize
until he mentioned it in a press report many many years ago
so when we were doing the early version versions of mac os 10
one of the differences between mac os 10
and the prior mac os's 8 and n was that mac os 10 had inherently built into it
authentication
they were us quote users
right
whereas the mac
the old mac was just
it was your computer
right
there was no who you were or anything like that
you didn't log into it or anything
and as we were trying to figure out what mac os 10 should end up being
and reconciling it with the past
and not being too disruptive to users while adding in a lot of new technology
steve really kept pushing back on this notion that you had to log into your computer
he thought that was just wrong
you should never have to do that
it's your computer
it's on your desk
when you turn it on
it should be right there at your desktop and you're the owner
and so
if you
if you think about when we're having these discussions
this is 97
okay
very early on before people thought about security and computers very much
um
and we'd have this discussion once a week for many months
and he would keep complaining and i would keep saying
no
we need it
but you know
at the time
i could never really articulate a good reason why we had to have it
because no one was talking about security
we had it
because you know we had a unix heritage and unix unix systems had this
and
but deep in my bones
i felt it was the right thing to do
and at some point
uh
after many
many months of of arguing this
he said i
i said
steve
i can't give you a really good reason why we must keep this
other than i believe in my bones
we must have this
and he said
okay
just make it easy to use
which we did
and now
when you you turn on
auto
login
your mac logs in
automatically
right
it just works
i mean your phones have the concept of users in them
but you never see it
yeah
okay
um
and so
as time goes on
we ship the product
few more years go on
what happens
windows starts getting targeted by viruses
for the simple reason that you can download and install software
by just accidentally clicking on a link and nothing ever pops up to stop it
whereas on the mac
when you downloaded and click the link
that was going to do something that required any kind of privilege at all
it prompted you for your username and password
and that was one of the reasons the mac was spared so many years from getting these
and he realized many years after this decision
that trusting my gut feel
and i i couldn't articulate that reason
then
because that wasn't an issue
right
but it turned out to be one of these really smart things that we did that he agreed with
because he had a certain amount of respect for me and because he knew that
if i felt really strongly about this
even in this case where i couldn't articulate the reason he had to go with it
interesting
that's
and so you know
that's just kind of how he operated
but you know you really had to keep pushing on him to to to do
that to get him to finally agree
that was not easy
yeah
so that culture that you guys came into
i mean it wasn't a gil
amelo was a a creature of the semiconductor industry
and he had sort of cobbled that on top of the apple culture
i remember
when i interviewed steve early on
he described the first time he saw gil's executive dining room at apple
and you know
he told me about the silver
and how shocked he was at the silver and how that had gone away
um
how hard
i mean
how
what were the cultural things like when you first came into the the
the
you know the into apple
there was definitely those things you talk about
um
you know
food was plated into a really fancy dish and and things like that
not that i mean that might happen if i were to go to a board meeting
and there was lunch being served
if i was just getting lunch on my own
i'd go to the cafeteria and get it
like most people there were
there was definitely some of those things
and to me
you know
my prior career had only been in a small company
startup
next right
or academic situation
where you don't get any of that stuff
and i just thought well
whatever
i mean
who cares
right
i mean i'm here to build products
and if they want their dinner or lunch served on a nice piece of china
great
who cares
right
it's a big company
we got lots of money
i guess in the scheme of things it
it doesn't matter
but
um
i don't know that that was really a cultural thing that hurt the company from a product perspective
i think
instead
um
the
i don't know if it's a cultural thing or a management issue
what what really hurt the company was
um
it had gotten very successful on a product that was paying all the bills and completely lost focus
and had a bunch of truly smart people who are off pursuing their own things without any cohesive strategy
and and no leadership
really figuring out
well
what do we do
what's important to do
and you know every decision could be second guess and cause massive debate and decisions would not be made
or even worse
you could have two really smart people completely working against each other
and that that's really what the problem was
and when you came in
i i'i've forgotten now were
were tagan and kida completely gone already by that time
or were there still sort of vestiges of that
did you have to
sort of
you know
carve that away
um
those were not things i had to carve away
they may have still been around in some minor form
but it was
they were not issues
all the issues that i had to deal with were
you know
90 plus per internal issues
yeah
building a a new software design culture at the company
is
i me
it was
um
the issues were at multiple levels
so there there was the sort of management of people level
and then there was the strategy level and the management of people level was one of
um
well
there's also operations
um
the management of people issue was
we had a lot of smart people who as i just mentioned
really weren't working on the same team
they were working for their own interests
and they all thought what they were doing was the right thing
um
and they needed someone to step in and say fundamentally
well
this is what we're doing
the decision's been made
either
you're you
i don't care if you agree or disagree with the decision
but this is what we're working on
and if you agree with it
great work on
if you don't agree with it
then just say you don't agree with it
but that you're going to support it and work on it or leave the company
and that process caused a lot of people to leave the company
because they could not get on board with the decisions that were being made
and they suddenly realized that their side projects or their efforts to derail
these decisions were not going to be successful
um
and so they left or they were fired
or whatever
some combination thereof was
apple labs still around
was that
one of the things that was
it was called
i believe apple research and we shut it down
not because we didn't like research
but because from an operational perspective
we had to have all hands on deck working on the products that we thought were important
yeah
and so we could no longer afford to fund it and we could no longer take the risk
if you will
that they'd be going off in directions that didn't match what the company was going to do
especially when they're spending money the fact was they were spending money
we needed to spend that money on the things that needed to get done
remember
we're losing a lot money at this point in time
we don't have a lot of luxuries to do things like basic research
i remember
you know
one of those technical debates was over the uh executable format for os10
there was this mao versus uh pf format
um
i remember being oddly honious
uh
at the time over something that seems kind of trivial or not so important in the long run
so i don't remember that specific technical back and forth
if you will to be generous
um
but there were many like that
and
um
generally
you know
i would like to believe that every decision we made was the right one
for the right reasons
so good technology
um
you know
the right technology
good fit with customers
um
standards based
or if not
whatever
whatever is appropriate for for what it is
all those kinds of things
but
uh
we definitely had
um
a lot of passion inside the company for different things
and the hardest thing was there
there
there were many times where we picked the technologies that were
it was next versus apple
if you will
okay
and the next technology was picked instead of the apple technology
and it was usually because the next technology could be shown to be demonstrably
superior in a number of ways
but people didn't want to believe that was the reason
because they just thought the apple side was losing
that was not the case
and you know there were probably a couple cases where here here's the issue
a lot of times
when these decisions were made
it meant there would need to be some kind of transition with customers or developers
because the technology was changing
and that caused angst for people advocating keeping things the way that apple had done it before
and um
let me give a great example of this networking
the networking standard for apple at the time was apple talk and apple talk was just wonderful
networking for a land and there were ways to make it work beyond the land
but it was kind of tricky
it was designed for a land
and in a land it worked great
it was way better than tcpip
but the rest of the world has standardized on tcpip and uh
it was obvious to me
and some others who weren't totally immersed with the appleway for many years
that tcpip was going to win all the battles
it was already winning the battles
and at the time apple had an apple team working on apple talk and their ip stack was outsourced
and so i said this doesn't make any sense
networking is a key part of the product
and oh
by the way
there's a standard networking stack that's open source
that's been in use for many years
and even if the standard isn't fully implemented in certain implementations
this one we know is interoperable because it's the same one everybody else uses
so we're just going to use this now just happens to be
that's what next was already using
so people look at that as a next versus apple decision
when it is
we are going to standardize on the networking of the future using the most standard
and oh
by the way
free software
and we're going to integrate that in
well
i got no end of complaints about that
they got
in fact
people went around me all the way to steve saying we're going to tank the company if we do this
and including the people who are selling us the stack
the software stack from the outside
they were making money off app
and so i just sat down
and i laid it out and said this is the standard of the future
number one and number two
this is the standard imple implementation
number three
it's free and open source
people will keep working on it
this is no-brainer decision
end of discussion
but it took an effort to get there
and and so the good news of that was
once
you know
usually i could just make these decisions myself
if there was still unrest in the masses and in this case there was a little bit
then
once i got bought in
then it was end of discussion
and i could usually get him to buy in on that
but there's a flip side of this
which is that um engineers and again
good engineers would come to me and they would say you can't do this
our customers know and love apple talk
they just plug in a new computer and it just works
and that doesn't work with tcp
i
it works with apple talk and they plug in a printer
it just works
i said great
so your job is to now make tcpip do this
and now
lo and behold
here we are today
20 years later using tcpip
everybody just plugs in their computer or their printers and devices and everything
and it just works
and that's
because we got motivated to fix a few problems
and fill in a few gaps with dcpip that didn't allow to do that before
and so the other point i made to them was what you're what you're advocating is a solution
that is going to keep 3 % of the addressable market
happy
that was the existing customer base
maybe it's 5
%
you're going to keep 3 to 5 % of the custo
the potential customer base happy
i'm like
look
i want to keep those people happy
but i w have a way to go get the other 95 %
and we can't get the other 95 % with something like apple talk
they just never going to buy it
okay
and you know we never got the other 95
%
but you look today and apple's doing pretty well
even with computers
yeah
and you know
there were some people they just couldn't get their head around this way of thinking
and they they either quit or were fired
yeah
and then the people that could
they said you know what
there's a few things wrong with tcpip today
but we know how to fix that
and we can work with the itf and change the standards and evolve it
and you know
do a few things with dhcp
and other standards
and fill in here
and fill in there and make some dns changes and we can make this all work
it does
yeah
go ahead was that
so clearly
embracing open standards and even incorporating open source was a big change in apple strategy
um
what motivated that was that something because of your
you know
because of nex
nex was already doing that was that just sort of natural
um
yeah
embracing open standards
um
and
uh
we even published some of our lowlevel source code at the time
that was a huge change for apple
in the history of apple never been done
it was something that steve wasn't all that jazzed about
um
but the the basic argument there was
we've got certain layers of software that have in the real world now traditionally become open source
in the sort of important demographics of users
developers
for example
um
and there's not really any downside to open sourcing
some of these things
and in the case of of implementing standards is lots of upsides
there's no need to have a closed network when you can now interoperate with everyone else
especially when you're not the majority player
um
and so it was a big change
uh
and it was not
it wasn't a no-brainer decision
but it wasn't a hard decision to make either
and
and remember
we always had the flexibility to control where we interoperated and where we didn't interoperate
and what we open sourc
but we didn't open source
we could control all those things ourselves
this may not have been in your portfolio
but one thing i saw in those first years
um
from the outside
as a reporter
is that apple started as a more open company
i remember maybe twice
coming down and interviewing you
um
and after the first two or three years
i mean it was you and phil and johnny
and i can't remember one other person
we just sat down
steve wasn't there and i was there
as a new york times reporter
i did a profile of johnny
i very early
um
and then the company gradually became a company that spoke with one voice
and i was that a strategy you were aware of
or did i mean
what did it look like from your side
so i hadn't thought about that very much
that's an interesting point
you raise
what i would say
is that
um
right after the merger
closed
while gil was still ceo
um
it was typical for many
many people to talk publicly
in fact
i remember
uh
that summer i went to paris to keynote apple expo paris
um
i don't remember exactly why i did it
i think
maybe because gil had done so poorly in january
they wanted someone else to do it
they sent me and
and so that was not really an issue
apple had lots of people out there in the press
um
if i were to speculate now i would say that maybe you're talking about a time
where steve is not really the ceo
he's interim ceo
yeah
i'm not sure
probably in ceo
and so he really does need other people to step up and talk
and so that's going to be the people you just mentioned that i
and then when he comes in to be ceo
then the lockdown starts to happen
yeah
it wasan
it was
i mean
i
i understood it
it wasn't
it
wasn't
you know
wasn't in my interest as a reporter
but i absolutely
i could see it working
um
right
from from steve's point of view
he was building
you know
a singular
uh
you know
he very clear
uh
picture of what apple was is
is what you got as a result
yes
um
so i'm interested in the in that still in the transition period
who were the sort of on the software side
the key players from next
and the
the people
the people who came in and took important roles
who who stands out in in your mind
so the key players from next
um
so at the time
it would have been brron stle
who is my right-hand man
basically brron brron basically took over what became mac os 10
uh
and turned that into the product
while i
i divided my time into some other areas like the classic mac os
quick time and other software projects
um
and so he was probably the key manager i had coming over from next
and then his key person would have been scott forall
and so you see that actual chain of who ended up taking over software over over the years
um
and and scott was sort of the right-hand man for a lot of what was the appkit
at the time
some of the built-in applications
things like that
they were sort of the key people that we brought over up front
initially
was there ever any question about as as the merger happened
about that role that you took as as senior vpf software
or was that part of the deal
did i mean
did that happen simultaneously
um
so the day the deal closed
i had a signed off for letter as senior vp of software engineering
so that part of it was
there's no question
um
what i think was more in question was
well
what are the actual responsibilities and how does this work in this huge organization
um
which we kind of worked out there was
you know
ellen hancock was still very much in the thought process of what strategy was and things like that
uh
still still held still
sort of had gil's ear on strategic decisions
um
which was causing a little bit of trouble to get things done
but we worked through that
yeah
and
um
what was it like to work for gil
you
you spent some time working for gil ailio
yeah
so working for gil
was interesting
i mean
i found him to be a very nice person
um
you know
i found him to really want to hear what i thought about everything
he was sort of a if you will
trying to be a sponge
trying to learn
cuz i was operating in areas he just didn't understand
he seemed somewhat frustrated that
um
everybody was always critical of everything he was doing rightly or wrongly
and so
and he gave me sort of free reign to do whatever i thought was right
um
he
really
you know it
when there were decisions where other people might be saying something that contradicted what i was saying
he would really listen to me and his gut was to go with me
and i think that was in part because he had just done the acquisition
he trusted me
but also because steve was telling him
trust
this guy
listen to what this guy's saying
what he says
makes a lot of sense
and so that was very helpful
so you know the negatives you hear about gil
i didn't directly experience myself
because i was doing my thing
that was independent
i didn't need his help to do what i wanted to do other
than to not get in my way
yeah
and what do you remember about the events that led to steve becoming io
okay
so the events to becoming io
let me see
if i remember the events correctly
okay
so we're
we closed the acquisition in february
um
gil is still ceo
steve is now adviser and um
steve is not happy with gil
clearly
um
he doesn't come out publicly and say that
but in the background you can tell that's the case
and the first thing that happens is shortly after the deal closes
probably in the march time frame
um
there is a sale of 1. 5 million shares of apple stock at 13 and a quarter
which is the lowest tick ever since
okay
that is the bottom price since 1996
this is pre-split like 28 times
yeah
equivalent of 50 cents a share
right
something
something like that
yeah
and no one knows who did it
okay
because these things aren't publicly disclosed
but i know
and the world knows that
as part of the acquisition
steve got 1. 5 million shares of stock and they restricted stock
but he'd asked for the restrictions to be taken off so they could be tradable
and most people thought that he was the one that did it
and i asked him point blank
was that your sale
and he wouldn't tell me
point blank
but he led me to believe that it was him
and so that was his public statement that he was not happy with gil in the company
because it was widely reported at the time or theorized it was probably him
yeah
probably remember that
um
and so you know
that was sort of steve's way of making sure that everybody knew that gil shouldn't be the ceo
and he did other things behind the scenes
and there was plenty of material for the board to come to the conclusion
that gil should not be ceo
um
so the board made that decision
i believe
um
in july
because i think fred anderson made the phone call to gil on the 4th of july saying
that he'd been fired
yeah
and funny aside
um
which i've heard from fred
so i believe it to be true
uh
is right after calling gil
he called hancock
who was also being fired to tell her she was being fired
and
um
she first said
he first said to ellen
i think
or something this
where
uh
gil is no longer ceo and she thought he he was calling her to make her ceo
but um
she was also being fired
so that was sort of
you know
that next step where fred takes over as acting ceo
um
the board had a confidence in him
and steve had confidence in him and steve was having enough conversations with the board
the board wanted steve to become to come in to be ceo
but he wouldn't do it
had pixar gone public at this point
where was i don't think i don't think pixar in public
was it until might have been 96 before that
yeah
or i don't remember it was around that time frame
it might have just g
head was pretty much in pixar at that point i remember
wasn't it
well
he never spent that much time at pixart overall
yeah
it was never more than a day a week
even when he was the busiest there
but i think he was sly thinking about it a lot u
but he was thinking about apple a lot too
trust me
he was thinking about apple a lot and he was working on these things behind the scenes
so it was
you know
at that time we have no ceo
ellen's gone
it's a lot easier for me and john rubenstein to kind of get down
what we think needs to be done
fred is going to let us do whatever we think is right
and steve is sort of there
kind of talking with us
making mak
sure things are kind of going
but he's not day-to-day but you know you can only go so long without a ceo
and finally the board somehow convinced him to become interim ceo
i don't know exactly what happened
but i think it's just this notion that
because he could be interim ceo it was kind of like a call option on the job
and so if if he saw the path to success
he would take the job if he worked on it for a few months
and said this is just not going to work
then he didn't have to get himself into it
fail at it
yeah
but i mean he dug right in and you know
he started making some big decisions that we were all supportive of
and you know
used his name essentially to to get behind what was going to go on things that were very unpopular
yeah
like what kinds of decisions
oh
um
like cancelling the um
the sabatical program right after a certain number
of years
everyone was entitled to a six
we sabatical
um
and remember there was this email that he forwarded to all of us
he'received no
there's an email that went around to the whole
he had sent an email to the whole company saying
uh
outlining a few things that were going to change
that was the sabatical
was one of them
and there were four or five other things
and then someone had forged another email and sent it to the whole company
that was sort of a parody of this saying
and you must now work 24 by7
or it was just it was
it was just horrible
it was horrible
was that that was
remember the park park
different controversy
yeah
was that around
well
that was sort of an ongoing joke
right
there's not one controversy
ongoing joke joke
okay
yeah
and there are plenty of pictures to document that
um
there are many stories of steve jobs in vehicular [laughter] violations
i
at what point
at what juncture did the microsoft investment happen
that was
um
that was that summer
yeah
it was
that was
um
it was just before ma world boston
whenever that was
the deal was done the night before
literally
um
because it was
it was announced the next day
remember with the uh
the
the video of bill gates and the front page
picture
in the new york times
with a little sten exact
the big brother bill
big brother
bill
that's right
so there's no time to rehearse to make sure it's going to look right
it
just that's the way it was
yeah
um
so that was probably might have even been that july that year
i think it was yeah
and were you in involved in that discussion
yes
i was
cuz
you know
we had
we had discussions related to
um
it was
it was a big deal
it was microsoft was investing
um
patent cross license happened
yeah
um
and
uh
we agreed to
um
we agreed to make ie the default browser on the mac
that's right
yeah
those were the sort of three big things
which later turned into an antitrust l
yeah
did you get
did you
did
you
did you get
did you have to test
you did have
yeah
that's right
as a second witness for the government
okay
um
let's oh so
and um
had you worked with
what was sort of
what was your working relationship with john rubenstein like
and when did you guys first start
so john and i started working together at
next
would have been when he joined next
i don't remember when it was
it
probably 90ish 91
is
uh
and john stayed there until we got out of the hard hardware business
went off and did firepower and then
um
in that period of time between signing the deal for the acquisition in december and it closing in february
we called up john and we had lunch with him in redwood city
we said john
we want you to come join us
obi's going to run software and and you run hardware
and he agreed to do it
and
uh
so we were sort of the hardware software team
um
and we worked together all the way through
we both resigned on
i think he resigned
his last day was like march 31st of 2006
mine was april 1st of 2006
we
didn't work closely enough to get him exactly the same day
um
but
so we worked together very closely for all those years
and you know
john and i had a wonderful yet strenuous
relationship
um
because we had to work together yet we often had competing goals
and so
you know
while he
his goal was to get a new hardware product out every 9 to 12 months
whatever the cycle was and have the software for it
my goal was to not worry about the hardware
schedu
just get the features right for the next release
and so we are always locking heads
um
we'd fight a lot about things and priorities and who's working on what
and
um
but we always figured it out
and you know we didn't miss our dates in any way that anyone knew
at least
um
and you know
we ship by working together
our teams ship great products
so so we always knew we had that common goal of our teams working together to ship great products
but behind the scenes
we had to fight a lot and you know
kind of keep our teams working together
yeah
when was it that you knew that
do you roughly remember
remember when you knew the turnaround had worked
was it around
was it around the pillow
imac
or was it around
hardware
was it around software
what
what was the sort of sense you know we've really was steve's return
when
do i
did i know the turnaround worked
i don't think i ever knew that
i mean
um
look
it was obvious
once the iphone started going off the the charts
okay
but even developing the iphone
it wasn't clear that the turn run had sort of worked
i mean we were obviously making money and being successful
and you know
we've
we've been selling
we've been selling a lot of ipods
and we've been selling more macs but still small in the grand scheme of things
right
and
um
the business is a tough business
it's a hit based business
right
and so you got to keep the hits coming
y
and it's a competitive business and you
you know
i guess maybe we felt things probably didn't feel as dire
once we were getting some traction with the imac
and once we had mac os 10 out there and customers really starting to use it
those were probably two two
you know
hardware and software events that really told us we didn't have to worry about
there's no existential problem
okay
um
but frankly we were still described in the press as the beleaguered copertino company
right
so i guess the interesting question would be to go back
and pull out all the press articles and find out
when bleer was taken off the name
right
yeah
i never fell into that camp
i remember
walt moser killed you off
remember the obituary on the front cover of the did walt do that
i don't remember
walt wrote an obituary for apple
well
it was the merc that was always the worst
yeah
there was
so i'll take your word that there was the walt one
i'm going to go look that up when i'm done here
there was obviously michael dell saying
just give the money back to the shareholders right
these are obviously low points
and um
so you know
i mean when [music] um
when 911 happened
we took a big hit
as did most of the economy
yeah
the valley
the whole valley did
and
and you know we were somewhat tenuous
anyway
we weren't the strongest company in the valley
and so at that point it's like whoa
what's going on here
yeah
right
and
and we felt pretty good
i remember
we did a small buyback at the time
um
just
you know
to show confidence and almost out of patriotism
um
but you know
we were shaken a little bit by what happened after that
you know
there was a time when the the cube came out
which was not a hit at all
and you kind of wonder
yeah
so it was
it was
there was never one point in time
even with the ipod
i mean the ipod start out relatively slow and it built up time
and you know
it did okay
and then had a big bump up when we released the windows version
and you know
brought more people into look at and stuff
but these were all slow things
yeah
so there was a moment where probably where i gained my most greatest respect for steve as a strategist
and it was
it was an interesting sense
um
he telegraphed to me this switch to intel a year before it happened
as like this chess match in the in the computer industry and i didn't get it
until you guys made the switch and it was about
you know
video games
going to the power pc architecture and p p going to the intel architecture
and he
we had a conversation like a year before
where that was all in his head
he knew he was going there
and he said something to me when i looked back
he had sort of told me it was going to happen
and do you remember the strategy component of that
well
so him telling you a year in advance is only a surprise in
that you're a member of the press
and he would tell you something that's coming
but he did he didn't really
it was looking backwards
i didn't get
he didn't actually tell me he said something in retrospect
remembered that it was obvious to him a year before that it was going in that direction
that's because we already had it working
yeah
so one of the things about being in tech right is when a product is announced
it was already working well before that
and so the people who were already working on it knew that it's coming now
he may not have known the exact date
but as far as i was concerned
we were working on that product the day i started at apple in 97
and and we had software running on all the macs throughout all those years years
yeah
um
and was that about options at that point to give you flexibility
or what i mean in terms of that strategic relationship and all of that
you know
ibm ultimately couldn't deliver the
was it 10 gigahertz processor that they promised
yeah
i don't remember which processor it was
but
um
for me
having our software running on an intel processor at some point in time was inevitable
and so it always was about options and how we would execute those options
and so i didn't know if
like
at next
we got out of hardware business
apple would have to get out of hardware business as a really radical change
right
in which case
we'd have software to oem to different people
or we'd be in the hardware business
maybe building premium computers
which apple's always been great at with someone else just doing a super lowcost computer right
which would probably be based on an intel processor
there are a whole number of or or what eventually happened
which is just to switch the heart of the mac to an intel processor
when the other vendors couldn't compete
um
on whatever access mattered
and so
um
to me it was inevitable
and so i viewed my job as running software to make
i knew that at some point in time steve was going to say i need this product
okay
and i knew
starting from scratch
it was a 3 to five year effort because of everything involved
okay to port an entire os and do emulation and everything else
and so i knew i had to have it ready so that
when it was time to pull the trigger
we could get it out in 9 to 12 months
okay
which is what we ended up doing
yeah
that's remarkable
the
uh
the end of newton and then the roots of what became the iphone
um
what
what did it look like from the inside
okay
so the end of newon
that was one of those um
straightforward decisions
where only a handful of people second guessed it
people in the newton division
you know
interesting technology
no market traction
after a long time spending a lot of money on it
we got to focus
okay
wasn't clear where the volumes were going to be here
so that was relatively straightforward
relatively easy
although it it did take a while to get that to happen
and that was in part because newton was off in a separate division
neither john nor i own that
if either one of us had owned that
it would have been gone instantly
um
but it was kind of off on some side with other management
they were just kind of keeping it alive
um
longer to kill off
like printers
and other things that were just hanging on that needed to be killed off at the time the iphone
um
was interesting in that
i remember
the first time i thought we would seriously think of doing an iphone someday was
when we introduced a feature in mac os 10 called um
i think it was the dashboard feature
that is the feature
where you press one of the keys on the keyboard
and and it brings up a bunch of widgets on your screen
remember
yeah
so there's a
there was a weather widget
a stock widget and you could add other widgets
there's all kinds of a little calculator widget quickly
bring them up use them
throw them away and i remember
i looked at that and i said to myself and i
the team were
the first time our ui team showed this to us
i remember saying saying
oh my god
someday we're going to build a phone and that's going to be the user interface
it's going to be these little widgets
and oh
by the way you take out your iphone today
and it still has that very same stock widget and very same weather widget written the exact same way
using little javascript stuff
and so that was
probably
um
got
got to be early 2000s
yeah
and along with that
and i forget the ordering of these things
we had done some experiments with tablets using multi my touch
and so
um
our lead guy doing a lot of our user interface stuff had built this prototype
where
using multi-touch um
you could with multiple fingers drag a map and zoom in and spin it around
and all this kind of stuff
and we thought that was totally cool
and so the hardware guys built some prototype tablets
a few dozen of them
maybe
um
that did a few of these things and i had one in my office and i'm sure john did
and steve
we all used them
um
but this was just when we were getting wi-fi out there
so it must have been early 2000s
when the ibook came out with wi-fi
i don't think we had wi-fi in this
um
it it might have
but i don't
it probably did have wi-fi
but that was it
so this product was only useful in a couple places
where you could get wi-fi you couldn't get wi-fi very many places right
wi-fi was still unusual
no one had it at home and there was no data
ms that were useful
so we thought
hey
this tablet's kind of interesting in
except that it's not useful
and this was back when other people were trying to ship tablets and finding there's no market for it
for the reasons
i just describ
there's no connectivity to anything
so we shelv all that
so we sheld that and we we kept going on the widget stuff
we kept improving that
and then at some point it just started to make sense
that you could in the form factor of a phone have enough processing power in a multi-touch display
and add the software to it and have it actually work
yeah
now
when we started working on this
i don't know
whatever it was somewhere in there
no one really knew it was going to go
yeah
it was just was another ipod
like project we're going to try it
we're going to see what happens
yeah
were you around for the debate about about
you know
at that point the
uh
the blackberry had
um
rim had
sort of
you know that was becoming
i think it was
it was out there in the world
uh
this notion of this chicklet keyboard
um
i heard that there was an internal debate about whether you would have a virtual keyboard
or whether you would actually have a a physical
as a matter of fact
i heard that phil schiller was on the wrong side of that debate
that that he was committed to to keeping a keyboard in the were you in those debates
so there was not much of a debate
i mean there's always debate about everything
and let's just say the extent to which there was such a debate
it didn't matter
because the decision had been made
there was going to be no keyboard
and so you can keep talking about it
you bw in the face
and i don't know if phil did or didn't
i don't
i honestly don't remember
but you know
the advantages of no keyboard and a complete display were obvious and it was one of those steve jobs
you know
there's going to be no rescue boats
we're going to
this
is it
you're
g to
we're going to
you know everything's going to be bet on this
it's make or break it
it's either going to work or not
because when you put the keyboard on
you're going to make decisions that are not good decisions
okay
it's like going back to the tcp typ thing
well
this is what we're going to do
make it work really well
okay
and if if it doesn't work really well
well
you screwed up
yeah
and so there was no
there was no serious decision to be made
the decision been made
yeah
what was your role
um
during that whole period
so by the time the serious work got going on the iphone
i was mostly on the way out
so my role was mostly
i would say
almost
i don't remember
my role was heavily to make sure the soft strategy was right
and
um
we had
that that was a project scott forstall took on himself to pretty much own
and from the software perspective to make happen
um
and my goal was just to make sure the software was going in the right direction
and then let scott and the team deal with it all
yeah
and then the
the kind of the
what's the right way to describe it
um
was there always tension between tony fidel and scott forall
was that an always a contentious relation relationship
um
gee
i don't know if i should answer that question
it's okay
um
yeah
i probably
i mean
tony and scott are both great guys who have it's
it's like me and john
we would argue a lot
but at the end of the day we'd come to terms to make the right decision to get things done
yeah
and let's just leave it at that
um
we didn't ask about
so the raps city to mac os
uh
transition
could you talk a little bit about that
um
how did it evolve over time
yeah
so
i mean you know
the rap city to mac os transition was larg
a marketing thing
right
i mean that's about
we can go from mac os8
um
which was just coming out when we all joined apple to mac os 9 and then mac os 10
it
it was a great marketing story
we're just completely upgrading all the technology in a way that is as seamless as possible to users
there are multiple layers of compati ab ility
built into it
and so
instead of just you know
telling customers something completely different
it's just transition
like with the hardware
one day a mac had a power pc the next day it had an intel right
but it was still a mac
yeah
i remember the
the key difference from the way that rap cid had been pitched initially to um
to the rebranding as os 10 was the availability of carbon
and initially he had tried to sell rap city at being completely based on the next apis
or the yellow box
as you'd called it
um
and it seemed like there was a lot of developer push back
and then carbon carbon was announced the the next year
what was the process like of getting of
you know of getting carbon up and how critical was carbon to the success of os 10
yes
so the issue was to release a new os
you have to have a way for developers to bring their apps forward
and we had what was called the blue box
which could run a traditional mac os app
just in an emulation mode
if you will
but that really wasn't good enough to letting mac apps take full advantage of the new os
and when we talked to a lot of the big ones
adobe
microsoft
and others
it was clear they had good reasons why they couldn't just switch over to the new apis
it was a lot of work
and so with them we basically agreed to build an emulation layer called carbon
which was a large part of the mac toolbox um
running on quote on quote
rap city
if you will
giving them the way to link against the new api to get most the advantages of the new os
now we were able to pull this off in part because little known secret is
if you go back in time and think about quicktime
quicktime was a mac application which also ran on windows
and the way they ran it on windows was
by porting a reasonably large portion of with the mac toolkit over to windows
so they had made a reasonably large portion of it portable
um
and so we started with some of that
and added a lot to it to really make it more complete
and came up with a whole carbon layer as
well
i had forgotten this but there was this um idea of um
open step
yellow box for windows
but that never really what be
what became of that
do you remember
yeah
so that would have been continuing the open step for windows product that next had
and never became that important
never became strategic to the company
yeah
so it wasn't pursuit
and
um
the turning going from mock to darwin
how how challenging was that
well
mock to darwin is no change
say
darwin
darwin is the mock kernel that we used open
sourced
okay
so you know
we obviously
over the years made many
many changes to it and add the unix
later
the free bsd unix later into that
that's what darwin
was
yeah
was it difficult to to to act to open source
it
um
i assume you mean from a sort of philosophy or philosophical perspective
it
it wasn't that hard because large parts of it
you know
both mock and unix came from open source environments to start with
so it's very natural to do that
yeah
and um
i i remember
you know
when os 10 shipped
um
carbon and cocoa were
uh
the message was that these were both both peer frameworks
they were both considered native and they would for the foreseeable future
both be going forward
um
obviously
in the long run
that wasn't going to be the case
um
but at that point in time like
where did you see the sort of arc for how long carbon would be continuing to be supported
um
everything you said is completely correct
carbon and coco were both peers
if you will
um
there was
at least in the early days
there was no plan to sunset carbon anytime soon
um
and yet we wanted to make sure that people transition
so you didn't really see new features coming out on carbon whereas you did on coco
and
uh
you saw efforts to get
we kept pushing developers on the coco
because there were many advantages to doing that
and
um
it
you know
i
i don't know if there was even a specific actual phase out date for carbon
to be honest
i
i don't
i don't remember when
maybe maybe there was
but it's not like we're actively trying to get rid of it right
i think it was when
um
when os 10 went full 64bit
and the coco went 64 bit and carbon wasn't and there was a big brew haa over that
that that's possible
yeah
it's possible
okay
um
from your perspective
what was coco's big advantage over carbon
why was it the the way to go
well
i mean that's a
that's a complex complex question
well
that's a question with a complex answer
and maybe the most succinct answer is just to say
when you wrote an app in coco
you were almost always guaranteed to have all your features work correctly
and consistently with the rest of the system with carbon
you weren't
because with coco
you would do a very high level call and everything would just work
you would get a complete text editor without writing any code
and that text
eder head the same feature in every single app with carbon
all those things have to be built from scratch
they're always all different
yeah
so it really contributed to consistency
i remember
at some point i don't remember what year
bud tribble
coming to berkeley
we were both speaking
he gave a talk
and i remember i was just so stunned that he at one point said you know
something like
50 % of the lines of code in macos are actually open source
he was talking about the bsd component
i'm 50
%
is what sticks in my mind
but it was
it was such a
you know
since
to the outside world
who knew you know it was
it was
it was hidden
um
but it was all there
and i was just wondering
i guess the
the question is
um
the
the attitude that apple had toward open source when you were when you were running the show
what the attitude was definitely mixed
um
you know
the company's history had always been to be closed
uh
with some good reasons
and so you know
we just
we just became pragmatic about it
and in those areas
where it made sense to be open source and you could clearly see benefits with minimal risks
we would do it
um
and other
would
wouldn't even talk about it
why bother talking about it just wasn't worth it
may i ask a question
yeah
um
i would
i would be interested to hear you describe those
let's just say
the first five years that you were at apple
what is a day like for you
you know
um
you're
you're tackling some really big engineering projects
um
and i'm just interested to hear you describe
like how you the role you played in making them happen
you know
were you in meetings all day
were you walking around
um
if you could give us some of of what it was like to be there and and doing that
it seems like most of my days would either be
um
i've got
we didn't have our online calendars
so i had
i'd have my note card with my list of meetings for the day
and they'd be all backed up to five
just because there was so many meetings you had to do
or i'd be traveling somewhere for customer visit or conference or who knows what
um
so
and in
you know
then
in the evenings there'd be dinner and then emails after dinner
whatever
so it was just
it was a very busy time now that having been said
um
i would have to say that the time was spent in really useful ways
making important decisions
whether it's in an executive team meeting
we're deciding on the strategy of the company or reviewing user interface
which could be a three to four hour meeting
that's just all back and forth
it's
i mean you barely think of it as a meeting
you're just meeting with your colleagues reviewing their work
giving them feedback stuff like that
really high impact kind of interactions
um
and it would be
you know
there was obviously the management
the direct management part of it
you know
meeting your all your reports
one-on ones and figuring out status and challenging them to do really well
all those things
um
but i think if you step up a level
it was sort of this combination of this man
we're in this position where we can do something really important
okay
we can really change what people do in their
what
people
having their deadly lives through technology
and yet this difficulty of making it work
you know again
the baguer company in copertina
right about to go out of business
yet
that's what the outside
inside
it's like working on this really cool stuff
that's better than anything else out there and it's going to make so many people so happy
right
and so there were these two competing things and it was a almost like a daily grind
where you'd have
oh my god
this is so great
this is going to be so cool
when people get to use it versus we're about to go out of business
and this was a daily occurrence for all those years
yeah
um
go ahead
yeah
uh
i guess you know related to this
um
you know
during those first couple of years
uh
you know you were still having to make sure that the classic macos os8 and os9
um
there was still work going on
then to keep that going
at what point
um
did you decide
okay
we can stop working on os9 and put all our eggs behind
uh
os 10
um
the strategy with os8 and then os9 was to incrementally improve it as long as we needed to
which meant until we could get sufficient traction with mac os 10 that we didn't need it anymore
and we didn't know how long that was going to take
so we had a whole team devoted just to doing that
and what happened was
um
just something very natural where
when i first got there
got there
we staffed that team up very heavily
a lot of people working on that it was was paying the bills and as the years went on
we would just gradually transition people off that team onto the os10 team
and i don't remember when we turned the lights off on mac os 9
to be honest
i can't remember when the last release was
in fact
it may have been because we switched to intel processors
to be honest
obviously it wasn't going to run on intel processors
um
but there may have been maintenance releases on most maxs right up until then
just because we could
but we we had a team dedicated to making that that work
and we
we
that team knew that over time they could transition onto the os10 team in a meaningful way
yeah
what was refreshed me on the arc of web objects
and and you know
did
did web
did web objects come over for a while or did it go immediately
yeah
great web objects became an apple product and apple sold it for a while
um
web objects was used internally
quite a bit at apple to build some of the internal it systems
i believe it was used for the first online store
um
i rically have been used for dell's online store
but over time it just out of neglect
probably it never really went anywhere and just died
a slow death
cor strategy was elsewhere
yeah
exactly
even though there had been so much potential
if that had been next direction
you said
yeah
you know
it's one of those things that really required a startup like company to keep investing in
and have it be super important
it was never going to be material to apple
yeah
so it just died off when you got into the
you know you've been at a small company all of a sudden were at apple
what did the competitive land landscape look like
i guess
either through your eyes or steve's eyes
in terms of
you know who the competitors were that mattered
you know
all it had been sun to certain extent
maybe ibm
those guys
all of a sudden you were in a consumer world
and who were the the people you cared about in in a way
while things changed
it didn't change
now
clearly
microsoft was more of the direct competitor
but you know we had spent a long time building a consumer os
and that's what we were still now doing
and so that wasn't that big of a change
arguably
the bigger change was operating on a different scale
cuz
the numbers were all much bigger
um
and ironically
i was warned that i would never succeed
because the scale of apple was much bigger than next and it wouldn't wouldn't be able to work whatever
um
but you know
software is one of those things that scales pretty pretty easily and pretty well
um
so that proved to not be too much of a problem
especially when you've got a good team working on things
yeah
what were the internal dynamics
um
that led you to
did apple have to let you testify at the antitrust trial
was that a discussion inside apple
or was that a personal decision of yours
um
the way that came to be
was
um
i think it was netscape that had taken the lead with the government on driving that lawsuit
and
uh
so the government was looking to build its case
so looking for other people to testify on their behalf
and obviously apple made total sense
right
having been in the crosshairs with microsoft for so many years
the the deal to bundle ie was an interesting part of that
um
and so i
what i believe happened at the time was they were trying to get steve jobs to testify
i see
and he said no way that's not going to happen and he volunteered [laughter] me
makes it very simple
so i had to do it
did
did ever cross paths with um
i think he was sort of your equivalent
a little bit
no
it was maybe one step below steve mcy at intel who also test
he was the one who
oh
yeah
what was his
i mean he gave the quote to me and i'm forgetting what his quote was
um
it was about burying
oh
we'll cut off the oxygen supply
that was right
i don't think i ever talked to him
and they were pretty good about not wanting witnesses to talk to each other
yeah
okay
um
the actual event and going to washington and stuff
do you remember anything about it in particular
was it was it fun
was it like terrible
uh
it was an incredible experience
um
the
i mean i
i
i think just testifying in any court case is probably pretty unusual but in this case it was like over the toop unusual
and i remember
um
so once it was decided that i would be the person to testify
we hired someone to represent me
um
and so he starts doing his work and so he he meets with me and he says
so
a
i want to tell you they put my name in as a witness
and so immediately microsoft starts sending subpoenas
and he said i want to tell you that microsoft has subpoenaed all your personnal records and i'm like
okay
why would they do that
he's like
well
they're going to look for something to use against you
he's like i've got your personnel records here and he added a folder
which was basically empty
he's like
why is your folder empty
and all that was
there was like a review in there from bud from like 1989
maybe 1990
a couple couple of pieces of paper like that
i'm like
well
i don't know
that's my hr file
i don't anything about it
i've never seen it
but yeah
i don't normally get reviews and whatever
so apparently this was a good thing
but that was the reality
and how difficult was the cross
do you remember anything about the cross
um
well
the
yeah
my part of the my part of testifying was actually
it turned out to be relatively straightforward
um
and it's because we literally spent months in preparation
so i almost had to like
stop doing my job for a while and work with the lawyers for months
yeah
on documents that are being produced
and what does this mean
what does this mean they're going to use this
they're going to use this
and it was
i mean room fulls of documents to go over
and
um
so you know
during my no
during the cross examination
very early on
something interesting happened where the person that was questioning me asked me a question very early on
and i gave a fairly long-winded answer
that was not good for microsoft
it was not good at all
it was
you know
i clear
provided more information on this guy wanted
that was not good and he immediately said to said to the judge
your honor
may i request that the witness keep his answers to the question
and the judge immediately said
i think that's exactly what he did
so at that point i felt as though i had kind of went over the judge and uh
he started asking me questions directly
which was virtually unheard of
where
remember
one of the big issues was
um
the bundling of the browser into the os
the embedding of it
which today nobody does right
and microsoft was arguing that it was absolutely required
so the judge turned to me at some point
and asked me my opinions for if he thought it needed to be embedded
and we're
we're just having this dialogue
and the guy cross-examining me is like twiddling his thumbs wondering what's going on here
so that part went okay
but still it was extremely stressful
you know it was one of those things where you walk to the front of the courthouse
the federal courthouse in washington dc
you know the capital is up on the side on one way
what the white house is on the other side and you see these
um
you know big scaffoldings with cameras
and news crews and cnn and cnbc and and all that kind of stuff
and and then so i'i'fly there
i'd fly home for the weekend
oh yeah
we watched you on tv all weekend or all all during the week
cu
like every 10 minutes
it's the news thing
yeah
so it was
it was kind of incredible
it's amazing
tell us about the transition to becoming
um
oh
sorry
um
i was wondering how impactful do you think your testimony was in that case
you know
there's there's no way to know
but given that the judge found for the government
right so the government want its case
and given the way he personally interrogated me
and given what i could say
well
you can have a browser in with the os
but you don't have to have it built in the way they've done it
i think that was
i'm told
that was pretty damaging to their case
but who knows
for sure
i mean there were many
many other witnesses
many
many other considerations
yeah
i wanted to ask about the transition to becoming chief software technology officer
and what what that meant
and what did it signify um
so that was the result of
so
i think we're
we're talking around 2004 now
and so so i had been in charge directly of software for seven years
and i'd been in charge of software and effectively leading software
for a long time
at next
nine years
right
so that's about 16 years in the trenches
on the line
delivering products
you know
under the microscope of steve jobs
and so somehow we got into discussion and it's like
you know
i've had enough of this
and let's find another way for me to keep doing kind of what i do
and so we came up with this chief software technology office officer job
um
which we both thought was a great
it was as simple as that
it was like you know i've been doing this a long time
but i don't want to leave the company
he doesn't want me to leave the company
um
and you know
let's give brron a shot to run this
um
and that's simply how it happened
and and response to david's question about what you did during your day
i wanted to ask two sort of follow on one is
did you ever find time to manage by walking around
were you
were you a manage by walking around
kind of person
or was that valuable to just wander out amongst the programmers
you know
i want to say yes
because or walking around with the programmers yes is
i want to say that
yes
because it sounds like the right thing to do
but programmers
they're in their office with the door closed
focused on their screen
okay
they don't want you knock it on their office unless you've got a good reason to
so what i would do instead was have a strong presence
either with a communication meeting
talking with everyone
filled in questions or in review meetings where there were lots of people
even 40 people reviewing a product being part of that process
asking questions using all the products
filing bugs for specific engineers
against certain parts of the project
doing all those kinds of things
which is a form
i guess
of walking around but not literally walking around
so i was very much in the stream of consciousness of lots of people
but in a way that's a little bit perhaps unusual or non-standard and then
you know
the kind of day you described
where you're basically interacting and responding all day long and even into the evening
when you became
um
the
the software technology offer did
did you actually get the time to think more than the next product release
i mean i
and what's that
like
i mean to to actually think more than one generation into the future
yeah
so that was a total change
the days were not booked
al all day solid
i didn't have any direct reports anymore to deal with
and brron dealt with all that
and i could just kind of go around and literally poke on things
and you know i'd hang around with steve and see what products he's looking out
review things
which was sometimes good
sometimes bad
um
and
and you know
i
i did think more strategically
i let me step back
and do things like talk to people about what the software strategy for iphone should be
how we can do that
cuz we had options there and and a lot of other things like that
you know
be more perspective about the intel switch
things like that
yeah
um
this is
this is um hansen's question
because i don't know enough about it
it says
he says
how difficult was it to convince steve that the itunes store had to be on windows
um
so that's actually getting the ipod on windows
getting the ipod on windows was the key thing in the store
yeah
they all go hand in hand
um
it was
it was about putting itunes itself on windows
which ena the ipod to work on windows
and you know it was
it just took time
it took time and it it took some numbers
you know
i
i give that decision credit to phil
um
phil did a lot of leg work to really show what the opportunity was
uh
by moving it over to windows
and you know
at some point
when steve is the only person in the room saying don't do it
and there's good data from marketing saying this makes a lot of sense
and everybody saying this makes a lot of sense
he gets convinced
yeah
but it took a while
so so culture
i remember being kind of crest fall with steve
i remember that the itunes product
you know
announcement and getting my 15 minutes and going in there
and and steve had clearly gone such an entertainment direction
he could see that that's the way the product was going to grow
and i was still back in that camp of
you know
the computer is a bicycle for the mind
and you know
you know i wanted to see the next version of hypercard
which was was dead
and he obviously understood what was happening in the world
and i don't know
do you understand that kind of d dichotomy that that the
the pc was becoming an entertainment device or computing was becoming entertainment centric
well
you're probably talking now about the whole um digital hub strategy
yeah
right
photos
movies
music
all with computers at the center
yeah
i mean that was just that was one of the things where steve was
um
really good at putting together a general message or a good message to explain why we're working
we're working on
and so you know
why do you have fire wire
you have fire wire
so you can get fast
io to a camcorder
right
and you know you have to have your music somewhere to sync it
at least back then you had to sync from a computer
and you want your photos to organize on your computer
so it all makes sense
as a nice package
it could
he could have come up with something else as well
it just happens to be the one that he thought thought of
based on the things that we were working on
that all looked promising
yeah
how much were you involved in in shepherding the development of itunes
um
i wasn't that involved in itunes
itunes
was
uh
done
after we acquired
um
uh
what was the name of the app
sound
jam
yeah
sound jam
and so we acquired sound jam
and then that morphed itself into
i
right
um
what
what led you to decide to leave
okay
so after after being the chief software technology officer for a little while
um
he was almost three
wasn't it
three years
it was close to three years
maybe
yeah
so
a while into that
it was becoming frustrating for both me and for steve
and it was frustrating because i was there to offer my opinions on things
and that was not good for steve because steve wanted to offer his opinions on things
and so we'd go from review to review to review
and he wanted it to be the steve jobs review show
but i had my own ideas and sometimes we'd agree
sometimes we'disagree or sometimes we just talk about different things that are completely complimentary
and so there was this tension
um
and i like to to think of it in terms of
of
steve
was never the kind of person that had a staff person working for him
just kind of doing things to help him out
was
that was
he was always hands-on um
he wanted to be the person that knew all the functions and the only person knew all the functions
but if i'm now following him around a lot and i'm learning all the different functions too
he's kind of giving up a little bit
so it was kind of
it was a little bit stressful for both of us
and like we had known each other for so long that it was just
it was kind of working
uh
um
but you know
there was that
and there
this other
unfortunate
um
mostly unfortunate thing where
on the executive team
i was the person that had the least responsibility by a large margin
um
i didn't have any day-to-day product that i was worried about
whereas everybody else around the table
oh my god
i got to get this thing done this week
or we're going to fail
right
or huge issues
even illegal
there were huge issues
because every week there was a bunch of lawsuits right
um
and so i think you know no one
no one actually complained to me
but i think there was some back channel to steve that my job was too easy
okay
for still having that kind of a role
and so for all these reasons we just kind of decided
the best way to resolve this is for me to just quit leave the company
because then all these issues go away and i'm adding some value to him
but you know he's going to figure these things out for himself for the most part
anyway
yeah
right
and so we just kind of mutually agreed that that was the best result
um
solved a lot of problems
in you haven't asked
but i'll tell you in retrospect
i think it was a huge mistake for both of us and
um
neither one of us could have known at the time
of course
um
but we probably should have
and
and i think it was a huge mistake for both of us because
well
for me
i mean i left just before the main inflection point of the company having massive success
okay
and so part of me misses being there to experience that part of it
having laid all the groundwork for it
you know what i mean
i do
and and i balanced that against
it was hard working there
but having a similar role like that
that would have worked well
like like with other types of ceos
maybe it would have been interesting
okay
so that that part was wrong for me
and it was wrong for steve
because i think he really lost something
by not having me around to just bounce ideas off or get sanity checks on
or whatever
whether it's things going on in the market or things going on in the organization
and especially
as the years went on
he became sicker and it was harder for him to do everything he wanted to do
i think you know i could have helped out even more
so i mean it didn't hurt the company at all
it didn't really hurt me right
um
we
we're
the company's fine
i'm fine
but in retrospect
i do think it was a mistake for both of us
yet
because of who we were
it was just hard to make it work
did you ever have a chance to have the conversation with him
that conversation with him after never
never
no
and when you left
did you have a clear idea of what you would do after leaving
um
when i left i assumed i just going to retire
which is basically what i did
yeah
okay
you know
i thought maybe there was a chance that i would take on another operating job
maybe as a ceo of a midsize company
that would take a chance on me as a ceo
um
but i also knew that it would have to be something really exciting to want to take it
yeah
because you know there's no amount of money they could have offered me to make me want to take it
so have to be something i really want to do
and i i really enjoyed not being in a situation of those n9 to5 meetings
under the gun
to ship a product
all the time
you know
people always complaining to you about who knows what
yeah
did you get a lot of offers for the kind of jobs you didn't want to do
uh
no
not really
yeah
no
interesting
because you're the l
i'm
i'm surprised because you have a set of talents that is kind of unique in the valley
well
it's
it's probably the case that
um
i never
lots of recruiters called and i never return the calls
okay
so so that answers the question
yeah
there
there was
probably
i mean there were definitely ct
many cto type jobs out there where there'd be some cryptic message
from a recruiter which i would just delete
yeah
many
many of those
i mean i did do some boards
i still do some boards
that's a different kind of thing
that's a a more natural thing to do
but never
really
i mean there were
come be cto of this huge company
i'm like
i have no interest in doing that at all
yeah
so i don't even consider that to be an offer
i never got
nothing ever got to that stage
i'm
i'm conf
confused on timing
were you gone
um
both
before the stock option
um
controversy
and were you gone before steve got sick
so um
i was gone before the stock option controversy
um
but i was there when he was sick
yeah
sorry
okay
yeah
and did i mean
to what extent
did you know
did sometimes people cut off people when they leave
did steve and you keep a relationship and did it get minimal
um
his general mo was that he spent his time with people who were useful to him at the time
and so i became not useful to him
yeah
and so i mean
if i ran into him
he would be friendly
in fact
i think
like month later i ran into him on a beach in hawaii
we're both vacationing our families at the same time
and he was fine and cordial
and all that
and if i were to send him an email on something
he would respond
yeah
um
but he really had no need for anything that i was doing at the time
and there was not really any reason for me to contact him
yeah
at least not all that much
and so we just kind of didn't keep in contact that much at the end of his life
when he got very sick
did you guys have have any contact
no
not really
yeah
no
and you know
i
i wish i had known just how sick he was like the month before
because then i would have initiated something
but i didn't
yeah
and the that you know when he sort of threw fred under the bus and all of that did
did
i mean you were
let's see
you became a partner
fred's after that
is that
right
yes
yeah
so
at the time i didn't really know many of the facts of what had gone on
i i knew some of them
obviously i was personally on the receiving end of some of the things
and i kind of knew what had happened there
and i'm just kind of reading what's in the press
yeah
um
but you know
look
i did not like seeing what happened to fred
um
but i really couldn't evaluate much of anything
at the time
anyway
yeah
um
would you just tell us a little bit of the story of elevation
how
how did it come to happen
yeah
so
um
fred anderson is one of the founders
and so i knew fred very well
of course
having worked with him at apple for many years very closely
we become great friends
and
uh
they founded their fund in i think 2006
and i was an lp in the fund
and so i got to know all the other partners
um
you know
roger
mamy
bono
mark bodnick and the others
um
and so
around the end of 2009
they asked me if i wanted to join them as an investor and i thought about it
and i
and it's like
actually
this is perfect
because in my quote retirement
i've been doing angel investing but not a lot of it
because as an engineer
i can find everything wrong with every business plan instantly
okay
so i can find every reason not to invest in a company without thinking very hard at all
so i wouldn't invest in very many companies
and
uh
and i found it to be somewhat of a lonely thing
because it was just me
and i'd have to meet entrepreneurs who didn't have offices and coffee shops was kind of weird
yeah
and i'm like
oh
this is great
you guys have a big fund you do big investments
the whole investment team love to join you and keep investing
and so i did
and and so we did
and did you get an area of responsibility in terms of the
you know
the technologies or the industry
or was it all
was it all
was it not that structured
completely unstructured
um
but obviously i was the technology expert
and so
whenever someone wondered is this likely to work
i would say yes or no
or try and figure it out
i i've known roger mamy in many roles over a long period of time
he must have been an interesting partner to have
yes
love
roger
he's a
he's a character
interesting
i have a question
um
did you ever consider starting a new company a startup
so i did start a startup
funny
you should ask that
um
and
uh
so i started started a startup
which failed
because it
was
it was
ahead of its time
um
i started a company
that was this idea
the idea was to use um crowdsourcing to predict the stock market
and so the idea is
the idea was if you could get lots of consumers to come to your website
and to tell you what they think about various companies
then you can predict the future stock price
so
uh
consider
if
uh
let's just use apple as an example
if people start basically sentiment analysis if people are feeling good about apple
because you're seeing a lot of people at apple stores
then that's going to be a predictor of good earnings
which is a predictor of the stock price going up
and so you would try to attract people to the website to get them to basically give you their sentiment
voting up
voting down
if you will
consumer type companies
and if you could collect enough data and you could data mine that
so it's crowd sourcing and big data
getting all the keywords in here in a crowd-based platform
right
cloud-based platform
you could now predict the stock market
but it preceded social networking and everything else
and so
just as we were starting to run out of funding
facebook started becoming interesting
and this would have been a great tie into facebook
where you're now sharing your thoughts
and getting other people to participate
and give their thoughts and have it you a certain amount of verality to it
but you know
we gave up on the idea and folded the company
so it it was a learning experience
did you come to market or did you not get
we had a website that was up and running
so it was working
we never got a lot of traction
what was the company called
it was called pick them
and what year was that
uh
this would have been we probably started in 2007
and we probably closed it down in 2009 or so
something like that
yeah
somewhere around then
c
can you give us your thoughts about
uh
tim cook as the
you know
the leader of apple and sort of you know what your
your perspective on tim is
yeah
so
uh
first of all
i consider tim to be a friend and i think he's just a tremendous individual
i think he has
um
really stepped up into the new role that he has as ceo
and
um
i've seen him grow a lot from when i knew him as a coo
in terms of the kinds of things he does
i think
um
what else do i think
you know
i think he's got an incredibly difficult job
um
running this huge company and trying to
you know
his
his background in operations
i think is very useful
because they have to keep the trains running on time with
that kind of magnitude whenever they have a new product that comes out
the scale at which it comes out is enormous and they can't afford mistakes
um
and i think under his leadership they've done a really good job of that
i think you know
if i were to be critical at all and i hate to be critical of tim again
he's a friend
i think he's doing a great job
i mean technology is not a strength right
and so
um
there's probably some innovation that they're probably not keeping quite the same pace of innovation they otherwise would
but what i like to say is they're staying ahead of the competition
and that's the most important thing
it's like staying ahead of the bear
staying ahead of your friend when the bear is chasing you right
so it doesn't matter how innovative they are
so long as they're ahead of the competition
and i think they've done a great job at doing that
yeah
um
what about
your
the
your successors in
um
in leading soft
for brron and scott
and now craig fed
so
uh
they're all friends of mine
we all work together right next
ironically
um
all very different individuals
i think they all have brought success to the job in a lot of different ways
you know
brron
of course
the techie of them all always worried about how the tech works
less about the management parts of the job
but again
good enough to do it
i thought
um
scott was an incredible person
incredible engineer
incredible manager
with
you know
a couple of issues that caused him to not get along with everybody all the time
um
and his style of management worked great
working for steve jobs
because steve was okay with conflict
and steve would mediate conflict and kind of make sure everything was taken care of without steve there
you know
scott's style of management was not always going to work best
even though i mean
scott
very often would make the right call at the right time
it was hard to see him ever making making a d callin
i remember
i mean i told scott many years before he got the job
just
you know
work on a few things here
getting along with people
don't just manage up
like you do with steve
a few things like that
and you're gonna have this job in a few years and he did
and you know some of the things i tried to get him to improve on
he didn't quite improve on enough
um
or else
i think he'd still be there and be very successful
but great guy overall
and i think he's perfectly happy doing other things now
anyway
craig
so craig
um
left and then came back
to take the job
and i think the world of craig as well
i think
uh
craig has a really good balance of understanding the technology and being a good manager
maybe one of the better balances of all of them
yeah
trying to remember
now
did you ever
you know
craig gets up on stage and does demos and stuff
did
did you have that role
did you
did you do demos
public
um
i did do some demos
so i would do them regularly at the wwc's
yeah
so they'd be a steve keynote and he'd invite me up for 5
15 minutes and do a demo with him
um
occasionally at a mac world
you know
over time
those things kind of dwindled and steve tended to do most of them himself
um
but i i did do some of them
yeah
those
as
as he perfected that
i mean
you know
from
i mean it started in the early 80s
but then it sort of ramped up and they became like rock concerts
i mean they
i mean
from from my perspective
it was like going to roide because it was a
it was a
you know
it was a staged event that was
there were even like the
you know
there were people cheered at the same things
one more thing became this kind of you know joke for a while and they were really quite amazing
uh
well
you guys in the press made it that way
right
so i mean it was a
it was a pr strategy
which is you keep things secret
you unveil it all at once in a big way
right
and then the press goes crazy over it
you get tons and tons of media exposure
right
you've got a couple follow-up stories to go along with it
and
um
so it worked
it worked
it was
it was really quite remarkable
um
i will add
it was also remarkable because the products were remarkable
so it
these weren't empty
you know
keynotes
right
i mean they were chalk full of really good stuff and you know
no matter how staged it was
if
if there was no beef there
it wasn't going to work
yeah
there's plenty of beef
was it stressful to give those keynotes
um
well
you know
again
my part in them was always small and so it wasn't that stressful
you know
things
we generally knew
things were going to work you know the the
from the engineering perspective
the most stressful part is just hoping and praying the demos work right
because you're always showing something is not quite done
and you know
if he veers off script and does something that wasn't expected and it doesn't work
oh my god
that's horrible
but the shows themselves were generally well planned
well executed
and so they weren't stressful
my part of it was a little stressful because you get up in front of a big crowd
but i'done it enough that it was okay
yeah
you talked about that that that you know
trajectory of 16 years
sort of developing product and this a hard question
but but is there something you're most proud of
i mean that you know
really
you know
you really take pride in from of of all the things you worked on
i mean if you had to
boy
that is a really hard question
because you know there's no one thing per se
i guess if i had to answer
what i would say
is that
um
when we
it was sort of in that year or two after we joined apple
where we just kind of set a new tone for the company
um
a new culture
a new way of operating the whole company
that led and still leads to massive success
because i think those fundamental things which
as you know
apple's now trying to teach to incoming employees
i think those are fundamental things that we put in place that are now surviving the test of time
and continuing to make the company successful
and and the really great thing about it is not only has it yielded a company that's successful
but it's yielded huge improvements in technology for everybody
and i mean even if you don't use an iphone
i mean android has copied so much of it right that it's everywhere now
yeah
and
and so it's just mindboggling the impact
that that sort of our changes in those couple of years have had
even though in those years we weren't thinking about a phone or anything that people have today
you really did
i mean those up until you know you
you were almost there
till the iphone was introduced
i was designing the technology that made that
i would argue
made that leap to the rest of the population
right
i mean it was
it was
you know
it was off the desktop
but it hadn't gotten out where every everybody in the world could use the technology
now we're at that point
that's right
with everybody connected all the time
yeah
um
but
yeah
what do you think is critical about about
that culture that that you set up there at that time that persists to this day
and that will carry apple forward
um
like
what's the difference
what's the apple difference
i think i think what we did
which m certainly made the difference then
and i think continues to make the difference now is this focus on exemplary technology
which means you get exemplary products
by having exemplary people who focus on getting things done and getting things out
and
um
you can kind of break any of those and you don't get success right
or you don't
you
if you don't have great people
you don't get great technology
you don't get great products and you can have great people and great technology
but if you don't finish them and ship them
it still doesn't do any good right
so you kind of need all these things
and these are the things that we really instilled on everybody
um
and you know there's other things like everybody working toward the same goal and stuff like that
which you know
really kind of ties it all all together
but i think those are sort of the core things that we really instilled in everybody
which is
you know
our value here is
this isn't really a value statement per se
but our
our value is to create an excellent product that people can really use
which means
you got to get it out there
you got to have the channels for it for it's not just the product
it's the channels
it's the marketing
it's everything
it's
it's a whole thing
it's the unboxing experience
so that people feel good about what they just purchased right
right
um
and that's sort of a a culture that we really put in place and held everybody toward those goals
how important is secrecy to that culture
um
you know
secrecy is on a completely different axis and secrecy is about
um
it's partly about not allowing current products to be killed
right
osborne
effect
we don't want that obviously
and it's partly about
um
making sure the competition doesn't see what you're doing
so they somehow steal your thunder and who knows what way
uh
and it's also about we just talked about a little while ago
having the big unveil
okay
where you've got this great thing that everybody's now seeing for the first time and every you know
a million people or more are live streaming it right
10 million
who knows what numbers they're live streaming to find out what's next
and secrecy gives you all of those things
yeah
secrecy does come at a cost
but generally
these things far outweigh those costs
yeah
i'm watching
um
i don't
tom guber came after you left
but he's was one of the architects of siri
and um
is someone i've known for a long time
and i'm watching him struggle in that framework
and apple has sort of opened the door for him to get out just a little bit
but i mean they're letting him talk at ted
which is just extraordinary that you know that somebody would would let someone from apple do that
cuz
that was
you know something wouldn't have happened
but he's
he's chafed at the you know that that system it worked very well
well
you know something things require not being secret
right
and so secrecy is not one size fits all
you have to kind of go with the flow and figure out what's going on
you know
if you're working on internet standards
you can't be secret by definition
yeah
so there's a lot of different degrees there
i have a steve question
and
and this is something i thought for some time
and i was wondering if you could tell me if it's accurate
you know
steve's given credit for lots of different things
and one of the things that i haven't seen
stressed as much but i've always thought is over a long period of time
he got the timing of technologies right
in some ways that i almost thought was spooky
because you can be too early
you can be too late
but he seemed to have some fifth sense for when a technology was rip for mass commercialization
am i
did you ever did it look like that to you at all
well
so i'm not even sure the premise of your statement is correct
i mean
obviously the cube and next step were too early
i know he made mistakes right
so
and and yet i think this
yeah
i think one of our strengths
um
which you're attributing
him
which is correct
is
um
we
like i said
we developed a prototype prototype tablet
right
but we elected not to ship it
because we just projected out who's going to use this and the answer was nobody or maybe five people
when everyone else hold five tablets right
so i think what he was good at
and what we were all good at was getting out of our tech skins
and figuring out what is the world going to do with this thing
okay
and is it ready
and maybe it's not quite ready
but in a year it'll be ready because we'll make it ready
okay
and so when we saw that
we could get all the elements together for a phone
it made sense
and
oh
by the way
next came the tablet
which now made sense
cu
we had all this connectivity right
and so so it was it
i'm not sure that it's that hard
um
i think it's really about having the ability to again step out from your normal technological skin
don't see things as an engineer or as a product person
and see things as the masses are going to see them
and will they want them and can they use them
yeah
but we clearly had technologies that were before their time
that we didn't ship for that reason
yeah
um
for my end
maybe
just one last question
have you ever considered a memoir
i'm not a writer
i mean if someone came to me
and wanted to write a book
and they just wanted to sit with me and i would tell them the story
i would probably do that and they would sell 20 copies right
but i can't see doing that myself
yeah
have you played with swift
um
just a little bit
not very much
what do you think of it
um
my general impression is they have made a really important step forward
it's going to be extremely successful
they're making the right decisions with it
i think developers are falling in love with
they're going to fall in love with it
it's a very positive thing for them to do
i was just wondering about your recent investing with um elevation
and i guess now with next equity next equity
yes
um
just
are you investing in software and where do you see the the software story going in the
in the near and far terms
okay
so let me talk about that
so
um
next equity is the fund that we have right now
which is in some form a successor to the elevation fund
but it's also a little bit different
the partners are a little bit different
uh
and and the we don't do
we don't do checks quite as big as elevation used to do
elevation
right
used to do checks in the hundreds of millions
we do
millions
uh
it's a much smaller fund where
just a small number of partners
small
much smaller fund and we're basically investing in anything that relates to technology
we
uh
you know
we think technology touches everything these days
and it means there's an interesting technology angle to lots of different types of companies
and we look at them all
we invest in the ones that we think are good businesses
and so for us
the angle is
do we think this is a good business
have you had any exits yet
or is it really how we just started
we've not had any exits yet
i guess my last question is
uh
what do you think is
apple's greatest challenge right now
apple's greatest challenge is probably staying innovative
given its size
you know they've got a huge
uh
installed base
they have to worry about keeping that installed base moving forward
which generally leans toward incremental changes that are slow
right
that's the tendency there
but in the industry they serve
you still need to have new innovations
it doesn't mean they need to be whole new product categories
but they need to be basic innovations
even in in existing categories
and so staying innovative is probably their long-term challenge
so
the last time that i saw steve was a visit that i paid with steven ley in may of
was it
so was about five months before
and one of the things he said that
um
he
he said that
you know
if i had enough energy i'd really like to take on detroit
and that was very striking
and i've often wondered
i have no idea
because the
you know
you saw
they just got a a license for testing a prot
you know
i was wondering whether tim cook was sort of honoring steve's sort of
spirit
or his interest in in starting a self-driving car company
self-driving car project
well
i
i think at this point it's fair to say that tim would be pursuing things
assuming he thought they made sense to pursue
and he's on record as saying transportation is obviously a big industry
which leads people to believe that they're working on something in that space
exactly what it is
they won't say
yeah
but i mean
look when your apple size to move the needle
you want to look for big industries right where you can really again move the needle
yeah
and there's not a lot of them
have you looked at flying cars at all
you know
never looked at flying cars
i'love to have one
there are a bunch of startups around
i mean i just made a list of 14 flying car startups including air
including airbus
it's of the largest
but so that's
that's from my end
that's great
that's
is there anything that we've missed
that's always a good question
oh jee
yeah
you know something something bur
well
as soon as you know
5 minutes after we're done driving away
i think of something
oh my god
weot to talk about this
um
you know there's so much that that happened
it could never will be covered
i think i think we covered most of the highlights
we can always do another session if we have to
yeah
great
i guess
u
i don't know if this is something you'd be comfortable answering
but i i was just wondering
you know
the day that steve passed
um
maybe what were your feelings
then
um
so i remember that day
well
because
um
that day i was taking my daughter to a volleyball practice
and just as we were walking into the gymnasium
my iphone started beeping with phone calls and text messes
messages all from the press
oh
and so i knew exactly what had happened
i didn't even have to look at any news or anything
i knew what had happened instantly um
and you know
i mean
look
we all knew he was sick for many years
right
um
i knew very early on just how sick he was
and you know
i
even though i hadn't met with him person
i still talk to people who knew a good amount of what the situation was
so it was like
gee
this is really sad
but it finally happened
because you know
in in some way
you all
we knew the situation was dire because of the disease
yet you always wanted to believe he would find a way to avoid the inevitable
i think he believed that
right
yeah
and
um
but it was just sort of wow
this is really sad
and then i went in and watched my daughter's volleyball practice
well
thank you very much
thank you
my pleasure
yeah