so blowing off steam with the team skiing racing
well
one of the ways we blew off steam a little bit was one of the
the
in fact
the guy that was the microsoft guy that had joined us early on
decided that
um
it would be a great idea to
uh
go down to laguna sea and go to the russell racing school
so i i think about
um
maybe about eight of us went down to the school and we went to
uh
the beginner beginner school
which i think was four days
and and we
we were in
um
a mazda open wheel car
and you know it was
that was a good thing to blow off a little steam
and and it was really an eye opener about
um
for me about driving a a race car
i really wasn't very good at it or wasn't as good as i thought i should have been it
and the beginner school
they just teach you basically how to drive the car about the dynamics of the car
uh
g-forces cornering and all that sort of stuff
but then they have an advanced course where you actually at the end of the course
you get to do a race
so
um
a few of us decided
well
we'd like to go to that too
so i don't know
you know
a couple three months expire and we go down and we do that
and
uh
so we do the race
we go through the advanced school and and they do some more things
um
and i'm getting a little better at it
and we finished that
we do our race
and that was fun
so i thought
well
maybe
you know
they have the school series
what they call school series
you basically go down once a month and you race on saturday and then on sunday
and you come home
so
and debbie was involved in this too
debbie came down and did the um
the beginner one and she did the advanced one
and so she and i would go down there every month for
i think we went down from oh somewhere in march
just september
something like that every month
so it was 10 races or something like that
so i did that
and and and um
that was fun
and so then they had a
they had
every year
they had a what they called a pro race and the pro race
they would
um
they didn't have governors on the systems
but they sort of would
uh tune
they would open them up a little bit
they
they reprogram the ecu
the engine control unit
and um
give them a a little more harsh power
and you know
they say we're going to have a pro race now
and the pro race meant there was a pri
there was a u
um
a price package
and you could win some money
i think probably the top was 10k or something like that
but this would draw a lot of drivers that were pretty good
so i i did one of those
i think i finished next to last
only because one guy
my first one
only because the other guy was worse than i was
um
so then i got involved with a guy that was one of the instructors down there
and another guy that owned a race team to import an atlantic car from uh new
zealand
and i
that was when i started into racing really seriously
and so i owned that car and he raced that car one year
which was 1995
and the next year i decided that
well
we really should have a a new car to race
so i bought a new car and so the question became what to do with the old car
so i climbed in the old car and gez
i was pretty good
so i de saided
well
i'll race in this series
so i started racing the atlantic series and i raced
uh
56 races in that series
it had some per
i had some pretty um horrific accidents
nothing that i was really hurt really badly in
but one at laguna sea
um
is sort of an infamous one because espn played this over and over and over again for i
5 minutes of broadcast time or something and it was in one of the turns
i did a a um longitudinal flip
so you talk
you think about a flip that's going end over end
it wasn't end over end
it was a barrel roll flip
i did a flip like this and landed on the top and it was in a corner
where there was really dusty and the dust flew and there was big dust clouds
and what
what turn was that it was turn 10 laguna sea
the fast downhill sweeper to the right to the right
yeah
and uh
um
espn picked that up and and they just played that
you know
they
they played it over and over because
you know
there's a certain amount of time
they
they have to the yellow goes out
they have to clear the track
then they have to
you know
get the wreckers out and upate the car
so the races
you know
stop stopped
but they just keep playing this over and over and over again
so
uh
that was sort of my big wreck
my best
um
my best result
i finished eighth one time at um
the milwaukee mile
uh
this particular series we raced um montery mexico
which was a real
that was a real eye opener
um
you know
the rac trcks here are pretty safe
um
the racetrack there was not real safe
uh
i raced in um
homestead
uh raced in cleveland at the airport
um
mid ohio
which is outside of columbus
montreal
tw rivier
which
which is up by quebec city
um vancouver
british columbia
portland
uh
long beach road america
i never
oh yeah
road america that in fact road america
not road america
uh
no
road america
this is elkart
elkart
wisconsin
yeah
i had a big wreck at
well
that's my second biggest wreck
or maybe my first biggest wreck was at road america
there's a turn there
they call the kink
which is about 140 or 150 mile turn
and i lost control of the car and hit a had a hit a stone wall there
and ouch
i got
out of the car and the car was rocking like this
and i couldn't really understand why that was the case
and i looked down and all four wheels are gone
i'm just sitting there in the car
you know
the car is built with what they call a monoco
yeah
tub
and i'm in the tub and the engine's still on the back
but none of the wheels are
they're all gone
so i did race at road america
yeah
your favorite one
the milwaukee mile by far
yeah
oh
i
nazareth
pennsylvania's there too
any
uh
any analogies from
racing into software development
yeah
actually
i think there is
and um it's focus
um
i've been always been a person that really can focus on the job at hand
and racing is driving a race car is focus
i mean what happened 10 milliseconds ago
it's gone
you're going to focus on what's coming up and what's going to happen
so
um
i think there's there's some analogy there about being really successful
i mean anything is to be to focus on what's important and uh
what what you um have to
uh
achieve
to get
uh
to the success of so
in race car driving is
it was just another example that so the super intensity of concentration
yeah
it's like when
when you're writing code
what
how do you achieve that
can you stand music being on or want to be in a quiet office
or you know
in general
noise doesn't bother me much
um
you know
i would prefer that somebody's not
there's one guy at work now that whistles and that
you know that's not a problem
but he whistles down the hall
and you know i'm like
i
i really don't like that
but generally noise doesn't bother me much
but but i do focus on
uh
you know what's going on
especially if
if i write a new piece of code
um
i
you know
i write the code and i i will spend maybe um
three or four iterations of of executing the code in my mind
all the air paths
all the paths that can go through
to see if i can prove that it's correct before i even run the code
and most of the time
when i run code it
it pretty much runs the first time
it may not be absolutely correct
but it will run
it won't crash
um
so that's being able to focus on what's going on and not have things bother you or whatever
in in the nt program you
it was demolishing bugs
and you know how
how would you
uh
change the process to create less errors and make them easier to fix
the easiest
probably the easiest bugs to
well
the question is how how to make uh bugs easier to fix
and
um
and fewer of them
pardon
and fewer of them and fewer of them
um
i think fewer of them is probably the easier of the two
because
um
the fewer the bugs are
the harder
the ones that are left are going to be to solve
and the hardest bugs to solve are ones around synchronization
they're not around correctness of code flow
they're
they're around the correctness of synchronization um
where
um
there's not the correct barriers
there's not the correct locks or there's race conditions between code paths or something
um
one of the things that also exacerbated the five years was multiprocessing
i had the the be in my bonnet
when i went to microsoft that we were going to produce mp systems
and nobody else was producing mp systems
um deck had
at that time they had the 782
which was this funny asymmetric thing and we had 1170 that actually was smp
but there was some unibus problem that we decided not to manufacture that
so um s smp problems synchronization
is a big problem
um
the problem with less bugs is i think through the engineering process itself
and and the the people you've got to have quality has to start from the bottom up
it can't start from the top down
you can't legislate quality
you have to quality
has to be something that's im born in everybody at the lowest level
and any link in the lowest level
that doesn't produce a quality
piece
prod produces bugs up the up the line because they interact with other pieces of the system
if you're
if you're building the
the lower levels of the system
then your leverage as far as causing problems up in the levels is very high
so i think
uh
reducing the number of bugs is is basically thinking more about quality and paying more attention to quality
i don't think that that that necessarily
you have this thing
well
we'll do 100 % test afterward
you know
we'll
we'll do everything and then we'll test to see how good it is
it's got to be built in to start with
so i think building systems with fewer bugs means paying attention to that all the way along
and not for me
i hate it when there's a bug filed against me
i don't like that
at all
and i don't want that bug to exist filed against me for any longer than i have to
i'll drop everything to go fix that bug
because i know i can fix that
um
so there needs to be that kind of mentality
i mean there's a lot of people that say
oh yeah
i got 50 bugs
you know
i'll get them fixed
well
it's like quitting smoking
you know
the best time to quit smoking is right now
it's
not
it's not an hour from now or a day from now
or a week from now
it's right now
so the best time to fix the bug is
right now
so that would be fewer bugs
um
the make them easier to fix
i don't know how we make them easier to fix
other than the
the uh building
better tools for analyzing what's going on
i guess
is
um
primarily the way we would make them easier to fix
and we we have lots of tools now we have
we have lots of tools that do the same thing that you know
somebody has said
um
well
that's a good tool
but i'd like the tool to do this
i don't own the tool
but i think i could build a tool that was a little better
that would do do this and maybe we could find something a little better
and so we have a lot of
we have a lot of tools we have
we have a lot of source level tools
um
one of the big problems that we had
uh
partway through
um
the
the evolution of nt was hitting a big security
um
uh
attack or wall or whatever
somewhere after um
about 2001
somewhere in there
i you know
we were
we
the internet
we really got going on the internet
somewhere in the late 90s and
uh
the internet suddenly had problems with people with uh
viruses and trying to attack your system
um
so we developed some tools that analyze the source and try to to find places where you have um
buffer overflows are the biggest one
and the amount of buffer overflows that we had was just mindboggling that that
and it was like we have this tool and the tool says
look at
right here this
this could overflow
and so that was great
i mean that made it so that it lowered the bugs
um
even things like um
arithmetic overflow can cause a bug
because you're calcul
maybe you're calculating the size of the buffer that you want to allocate
because you got a bite count
and you do this computation and gez that overflows and now it looks like you need a small size
so you allocate that size and then you use this other size
uh
to to transfer data into it
and all of a sudden you have a problem there
so we have some tools that that analyze the source and
uh
and actually
um point out places where there's bugs and and we actually fix those like they're bugs
the problem with those tools are that they're static analysis tools and they have a lot of false positives
so you see a lot of things that that aren't really problems
and it can't see some things you know you
you
you may have in your code
you may have had logic that made it impossible for the thing that it's complaining about to occur
and it'll say
hey
this is bad
so those have to be filtered out
and so we have ways to filter that out too
if you go back a little bit to
you know
getting programmers to really produce good code is
is there a dave cutler school of how to get a programmer moving along in that direction
uh
do i have a a way to move people to build good code
um
i guess
the only way that i can say that i have
um
helped people build good code is
by example
you know
um
everything that i do
i try to make it get my best and everybody sees
the source
and obviously they see that i don't have a very big bug count or a zero bug count
um
they look at my code and i i hope that that that really
helps them become better programmers
um
but another aspect of this is is really with the young people starting out to really ingrain in them
the the importance of quality
i mean i
i
for me
there's nothing worse than software that doesn't work
i mean i
i just can get really upset with software that doesn't work where it's obvious that something
just
i mean something simple
i mean if something doesn't work on your phone or it doesn't work on your tablet
or it doesn't work on your pc
that should work it
it
it should infuriate you
because it just should not be that way
right
it should be all the stuff that doesn't work
should be stuff that that is little tiny things
maybe it's like there's a few pixels over here that are wrong
uh
or or something that that's just minor
in fact
a lot of the bugs
uh
um
that are that have been and continue to be filed against nt
are
are these kind of things
they're cosmetic things and they tend to
they have low priority
so those things are not upsetting
but it's upsetting
when you have something where you ship a product and it's in the field for four months
and all of a sudden there's this disaster that happens where you wipe out
you know somebody's data
and then all of a sudden it's like wow
that's really a problem
so i think quality is something that starting out with young people and saying hey
you know
we really got to have quality
so you
you come to 93
i think it is in the final
93 is the release date of nt
the official release
millions of copies shipped
the uh
initial version of nt is shipped in uh
and then we shipped
um
n35
which was alpha support about six months later and and part of that was also a a uh
kind of cleanup
let's improve the performance of the system release
um
we did not have the performance level in the system
in the first release
we would like to
had
it was a little bit bloated
now bloated in those days was like maybe it took 24 megabytes
this
of course
a two gigabytes or four gigabytes
um
so daytona was kind of this dual thing
where it was this
it was called daytona
it was actually the daytona release and our our big thing
there was the racetrack and everything
and um i think we actually may have
uh
well
we had some racetrack stuff because we off been all off to the race school
uh
and we
and we incorporated alpha support
and then
just a little bit later than that
we did the power pc
so that brought us to the first
the end of the first release
and then the next release was um
nt40
and nt40 is an interesting release
because at the end of of the release release
one
or we actually call it
we actually call it 3. 1
because windows was 3. 1
the 16-bit windows was 3. 1 and the the
the feeling was that nobody would buy an operating system that was a 1 nobody
so would start out with a number that wasn't a 1
and well
we pick the same number as the 16bit thing
so then then we had 35 and 351
well
the next one was going to be 40
and in the meantime another guy had been hired from banyan
his name was jim alon
and he had actually was starting another project called cairo and cairo was
was envisioned to be a system that would incorporate some of the things you now see with internet search
only it would be locally
an indexing
file
a new file system that had indexing indexing all your mail and everything
and it was internally in
microsoft was called information at your fingertips
and he started this project
and it was kind of running with in parallel with the tail end of release one
so when we started release 2
um
well actually was would be it was n4o
the cairo project
alon actually came became my boss and the cairo project
uh
became part of the n development
and that was supposedly where we were going to be going
and i was really worried about this
so
um
i proposed another project called and we called it tucka
and the reason we picked tuck willa was
because we know where tua is and we know how to get there
it's just down the street
so i convinced jim that we should we had the the capability to do both of these at once
and throw one away
and it turned out that the one we threw away was cairo
and nt40 was probably one of the best systems that we produced
um
certainly not functionally
but as far as
uh
its acceptance and quality and performance
and
um
it contained the
uh
it was in 1996
so it was just after windows 95
we talk a little bit
we'll talk a little about that lineage of system
yeah
um
so it contains a new graphical user interface
which was drastically different from 3. 1
3. 1 was sort of
it was graphical
but you sort of put things together
you built your menus
and you had to do a whole bunch of stuff
um
and then the new ui actually had all that stuff
you know everything
when you got
the system was already installed with start menus and all that stuff
so nt40 had the new ui in it and it was an evolution of nt
caro
would have been an evolution of also
but it would have had a new file system
a new shell
just a whole bunch of new new mail system
everything
um
so i started to diver
or
um
i digress into windows 95 and widen
windows 95 came about
windows 95 is actually built on the dos code base
so it's actually the 16bit system with the capability to run 32-bit programs and it included this new ui
and it actually was very popular and sold a lot of systems it sold in in that time frame
it
it sold a lot more systems than nt sold
um
but nt sold in the places where you were doing enterprise stuff
uh
you needed some security
you needed to run server
you wanted to run file servers or print servers
those
those are any kind of servers
we had
then
um
so nt was alive and well and very healthy
but at the same time
windows 95 made the company a lot of money
and then they continued on with that same code base for windows 98
and then was with millennium
um
which i believe was in 2000
so
and it died
it completely died
it was
um
uh
a non-extensible um
it was bug written
it was notorious for doing just hanging
you know
it just freeze
and that was
not
um
unexpected
because it was built on doss
it wasn't built on security
no
security
none
um
one of the things this
you didn't ask me about this
but i might say something about security
you know
we started out in the beginning to have really robust security
and we designed of the original security model was pretty robust
but by today's standards completely different
because in those days you were protecting things
um
you were protecting people against f file access and um
uh
system resource access
but it wasn't like the security today where um
somebody invites the
the breach right into the system
they're in the browser and they click on something
and here comes a program they didn't even know about
all of a sudden
it
uh
it exploits a buffer overflow and bang
it puts something in the operating system
and now you're under the control of the virus
right
so anyway
there was a lot of controversy about whether we should make people log on or not
because the original pc
you know
you turn it on
there
it is well building
we're talking about security
and and the fact that we maybe shortcut the system a little bit with security in the beginning
because
um
the pc mentality was you just turn on the system and use it
and we really
we had come from the the background of time sharing systems
where everybody lo logged on and everything was shared and you worried about
you know
people accessing your files
and geez
if it's a pc
you own it
you can access your files
so we actually designed the security system and built the security system and we did have log on
uh
but there were some aspects of the the system
that we didn't do quite as well as we we we could have
uh
one was
um
uh
when you install an application
you should really install an application for the user that installed it
not for the system
but since it's a pc
you install it for the system
so that was one problem
because now
um
you assume now that that everybody is going to use this thing
and that if two people have two different versions
well that you can't have that
you can only have one version
and then the other thing that happened with that was
um
we would have all these people that were reshipping binaries
and so somebody would have an application like office and they'd reship a binary and somebody have
maybe a database application that would ship a binary
same binary never been tested against the other guy's product
right
so we
we had
we
and we're still somewhat trying to work through this about state separation
which is part of of of casting this as part of security
is separating everybody's state
so it's only their state
so
but nt does have security and had security built in oras
um
windows 995 did
not
so the end of the
the dos windows
uh
comes to
you know
it can't go any further
and where does nt go in terms of influencing the future
it's called personal operating systems
where does it oh you mean like
uh
xp
you know seven
oh so on
well
let me tell you
it's all nt
there is nothing that's not nt
when when 10 is nt
it's all the same stuff
it's an evolution of the same code base going all the way back to 1988
um
there is some interesting
um diversion along the way
um
if you want to go
you want to go into that right now or or sort of a little bit later
because i was going to
well
you know
take the direction you want to take
okay
i
i was going to say what happens in after nt40
yeah
good
after nt40 nt has grown to 400 people
and i'm sort of
uh
at the point of of
um
maybe i don't want to manage 400 people
maybe i want to just work on the technical things that are important
um
so i decide at nt40 that i'm not managing the the system anymore
that somebody else is going to manage the system
and
um
i become an individual contributor
and being individual contributor from then on basically meant i was doing the same things i was doing on the the coding implementation side
as i was doing before
i just wasn't carrying all the other stuff with me
so the next system we produced is wind
2k windows 2000 and windows 2000 was uh probably one of the first systems that we really produced
um
we
we produced a a separate serv system server skew from a
uh
a personal skew
i don't know whether we produced the server
sk
we probably produced the server skew for n402
but the 2000 was more oriented towards that about writing server applications
um
wind 2k was another
you know
great system
as far as um
the reliability and everything
um
and my part
it was just basically
um
any new features we put in the kernel performance
nothing real big
um
and then we shipped that in 2000 and in 2000
there's a guy that's in charge of the consumer group
and there's a ch guy that's in charge of the server group
and you know they've been working together under another guy to produce the system
this
but the guy
that's in charge of the consumer group decides
that that um consumers don't need the quality that the server group needs
and the server group's um laundry list of features
that they want to put in the next release is way beyond what they they need for the next consumer release
so we split the codebase we split in xp
and the other one was a server 2003 codebase and that turned out to be not a good decision
and and what happened there was
um
the server 2003 codebase
we fixed all the security problems we were having
uh
we put in the server features and it actually turned out
in the end
it almost shipped at the same time as the the xp code base and the xp code base
uh
shipped with some new ui stuff
it
you know
it had this start
the the new start button and some other stuff
it was mostly ui work
uh
but also shipped with a lot of security problems and more bugs than the server 2003
so and i work mainly on two
our server 2003 and about this time
um
i don't remember the exact day
but it
it was slightly after 2000
amd came to us and said um
we have
um
a new
or we have an extension to the x86 architecture that will extend it compatibly to 64 bits
are you interested
and one of the things i kind of left out here is the addition of yet another platform
in which was in two in 2k
which was the itanium
we added itanium support in in uh wind
2k and the itanium would run x86 binaries
32-bit binaries
but it wouldn't run them at speed
so there was a speed penalty plus the fact
that titanium was never ever as fast as the fastest x86 ever
so amd proposing this
this extension
you know
looked kind of good and so we sort of looked at it and said
well
it looks pretty interesting
you know
why don't you go back and um
come back when you've got it more solid and you're
you know
you're
you think you really want to build it
so they come back back in like 6 months and say here it is
and and i i look at it and say boy
this is great
the x86 runs at speed
we can produce a a small
like the ame thing
we can produce a small wrapper envelope that just executes x86 binaries
and they'll run it
whatever the speed of the processor is
the 64bit stuff will run at the speed of the processor
except it'll have a bigger address space
so i said this is pretty good
um
you know we we need to talk about whether we're going to do this or not
so i don't know
not very much time went by and there was not much
um
there was not much happening and i just
i went to al and said we're doing it
we're just going to do this
i'm gonna
i'm going to do it
i got a couple guys and we'll do it
so i basically four of us started out to do this
and we had done a lot of groundwork on making our codebase um
data type
neutral
as far as pointer size because of the itanium
and also because we were actually at one time doing a 64-bit alpha system
and then compact said we're not building those anymore
so we quit doing that
so we started out um on the the
what became the the x64 version of nt in the ear
early 2000
at the same time
amd was developing the architecture and got um a pretty good say in some things that were really important
um
we
i think we got about six features put into the processor architecture
that i consider to be one of them was absolutely essential
and that was they put in relative addressing and it's 32-bit displacement
so it meant that if we were willing to
if we were willing to say our binaries were never any bigger than two two gigabytes
then that displacement would always span a binary
so they put in the the rally of addressing they put on
they put in some other things were performance oriented and i had a really good relationship with a
with a
the lead micro code guy
i mean he was having a graph was just great
um
and we
going back to the how important this 32-bit displacement thing was
maybe you wouldn't think that would be important
but one is position independent code
it's hard to write code for the 64-bit architecture that isn't positioned independent
which means that one of the main security things that you do is something called alsr
which is address space relocation
uh
randomization
so you take an image and you randomize where you put it in the address space
well
you have to relocate it when you do that
if there's no relocations
you don't
you don't have to do much right now
there still can be relocations
but but to have position independent code
you need the code to be independent
as opposed to the data
you can always produce pointers to the code or the data
so anyway that we decided to do that with a windows 2003
uh
codebase
in the meantime the xp is shipped
and we're producing a system on the consumer side called longhorn and it became
i call it does it matter
horn
because it became so bug written
and so hard to actually get it to run
that eventually it got to the point that i convinced alan
i said we should just junk that codebase and start over with a wind 2k
i'm sorry the windows 2003 codebase is the nude codebase and we did that
we started over that system became vista and vista was that
that's the way that that got delivered with system was vista
but we actually delivered um the x64 support as a service pack to the windows 2003 server
was
it was
it was windows 2003 server sp1
and it had some new sks and they were 64-bit sks
there was a a professional um desktop skew
and then there was a server skew and um
um
that turned out to be very successful
i mean everything's 64 bits
now
almost everything
the telephone's not
well
i can't say the telephone's not 64 bits
because um
your cell phone is
anyway
well
the cell phone it turns out
the cell phone turns out is actually going to 64-bit arm
so um
they want more than 4 gigabyt of physical address space
so they're going to go to
uh
64-bit arm
there is some places where 30
well
i thought the 32-bits would entirely go away
but there are some things like cell phones where
uh
smaller pointer sizes actually do end up meaning less memory
you leave less memory
and on phones
less memory means less power drain
less power drain means happier users
okay
so in the meantime here we ship 2003
but just before we ship 2003
we have to go back to xp again
and we have to spend a ginormous effort on xp to bring up
all
bring it up to all the security enhancements we've made to um the server system
so basically we do xp
service pack 2
which is basically a release
a re-release of that software
so that sort of brings us to the point where where and again
this is all nt
this is not
you know
you read
like you read mary joe foley
i don't know if you ever
if you know who she is
she's
um
she's written about microsoft forever and it's like this is a new operating system
well
it's not a new operation
it's an evolution it's like
um
every time linux comes out with a new release
it's not a new system
it's an evolution of the old system
so the xp sp2 was really a new system because it was a re-release of almost every single binary
and then we went back to
we did xp
we d it back to
then we did the the x
the x64 release
and then we went back and and put the resources back on vista
and so vista came out basic as a 64-bit system and 32 and i vista actually supported vista
i think vista actually supported
um
the itanium
also meantime
one of the things you left out here is the risk systems were dropping off
and i the reason here's why i think they dropped off
i think the ris guys were so so focused on simple architecture with simple implementation
that they in intel intel was like they got this architecture
it's a little complex
but they got got lots of transistors
they got lots of design and they got lots of verification expertise
letus put these these transistors to work to make everything run faster and running faster
is things like
uh
very sophisticated branch prediction
better caching
you know
set associative caching and just all sorts of stuff
um speculation all that that the risk guys are like
well
you know
we don't really want to do that stuff
we want this to be simple
so the thing about risk having a performance advantage
just kind of went away
it went away because they didn't want to
there was nobody that had the resources to put to work on the chip architecture
and the chip design that intel did
and they didn't have the resources to do the big designs with all the transistors they had
i mean the they're
you know
they're billion billion transal chips now
right
so in the risk gu going to
you know they want to build
see
look at this
we built this machine with three
you know
300, 000 gates right like
so what
and this
the stuff on the intel processors now and the amd processes is really complicated
it really is there
just a ter
you know
out order
uh
execution
and all this stuff there
r guys
you know they don't want to do that
um
so i think
that's why the risk systems kind of went away is
that they couldn't offer the price performance that the intel systems could
they couldn't pro
they couldn't provide the compatibility through the line
i mean we had all these um software emulators running
and and one of the things that we're doing now in in itanium
and and actually alpha started
this too is binary recompilation
where you take a binary
you take an xx6 binary
you run it through a binary recompilation
produce another binary which runs under a special um emulation
uh
system that mostly executes at speed of the processor
because it's translated everything that it can find from x86 code to to alpha code
or whatever the carget is
but there's still maybe a few pieces around there
and so you're actually run the real binary
and sometimes you have to actually flip into a mode that actually emulates the instructions
but most of the time
excuse
so binary compilations has come a long ways and we would be a lot better off
but still you have
it's not like you just do the
re
the binary recompilation and then you say you
well
i'm sorry
you just say i'll do the recompilation and i'll just
i'll just put it in the store
right it
it'll work
then
well
it doesn't
you know
you have to go and make sure you have to test and make sure
so it's a doubling of the work
so
um
i think the the risk architectures with um with um went away in their popularity
because of all those things now arm arm has taken a hold in um phones
and it's taken a hold in some of the mobile devices
um
but arm is not anywhere near the performance capability of the x86 stuff and either from
uh
from amd or intel
and you know they're trying to get there
they're
you know they're trying to to up their their their performance
but they
they've been primarily aimed at power and you use
you use amd or i'm not amd
you use arm processors and applications where you don't need
um
a lot of power
maybe you need a little ship
one of the things that's happened is
you know
intel and amd to to a certain extent is like we got a billion transistors we we got
we just got to build this chip
that's this big mh
the last one was that size
the next one's got to be that size
even though we have four times as many transistors
we're going to build it the same size
right
well
the arm guys actually haven't done that
arm guys have kind of a
they have a uh
a portfolio of a lot of different size chips
so if you're building a watch
you can build it with a chip that's smaller
right
yeah
so but intel and amd have never taken this thing about
well
let's take
we now can build the same functionality in one quarter the size
maybe that would be a good product
well
this whole semiconductor process technology
you
the the end game with a p4 is we get to maybe four gig gigahertz and we
and
and the
you know
the chip is incandescent
so now we go to multicores
so this is a big event in the operating system world
that we're going to have four processors to play with
how did that start coming into the
well
we started
you know
nt
from day one was
we built nt to be mp
and we
our
our initial
our risk prototype
or our reference was mp
so we were mp from day one
so cores are no no different than you know
there's two kinds of cores
actually
do you think about cores as being autonomous cores or multi-threaded cores
if they're multi-threaded cores
then they're
they're a con set of context
that's a thread and the core hardware that actually executes that context
and then you switch among these contexts and intel did
um
it's called smt
uh
well
multi-threading just call it multi-threading intel did this early on
but we already had mp support
so the only thing that was kind of a curveball
there was that sm smp in uh
increased your parallelism
but not necessarily your performance
because you basically have the same amount of execution capabilities that you had before
you just have multiple contexts that you can run that run against that
now the place that you could gain is that there's delays
like
uh
cash misses
where you can say
well
that cash miss
i
i missed in the cash on this set of context
i can switch to another context and it can immediately execute
maybe it had a cash miss before and now that data is there so you can get
you know
maybe 15
%
you can also lose 5 % or 10
so very unpredictable
so that kind of threw us a cruit ball
amd went the other way and they did what was what they called cmt
multi-threading was called smt
symmetric multi-threading and the other one was called cmt
and cmt was chip multiprocessing
which actually put more than one processor on a chip
so the original amd 64-bit chips were processor chips
so they had two real processors
now
since then they've
they've all migrated to this multi-core thing where they actually have
uh
core logic that shares some other piece
they may share
like you may have uh a couple cores that share an l2 cache
for instance
which then shares
then all the the the two pairs share on l3 cache
and all of that
all of that now is all in nt
you know how many levels of cash do you have
how many
what are they
you know
uh
how many waste set
associative
are they and all of this stuff
so the thing didn't really affect nt
particularly it
but it affected the applications
because the applications now could get more performance if they're multi-threaded so if somebody started out originally with nt
and said i just have a single threaded app
then these other processors
well
they
they they progress through to the point where we're at 3. 5 gigahertz
and you know they're all ready for the next leap to four
and the next leap to four doesn't happen
because we can't build it at four because we would have such high
uh
current leakage
that you're right
it would
it would glow
the thing would glow
so we start building cores
and then it seems to be like a race of how many cores we can get on a single die
um
i don't know what the biggest one is
but it's big
it's like i don't know maybe 80 or something like that
so there's a lot lot of cores
but but for nt itself
that doesn't mean much at all
not at all
it's
it's mainly the applications
where do we go from here
so we're in the the kind of chronology here
we're
we're at vista and
uh
you know
we we retargeted longhorn to one code base
so so we're actually back to one code base and i'm still an individual contributor
and and i worked on vista
i did some things for vista
um
mainly x64 related
because i i've been the guy that that was the spearhead for x64 and you know
of course
i
i say we're
there are four of us that that basically did this
we
we did a lot of it
um
we did the line share of it
but there was a whole another effort going on that compiler world
where we had a couple guys from the compiler group that were just absolutely superb
and
um
they did a great job with a compiler
so there was a a whole another group of people
i
i mean i don't know if you
how many people actually
you would say you know were responsible for the x64 uh system
but it was pretty small
you
maybe a 100 people mh
anyway
so vista we shi vista
um
and vista is big dilemma
because it's like
should we ship it or should we start over
you know
it's
doesn't look very good
it's not
it doesn't look the same as windows
it doesn't look the same as xp
it doesn't look like the same as anything we've done before it's different
um
so we shipped it and with not very good market reception
a vista was probably the poorest received version of all of the windows systems
that is show
there was some other bob and some other things
well
window windows systems
yeah
window bob
bob lasted
um
i don't know
three to six months
that was about it
so this is shipped in
uh
november of 2006
and
uh
so i sort of stuck around on the operating system group for a while
but then
and
um
later on in that year
and i think it was around october
um
cloud computing was becoming a hot topic and cloud computing
is basically
um
moving back the other way
where you know
we
we move
we had server
we had time sharing system
one time
then we moved to servers
then we moved to peurs computers
and now we're moving back to central storage
again
where in central computing
where we have a big server farm somewhere
that that you can somehow you can interface through from whatever your device is
and all the heavy computing or the heavy storage will occur on that end
and we had server um farms in several places
but they were specifically for servers for this
or servers for that or whatever
so there was a project that or incubation project actually was started called azure
and it was to produce a um
a system that would
uh
provide
a platform for for people to rent
where they could rent compute power
they could rent storage
and so i
and we decided it was going to be a virtualized system
because you want to run multiple instances of operating system
so it had to be virtualized
and this was at a time when the first virtualization extensions had come out for amd and for intel
and we're not quite um
at the level that we thought we had to have um
specifically
the paging was a real real problem
and the virtualization systems that that existed
the virtualization in implantations that existed at that time were their hypervisors
that mainly did shadow pages
shadow page tables
and we thought that the direct translation was better
so we decided that we would go with direct translation
which adds more translation levels
but it's direct
and you don't have this
this duplicate copy of page tables on the side
and amd was the first um company that was producing those intel came along
later
um
and we decided that that our hypervisor would be based on that
and i became responsible for the hypervisor for azure
and we
um
brought azure up and you
we started a server farm in quincy
um
washington
i don't remember how many servers we had
but it was quite a few tens of millions of dollars worth of servers
which was our just our test system right
and we carried on for about two years and our
our main differentiation at that point was
and
and what we were actually asked to do was produce a system that was a platform as a service
which included all the things that you have to do
if you have a server
you know you have
you have problems with configuration control
where you have to keep track of the operating system you're running
what version
it is
what versions of all the apps are
and all that
and then if you have multiple of these
you you have to update them all together
so we build all the infrastructure to do all that stuff
thinking that that was going to be the big thing that people really wanted
and to a certain extent it is because you don't want to have to have
um
you don't want to do this manually
you don't want to manually
uh
have
say
oh geez
i got 150
i got 2,
i got 10, 000 servers and a new update came out for the operating system
well
i've got to update every single one of those
right
do i want to sit there and do that
well
no
and there were some internal people in in um in microsoft
that actually had developed some tools to do that
and they were mainly the ones that were running our web services
so we decided to produce another set of tools
and
um
i guess
about
um
i think
about two and a half years into the project
we were doing well enough that
um
steve bomber decided that
well
geez
we are to really make this a product now
so we we made um azure a product
and i forget exactly when the first
i think 2010 was the
when we introduced
um
azure was the platform as a service
and at that point we
we're out of the incubation
and um
you know we're were
um
worried about
you have multiple data centers because you want triple redundant logic on all of the storage
and of course
um
we have
we want to do this internationally
so we have
you know
we're building data centers in germany or in europe
we're building data centers in the east in far east
and
uh
then you have problems about
um
we can't migrate any
you can't replicate any data across
uh
geopolitical regions cost money to move it to canada
well
it's mainly because of the geop geopolitical problems of interesting
you know
if you're storing a replication of data from germany that belongs to the german government
they really don't want it stored on servers in texas
right
so
um
we had
we shipped the first version of azure and um
there was
um
a change in the management
the server group and the guy that would run the server group
um took over azure
and at that time
um
a couple of us decided that we'go work on the xbox and the irony of working on the xboxes
is
i once sent steve bomber
a piece of mail that said steve
i got an idea
why don't we take that million dollars a week that we're losing on xbox
and take it out in the parking lot on friday night
and have a bonfire and roast hot dogs and and marshmallows
we can take the people that we're working on that
and put them on things that'll really produce some good stuff
and we'll save all that money
of course it was just kind of a tongue and cheek thing
so here i am
like seven years l
going over to the dark side
seven years later
i'm over on the dark side
so the xbox was was kind of a real um new thing for me
because this is working on something
where the security is something that's much different than the security for anything else
you think of security
um
the way you you generally think about it is physically
phys
you physically have the machine
it's yours
it's secure
and now you just worry about keeping all those other people out that could invade it through the web
or whatever
the xbox is entirely different than that
we
we want to guard against people that have a soldering iron and a logic analyzer
they can't break the system
if they do something to modify the system
it will immediately see that it's been modified and it will not
it
will
will do what it's called bricking
it will brick itself
it now becomes a brick
it's no longer an xbox
it's a brick
so building such a system is kind of interesting and it requires a lot of uh
a lot of detail and attention to security
a lot of hardware
um
not necessarily in terms of cost
but a lot of hardware
a lot of
uh
a lot of encryption
um
amd is in the business of building custom s soc's and they built the custom s
so for this
and it has um it has eight cores
um
and they're split into um four
two core groups
but it also has a arm security processor
so the secure boot is actually secure
you can't decide that you're going to solder some parts on
you can't decide
you'll take some parts off and reprogram them and put them back
it will discover this
you know everything's
everything is encrypted
um
it runs with a hypervisor
so there's a hypervisor level of protection in the system
um
it runs
it's a three-headed operating system where actually runs three virtual machines
one is called the host system which communicates with a hypervisor
and it's part of the trusted computer base and the hypervisor
actually
you know
you could think of that
it's running on the bare hardware
but under the opes of the security processor
you know
the security processor has the capability to just gate off certain pieces of hardware
so you can't even see them
so it's if the hardware is only going to be accessible by the security processor
it has the ability to do that
it has the ability to just stop the processor
it has a lot of control over what's going on
so back up a bit and say why
okay
so the question that we were discussing was
uh
why all this security on the xbox and make it so that it's
so the
uh
the owner can't steal
and the answer is piracy
the xbox games are
are called aaa rated games
and aaa rated games means that
um
they're very responsive
they're high
uh
frame rate games
um
the
typically
the people that produce them spend a lot of money producing them
and they're not like a pc game
where typically in a pc game
there's piracy
but they get a big surge when they
when they put them out
and i guess that they figure that that
um
that that offsets whatever piracy that
but a aaa rated game
um
is one that's a high expense
it might be hundred bucks
and we guarantee that they can't
we people can't pirate those games and we actually get
uh money for that
so if they can't pirate games and we can convince the people that write the games
they can't comp pirate the games
we make money because of that
okay
so you're talking about all the all the security functions
and so you've been working on the
you worked on the hypervisor
i work on the hypervisor
and
um
you know
the hypervisor isolates all the memory um does all the scheduling
one of the things on the xbox is that
and you know generally an operating system you want to share on the xbox
you don't necessarily always want to share
and there's a lot of actual physical partitioning of the system
depending on what you're doing
if you're running a aaa rated
games would take a set of cores and dedicate those to the game in a vm
and so they don't deal now with the interference
that they get with other things going on in the operating system
and there's a lot of housekeeping stuff that goes on
uh
and the other things that on xbox is you actually can be running a game
and viewing live tv at the same time
or even skyping at the same time or running the internet
explorer
so
um
and not having them interfere with each other
so if if you're running a game and it's in the foreground
youve got six cores dedicated to you
if you're running a game and it's in the quote background
in other words
you're
you're focusing more on watching tv
then you have four cores
and the other environment has
uh
four cores
so we have eight cores total
so we're constantly switching these cores around
and the hypervisor doing all that at the command of the host system
the host systems
keeping track what's going on
um
so it's
it's a much different
you
you think of this as like you think of virtualization as you're running mobile operating systems
so you could think of the xbox is just virtualization
but it's really not because all this is the operating system which we call hydra
and it it really has these three different os's running or three different vms running all right
and one of them
the the system os is called is our shared resource environment
where you actually could be running things that were like
um
you
you'be running live tv or netflix or hulu or whatever there
and it has all the ui
so everything you do
your game controller is interfacing with something in that particular operating system
but all the device drivers and everything are in the host os
so there's some communication between the two through shared buffers
and the game is setting it in here in another vm all right
with its own resources
and whatever
so the memory is is separate
we don't
it's not like
uh
a demand page system
where
like a time sharing system where you steal pages from joe to give to sally
right
they get what they get
so that
so that every time that game runs
it runs the same
the audio doesn't glitch
the video doesn't glitch
and of course
behind this is some some pretty good
uh
gpu hardware
so is this is got you fully engaged in terms of the future of xbox
or you have your eye on something else
right now
i don't have my eye on anything else
i'm sort of
uh
just trying to to keep up with what we're planning to do
um
in the future
which will be
i mean most i can say about that this time is it's evolutionary
um
there are some thoughts about
you know what do we do
do
we do should we really have a console
or should we really try to
uh
beef up the the um
the pc environment to be able to run these aaa rated games
and what would that mean it's not going to be a secure
um
for instance
on xbox
um
there's a bunch of u certificates that you get when you buy one
and that say what you
well
there certificates say what you can do
if you're a c
if you're a consumer
you get an xbox that you can play games on and you can do these other things
that
what are they apps for
you can't run kently buggers
you can't do any of that stuff
so there's no opportunity for people to run those kind of attacks
but on the pc operating system that you can't
uh
rule that out because somebody buys a pc
they say i own the pc
it's mine
now
thankfully
from the day we introduced xbox
until now
um
the people that buy xboxes
they actually
uh
have become accustomed to the fact that that environment doesn't really belong to them to tinker
with
they can't load device drivers
they can't put code in the operating system
um
the typical attacks that somebody would have through the um
the uh
internet explorer or the browser are not possible
um
or they're severely mitigated by the way the layering in the system
one of the things that the hypervisor does is
and it we do all this through
uh
um
i won't call it cryptography
but it's secure hashing is
uh
we use nested paging
which means that the hypervisor has the real page table and the real ais bits
and that the vm has what it thinks are the page tables
and what it thinks the access bits are
but it can't get an
can't get an execute bit turned on
unless the hypervisor turn it on
hypervisor only turn it on
if it's in a page that has a hash that we recognize
so you can inject code in the operating system
if you find a buffer overflow
then the best you can do is maybe you can jump somewhere where you can
you can find a gadget
and a gadget is a bunch of btes that are executable but not necessarily on instruction boundaries
that do something
some weird thing you know
since the x86 is a is a variable length instruction machine
there's no nice crisp instruction boundary
so you can jump into the middle instructions
so
that's typically what these guys do is they find a buffer overflow they jump into the middle of one of these gadgets
which then jumps somewhere else into code that they've loaded or something
but you can't do that on the xbox
so let's shift gears into little prog prognostications about the future
you know what's the future of operating systems
that's a good question
uh
well
the question is what's what's uh
the op
the future of operating systems
and
um
you know
we vms is still alive after whatever
it's uh
35 years
a little over 35 years
it's 37
yeah
37 years
um
vms
i do not believe is nearly as big as windows as windows
i
you know
i hate to guess how many lines of coder in windows
but i think it's well over a billion
uh
might be several billion
it's huge
um
linux is smaller
unix is sort of gone
um
i really thought that linux would go the way same way that unix went where everybody took
unix
got a license to it and then tried to add their value
by making it incompatible with all the other versions of unix
which was great for us
because it just made it so that there there was fragmentation
um
linux seems to have not gone that way
i mean they've pretty much seem to have held themselves to be compatible
um
but still that's a huge system too
it's not as huge as as as windows
because it doesn't have 28 years behind it yet
you know it's got 15 or whatever it's got
but in 10 more years it'll have that too
um
there's a lot of
uh
little things that you can do like there's there's people that are building little operating systems for engine control
or something
but to build a big operating system is in in to build some level of compatibility
to run all these apps that exist is a very large effort
it may be an effort that even the the us government would want to take on
so the the thought that there's going to be a new operating system at the level of of linux
or of um
even unix or even
or or
uh
nt is kind of like
you know it's going to be difficult
um
i don't think it's going to happen very
if that happens
it's going to be a long time from now
um
and it'll happen
if it happens
it'll happen because the complexity the code bases grow to the point where it's like
do we want to solve the complexities of the code base or just want to throw it over
throw it away
and start over and people may say
well
we just want to throw away and start over
however
throwing it away and starting over doesn't mean that you can just junk the compatibility because you can't
you can't junk the compatibility is is big data
kind of a fork in the road for what an operating system is
no
big data is big data
the way i understand big data is just it's um
employing applications to um
visualize analyze sort through big big sets of data to find relationships that you otherwise couldn't find
it's not really an operating system per se issue
it's
it's more of a a data analysis thing
and it's
you know
it's
um
we have these huge data sets
we were doing this stuff at dupont
we were doing one of the things they did at dupont
they they did their own own program called rammer and rammer stored for
uh
regression analysis and multiple regression or something
which was basically
you're all the time at these chemical plants
you're trying to take the data that you collect and see what environmental variables
human variables
operational variables
chemical purity and whatever
what correlates with what
so you can rise to the optimum on some curve
some process
some on pro
right
and so that's part of the engineering services department had
was a a math and stat group that did just that
right
so we've been doing this stuff
but now people are starting to look at it in terms of things like marketing
you know
where do you target ads
um
and a lot of different things
i don't think it's per se an operating system thing
i mean
at some point we may have
in fact
we probably already do have big cloud applications that people you can buy
um and run and provide your data and have thousands of processors
yeah
well
one of the things that's nice about the cloud is the elas icity
is you can say i only want one processor right now or one core
or you could say i want 10, 000 and you could get 10, 000 processors all running in parallel
and
and maybe
um
they wouldn't be
they would be running as multiple instances of of um vms
or they could be running as multi-processing within a vm
right
so
is there any hope for the general decomposition of programs into parallel processing
well
you know people keep banging away at that stuff and it keeps getting better
um people have been doing that
you know
uh
ken kennedy at rice
i mean you
maybe you know
ken
kennedy was the big guy for the dusty deck fortran and infamous
and i'm sure he must be a fellow is
if he know
i don't know
yeah
um
he was part of
uh
the tera cray startup
m
um
he was doing dusty deck fortran in 1970
right
where they were taking fortran
and trying to take dusty deck fortran
and compile it so it could be vectorized and and done in parallel
and you know there's just lots of stuff going on
i think more of the the stuff is going on now
um
to not to not necessarily take the old stuff and make it run in parallel
but to always produce the new stuff to run in parallel
uh
one of the things in windows 10
in fact
i think it was in windows 8 too is um
user mode scheduling
to make it so that you can have
you know tens of thousands of threads and you schedule them yourself
um
so that there's a minimum overhead
because you know how you're switching
you don't necessarily have um 10, 000 processors
you might only have 20 processors
but you have
you know 10, 000 things that you might schedule
so there's s of sort of a move in a direction
that's
um
partly partly what was driving
that was the core um frequency thing where people realized
um
i don't know when that was about five years ago
or so
we realized that when
when fact intel said within 10 years we're going to have a 10 gz processor
and then they said oops
we're not probably ever going to have a 10 gz processor because of this problem
unless we
you know
we find some other way to build transistors
so
um
being able to run multiple threads
and schedule them yourself became something that that at least our people thought was um
essential to being able to
uh
to exploit parallelism inherently in programs from the start rather than saying
oh
we're going to take this old program and make it run in parallel
what do you think of ai
current state of ai ai
well
you know
ai is doing some things now that that
um
i think you know there
when ai started
there was this huge uh
uh
uproar about
oh
well
gez
you know
it's not going to be long because computers going to be everything
and it wasn't long before we thought well
computers ever do anything
but now you know there's a lot of ai that's going on
that's pretty
uh
groundbreaking
like
um
well
i i would
i'll call this ai
i don't know you call it ai
but i think the skype translator is absolutely unbelievably something that that is just unbelievable
this is where i don't know if you know about this or not
this is where you can
you can be french
and i can be spanish
and we can actually talk to each other and the skype will automatically translate it
when i talk
transl my language to your language
that's
that's unbelievable
right
how many phd theses were written about this before it happened
a lot
and you know
now we have on windows
we have um
fingerprint recognition for log on and we
debbie's
like she's
she just got a new phone
she dropped her phone i guess yesterday morning and broke it
and she says she's got her new phone
it's got windows 10 on it
and she says
look at this
i can log on with my eye
my eye print
my iris print can log on
so i think ai is really taken off
um
i
you know
the other thing
i guess ai
i
i guess you should think about
um
computer controlled cars
right
is ai
and you know
i think that that's great
but i see on one of these things that you gave me
uh
there was a question about
you know
will you ever sit in the back seat of a ai car
and i think the answer to that is not for a long time
um
you
i
i tell you why i believe that
i believe that
because i you know
that kind of ai is a little different than the speech thing
it's like the difference between
uh
having a machine like
um
a cat scan machine kind of machine
where you have
you have a real-time control
that machine
and if that control goes wacky
it kills somebody
as opposed to
we're speaking back and forth and we gar garble a word
that's a very different thing
right
so knowing how big and how complicated windows is and how complicated and big
uh
linux is
um
i think that there's a high probability that there is a large number of bugs in the software
unless it's extremely simple
now they may have taken linux
and stripped it down or whatever they took
and stripped it down to such a small thing
that they can actually reasonably be able to prove that it's correct
however
you know computers are not 100
%
you know they have every once in a while
there's like what happened
it just went away
you know
like
well
you know
tandem built systems that were triple redundant logic or whatever
so i don't know
i i haven't read anything about whether they have triple redundant um controllers in these systems
uh
that control cars but i would expect they do
and the other thing is
you know
like what happens when you know
one time we're in lancaster california and we've
we're going to a racetrack and we've rented a car from herz that has a neverlost
and guess what we lost
the never lost and we lost it
because the atmospheric conditions were such that the gps could not not work
so what happens
when you're whiting down the highway
and those atmospheric conditions occur and the gps doesn't no longer works your your proximity
uh
things work
but you don't know where you're going anymore
so i think there's some questions
that need a lot of answering before we put cars on a highway at 70 m an hour
and say yeah
here we'll get in the backseat and watch tv
me