Well, I'd- I'd like to introduce you to Alex Karp
and I know all of you are thinking
"Well, this man needs no introduction," and you're right about that.
But, you know, you know Alex Karp
the tech mogul, the defender of the West
the man who dreams of spraying fentanyl-laced ur- urine on
uh, short sellers, the author of The Technological Republic
the subject of The Philosopher in the Valley
the only person who has an optimistic of view- view of AI and American greatness.
But in other words, you know Alex Karp
my boss, and I want you to know Alex Karp
my friend.
Next to my late father, no person has a greater impact on my life than Alex.
And that's true in obvious ways, the success of Palantir
the face that he- the faith that he's placed in me
but it's also true in other ways.
You know, he's been my rabbi.
He's been my confidant, my guru, and at times
when I've given him cause, and I've given him cause
he's been my parole officer.
One of the first things Alex told me 20 years ago when we started working together is that he thought I had the constitution of a goat.
And he did not mean the Gen Z expression of greatest of all time.
He meant the animal.
That it seemed like I could survive eating trash and plastic in a barren wasteland.
And such a skill would come in handy in Washington
DC.
That's not a standard rubric for getting a job
but there's nothing conventional ab- about Alex.
Some months later, he asked me if I knew why French restaurants were so good.
I, in fact, did not.
At the age of 24, the closest I'd gotten to a French restaurant is a french fry.
He educated me that it's in part because the waitstaff are actually part of the kitchen staff.
They understand the technique.
They understand how the food is made.
They understand the methodology.
In other words, they understand the food from first principles.
They were a part of a complex system of delivering the experience
and this was his inspiration for creating the conception of Forward Deployed Engineering.
Now, I didn't have the heart to tell my father that my Cornell and Stanford education was about to qualify me to be a waiter at Chez Karp-  .
..
but that's what happened.
My- my father and Alex did agree on one thing for certain
which is that the Bhagavad Gita is amongst the most important books ever written.
Now, my father believed this despite never having read it.
To Alex, it was the most important business book ever written.
Well, maybe co-equal with Menachem Begin's biography.
And frequently, and as my literal guru in this case
he'd remind me of how Krishna selectively revealed the truth to Arjuna as he was driving his chariot into battle
purposefully matching what Arjuna was ready to hear and how he was ready to hear it.
And that begs the question, of course
that I'm sure you have, which is
what movie does Alex hold as the most important business movie ever made?
Well, that would be the kung fu classic
The 36 Chambers of Shaolin.
If you know the plot, then maybe you can see why.
But for everyone else, you're just gonna have to ask Alex.
You know, talking to Alex has always been like talking to an oracle.
Um, even when you understand what he's saying
the revelations are inscrutable.
When I do understand him, the predictions beggar belief
but then somehow, he's almost always right.
Al, as his friends at Haverford knew him
is a mensch.
He wants to see you succeed.
You.
He has a wildly positive-sum view of the world
rooted in a deep belief in the individual
especially the individual as an artist.
And he modeled Palantir as an artist colony
not a factory.
In place of conformity to process, he created a place that celebrated creative rebellion
a place of risk-taking, a place that seeks to tease out
develop, and back the artist.
And he says that makes us feel like a cult.
I agree.
We're a cult, not a company.
But he'd quip now and again he was the leader of a cult
but had none of the benefits.
I'll leave you with one final story.
I remember in 2008, our first Department of War deployment.
I was leading a ta- team of 10 people.
We were working for literally 14 hou- 14 days straight
19-hour days.
We consumed a heroic amount of Red Bull.
At the end of this, I called him incredibly grumpy
humorless from sleep deprivation, and I told him
"This is not gonna work.
It's unsustainable.
You know, like, we're gonna fail here.
" Without skipping he- a beat, he broke out in deep and self-satisfied laughter what was probably 30 seconds
but in my humorless mood felt like 10 minutes.
And I was shocked.
And of course, he understood that this was the only way that it was going to work
even if no one else did.
Not our customers, not our investors, and least of all not me.
The Hudson Institute is presenting Alex with the Herman Kahn Award
which is fitting because both men share many similar qualities
brilliant, unconventional, and people who make others nervous at dinner parties.
Herman thought about the unthinkable, and Alex built a company to make sense of it all.
And beneath that philosopher's hair and the ski gear is someone who believes that serious technology should serve serious purposes.
That the West needs to defend itself with both wisdom and strength
and that you can't protect democracy without occasionally making everyone a little uncomfortable.
So please join me in welting- welcoming a man who proves daily that you could run a half trillion dollar tech company while looking like you got lost on the way to Burning Man
Alex Karp.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
I, um, um, you know, I.
..
This award, award means a lot to me
um, and I obviously, um, you know
the alignment, the way in which the founder and participants
uh, here have shaped the world on the back of technology is super impressive.
I have a lot of remarks that I wanted to make
but I would say, um, for all
all of you who are, uh, younger and on your way to build important things
there is no greater award than getting a speech like that from Cham
um, especially since Cham can barely write.
He must have spent a lot of time on that one.
So it's, uh, it's, uh
it's.
..
Um, and we all know that, uh
the ups and downs, uh, we went through.
Cham's father, he mentioned, uh, was one of the great figures in building Palantir and told Cham
"You may never leave Palantir.
" That's probably why he didn't leave.
Also, with a great deal of love towards me
which I really appreciate.
And I'll tell you a story where maybe I've saved Cham and others many
many times, but Cham saved me when I.
..
After, in COVID, I'm, I'm basically an introvert
and every day, I enjoyed being alone more than the day before.
Every day.
It's like the silence, it was just the best thing that I.
..
I mean, obviously, once we realized we were gonna survive
uh-  .
..
I was like, this is.
I, I have this place in New Hampshire.
I have no neighbors.
I have bears and deer and, uh
and actually, all the neighbors I do have vote the same way everyone in this room does.
So, uh-  Um, and then Cham showed up one day
and he's like, "This isn't cutting it.
You gotta get back.
You gotta come back.
This isn't gonna work.
" And honestly, if anyone else had showed up
I'd been like, "That's so nice you said that.
Really enjoying  myself.
Can't spend a lot of money in New Hampshire where I.
..
" So like, so, um, and thank you
uh, and thank you all the Palantirians who
uh, burned the midnight oil and still do
uh, for, you know, sticking up for the West and listening to my crazy ideas.
And, um, I wanted.
..
I have a bunch of remarks that, to me
honestly, are less important than, than that introduction
which really means a lot to me.
Um, but just slightly remarks on, like
what have we learned about AI and business that's relevant?
And, and what I, what I, what am I'm pretty certain is going to affect our culture?
In, in philosophy, which I was once gonna be my metier and I realized should not be
um, uh, um, and, uh, for
for lots of reasons, but, um, in- including
most importantly, I thought it was more important to actually do things.
But it, it, one of the things people forget about philosophy is
the core concepts are actually downstream from things that were built in the world.
Modern architecture led to modern philosophy.
Post-modern architecture led to post-modern philosophy.
Um, and there's a weird way in which I think a lot of the trends that look inscrutable to us are actually downstream of
of tech and culture and are particularly pronounced in this culture
which is the only culture that really, really matters in AI.
It's from chips and what we call ontology to large language models
uh, to the talent, to the venture backing
to the understanding of how to organize the talent
they're in one country, and this.
..
our country.
And this does not make sense because the
the, the.
..
It would've, could've made sense in other trends
but actually, the mathematical basis of large language models started in
in, uh, in Germany.
It was Leibniz's idea of how to do probability
and then moved through France, and the best mathematicians in the world are mostly in France and in Russia.
And so what was it and what is it about
uh, what's happening that is affecting things that look very odd?
Like, um, why do, um, uh
you know, Ivy League-trained humanities, uh, uh
highly privileged people vote against their interest seemingly to elect political figures with no experience
uh, and who clearly.
..
Why are they misaligned with their own interests would be a question.
Um, and then why is it in America?
And I want to just start with the most obvious
um, obvious point that is so obvious we
we forget that the rights we have in this country are inalienable and they are given to us by God.
Because if you compare this to, say
the German constitution, which I, you know
wrote down the same as where we talk about endowed by their creator with certain unalienable rights
the German con- the German version, which is
um, translate roughly as, "A cons- conscience of his responsibility before God
" so not from God, "and mankind, inspired by the will of an equal member it- to be part of
" this is rough translation, "United Europe and to contribute to world peace.
" Okay, so we have these rights that are incorporated in our First and Second and
and now in our Fourth Amendment that aren't given to us by humans
they're given to us by a higher power.
That's very, very important in understanding.
When, when, when you look at businesses as an example
some businesses that look, that are five years appeal to be 20 years old.
Some businesses, uh, you know, we have Rupert Murdoch here who seems to be getting younger every year.
Uh, every year.
Uh, I've known you for a long time.
Uh, um, why is that?
Why, wh- and, and-.
..
the, the, the, the, the principle and then w- you have this
so you have this revolution, it's happening i- in a country which at least constitutionally
obviously not historically, is much, much older than Europe 'cause Europe
United Europe is only, it's under 30 years old and it's still not clear what it is really.
Um, you have a country which should not have been the leader of what matters in the world but is the leader in the world.
And, um, and then we have a very big moral problem in
in, i- the basis of most humanity
human rights historically, philosophically, legally, except for in America
have been based on our sec- basically superior cognitive capacities.
Um, and, you know, as Huntington
uh, once famously said, "We believe in the West that our values are superior.
" The non-West understands it's our org- it's our ability to organize violence
which is an in- intellectual and technological endeavor.
And that's the thing that has made us
at the end of the day, uh
be able to be superior over, uh
non, non-human life forms.
But with large language, which is, which-  .
..
but with large language models in AI, you actually have the first time where we
how do we, how do we justify our obvious superiority not just as a culture
but as a species vis-a-vis something that may be able to do cognitive things that we can't do?
And we are the lone country that has the basis for this.
Our rights are not given to us by our intellectual superiority.
They're not given to us by consensus built in Germany or in the United Kingdom.
They're not built to dedicate to world peace
although that would be nice.
They're given to us by our right that we were born here as Americans and those rights are indelible.
This is a very big distinction.
And it's one that we neglect and do not talk about and for lots of reasons many in the Valley may not be interested in talking about.
Um, and then there's, and then w- why are these so important?
Well, first of all, so obviously we have our rights vis-a-vis the machine.
Um, you know, and, and, and I think
and then you also have what does it mean to be in a world where you have very high-end labor being exceedingly valuable
formerly high-end labor, meaning you studied humanities and you would be working at a 501) dedicated to the United Nations-  .
..
not being objectively valuable.
I don't mean morally.
Most of us here would look askance at that as being misaligned with what they're saying.
But even if you don't view it that way
the reality is, a large language model can do all that work.
And if it's an ontology, we can do it much
much better.
So it's objectively not valuable.
What is valuable is working class, vocationally trained people with specific knowledge.
And here, I would see a, I see a tethering between the specificity of America that we have a Constitution given to us by God
that we believe in higher principles, that we defend them if we need to with our own guns
with our own free speech and with our own rights of privacy
and the specific things that create value in the world now.
Meaning specific knowledge of how to build something
how to target something, how to protect data
how to be a nurse or a doctor.
These skills can be very levered and are excruciatingly important.
So you have a constitutional and moral tethering of exactly what you would need in one specific culture and that's this culture.
But you're gonna have a lot of turbulence because we're now moving from
you know, w- people who believe they deserved empathy and this is when I think the biggest tensions
one of the very radical things about Palantir that our enemies do not believe
we at Palantir have maximal empathy for Americans
for the right of Americans to be free
and for men, men and women that actually do work.
And our society, if you, if you go
if you look, if you look at any professions what you'll see
we read the law so somehow the law will not allow us to protect Americans who are being murdered by fentanyl.
But more th- more Americans have died of fentanyl than have died in any war since World War II.
If those were Stanford grads or Cornell grads
you can bet your last dollar they are your d- uh
uh, jurisdictions would read the law so that you could stop that.
But they're not.
They're working class, they're mostly male, they're mostly white
and mostly people don't care.
And we have to change that.
When things go wrong because those people know that no one cares about them
that's also our fault.
Like not anyone in this room, but like we don't show empathy if you look at
if you look at, for example, the way analysts more neutrally do models
they love the people they like.
It shows up downstream in the model.
That's why Palantir was undervalued.
We were undervalued and misunderstood because we were doing radical crazy stuff they didn't like.
If you look all across the world and what you're seeing go on in America now is an enormous shift towards we have to actually look at where the value is created and have empathy with people who really deserve it.
And those people have not got enough empathy and technology is about to change that and it's gonna change everything politically because it is actually real.
The worker, the person on the front
the people that write the scripts that protect us
all those projects you saw are being done by people with vocational training in the military.
They're creating enormous value and they deserve the respect that they are going to ask for and they're going to get.
And Palantir and all of us who are Palantir are behind that.
Uh, and th- and I, this just and
and then conversely, how do you get a situation in the city where you just vote for someone who has no experience in doing what they're going to do?
None.
Even like I grew up, I view myself as classically progressive.
I care.
..
You know what classically progressive is?
The government has to work.
You know what that means?
You need the very best people.
Who are the people?
They have experience running complicated organizations.
They have ideas on how to run software.
They understand the complexity of the law.
They enforce it.
If you're really serious about making th- things work for the worker
those are the people you vote for.
Those are the people that need to be in charge.
And that's, that's why a lot of these crazy things are actually very much explicable based on what is going on in AI and who's creating the value and how they create it.
Th- th- then last, maybe not least
on the AI front, one of the reasons we are in a kind of a doomer AI circle is because you can only explain the promise of AI if you understand and embrace the superiority of America and its culture.
Because there are dangers in AI, but the reality is
there's only two cultures that are going to win in the next year.
It's gonna be us or China.
Th- th- Europe, I spent half my life in Europe.
At this point, we, when we talk about Europe
we do exactly the same thing as when we hear about educational programs th- in
led by mayors or safety programs in the inner city.
We just say that, "I really hope it works out.
"  Please.
And I want Europe to win, but we're on our own.
Uh, and, and that, of course there are dangers in AI.
And, uh, and AI is also and will never be anything other than a dual use technology
but we must, must embrace our ability to build it
our ability to own the chips, to own the software
build the large language models, and run very
very quickly, because again, to quote Huntington again
"If we are not the ones controlling the violence
we will not be dictating the rule of law.
" The things we hold precious in this culture
I would say embodied by our Constitution and especially in our first four amendments
those things will not be the same if we are not the dominant technological culture in the world.
And while we may have tons of disagreements on these things
we must, the, the, uh, th- those are really the alternatives
and most of what we can do, in my view
to counter adversaries is also to build the technology and then
you know, one of the lessons of Palantir is no one's coming to defend you.
You have to defend yourself.
We used to live in a world where you could rely on experts to articulate our vision.
But who showed up to articulate our vision in this last election in my hometown?
Formerly hometown.
Like, we, if we're waiting for people to articulate and fight for us
we are cooked.
And like, and, and  it's
a- and so, and, you know, the people who disagree with us are
like, often better organized and better motiv- and more motivated.
And that's a huge problem we have to solve.
Palantirians, half of the reason we succeeded is we were just motivated
and very organized, and very meritocratic.
Uh, meritocracy is the most underestimated, powerful
revolutionary tool that exists in any enterprise ever.
And that means, you know, Sham is a great example.
Sham was not everyone's cup of tea.
And s- he advanced because he, for really two reasons.
He advanced because I thought he was gonna be an incredible human being
and second, and I'll leave you with this
because I saw him interacting with his brother and I was like
"If he could love Palantir half as much  as he loves his brother
we are going to have the most important enterprise in the world.
" And like the capacity to identify and advance people on a meritocratic base that have capacity to care is the single most revolutionary tool.
And my kind of thinker has been infected
meaning the progressive party of the Democrats, by people who do not believe in this.
And by the way, to my Democratic friends here and whoever sees this
that we must stand up.
One of the most important lessons in the West is
if you do not fight and in a- as importantly
if you accept the logic that you can never vote for somebody
uh, because of they have some sub-belief structure you disagree with
you are empowering the radicals in your own party and they will control everything.
Whether it's immigration in Germany, which functionally controlled by people that still believe in chain migration because you can never do a coalition with the right
or whether it's the Democratic Party that is functionally being torn apart by people who believe in anti-progressive
anti-meritocratic values as embodied by not having a border.
No progressive ever has believed in an open border.
None, never, has never existed because that com- undermines the value of workers and their labor.
And if you wanna see what happens to a culture when you don't fight
look at, there's, who's standing up in my former party to say
"This is ridiculous"?
Who stood up in Germany to talk about migration?
We cannot allow ourselves to become Europe.
We really have to fight.
And I'm, I'm sure many of the
in here are gonna be involved in that.
And Palantir, I think, has been at the forefront of this and I'm most proud of the fact that we've been able to shift the culture to being
in Silicon Valley, away from being skeptical of America to being pro-America.
The idea that you would give tools to give Americans an unfair advantage in th- on the battlefield was viewed as heretical until recently.
Now it's viewed as common sense.
The idea that we have, uh, we enforced meritocracy when we were getting sued by the DOJ for j- basically just hiring the most qualified people.
Um, and, and, and if you do that and you succeed
you can actually change the way people think.
And .
..
Thank you.