the following is a conversation with ray dalio
his second time on the podcast
he is a legendary investor
founder of bridgewater associates
author of a book i highly recommend
called principles
and also a new book called principles for dealing with a changing world order
that looks at the geopolitics of today
especially us and china
to the lens of history
providing a fascinating model for the rise
and fall of empires that can be applied to the analysis of our world
today
this is the lex friedman podcast to support it
please check out our sponsors in the description
and now here's my conversation with ray dalio
when you look at the history of the world as you have done in your new book
principles of dealing with the changing world order
what is more important
more
impactful
money or power
they go hand in hand
they support each other and they
um
compete with each other
those who have money
have power
a certain type of power
um
that power has to do with all that they can buy
but it also has the ability to influence those with political power
so
um
and
and so you see this throughout history
this symbiotic relationship
you know
um
for example
between
um
the royal families
the nobility and the church
so you see that group of people supporting each other in various ways
and then wrestling around with each other for the money and power among that group
so the dynamic that's quite classic is you could look at the parties in power back in
you know the 16th 17th centuries
you would look at
uh
royal families
nobles and um
and the church
if you're in europe
and then you would look at agricultural land and there was a certain dynamic
and that varies over time
it changes as those people get thrown out and technology changes
so when we evolved
when the society evolved so that it would produce goods and services
and you have something like the industrial revolution
the first industrial revolution
you have machines and you have the talent of people that are off the farms
and then you have a struggling for power
you see that power mix change
and so we don't see that same power mix anymore
but you still see the same dynamic
you see those with money
dealing with those who have political power around those assets that are considered most valuable to
particularly the productive assets that produce money
and political power is usually centered around nation state
so the major locus there's of power is the nations
yes
in 1668
after 30 years of war
there was the development of nation states
before then we had
it was really the development of countries
as we know it
that there were borders and that within those borders
uh
those who had control got to control it
and there was not to be intrusions in those borders
and that's how we established the nation state
and then
of course
within each country
there is levels
there is a central level
and then there is a typically a province or state level down below
and then there's a municipal level
so they each have different levels of power
and it's the coordination of those that determines how the country is run
you write that the quote archetypal big cycle governs the rising and declining empires and influences everything about them
including their currencies and markets
the most important three cycles are the ones you mentioned in the introduction
the long-term debt and capital market cycle
the internal order and disorder cycle and the external order and disorder cycle
can you describe this big cycle
there are two orders
there is an order by a sip order
i mean a system
how the system works
so there's an internal order
that is the internal governance system and it's usually set out in a constitution or some agreements
and then there's the world order
uh
how the world system
so
for example
in 1945
um
at the end of a war
which is basically a fight for determining the world order
um
the winners of the fight got together and created the world system
as we now know it
they created the brenton woods monetary system that determined the money pretty much
and because the united states won and had 80 percent of the world's money
gold was money then and had 80 of the world's gold
and it was half the world economy and it was the great military power
the order was built around an american world order
so that the united nations was in new york
the world bank and the imf were in washington and they built that new order
so classically
you have a war to determine whose rules we're following and then you have
um
the new water beings constructed after that
there is usually period of extended peace and prosperity
uh
peace suits prosperity
um
and so there's not
and the reason you have the peace is because no one wants to fight with the um dominant power
you know you're going to lose
you've surrendered
there's been the surrendering
they carve up the world
they say what it's going to look like
who's going to control what
and then you come into that period of of peace and then prosperity
where then there's uh
a working together
usually at that point you've wiped out a lot of the debt
you've wiped out a lot of the issues
the class warfare and so on
and then there's good working together
so those great periods um such as the industrial revolution in the late 1800s
or what we've experienced in the post-world war ii period are peaceful and prosperous periods led largely
by the dominant world power over a period of time
since really 1500
and maybe before but really 1500
when the dutch invented capitalism
and what i mean by that they invest
invented the first capital markets
the first stocks and the first stock market
um
that since then
capitalism has been an effective tool for building wealth because it got resources into the hands of inventive people
that's when we moved from agriculture to the importance of inventiveness of people
they got resources and then they built that prosperity in that process of doing that
they create wealth gaps
naturally
those who make a lot of money make a lot more and than those that don't
and it also produces opportunity gaps
because
uh
for example
those who earn a lot of money have that wealth
they have the power to educate their children in a way that others don't
and the gaps grow and also the debts grow at that time
when they go around the world with their competitiveness
they earn a lot of money
so
for example
the dutch
the dutch empire learned how to build ships
um
and that would go around the world
a key ingredient of this improvement in this cycle is the improvement of education and by education
i mean the skills that come from education
but also civility
the ability to deal with
well together
so the dutch invented ships that could go around the world and they had military power
but they were also very inventive
society
25 of the world's new inventions came from the dutch
and so
as they went around the world
they also brought their currency and they brought their military
they needed their
the currency they paid for things
um
and that currency
and then the more that happens
the more that becomes a reserve currency
and then they have their military
so they need their military strength
and so you see it evolve in all of those ways
but over a period of time
um
as they become more successful and more expensive
they became
they become more expensive
um
and and newer countries come along like um
the uk
um
then
uh
be learned to build ships from a lot
the dutch and could do that less expensively
and also
when they become more expensive
so less competitive
and also the work ethic begins to change
they believe that since they're richer
they can enjoy life more
they don't have to work quite as hard
and so you start to see the tilt
now you start to see the development of the top and
when you have a world reserve currency that allows you to borrow a lot of money
because those who want to save
want to hold your money
and that means that they'll lend you money
and so those countries get deeper into debt
so you see that they gradually lose their competitiveness and they
um
and they get themselves into financial circumstances
which are not good and they have large wealth gaps
which set the stage for downturns
and when they have downturns
um
the first question is
do they have enough money
and traditionally you know
uh
money is
is resources
um
so you classically see that the coffers are bare
that they're spending more money than their than they are earning
and they run out of money in the coffers and their granaries are empty rather than stocked
so that they give them the buffer
and as that deteriorates
that's that worsens conditions
and if they have a rival power
that's also challenging them
they see greater internal conflict over wealth
and then they have the problems internally and the problems externally
which usually results in an internal war
or an external war that leads to the change in the to the new world order
and to you
the dutch empire is a good example that
the british
what are some of the key examples that you think about in the book of this process
that follow the big cycle
well
the leading reserve currency empires
but it applies to all the empires
um
were the
the dutch
the british
uh
the american and the chinese
um
but
you could follow the same pattern
um
in the book i
it was very important for me to not just use words and concepts because that's subjective
it was very important for me to use actual measurements
so as you see
in the book
you can see every level of this
you can see
where is the education level
what is the military power
each one of those
and you could see them back going over the 500 years
and so
um
you can see the arcs and the composition of those arcs
and what you see is really in most countries
in most dynasties you can see that
but you also can see through those numbers
the health
um
of those countries today
there are
there are statistics that you could
that are in the book that show what is the level of education
what is the letter level of economic output
what is the level of um military strength
what is the level of a number of different measures of strength
so that you can then compare that
and i think that because there are objective measures of strength that you could see change
that shows the picture of where we are today
and i think one of the most important things about the book is
that it allows people to monitor how those things are transpiring
i think for policy makers
um
you know
are your policy policymakers doing a good job
and there's so much subjectivity in that
but i think it's very simple if those lines on the chart are improving
if your health index is improving
then you're moving toward a better life
so that's what the book works like
also it was used to create a model for the future
in other words
there are cause effect relationships
everything that happens has reasons
causes that preceded it
that made it happen
and so by having all those in numbers
one can see the probabilities of certain things happening
so
um
that's what
that's what you see in in the book
it's not just
you know
rey's interpretation
i didn't want to make it raise interpretation
because i don't know if i'm right
yeah
so one of the fascinating things in the book
so you have list these 18 measures
and there's like a little scorecard for the countries of the world today
so let's say u.
s china
and europe and what it was 20 years ago and looking at the change from 20 years ago
and that's another indicator to change itself to see where things are headed
maybe
can you comment on
from a score perspective
how is u. s and china
doing and in the 18 measures
what are some measures that stand out to you
is particularly important to think about today
for the united states
for china
well
there are a number
um
financially
what you see in the united states is that
um
we're borrowing a lot more money
creating a lot of debt and we're
uh
printing a lot of money and our capacity to do that is very much is limited
first of all
because
um
when you
when there's a sale of a bond
when the government borrows more than it borrows money
because it spends more than it takes in
um
you have to sell a bond and the world right now has a lot of us dollar denominated bonds
because as the world's reserve currency
they sell sold on them
and they have very bad returns
negative real returns
negative
real returns
significantly
and so on
so that um means that more bonds has to be sold than um are bought
and
that means
that the federal reserve has is faced with the choice of having to raise the interest rate to curtail borrowing
which slows the economy and hurts the markets
or by filling that difference and producing money
the debt monetization
which produces an inflation in goods
services and financial assets
so in that regard
that's our the united states's position
in china's case
its balance of payments
um
is a better
china has displaced the united states as the world's largest trading country
in other words
more exports to other countries and as a result
it's economically competitive
but it doesn't have the world's reserve currency
it's a real blessing
so the united states
it has the world's reserve currency
but it is risking it because of this imbalance
so if you look at history
you see that those go slowly
but when they go eventually
they go quickly
so there's a risk of of of that financially
then there's the issue of
uh
internal order
so i'm just giving you the major ones
but i'll get into some of the other ones too right now
um
there's a lot of internal conflict in the united states
uh
which affects its
and um
how well it works
um
in china
there's less internal conflict because it's a more autocratic state
but also they've created this bifurcation of what is political and what is um economic
in terms of producing that prosperity
so if you stay out of the politics pretty much um
and then you're seeing um entrepreneurship
you're seeing the finances of new businesses and so on
and so that internal working
um
you know that's subject to different people's
interpretations
whether they like it or not
but the internal conflict in terms of those kinds of measures is
is less sorry to pause on that for a second
so these measures
i guess you don't want to sort of um
romanticize any one measure or something like that
over interpret any one measure
but is internal conflict
always a bad thing is some
is this
uh
is it a complicated calculation
or do you kind of the way we think about these measures that you've presented
we should be thinking like the higher
the better
the lower worse
or i mean
of course
depending on
well
in many cases
the conflict that produces the revolution produces revolutionary changes that lead to resolutions that and lead to new starts
and so their short term
a short-term civil war is a hellacious experience
and at the same time it can be
um
the transition to a new beginning
also
there are different types of conflict
uh
competition
which makes things makes everything better
is
is a productive conflict
whereas destructive conflicts are not good over the short time
so you know that's how that those go
so
within each measure
the story is complicated
yeah
but my measures are are sort of clear meaning
how much political conflict
how much social conflict
in other words
you can measure conflict
you can measure fighting
you can measure crime rates
you can measure
um
lots of different ways of conflict
so the measures are a composite of different types of internal conflict
what are some other interesting measures
maybe if you can also mention
like
for me
in particular interest is education and innovation
yes
the classic cycle
the most important leading indicator is the quality of education
most importantly
broad-based education
drawn as a from the largest population
because you can never tell who the talent is going to be
so where they're going to come from
so
for example
if you look at the chinese dynasties
the great chinese dynasties
um
and the confucian approach
it was meritocratic
of um
everybody could sit for exams and so
on broad base of drawing in the populations and you see that
if you go across societies
because that draws on the largest number of population to get education
and it also
um
that creates
a reality and a perception that the system is fairer
equal opportunity
not just one of privilege
and that helps to create social stability
but education is not just
uh
education in understanding facts and so on
it is education and um
civility of how to behave together
and so if they're smart
they understand how to be productive
because they work well together and they're productive
and then that leads to the next stage
you could see
in the lines in the charts
we i plotted these so that you could see in a typical cycle
you could see that education is the long leading indicator
and then you could see
as you mentioned that you
what you see is inventiveness and technology measures then follow
and you see
then also competitiveness in world markets
follows
for example
in the early stages of a cycle
the industries that they go into um
tend to be very basic industry
because they have cheap labor
something like textiles and simple manufactured goods
and so on
but as the education rises
then they move up the value chain to uh tech
greater technologies and so on
which raises incomes and raises productivity
so yes
those
and
and you know
as you say
there are 18 different measures like that
but education
um
and then civility and the inventiveness
so you see it reflected in in who's inventing what
um
and that corresponds
then who's trading with
who's a big trading country and where's the value of economic output and what are per capita incomes
they all follow those arcs
yeah
like you said
the fascinating thing about your book
so there's philosophy
there's wisdom
uh
but there's plots
yeah
you can see it
so it's not just your opinion
it's kind of like
uh
you can interpret it any way you like
but you're just giving a lot of of your own insights along with the numbers
if you were to look at the american nation
the american empire and the trajectory is looking into the future
given these measures
what is the trajectory that leads to the collapse of the american empire
based on these measures
what are the concerning indicators
and if
um
if those break down further
what does that look like
well
all of those indicators are concerning
um
maybe except for one
which is technology
the technology niche
although
even in that area
the united states is improving at a slower rate than is china
for various advantages that they have there
they put out about eight times as many computer engineers
they have free data
and so on
but if you look at them so the financial is a is a concern
the internal order disorder is a concern
then if you look at education levels
the united states is in many way is is losing its educational advantage
if you were to look at
compare it with china
if you take general public education in the united states
it's deteriorated tremendously even in comparison to developed countries
there are scores pieces scores
and so on
and it's
you know
something like 38th in the world or something
and that was a big plunge
average public education
if you look at the best universities in the world
the united states is unique in having the best universities in the world
so there are these privileged spots
um that are
you know
excellent
uniquely
so when you look at the comparison
education in china is improving rapidly and it
and the quantity is a quantity of educated people in the areas that they're moving in
are
is is greater and the resources that they're putting behind it is greater
and so you see
the results are greater
um
but
it's sort of along the lines that i'm i'm dealing with
if you were to follow through in terms of um
actual productions
i i think
uh
you
you know
in terms of technologies
um
there are some areas that the united states is in a lead at the moment
there's some areas that china's in a lead
but china's gaining very quickly when i first went to china
i would bring 10 calculators
and i gave them away as gifts to high ranking people and they thought they were miracle devices
um
right now
in terms of areas like quantum computing and a. i
and
and you know many areas
you have a race going on
and so if you take the trajectory of the competitiveness
not just look at the current level
you have a situation where they're improving at a much faster rate
this is all good for the world
if the world can get along
and the main thing i think is
um
in just how do you have a healthy world and how do you have a strong economy
and how do you have a strong situation
is
be strong
the united states is
war is with itself
that's the main war
you know it's very simple in history
[music] be financially sound
earn more than you spend
um
and be strong in these ways and pretty much everything will take care of itself
but you make it sound simple
of course
because there's a momentum when things degrade when the education system degrades when you start borrowing
when
um
i mean all of these indicators once
once they start going down
it's
uh
there's a momentum to it right
so it's hard to reverse it right
and there are circumstances that you're then in
uh
for example
indebtedness
you know it's politically desirable for those in to borrow money and spend
because their constituencies only look at what they get and when they get a lot
they don't pay attention to the balance sheet and how much debt is on the books
so it's always better to borrow spend and then leave the cleanup to the next guy
and so you inherit a lot you inherited as a new president enters in
or new legislators
they have a lot of debt
they have a broken down infrastructure
um
they don't have enough money to fix that
and so that's the lay of the land that the prior generations put you in
and there you are
and so that's right
um
it's difficult
because when you start to think
okay
what's healthy
well
spend earn more than you spend
that's not so easy
because you know
what does that mean
go earn more
i mean
okay
that's not so easy
spend less
that isn't going to work
so now what do you do
okay
you have this debt that you then monetize
and that's why it's classic
so
yes
that's why these cycles occur
because what has created before
put
what happened before created
the lay of the land
that is then increasingly difficult to deal with
so what can great leaders do in this moment
i mean
maybe
um
my sense is leadership is crucial here
so for example
to do very large projects that invest in the education system
that sort of try to fix the fundamentals or maybe invest more
and more into the innovation and the develop development of new technologies
and so on
it feels like that just doesn't happen organically
so you have to have strong leaders that convince the populace of the importance of these ideas
well
i completely agree with your list
what we have is a situation where everybody has their opinions
and they have to sort of get them exactly right
and they all fight with each other about whether their opinions
so
the most important thing is that we are become bipartisan so that we don't
and we get over our differences
i would have a bipartisan cabinet
i would draw upon um
both members of both parties
the the moderates
who are going to be able to work together
so as then we have one country
and then we deal with those in a means
that works for the majority of the people in the middle rather than the polarity
i think our greatest risk is in not being able to do that
so i would say that's a paramount importance
because we have the resources
you know
um
wealth
real wealth and and science
and everything has never been better than it is
but the notion is that it has to work for the majority of people
and we have to keep it being productive
so that that group has got to calmly and knowledgeably work together
so that they increase the size of the pie and they create broad-based prosperity
so that is a paramount importance
whatever they do
if they do it
that way
i can say i'm happy about
because that other alternative is the really scary alternative
the
the scary alternative
the different ways it has evolved throughout history
some of it has led to wars what are the future trajectories
that lead to a potential war with china
cold war or hot war
is this something you think about
is this something you're worried about
yeah
i'd like to talk about both wars
so the war with china
as i say
there are five kinds of wars
there's a trade war
tech
um
technology
war
geopolitical
influence
war
um
capital war and military war
i
um
as far as military war goes
i only
i think it's only a taiwan issue
um
but that's a big issue
and we could talk about that for a minute
but those others there'll be
uh
rough competitions and we'll have that type of evolution over a period of time
that's what that war looks like
taiwan has been for a long time
a sovereignty issue to china
and it has its roots in what's called the hundred years of humiliation
from the 1840s to 1949
foreign powers came in took advantage of china
they had the opium wars and such times
and
and that represented the 100 years of humiliation and taiwan represents
is their sovereignty and their important thing
and 50 years ago
starting 50 years ago
there was an agreement that there is one china
and taiwan is part of china and that there would be peaceful reunification
the the peaceful reunification hasn't happened
and in their view
that's a very big issue
and so it's a big contentious issue
and that
uh
could produce a military war
um
could produce a military accident
could produce a
it's a very tense situation
and if we had a military war
god help us because of the capacity in all different new ways to inflict um harm on each other
but anyway
that's that's that
if you don't have that military war
you'll have the competition between those other kinds of wars and whoever is strongest in those areas
will um win
where do you put cyber war within the five
well
cyber war is a military war
i'm assuming the type of cyber war that you're using you're referring to
is that
which it's used to inflict pain on the other party through cyber
so cyber wars
you'll see cyber war
you could see space war
you can see drone warfare
you
um
new types of warfare
not just the traditional and nuclear type of warfare
but you could see any of the above
what are the defining characteristics
what are the interesting things about xi jinping
the president of china as a leader on the world stage
his father was a early leader
he was himself
[music] in the cultural revolution
at times treated brutally
um
and during that period of time
it was very
very difficult and he came up
you know
through the ranks
and he's a very intelligent man when he first came to power
they
as you know
they have two five-year terms and we're now coming to the end of the second of those five-year terms
when he first came to power
he felt that there should be a lot of reform
and reform meant moving to much more of a market
an open economy
when that happened in him coming in
i had some contact with economic policymakers
but
and the circumstances then were that five major banks lent to state-owned enterprises
and local governments with implied government guarantees
and so there was not control of that
and they
and the movement to aim more of a market economy and the development of markets
uh
was a primary and also the dealing with the corruption issue
there was a lot of corruption prior to that
and that was viewed as an existential threat to the system
so that became the primary objective
and then
as time progressed
over those 10 years
there was a a lot of changing in the world
finance
their financial circumstances
opening many
many other markets
they particularly getting money to small
and medium-sized enterprises and developing a lending system and then establishing controls on it
so right now
um
there's a vibrant
um capital markets
um
you can raise capital
you can be an entrepreneur
you can become a billionaire
um in the capital markets
and they develop the markets to be the second largest capital markets at the same time
um
they had to deal with their um
rising debt issue
which they began to deal with
uh
really about four years ago when the second term began and the um
and then uh
lu huh
became
um
the vice premier
responsible for that and to um and deal with uh
those issues
so you see right now that what's happening is
uh
the dealing with the real estate bubble
there was a development in real estate
a bubble which produced
um
a lot of unproductive lending
and xi ping said you know houses are meant to live in
not to speculate on
and so that was wasteful
so they established what they call three red lines
which are financial ratios that the property developers had to live within
and that is then causing the adjustments that are going on now
which in my view are very healthy
because
um
whenever there's uh
bankruptcies and so on
the most in the public
think
okay
that's a problem
it's in many cases really a cleaning up of bad debts and bad practices
and so
um
that's what's going on
so that's let's say
economically
at the same time
there is the changing relationships
the changing world order the changing relationships with the united states and other countries
which is becoming
um
much less cooperative and much more war-like much more confrontational
those two things
the the domestic debt problem and domestic has led to
um
what's called core
what they call core leadership
which means a leadership more around him
that is less challenging
because they believe in history
that during very difficult times
um
a more centrally controlled decision-making process lends itself better than to a more fragmented political contentious project
and that's basically what's going on
now you said it very eloquently
but you mean the leadership is surrounded by yes men
and there's a lot of centralized control
that characterization is
view
is much more black and white than it really is
uh
but it leans towards that direction they're like
for example of the standing members of the polar bureau
four are more eligi allied him three or less
so you have to understand that it's kind of a collective leadership at the top
and then
of course there's just jockeying for power
um
you know
in a highly political sense
um
at the top
uh
but no one leader can be successful against the uh
all those powers at the top
so it's very politically negotiating
it's
you know
it's very much more like
if you put um in the united states
the democrats and the republicans and they had to be in the same government and they work it out
uh
it's kind of something like that
and then
so that's that struggle
but it's an internal struggle
where do you put the importance of some of these ideas at the founding of the united states
when then now we're talking about at the context of china
the freedom of speech
freedoms
what china is doing with the central management of a lot of things
it's enabling a lot of growth
but it's also limiting people on the very basic level
in terms of freedom
the kind of freedom that i think can lead to entrepreneurship to starting new businesses
to having big dreams and chasing those dreams and then creating totally new things in whatever the space
maybe in technology
in business and whatever
what
how important is that as a metric for society
well
they have a view
which is the idea of a dialectic
which means that two things are at obvious
that everything comes with pros and cons and two opposites exist
and you want the benefits of those two opposites
and how do you deal with the benefits of those two opposites
right
so let's say you want the capital markets because it gets
uh money into the hands of the entrepreneurs who are motivated they build fortunes
and that drives an economy to do very well
and at the same time
um
it produces
uh
the other problems
the wealth gaps
then the debt cycle that we're talking about
and so on
and deng xiaoping
you know
how do you reconcile communism and
um
the market economy and the capital markets
and he
uh
famously said
um
and if it doesn't matter
if it's a white cat or a black cat
just as long as it catches mice
in other words
if it
if it works in making the country richer
then that becomes the objective
and then they move that along
so there are these conflicts
um
and um
one of the leaders described it to me as follows
because it's confusion and it goes back over a period of time
there's a a hierarchy and it's an extension of
uh
the family
he described it and he said the united states is a country of individuals and individualism
and that is its vibrancy
that
um
we see the individual rights to speak up
the individual [music] protection of the individual
individual property rights and all of those things
as of uh
paramount importance
and we build our organization
that's why democracy is from the bottom up
or even a company
we'll get together and we'll be partners to proper prosper
together that is the american approach
um
he was describing that in china
it's an extension of the confucian family essentially
and so it's almost like
um
you know
there's a hierarchy
and so what they think about is the common good
uh
not the individualism
so
for example
if they want a high-speed rail to go from one place to another
and that's best in the common good
then the individual protections that would stand in the way of doing that would be of secondary concern
so that notion of uh controlling
so it
it
for example
um
the what what they're doing with
uh
video games
um
they
control
uh what type of video games and how many hours a day
kids can be on video games
um
operating in that way
because they believe that that's good for the society and that's very controlling in the united states
i i think probably most parents would say
leave it to me
and it's it's a matter between me and my kids
the same thing has to do with data
in other words
in the united states
who controls the data
does the company control the data
do you individually control the data
and so the inclination would be to figure that out
but nobody would say that the government is going to control the data
because of our inclination of really anti-government control in china
it would be that the government will control the data because that's going to be best for the society
and it depends who you trust
but that's so that difference in philosophy is very much at the um
you know
at the heart of that
as far as um
your question in terms of effectiveness
it really is in china's case
it's how you balance the things right
so what they're attempting to do is to create a lot of freedom and creativity
um
in areas that are not
uh
political
let's say
and and so you see
on a lot of entrepreneurship
you see a lot of product development
you see a lot of creativity
um
happening in that way
so the stereotype that you don't see creativity happening is is an old stereotype
where's a lot of creativity
certainly happening
and the system can work well if they can achieve that kind of balance
it's proven to have worked well since i started going there in 1984
per capita income
real per capita income has increased by 26 times
the um longevity rate has increased by 10 years
the poverty rate has fallen from 88 to less than 1
in terms of
you know
basics like starvation and things
and if you read history
plato's republic
you know he talks about the cycles
democracy
you know an autocratic and the benevolent despot
and all of that
each has their own vulnerability
the vulnerability of democracy
which has been a remarkable remarkable system and i don't have to extol the benefits of it
um
but the vulnerability of it has always been
uh
the um
internal conflict that produces itself as anarchy
um
in world war ii
uh
four democracies chose to be autocracies
um
because there was internal disorder and there
was
this is the belief
will somebody bring about order and get control of the situation
you know that was in
um
germany
italy
uh
japan
and spain
um
they were parliamentary dictat systems that
uh
turned themselves over to that
so both systems
um
have vulnerabilities
i think the main thing now that we need to think about is those vulnerabilities
democracy is an amazing system because it requ
the
the adherence to the rules
and the system
and the checks and balances is quite amazing and it gives it a flexibility to change without civil wars
um
but there has to be the respect of the rules
and when you see something like that
they will not accept elections or they will not accept rules
and history has shown when the causes that people are behind are more important to them than the system
the system is in jeopardy
so we have a situation that's very much like that
in terms of let's say the 2024 elections
i believe that there's a very high chance that neither side will accept losing
for example
and so we
um
we have that kind of a situation
so one would hope that one could rise above the disagreements and rely on the system
uh
for resolving disagreements
because if if that doesn't happen
then we have our own
uh chaos
so the kind of the trend that started in 2020
this
or i mean
i mean
i suppose it's been there
it's been growing a rep
one representation of this internal disorder has been the growing trend of being skeptical about the results of the election
well
it started before that
there was the emergence of populism
where
before uh president
uh
trump was elected
he was basically elected as a populist
because there was a large percentage of the population that felt that the system didn't work for them
and he tapped into that and he was largely elected as a populist
leader
first
populous leader in a developed country
um
and so populism began that
then
and that was a battle of one group against the other group
and so since then it's been like that and it continued to grow
you've mentioned the vulnerability of democracy
that internal disorder is the vulnerability of democracy
what's the vulnerability of a system like china
maybe one way to say is put china aside and look at history like a soviet union
what's the vulnerability of a communist type system
well
i'll call it both communist and autocratic
sure
depending on how much autocracy is that it lacks flexibility
it
it lacks
um
the ability
so
but i should deal with them differently
um
in other words
there's the economic system
the economic system
um
threatens motivation and productivity
so communism or socialism
uh
has to be done in a way where
um
you can threaten productivity
capitalism has
and what i mean by that
i mean free markets and capital markets
i have been an effective way of allocating resources and also creating the
the incentives and the resources
providing the resources for the inventiveness of new ideas
and so if i compare that
what the chinese have done to a large extent is to recognize that and have made a move
that's why the uh seeming dialectic or the conflict between those two things exists
but anyway
that's it
as far as an autocratic system
rather than um
one man
one vote from the population up
the risks of the autocratic system is
that there's enough discontent that arises that the system doesn't have the flexibility
and that
rather than bending
um
it breaks
that's that's the big risk
um
the notion of trying to control a um
if there's that
rather than giving it the flexibility
um
so that's the
that would be the big risk of the autocratic system
what's the human
uh
because you mentioned
like the top gets bigger with empires
and you start taking things for granted is the some of this just human nature
so the concern with with china with autocratic nations
the concern with the the third reich
the soviet union was that fundamentally at the individual level
the humans involved at the top they start becoming
they're starting to lose touch with reality in a way that no longer makes them
i guess that's the representation of the flexibility that you're referring to
well
i'm
i mean
in a democracy you could change
you can go as far left or as far right
you can change the leaders easily
and so the people don't become
um
you know
they pretty much only have themselves to blame
uh
yeah
you know
and one of the problems of that is they may not choose the best leaders
but they
they have that flexibility
so if vote and you get what you wanted in the case of the autocratic
let's say
leaders
and then the movement from democracies to autocracies
what you see
normally that movement is that one of the systems
is
it is not working
let's say the democracy is not effectively
everybody's arguing with each other and nobody's getting anything done
and you know
like mussolini
the trains are not running on time
and that would be the example
jesus
this place has gotten chaotic
will somebody get into control and then they
then you get the autocratic um
and then he's autocratic enough to boss people around and um
and then you follow those kinds of orders
and it's like a
maybe a ceo in a powerful company ordering around
and that could work well
or it could work badly
you know
most um companies are run as
um
like autocracies in a sense
you know there's the hierarchy and you the command economy and that kind of thing
and now that can work well or not
um
but then what
quite often
when you get the populist
autocratic
their personality is something that they want to fight
and they become more nationalistic
and they tend to become more militaristic and human nature at that stage lends itself to fighting
there's an arc here that when we think it's we think of a country
um
and we say we
when we think of a country
um
it's not true
it's not like that there are individuals who change
one generation dies and another generation comes along
and one of those arcs is that
um
the ones who have been through war don't want to go to war and are more happily
you know
willing to
um
abide by whatever the rules are
as you get farther along into that cycle
and you get a new generation and they forget about wars and the horrors of wars
then they
um
then they want to
uh
fight
and so you're seeing right now
the emergent of fight for right
and and what that means is you see it internally
uh
fight
where are you and fight for that thing
and they mean fight and then into externally
fight are you going to be
uh
the strong one who will fight and win and that develops
on both sides
this fight and win and each side is cheering each other on into
uh
a war
but that's comes by those who really have not experienced war
because it comes in their part of their lifetime
humans are fascinating
and by the way
human nature has not changed over the thousands of years
so it's the
it's so interesting
because
like in doing this study and it comes across in the study
it's like watching the same movie over and over again
you
you know
you see the ark
and you see it happen over
and over again the only things that seem to change are the clothes people wear and the technologies
uh
yeah
and then somebody probably will disagree with you about the clothes
maybe there's also cycles within fashions
maybe we're not even creative there
uh
what do you um make of
russia and vladimir putin
what do you think about putin as a leader as a human being on this world stage
within the context of the cycles of empires that you think about
well
putin came to power at the failure of russia's last order
so there was
there was the end of communism and there was the development of the market economy
the collapse of the soviet union
and at that
time he was appointed by yeltsin
who was an alcoholic and had problems managing and was put into power
and the conditions in the russian were the work
there was anarchy
um
there was no money
it was
it had the classic end of cycle ingredients
it was broke
it was people were fighting with each other
was the anarchy
and that's when he came to power and
um
there were not institutions
the whole thing had collapsed and it was not effective
ministry of education
ministry of anything
and so the idea was that they needed 25 years of stability
and they needed a democracy and they needed the the improvement of capital markets
um
so he's been in that position as
a
um
as i guess i would call him
a semi-autocratic leader in that
from all indications
he would respect the democracy
um
and he's very popular
he's won democratic elections because he's been a strong leader and he's brought uh
peace and stability to the soviet u
to
to russia
after the breakup of the soviet union
and
um
he's a strong leader in pursuit of the the country's interests in
a way where russia is not a significant economic power and but it is a significant military power
um
so
the issues
and then there's a strong alliance between russia and china
now
um
so
that's kind of the lay of the land
and then there are sensitivities
the ukraine issue is
uh
a sensitivity
um
because of
there are a lot of russians who live in the ukraine
and there's also the issue of nato on it
on their border
um
so there are those kinds of things
and he has military power and he has a strong alliance with china
um
and i guess that's my best summary of
what his position is strong leader
um
popular
[music] these are not subjective interpretations
these are
uh
objective interpretations
yeah
it's interesting
just in this conversation
you're not sort of um
doing the usual criticism
of any one particular system
you're looking at these systems from the perspective of history
you're just describing how they work
it's often times
when you talk about what russia is today
or what the soviet union was or what china is today is you start to criticize
well
they
they do this kind of censorship or they do this kind of
they limit freedoms in this kind of way
but you're just kind of describing this as a nation with ideas
what they think is right
this is how they hope to get it to work
this is why it's working
this is what's not working
here's metrics that show that it's not working
i think that's a refreshing way to think about it
it's easy
though
i mean you got some criticism
um
saying that
i think china's a strict parent
um
you know
some people criticize these countries for doing
uh
so for violating human rights
i suppose there's some people that criticize the united states violating human rights
but what are your thoughts on the world stage today about some of the behaviors of this government in terms of respecting the rights
the basic rights of human beings
you described accurately
how i just try to look at things in an um
a non
i don't want to impute my values yes on anybody
um
i mean there are intolerable things
so i'm not saying there aren't intolerable things
but
um
one of the great things of being an american here is
that i grew up with all different nationalities having all different points of view
and all different religions and all different ways of operating
and i've come to treasure the fact that that is
you know
what's their
business
is their business
and then the question is
where do you cross the line
under what circumstances that that others have got to do it my way
and then
when you do it internationally
uh
the ob
the issue of what is a sovereign state
you know which
um
as i say in the piece of west failure and you have borders
and you
then
when do you cross the line
that
um
my way of doing things has got to be their way of doing things
or what are the various rights
and so that's a very
uh
delicate question or a very difficult question
and we all have responsibilities to different parties
and we all have different levels of knowledge about those particular things
so
um
for example
as an international investor
i have a responsibility to my investors
those who run companies have a responsibility to theirs of how do they run that
so if you're taking nike or stinkers and so on
and americans can decide whether they want to buy product
chinese products or not buy chinese products
we are all faced with those types of choices
so you have what do you want to do in your constituency and you have your choices
and then
beyond that
in many cases
the issues are quite complex
like there are geopolitical questions that enter into it
so
um
uh
and then i i believe that if if you disconnected
if all those
if entities like myself
the businesses
uh
doing business with china disconnected
i think that that would be disastrous
economically disastrous
and it would also be um reduce
um
the
the understanding that comes from working together that helps to reduce wars
and so these are all complicated
so what we do is
uh
and and who makes it
my opinion matters the most
why should it be my opinion
that matters the most in making that decision
so i largely look at the guide
the government guidance that i get not only from my own government but from the other governments
and i follow the rules
i'm in 40
we invest in 40 countries
and we want to do that in the best way to provide the diversified portfolio
and we sort of need that every one of those countries has similar complexities
there are always one issue or another and then
and there's only so much that we really understand about all of those issues
so we rely largely on the guidance that we you have
get empathize and show respect to the the culture of the place
the way things are done
you don't necessarily
um
the way you heal relationships between nations is like
like you said
you work together
and that requires kind of um to listen
maybe more than you talk
and i think people in the public sphere
uh
talk a lot about china without really listening
without understanding much about china
without one of the things that makes me really sad
because i know how to speak russian and i can
i know how much is lost in translation
it makes me sad that i'll never really get to know the chinese culture
because
like i'll never really get to know the language
the literature
the just talk to regular people
it's not just the government or officials or scientists
just regular folks
get the culture
i think
if you don't understand the culture
uh
just the basics of the human nature of what people love about their country
about their family or the kind of hopes they have
you know what kind of values they have without that
you're not going to be able to um
fully
um connect with them
and you have to do that first to have a chance of building a good world
i couldn't agree with you more
i was very lucky
because
as i say
uh
you know
since 1984
so
for more than half of my life i've been going there
and i and the common people and all sorts of people
and i've got to meet them
i don't speak the language
but it a combination of through translators or men
them speaking english and being in situations
i had my son go to school
a local school and we
we developed those kinds of understandings
i think that
um
but the not wanting to know the other perspective is the thing that's most scary
yeah
like i'm right now in the middle and um
and all i want to try to do is to help mutual understanding
you're right if there were questions probing me asking me what is it
i'm not on one side or another
i get
i don't want to be on one side or another
i believe that each has their right within there to approach their different culture in their own way
so many ways you gave an example it
uh
um
if they're not
doing harm to others
i mean so
but that issue of um trying to understand is so much better
that doesn't mean agree with
if you are wanting to out-clever and out-compete somebody
it still pays to understand what they're thinking
so
to achieve understanding of what they're thinking even if you want to go to war with them
that understanding is the best thing to have
what we have now is a situation in which there's an enemy mentality
and that means that anything that serves the
seems to be like understanding
or conveying understanding seems to mistakenly create the notion of i'm on their side in a war
and that's kind of a dangerous thing
because
um
there's a momentum here to fight henry kissinger
praises your new book and you thank him in it in the dedication
what's your relationship like with him
what makes him interesting
maybe
what makes him controversial
what makes him such a central figure in history the first
most importantly
he's unique about seeing things through all the others eyes
so if you were
it's like there's a chess game
i mean
i think geopolit geopolitics is like a chess game
but with multiple chess players playing the same game
yes
so imagine there are six people around playing the chess game
and he could sit in each seat
and he could know how they see it okay
and see it in a calm way of how they see it
he's unique in that way
he's 98 years old and he's equally able to do that
and he has a background that
in which he's a historian
so he really understands history
super
um
he doesn't understand economic history as much
so that's why
to some extent we enjoy having a conversation
because he's interested in the act and in the economic piece
he doesn't know
and i'm so interested in the geopolitical piece that i don't know as well
but anyway
he's able to do that
but not only a historian but a practitioner
so
when you go from an academic to a practitioner who has
that talent to see things through others eyes in an objective way
and to be strategic rather than just tactical
that's a very special person
and that's why henry is
uh
to me a very special person
yeah
he's lived a fascinating life
just all all of the world events he's been involved in is fascinating
and like you said
that's such an interesting skill to have to consider
what are the concerns
the hope
the dreams
the fears of the
all the people at the table
what are they thinking
i find that people don't once again
don't do that enough
when it's the obvious thing you should be doing
whether it's business deals or um
political negotiation or geopolitical negotiation
i'm often surprised again
sorry to go to the russian thing
because i i i hear
sort of like
i hear putin talk in russian and you start to infer certain intentions and like not the trivial stuff
like the human being
what is what is that human being hoping for himself for his country
for his
close in a circle for the bigger like
and i i just see that that's often just lost in translation
i just see
like american leaders talking to putin
and it's just not
it's
there's not a connection
absolutely
i know exactly what you're talking about you
i
it has never failed that in my listening to a conversation and or even reading a speech
or
and you see
then it reported
the inevitably the reporter picked some headline characterization
that has very little to do with what was really happening
but might be a headline grabber
that's at some kind of distortion and there's a lack of understanding of really what's going on
if it's okay
let me ask you a couple questions about cryptocurrency
uh
you've had a few opinions about bitcoin over the years
what are your thoughts about bitcoin today
its role in the global financial system and just in human society
in general
well
the evolution of bitcoin over the years is one of the things that has influenced changes
in my view
it has proven itself something like 10
11 years ago
imagine the programming of this
and here's the
you throw it out
and that's the idea
it has not been hacked
it has
um
operated
it is built
it has come an amazing way
um
over that 11 years to be
maybe probably the most excited topic among a lot of people
um and has been used and and is now um has obtained
you know the status of having imputed value at the same time
it is one of those assets that is an alternative money
i think we're entering an era where um
there's going to be a competition of monies
um
because of the printing of fiat money
and the depreciated value
there will be a competition of monies
um
and bitcoin is part of that competition
but there'll be many monies
not just crypto monies
but there'll be central bank crypto monies
um
but they'll be
uh
different kinds of monies
um
and even monies
are things that you buy and sell nfts can become a money
uh
a type of money
you own it
and it's an investment
and you could say i'd rather own it than own
uh
bitcoin
has ray dalia bought any nfts not yet
okay
um
but
only only just because
like
i
i definitely want to buy nfts to just experience them
you know
like
i think
think i should produce one
yeah
and i should
uh
i should have asked that
have you made it
have you minted an empty
you probably should
just to know what it's like
yeah
that's right
this stuff is happening
yeah
this stuff is real okay and how it operates
but like all new real things
um
some are gonna go
and so i'm gonna
you know
it's like in the internet in the year 2000
um
you know
pets. com could have been a great
but maybe pets. com doesn't make it
and who knows
that's the beauty of the competitive system
that will evolve and some things will be treasured and some things will be
uh
trashed
so
um
but when i look at it
i think we are in an environment of
you know what is an alternative money
a money has two purposes
a medium of exchange and a storehold of wealth and we are looking for
and it's portable and you can
and it's best if it's recognized in other countries
um
so gold is one of those
so i look at it as an alternative gold
but i look at a number of things as alternative gold
um
and i think that
and i think
and gold is still my favorite because of certain qualities
for example
um
you can't trace it in in bitcoin
you can trace who owns it where it's going
and and so on
governments can't have that ability to trace it
and so on a gold piece of coin
it's
it's not connected
i think not connected has benefits
particularly in a world where maybe connections can be more risky
um
so
and then also gold has been for many thousands of years
universally recognized as a source of money and central banks
it's the third largest uh source of money in central bank reserves
and i don't think bitcoin is going to serve those types of purposes
and so on
so for various reasons
i prefer gold to the other
but it's a little bit part of my mix
but then you look at it
it hit
i think 69
000 this year as the high bitcoin hit
do you think it's possible
you mentioned gold
do you think it's possible it reaches very high numbers like 1 million some people talk about
i don't
i don't think that's possible
because the way i look at it is
there's a certain amount of um
[music] a certain amount of it
and there's a certain amount of gold
i'll use gold as a benchmark
the amount of it is worth about five
uh
about one trillion dollars
total cryptos
about 2. 2 trillion
but let's say bitcoin
uh
it's one trillion dollars
if you take the amount of money that is in um gold
that is not used for jewelry purposes and not used by central banks
and i assume bitcoin won't be used for jewelry purposes or central bank purposes
um
that amount in gold is about five trillion dollars
so right now
if you were to have a portfolio that has um gold and crypto
um gold
then bitcoin
it's worth about 20 of the value of gold
do i think it's going to be
uh
worth more than gold in terms of that mix
i don't think it'll be worth more than gold
but let's say it became worth as as much as gold
i don't believe it will be
i think that 20 sounds kind of about right
i really don't know that what the right answer is
um
and then there's the question of what is all of that pool of money
that
let's say gold and gold equivalents relative to everything else
does it go from
you know
let's call it six
seven
eight trillion to sixteen trillion
maybe it could double
it depends what it is in the world environment
but basically
if you use gold as a measure
i
um
there's no
it just makes no sense that it's going to be used
um that much more
am i sure about that
i'm not sure about anything
but
logically
it seems to me
that there's a limitation on its price in relationship to other things that are like it
let me ask for your deep financial analysis on a very important issue
uh
i've just talked a couple days ago
the elon musk
he wants to put a literal dogecoin on the moon
uh
what are your thoughts about deutsche coin
and
uh
do you think he'll be the official currency
maybe
uh
reserve currency on the moon and on mars
my reaction is that's cute
i remember elon
when he first got
he
he first got his money from paypal
i think he said to me it was
he got 180 million dollars
90 million dollars
he decided to say why aren't we going to outer space
and he wanted to take a spaceship that would be modified using russian technology to put a um
a plant and a watering can on the moon
um
or on mars
i think it was um
and and and he said first life on mars
or first line as an inspiring
uh notion
and so then there's always what's behind it
i have a lot of respect for elon's ability to do other things behind it
uh
and so i would take that as um symbolic
and i'd be asking him what's behind it
what's what's next
and i'm also just on the topic of deutsche coin and meme coin and
uh
there's some aspect of humor and lightheartedness
that's that's really interesting about the way we communicate what ideas become viral
how to captivate people with ideas
there's something about taking things too seriously that somehow slows it all down
and it's interesting
you're right
that's part of human nature
somehow
so
like humor is part of this whole thing
you've
uh
talked about the importance of writing ideas down
and
uh
you have principles
in particular
in principles and you have this really nice thing in your
in your book
we actually
um
i think there's such a brilliant way
okay
uh
you have such a brilliant way of highlighting which parts are extra important and you make them bold
that's a brilliant idea
but let me just ask the high-level question of what's a good system for um
taking notes
well
i find that almost everything happens over and over again
um
and we're in this
the blizzard of these things happening
and what i found is that if i'm making a decision
that that after i make the decision usually or right at the time
if i pause and reflect and i write my principle down
in other words
principle is sort of a recipe
what would i use to
how would i make that decision and what are the criteria around it
i find that i make it much more clear
it becomes clearer and it applies to the next thing that comes along
it'll be that way
because everything happens over and over and over again
and i think people make the mistake of looking at just the one like it's the first one they have
i don't know they have the first problem of this sort of the first child or whatever it is
and this has been happening plenty of times
and so
if you have the principles
i found that that helped me think more clearly about it
and it helped me communicate better like why
and so
over the years
over the last 30 years or so
that's what i've done
i did it originally to communicate very well with the people i work with
um
you know
i set up my company and and i
it was very important to have good communication
and then we could debate the principles
and so that's the process
i urge people to do that
there are many excellent decision makers
um
and i just wish that they wrote down their principles when this set
so
for example
we talked about henry kissinger and his new book is going to come out with a book on leadership
um
and don't just describe the leaders describe
then what about them
were the essential elements to make a good leader under what circumstances
and so if we think about that
when
then also
then you begin to think in a principled way and then
when you start to think in a principle way
life becomes
it's so much easier to make decisions and it's so much less confusing
because it's like coming up on a species and you say
okay
well
what species
is it not just another
it's a thing
no
what species is it
and how do i deal with that species effectively
and
and so that's what that is
and so i encourage people to write it down
i wish anybody who's successful
wrote down their principles or their recipes for making those types of decisions
so the events of interest here happens over and over and over in similar ways
as you're looking for the patterns and you're defining the process that's right to respond to those patterns
and you call that the principles and that allows you to deal with the future
effectively
so like that codifies the lessons from the past to be able to deal with the future
what advice do you have for young folks today
in high school
in college
thinking about how to live
uh
have a career they can be proud of or maybe have a life they can be proud of
know yourself
follow your passion
make your work and passion the same thing while considering the money part
because money will get you freedom and choice and be able to make that
but if you know yourself
feel the pull um and um and pursue that passion
um
and along those lines
by the way i found
um
that using personality profile tests has been very helpful
i've used those for about 25 years for people to help to understand themselves and understand each other
so i created a free one that is called principles you
it's online
it's had remarkable
loving people who've taken it
learn about themselves
but also you can put in somebody else and it'll tell you about your relationship with them
that's like 30 minutes
is a quick discovery
but the main thing is to understand on your journey
your hero's journey
when you're um
that you will have uh mistakes and you will have weaknesses and to understand those
not fight those
because by understanding mistakes
you will learn not to make mistakes again
i have a principle
which is pain
plus reflection equals progress
and so that reflection is important to know yourself
know your pulls
know your weaknesses
and when you also know your weaknesses and the strengths of other people
there are people who um
have strengths
where you're weak and you have strengths
where they're weak and to be able to work well together is the most effective way of achieving
uh
success
so yeah
it's that journey and there's a life arc
and there's a journey and you want to make it the best that you can make it
and it has
it's like a video game
you know
it has the challenges and the obstacles and the learning experiences and the temptations
and all of that and the maximizing learning to go
where you want to go to achieve the life you want is the most important
that's kind of maybe a long-winded way of suing it
but to learn
i think i'll try to say it simply
there's a five-step process
step one is
know your goals
know what you're going after
you could have almost anything you want
but you can't have everything you want
and so you have to prioritize and you move in that direction on the way to your goals
you're going to encounter your problems and your obstacles
so identifying step two is understanding your problems and your obstacles
identify them
step three is to diagnose them
to get at the root cause of the problem
and that could be many root causes
but it could also be your weaknesses or weaknesses of others
but you have to be objective about them
once you diagnose them
then you go to step four
which is to design a way to get around them
and then
after you have that design
you implement that design
so you have to follow through and do it
and you do that
and and that will then produce its new results
which should be better results i have
i call this kind of the looping process
it's the evolutionary looping process
and
um
you do
you just keep doing that
and you learn over a period of time and you move in the direction that you want
last question
and you only have one minute to answer it
you dedicate the book quote to my grandchildren
and those of their generation who will be participants in the continuation of the story
may the force of evolution be with you
so let me ask
where is this force of evolution taking human civilization
and what in this story that evolution is writing gives you hope evolution isn't a direction toward improvement
um
and the greatest force is a man's capacity to adapt and invent
and so you see
in the charts in the book
you see that
um
this upward movement
life expectancy
um
uh
health or all the things that we think are better
you see the
there's a chart
and it shows that over a period of time and you barely see the downturns from depressions and wars
in that that is the greatest power
man's ability to invent and adapt is evolution
and that's the greatest power
and that is what gives me justifiable hope and a continuation of that
like we mentioned with elon
maybe we'll become a multi-planetary species
so not only will we keep creating amazing things here on earth
will keep expanding out into the cosmos
my time horizon isn't
doesn't have me analyzing that yet
but i
i
i hope
so
and i
uh
agree that that would mean the nature
so i'm not going to ask you for the best financial system on mars
um
i think we'll focus on earth for now
right
thank you so much for your brilliance for the
for the books you've written for the works you've done for the inspiration from of millions
so
and thank you for spending your valuable time here with me today
thank you
thanks for listening to this conversation with ray dalia
to support this podcast
please check out our sponsors in the description
and now let me leave you with some words from ray dalio
himself
every time you confront something painful
you are at a potentially important juncture in your life
you have the opportunity to choose healthy and painful truth or unhealthy but comfortable delusion
thank you for listening and hope to see you next time