pay attention. pain plus reflection equals progress.
and from that principle, my company became the largest hedge fund in the world.
managing how much? $ 150 billion.
but i learned
that history of things
that never happened in my lifetime before were important things to understand in order to predict the future.
and we can get into that if you want. peace.
so ray dallio
is the legendary billionaire investor who decoded the cycles of human history to predict financial crashes.
build the world's largest hedge fund.
and now to warn us about what lies ahead. are you optimistic about the future of the uk?
no.
what about the united states?
why?
okay.
in order to bet on what's going to happen on the global economy, i learned
that there's five big forces that create a big cycle that's repeated through history
which lasts about 80 years. the first is the money debt force that creates wealth and opportunities gaps
and it's connected to the second force, the internal conflict where you don't trust the system
causing wars between the left and the right
and it's not easy answers
like tax the rich and we can get into that.
but the third is geopolitical force. in other words, international conflict.
then there's acts of nature. and then number five is man's inventiveness particularly of new technologies.
now the question is who wins the technology war
because the winner of that determine how the new world order works.
is it something to be concerned about?
no.
the question is how you as an individual handle it.
how do i as an individual handle it?
so there's building your financial strength, flexibility, the importance of being open-minded
and how to get more out of the minute, not how to work harder.
and i really urge your audience to learn all of this.
so, first of all, i see messages all the time in the comment section
that some of you didn't realize you didn't subscribe.
so, if you could do me a favor and double check if you're a subscriber to this channel,
that would be tremendously appreciated.
it's the simple, it's the free thing
that anybody
that watches this show frequently can do to help us here to keep everything going in this show in the trajectory it's on.
so, please do double check if you've subscribed
and uh
thank you so much
because in a strange way, you are
you're part of our history
and you're on this journey with us
and i appreciate you for that.
so, yeah, thank you.
[music] ray, i i want to describe to you who's listening right now.
and the question i have for you is what is the most important thing
that this persona of person should be thinking about at the highest level right now.
so the person that's listening is someone who is intent on improving their life. they're
they're really interested in business, potentially starting their own business.
they they care about
where they're investing their their time and energy and also
where they're setting up their home based on in terms of geography.
they are aspiring to accomplish some goal. they're probably between the age of 18 and 50 predominantly
and they are very very interested in understanding what's happening in a world that feels incredibly scary, fast-paced
and uncertain at the moment.
this is a very difficult question, but if anyone i was going to ask anyone, it would have to be you.
what
what's one of the first things they should be considering at this moment to safeguard their future, their family, their finances? i don't think it's a difficult question.
i um
i think it's it's very clear. they have to understand how the life cycle works.
okay? they have to understand it how it works. we were just talking before, you know, in the book
and there was the arc of the life cycle, right?
and you have to understand that you're on an adventurous journey.
okay? and you have a certain nature.
you know, those qualities that ma make you have your preferences and so on.
and then you're going after the things that you like
and you're learning and it's going to have the ups and downs and so on
and how you approach that. so you asked
from the higher level
if i'm looking down
you know
like that life cycle
that arc
what's that journey like
how do you approach it
you know
what are your principles
how do you even learn how to approach it
that's why we're having these conversations right
y
so that's clear
you know what's your nature
how's the journey
how do you find the path that's suitable to your nature
and then you'll go down that path and you'll discover and you'll evolve.
what's that like? that's what they need to know. you said what's your nature?
what do you mean by nature?
people are born with and then also their environment creates their different nature.
you know, we have our preferences, our inclinations.
we think in a certain way.
you chose to be entrepreneurial. okay? you're living out your nature. okay? this isn't for somebody else.
you know, some people have a different nature.
okay? they would like to have the stability of a job and clarity
and so on.
so
when you have your nature, you want to know that
and then find the path that is going to be good for your nature.
then there's the particular tactical stuff.
so if you would ask me, should i be in the uk or should i be in the us?
well, that depends on a lot of things, but that's a tactical question.
so if i want to be an entrepreneur and i want to build a technology company,
do you think i should be in the uk
or the us? i think you should be in the us.
why? the us has a culture of um entrepreneurship, inventiveness.
there's a whole different culture
like in europe
generally speaking
and in and in the uk
there's an establishment culture, right? and here
um
you could be 25, have a blue streak in your hair
and have the talent, but if you got the talent to pull it off, you can get the resources
and you can be an entrepreneur.
it's there's a culture of that.
that means that it's happening more.
that's why you even see the differences in the economies.
okay, where is the inventiveness really happening? okay, it's happening here.
so i would say if you want to be an entrepreneur, this is an environment
that's particularly conducive to being an entrepreneur.
so what is your honest perspective about the uk at the moment? the uk has a financial problem. uh
the government has a debt problem
and it doesn't have enough money for what it wants to do and what it can do.
and so what you see is the nondom problem, people moving and so on so forth.
and throughout history, when you have these sorts of things, then there's great clashes in people.
okay? and the uk has been in decline since the war.
even the development of the capital markets, can you raise capital there? all of these things are much worse
than they are in the united states.
and it leads to clashes. he said, " of course,
you know,
there are five big forces that create a big cycle that lasts about 80 years, give or take 50,
let's say.
and the five big forces are
there's a money, debt, economy force, okay? debts are spending power.
so what happens is when you give somebody credit they can spend and then
but it also produces debt
and debt has to be paid back
and so what happens is if there's not enough income to pay back the debt
then you have um debt
rising relative to income
it squeezes out
spending
people don't want to hold the debt assets and so on
the uk has gone through that and has gone through that
and it's connected to the second force
and we're all going through this in varying degrees. the second force is the internal political and social force.
in other words, like between the left and the right
with wealth gaps and opportunities gaps.
we have big wealth and opportunities gaps.
so when you have big wealth and opportunities gaps, there's conflict.
okay? conflict between the left and the right.
and
when you get to the situation
where you don't believe the system is working for you
and you don't trust the system, then there are wars.
there are internal conflicts over over that
and so on. so the third force is the geopolitical
force.
in other words, u
there's a cycle that usually goes from one big war to another big war.
so the last war ended in 194544
and we began a new order in 1945.
and the way that works is that the winners of the war determine how the world order works.
they draw borders. they say here's how it's going to work. and that's the new order.
okay? and that continues until there's a rising power challenging an existing power
and the existing world order
which typically is deteriorating at that time.
and then you have international conflict. okay, these orders, there's a monetary order, they all break down.
there's an in internal political order, they all break down.
and and there's a geopolitical order.
they all have this conflict and they work together. the fourth force throughout history has been acts of nature.
droughts, floods, and pandemics, for example, have killed more people than wars.
and acts of nature, nature has a big effect.
and then number five force is man's inventiveness particularly of new technologies.
okay,
because if you see
that inventiveness
that has raised per capita incomes, gdp per capita, any measures of living standards over a period of time
and and so on.
but it is also related to the first four that i said those four four forces interact.
now when we go back to your uk case, okay, they have a financial problem.
they and almost every country now is dealing with more of that internal political problem for the same reasons.
wealth gaps, opportunities gaps,
what do we do?
who's got the power?
i don't trust the system kind of thing.
okay.
number three is we are certainly in an international great powers conflict, right?
and it certainly affects europe and the uk as we're dealing with not only the ukraine situation
but the russian situation
and what does that mean
and that relates to the money thing
because
okay
where's the money coming from to have defense or military expenditures
and so on so forth.
so that matters right
the geopolitical
matters
climate certainly matters
and then
of course technology
man's inventiveness.
so everything could be looked through at through that lens.
and so what does this mean for the uk if all other countries are going through this as well? doesn't
that just mean that all countries are going to suffer equally? no.
no.
because they're not all equal.
okay.
some are more in debt than others.
okay. some people are more willing to hold their debt than others. um
some means they they have more resources. some are bigger and more powerful.
some are less powerful.
they're different. okay. they're all go in different conditions. some countries have surpluses. some countries, you know,
are not in the middle of where there's having a war.
are you optimistic about the the future of the uk at the moment?
no, no.
because it has high debt.
it has the social internal conflict.
it it's affected by the geopolitical factors.
and in terms of inventiveness, it doesn't have the culture that other countries have
like
like the us.
is that
yes.
the cult culture
and the capital markets to support
that at a scale that it needs to be supported to play seriously in the game.
and for anyone that doesn't know capital markets mean
basically the investor markets is way of saying
well
i mean it gets you the money.
in other words, you're a guy with
you know
what happens is
um
we have to enable people.
okay.
what what works is finding great people, talented people,
and identifying those who you want to bet on and enabling them.
and that works. that's the most important force, much more important than money.
okay? because you could see who's got the money and power and where did they come from?
where did nvidia come from? where did where did they all come from?
okay? there are guys like you, entrepreneur
in a sense, who's been enabled, okay, by you
because you have the talent and people want to bet on you
and that's the capital market.
so they give you money to help enable you
because they want to bet on you and then good things happen.
but are you
are you optimistic about the united states at the moment? the united states is very much a big picture.
no, i think it's very much in this issue there.
so, if i go down my list, it definitely has this uh debt money economy problem.
we can get into that. okay. it definitely has the internal conflict power
in which there's a fight between the left, you know,
the hard left and the right
due to wealth and values gaps and people not believing that the system will work for them.
and so democracy is at risk because they don't believe this.
they they're not going to follow the rules in the sense they don't believe the rules are going to
uh
number three
it's of course
the leading one side in this great power conflict of the world
right
in other words
yes
between the united states and the one side
let's say
and china and the allies
their allies on the other side.
i mean in the news
you just saw the meetings of xi putin
modi and that group over there
walking down
you know
and okay
so now it should be pretty clear how the sides are lining up
okay
you
it's always better to be in a place that's not in one of those wars
like stay out of wars
um
and of course
climate has an effect
then we have technology
the united states and china are in the big technology compet competitions.
the others are really not in the game.
they don't have the money that this innovation and talent in a sense to play at that scale
and so on.
so we have a great
you know
technology war
which can be used to create great advances but at the same time could be used for great conflicts.
and so now the question is going to be who wins the technology war
because the winner of the technology war is going to win all wars.
okay.
in other words, they'll win the economic war. they'll win the geopolitical war because technology
and i'm not saying anything that hasn't repeated through history. give me that historical context if you can
just for the technology
for example
nuclear.
yeah.
nuclear won world war ii.
and and does this cycle go back further than just
oh, no.
it goes back i that book. okay.
um,
in order to understand these things, cuz i have to bet on what's going to happen.
i'm a global macro investor.
i study the last 500 years of history and and it happens over and over again in all cases.
so, i could take the british empire, i could take you through all the empires, the dutch empire before
that,
and all this, and it it it happens
uh
all the time.
i watched your
i watched your videos about this
and it was truly fascinating how predictable this stuff is
and the work that you've done to uncover this trend throughout history.
i mean, it's almost for me
it was almost irrefutable watching the evidence in in
i think it's like a 40-minute video on youtube where you show how this played out through empires.
and it begs the question, you know,
because
when you live in the united states,
when you're when you're in the present time, you almost never assume that the empire you're in could fall.
you just don't you don't see how it could happen. we're so strong. we're so great, you know,
we're so that doing ai over here, have money over here, everything's good, the sun's shining.
it's inconceivable.
of course, people always think that the future would be a slightly modified version of the present,
and it's not.
okay.
watch over decades, but it's like watching a person grow.
yeah.
okay.
you know, you watch your kid or you watch a person at your age, any age,
and that's what you see.
yeah. okay. and you don't see the life arc. yeah. okay. but the life arc is in irrefutable.
but the u do you think it's conceivable
that in the next 50 to 100 years the us could no longer be the dominant power globally? yeah.
yeah.
more than conceivable. more than conceivable.
what does what do you mean by more than conceivable?
i mean that these evolutions always take place and they take place in a certain way
and that
um
if you look at the probabilities
and the paths and the symptoms
there is a challenge
the united states is facing a number of those challenges
and we're at a moment where
um
it's a question of whether the system
and the people could can get control of the situations and deal with it strongly and well
in a way
where they are not fighting to the point of damaging each other
and damaging managing the prospects for the future.
but i mean, the united states is very innovative. got all these great innovative companies here. so surely yeah.
but you you can't make generalizations about the united states.
and you can't make generalizations, by the way, about the markets either.
um
what you see is um
%
a small percentage
1 % of the population
if you're looking at the breakdown of incomes and also you're looking at the innovation
the stock markets
which stocks are doing well
who owns those companies and all of that
about three million people in a country of uh
330 million people are really unbelievably doing great
and you could pick the neighborhoods they're in and what they're doing.
and then there's the top 10 %, let's say, which is the people around them.
and they're really, really doing great in that world. at the same time, the bottom 60 %
60 % of americans have below a sixth grade reading level. wow. and that population
in terms of um
the basics being productive, you have to be productive and be prosperous.
so what what you need to have a su successful society is to have broadbased productivity and prosperity.
okay? and that's a problem.
okay? so, which america are you looking at? and are you watching the war that's happening between these?
it's a little bit complicated for me as a as a bit of an outsider
because i see trump saying he represents those people,
but obviously trump is a from the billionaire class himself.
so, i mean, is he is he a savior for inequality? is he correcting?
i think i think he sees a lot of the problem and he
uh
i think he sees the debt problem.
i think he sees the internal conflict disorder problem and i think he represents
uh
the red,
let's call it the red states.
i mean, you look at a map and there's red and blue and you see
where they are, okay? and he represents that
and they're united behind him in terms of doing some things.
okay? so he represents
let's call it the red side
which is located where the maps shows red
and then there are the blue
and
and he's
um
he views himself as somebody who needs to take charge and to do certain things.
others in
that population would say those who let's say are not getting are having the food stamp program cut off
or having other programs cut off that they're dependent on
would say
uh
wait a second
that's not representing me. and so we have gone
that population has gone to significant number behind him
that are devotees. they're all in.
okay. at the same time as we have the other side
which will have their devotees if you know we're in new york city.
okay.
and the up upcoming mayoral uh election will be an example of the two sides.
okay. and they will try to use the system
but there's a question
will the system have enough support to work.
okay. but that's what we have. just just to close off on this point of the uk in particular,
if if you were to try and fix it, what would you be aiming at? i say this
because we do have a millionaire exodus that's widely reported in the uk
where i think this year we're set to lose 16, 000
roughly 16, 000 millionaires.
um, when you look at the big big countries like china, america, the uae, the uk,
we're losing more millionaires than anybody else.
and i was wondering if you think it's fixable
and if you were in charge of the uk, what you might aim at first.
it's diff,
you know,
first of all,
if you go back to the basic problem, which is there's too much debt, there are deficits,
there's differences in education and opportunity levels
and so on.
the most important thing that you can have is a strong middle.
political middle.
political middle to be analytically strong
and also strong enough to get the people to do what needs to be done even if they don't want to do it to get to be productive.
now that's an easy thing to say.
it's not an easy thing to do.
but you do need that strong middle
and you do need to convey to people that you need to have the strong middle to change productivity
and you know
and are you in it?
are are you in it?
are you patriotic and in it
and you know
but you look at history
how did the united states come to be the united states? people will go to the places
that are better than them
then stay in the places that worse for them. this is fundamental
right incentives.
okay. so you have to make the place better. okay. now i would say also
you can take pockets and they go into the pocket and let it spread out.
but you also have to have this equal education or you know you've got to strive for equal opportunity.
but anyway, it's a difficult question that i'm afraid i'm incapable of um solving.
it was unnerving to hear the tone of your voice drop when i asked it. you seemed slightly
um
as if you you've kind of given up on the uk a little bit. your facial reaction? well, i'm
i'm just a
i'm a practical guy. i'm a realistic guy. i made my money. i'm in the business
and it's my nature to try to be realistic and to bet on how things will transpire.
and that's not healthy.
the situation in the uk is not healthy.
and the situation in the united states is very risky in many ways.
it's what we're describing. so, you know,
and then if you look where are people going
then then you see the places that have the qualities we're talking about.
they're civil.
they're creative.
the people aren't at war with each other.
what happens next in history? well, usually there's a a big fight for control, political revolutions
and things like that.
the system breaks down because they don't trust the system.
so will the legal system resolve
that? will the parliamentary system resolve that these disputes satisfactorily to the satisfaction of those people
and the other people who have different points of view
and the sides won't believe it. and this goes back
this goes back to rome. it goes back to caesar, you know,
the senate.
and you know this goes back through history all the time,
right? and in in the 30s, four major democracies chose to be autocracies.
okay,
that happened in italy, germany, spain, and japan. what's autocracy for anyone that doesn't know the word?
well, it's
it means a dictatorship essentially of a limited number of people at the top who are autocratic,
which means that they are directing things rather than a democracy
in which
um
there's representatives of all different points of view that get together and follow rules to make decisions.
so the uk could become an autocracy as could the us.
i guess
um
you're going to see a lot of pressure for that strong leader who will get control of things
and make it work well and will
and you're likely to see two different views as to which side, you know,
the red and the blue sides,
so to speak.
you're likely to see that type of clash.
you said the us is playing a risky game itself.
is that from a de debt perspective or otherwise from these things? okay.
from the debt, from the internal conflict, from the changing world order, the geopolitical world conflict,
you know,
i don't know.
we're playing with nuclear weapons and, you know,
in wars and different places
and then of course climate
and then the technology war.
how we're doing that. yeah, i saw that image the other day of putin and um
president xi and china together walking together.
if china does become the dominant force in the world, the dominant power does
is that a smooth transition?
first of all, i don't think either side is going to be the clearly dominant power for for a very long time
and
and the the quickest way to have it is some kind of a war
and that's a dangerous thing
and but maybe it evolves
hopefully
the way the soviet union evolved that the the worry of mutually assured destruction keeps everybody
not having that kind of war
and then what then then the systems
one system or another system wins
but that's an evolutionary process
and you know i can't say
and um
do you think much about time frames
because when i was watching when i was going through the changing world order
there seems to be somewhat consistent or predictable time frames when these these transitions happen.
do you think about where we are?
well, they're long-term big cycles. yeah. right. it's
it's like a life cycle
on average
they are about a life cycle about 80 years
but it's not predetermined
just like your life cycle is not predetermined like
if you take care of yourself and you
you know
i don't know
smoke
eat
well
exercise and so on
so forth
then you will probably have a longer life cycle than if you don't take care of yourself
and it's um kind of like that
you know
and so you see them
in industry
they evolve
but you can see the symptoms. okay,
you can see the actions and the symptoms
which like taking a physical
uh
then gives you a sense of where they are in their life cycles.
we're 80 years from world war ii. 80 years from world war ii.
yeah.
and you're seeing the symptoms.
symptoms are clear.
they're all in that book.
you can see the charts of all the systems.
is it something to be worried about or concerned about if you're in the united states? no
i mean, yes.
and then the question is how you as an individual handle it.
how do i as an individual handle it?
well, first of all, i think i think you have to be aware of the situation
and the risks for me and my family
though
in terms of risks and how i should um counteract those risks.
is it a case of me saving for a rainy day? is it a that's part of it. yeah.
um
there's a
there's a saying in hong kong
um
a chinese saying which is a smart rabbit has three holes. and what that means is you can see
is it the uk or the us
and
and i can then move to the better place and get out of the place
that's a terrible place.
so can i successfully be an immigrant or whatever and change my location? throughout history
that's been important. so the ability to go to good places and away from bad places. um
so that's part of it. um
secondly,
building your financial strength is important
which has to do with how you earn, spend and save. that will determine the amount.
and then what you do with that amount is invest.
and so how you invest
uh
is also important.
so if you have your financial ability
and you can make the move
and then you have knowledge you know about what's happening so that you can change things.
those are the things you need. so on that first point about a smart rabbit having three holes,
is it therefore a better decision at this point in time to not to not buy a house?
because a lot of people end up buying a house
and anchors them to to a place and it means that they then have to pay into a mortgage.
so a lot of lot of the financial advice most of us have growing up is
when you get enough money to buy a house, move in, pay that mortgage for 25 years.
but if i'm in a new economy, in a new world,
and flexibility and the ability to get up and go and move is there's
there's uh value to that.
the ability to move capital matters. and if you look at history, this has been an important consideration. yes.
so it matters. so if you're nailing yourself down
and that's your primary capital and it's nailed down there,
then that's does limit your flexibility.
and on the point of earning, spending, and saving, wonder what you you're a
you're a a father, aren't you? yeah.
what what advice are you giving to your children about earning money in the in the current world,
where
where they should set up their shop, the skills
that are most valuable to acquire, the technologies, the we talked about the us being a place to one of the better places to build your career for all the reasons you described.
well, that's, you know, that's kind of like the particular that you asked me for.
that's below the level of the higher level.
okay. the higher level is i have a principle. make your work and your passion the same thing.
and don't forget about the money part.
okay? if you make your work
and your passion the same thing so that you're really enjoying your work, you'll have an enjoyable satisfactory life
and you'll probably be better at your career
that
um
as a result
probably advance
and so on. so you have a happier life and you will have a more
probably a more successful life.
but it is true that the careers that you choose will have financial implications. mhm.
and if you say, " i want to be a poet or something along those lines.
" you better consider the financial implications of that.
that doesn't mean that you have to go make a ton of money
because i think that that's
i think a lot of people fall into that trap that they think the money is
um
like vast amounts of money is vast amounts of success.
and that's not true. in other words, is your work and your passion the same thing?
so, i think that what brings people happiness is meaningful work and meaningful relationships.
okay? if you have meaningful work, you know, that you're into
and your, you know, your passion and your work's the same thing.
and you have meaningful relationships, whether through that work or beyond, you're going to have probably a great life.
okay? and so, you have to keep that in mind.
and it doesn't have much correlation past a certain level of money.
uh
it doesn't have much correlation with um
that well-being with the amount of money you have.
and if you see studies across societies
and you'll see that past that certain basic level, there's no correlation between the amount of money they have
and how much happiness they have or well-being.
okay? that the highest level of co correlation across societies and studies of happiness and well-being is community.
do you have a sense of community? do you have those around you
who are your community?
you'll live longer that way. you'll have a more joyous life and it'll be a better outcome.
but anyway, so thinking about those things i think is important
based on your life cycle
in this book principles your guided journey.
create your own principles to get the work and life you want.
do you think you have to play different games in different seasons of your life cycle as it relates to generating wealth?
and what i'm talking about here is really like risk profile
um
or what i should be optimizing for.
should i be
should i be trying to hang around with ray dalio
or should i be focusing on the job that pays me the most?
first of all,
the answer is yes.
and the second question you asked
the answer is um
that you should be around the the people who are the best people to teach you to operate
by the
the mentors and the learnings
and so on. you should be around the best people
and when i say best people
i mean people of good character and good capabilities. okay. and uh
so you should be around the best
not the job that pays you the most.
and i could explain why that is,
but and yes,
in terms of that arc, you will play it differently at different parts of your life cycle.
so in the early part of your life cycle,
what you're going to do is
i mean the more learning and experiencing is the most important thing that you can do in the learning
in the early part of your life cycle.
it's like you're going to make your choices.
what direction am i going to be in and so on so forth. so learn.
okay, that that's that's most important.
and then what you're at the end of your life cycle, you're pretty much relieved from all of that.
you're not going to be working to earn, okay? you're going to be free of all of that.
you're going to have um
and you have freedom of choices
and so on.
and you're going to be thinking about transitioning.
how do i transition well-being or how do i transition my wealth
or how do i transition and so on
you know
that's
that's where you are still learning is a joy
but at the same time
in terms of trying to accomplish
it's not the same at your late part of your life cycle
as it is in your early part of your life cycle
so i want to ask about your early life cycle
and what the most important strategic or wealth generating decisions you made that you would encourage
encourage everybody to consider if their nature is aligned to yours. okay. my nature was
i hated school.
i didn't like the whole thing of remembering this and remembering this and then give it back to me
and there were these uh you know history
like there's william the conquer in 1066 and what did he do
and you know
like all of that was what education represented.
and when i was um 12, a kid, i earned money with odd jobs like
um
i had a paper route and um
i mowed lawns and i caddied and i took my cadding money
and when i was 12
i got
everybody was talking about the stock market.
so i put some money in the stock market. i didn't know what i was doing, of course,
but i
um
i picked um
the stock
that was the only stock i ever heard of that was selling for less than $ 5 a share.
and my reasoning was i could buy more shares, so if it went up, i could make more money.
okay, that was a stupid criteria, but it was a company that was about to go bankrupt.
and another company acquired it and it tripled in price.
and i said, " i like this game. " [music] so, i got
i got hooked on the game.
i'm still hooked on the game, right? so, i liked it.
okay. that that affected me. so, i barely got into uh cw post college and then i went to
uh
harvard business school
and that opened my eyes to the world in in many ways
because of who were there and what it was like and all that, you know,
the best and the brightest kind of thing.
but i always still traded markets because i always played the game.
i could tell you stories. you want a couple of quick stories? 100
%.
okay.
so, i'm clerking on the floor of the new york stock exchange between graduating from college
and in the summer
between graduating from college and going to uh harvard business school. and that is 197
the summer of 1971.
mhm.
and on august 15th, 1971, richard nixon gets on the television
and says
that, you know, the promise that that you were going to be able to take your paper money
and go get gold,
you can't do that and we're not
we're going to cut off that off.
he didn't say it in exactly those words, but money then was gold
and what we think of as paper money, fiat money was claims on the gold.
so i walked on the floor of the new york stock exchange that summer
and i thought the market was going to go down a lot
and the market went up a lot and i didn't understand why
because i never went through a devaluation before.
and i studied history
and i found that in march of 1933, roosevelt got on the radio
and made the exact same announcement that you're not going to get your gold
and they're going to print the money.
and when you print a lot of money, you have that.
okay.
so, i learned that history of things that never happened in my lifetime before were important things to understand.
i went back then to harvard business school two for two years
and and two years later as a result of all the printing of money and the oil shock
because of all of that
uh
we had the in 1973 oil shock
and now because of my background
i'm head hired to be director of commodities at a wall street brokerage firm.
okay.
mhm.
which
and then all sorts of things happened. um
turbulence
and so on
so forth.
that firm went broke. i went to another firm and i was
uh
rowdy.
i wasn't your typical good employee,
you know,
follow everything.
and
uh
so i got fired and that was in uh
and then
i
but
uh
clients all liked me and for things
and so they would pay me for advice
and i continued to trade the markets and that's
when i formed bridgewwater. okay. and what that was 1975.
i just passed along bridgewater 50 years later.
yeah. okay. so there's a journey there that has failures and successes and learnings.
you know, i have a principle. pain plus reflection equals progress.
okay? your best learnings come from the pain.
it's a message. pay attention. learn how reality works and how to deal with it differently
so you have principles for re dealing with reality better.
and i learned that process.
and from that process, my company bridgewwater became the largest hedge fund in the world.
um, extremely successful, managing how much? $ 150 billion.
1, 500 people, $ 150 billion.
and that's made you a very wealthy man.
and made me a very wealthy man, which by the way was not my intention.
okay.
i just wanted to play the game and to have meaningful work and meaningful relationships.
that was paramount.
but it happened to be the game i played.
if you're good at the game, you make a lot of money.
and now i'm at a stage in my life where i'm
i want to pass things along.
i need to pass things along, right? so, hence the books, hence our conversation
and here we are.
that's the life arc.
but i learned a lot. and so that's the journey.
i think b2b marketeers keep making this mistake.
they're chasing volume instead of quality.
and
when you try to be seen
by more people instead of the right people, all you're doing is making noise.
but that noise rarely shifts the needle.
and it's often quite expensive.
and i know as there was a time in my career where i kept making this mistake
that many of you will be making it, too.
eventually, i started posting ads on our show sponsors platform, linkedin.
and that's when things started to change.
i put that change down to a few critical things.
one of them being that linkedin was then and still is today the platform
where decision makers go to not only to think and learn but also to buy.
and
when you market your business there, you're putting it right in front of people who actually have the power to say yes.
and you can target them by job title, industry, and company size.
it's simply a sharper way to spend your marketing budget.
and if you haven't tried it, how about this? give linkedin ads a try.
and i'm going to give you a $ 100 ad credit to get you started.
if you visit linkedin. com / diary,
you can claim that right now. that's linkedin. com / diary.
just for context, people don't like talking about money
and i understand it, but you're a prolific philanthropist.
also, google says that your net worth is in the tens of billions of dollars.
and i'm sure there's some people that have clicked on this conversation
and aren't aware of the scale of wealth you built up
and the scale of bridgewater capital and how prolific and famous it is in the investing world.
in that 50-year life arc, one of the things you mentioned is pain. all of us will encounter pain.
and you said pain plus reflection.
reflection equals progress.
how have you leared to deal with pain? you've had a lot of pain in all facets of life
because you've lived the life arc
um
and you continue to. how
what's the best principle for dealing with pain? first of all,
um to calm yourself down and to get centered.
meditation has had a big beneficial effect on my life.
we can get into meditation in a minute of how it has.
but the ability to, you know, in a sense calm yourself down and
when the time is right to reflect on what's happened
both to understand how reality works.
you know, you want to be a hyper realist.
i understand how reality works.
therefore, i need to do this under this set of circumstances, which means developing principles.
and so what i did when i would do that anytime
whenever i would think
what
what should i do
whether painful or not
i would pause
reflect on
you know what should i do if that happened again
and that's how i would write down my principles
and what i did was
i wrote down a lot of principles
a lot of principles
if this happens
that happens
and whatever
and then so i wrote these principles down and then i found that in investing
um
if i can computerize those decision rules
i could back test them
see how they would have worked
and so on.
so i built systems, decision-making systems. um,
computer would make decisions.
so it was ai before llms, but it was ai to have decision-making criteria.
so it would be like i i would make a computer chess game
that would play while i was playing my mental chess game, what moves we would make.
and it's completely automated and so on.
but i'm what i'm trying to say is that reflecting on how does reality really work
and what do i do when this happens to
that happens is the development of principles
and that has been invaluable
and it also makes me see things differently
because a lot of people
um
and if i didn't do this
i would be seeing almost as uh
a blizzard of things coming at me
instead
i see everything as another one of those. so let let's say
for example
it
it's a species. so it's like seeing okay
that's what kind of species is it
and how do i deal with
that species? so it's one of those rather than just a lot of things coming at me.
pattern recognition of yeah.
but but let's say if you think of a
it's a duck.
okay. okay. oh okay. it's a duck. how do i deal with a duck? or it's a lion.
okay, how do i deal with a lion? rather than just a lot of things coming at it.
so this principle thinking
and seeing it that way had a big effect on the quality of my decision making
and and that helped. two questions i had there is to become a principal thinker
i need to do more reflection, right? and then the other
think about how does
how does the machine
how does
how does life
how do these things work?
so that's what i mean. okay. and to write that down.
uh
yeah.
write down your thoughts. i find sometimes what i would do is i'd uh
dictate them into my iphone. okay. okay. i'd say no.
okay. ah
this is how when you're making a decision. why did you make that decision?
so, not just make a decision, but think about the criteria you're using to make the decision
also my emotions, my trauma, my insecurities, my anxiety,
right? and and you might say when reflecting on that, is that helpful? is that harmful?
and what do i do about that?
like
for example
when what you're referring to is
yes
the
um
that the motions and the things and all of those
we
uh
you have to understand that that
basically the brain's got two parts to it
right
it has the logical part of your brain
reasonable
tries to reason things through
and then which is conscious
and then it has the subconscious mind
which is the subliminal
that is really driving you
and so
when you can reflect
okay
how are my emotions entering into it
what do i
you know
and so on
and you can think and you can align
that
that's very powerful
and meditation by the way
naturally does that
because what you do when you meditate and maybe a times come
i should explain meditation
okay
how it works
um
what you do is it's a process process by which you sit quietly and you repeat in your mind
what is called a mantra
which is a sound
that it's a word that has no meaning.
let me say
the most classic example of that would be okay. so you're quietly there and you go with your breath
you go
you know [music] like that
but you need to be taught
but anyway
i
um
and so when you're doing that
uh
because your m is in your mind or your mantra is in your mind
you're not able to have other thoughts.
you'll see yourself wavering between doing that and staying on the mantra and then having thoughts.
um
but what
and then you go back to your mantra. when you are
uh
in the mantra
a a lot
then it disappears. the sound disappears and you go into your subconscious mind. that's what they call transcending.
transcendental meditation is the type of meditation i do.
and so you go there
and you're not in a conscious state and you're not in a subcon unconscious state.
you're in a conscious state. so it's subconscious state. it's not unconscious
is you're sleeping.
conscious is that you're awake like we are.
you're in this.
so it's a different state.
like if you hear that noise, you would hear that noise.
it would be big. not when you're sleeping. but when you're in your subconscious state, then it's relaxing. uh
it's helpful
and this process helps to
um
bring your conscious state and your uncon subconscious state into alignment.
in other words, you recognize both
and it calms you down. it
it's like the ninja in the ninja movies, you know,
they're fighting
but they
it seems in slow motion.
the camera shows them in slow motion and they're doing whatever they're doing along that.
it kind of makes you in
that kind of state of mind so that you're dealing with what's coming at you in that way.
and so what you referred to is this
um
these things that happen and how you deal with those is really important to the quality of your decision-making.
how influential was transcendental meditation in your success?
oh, enormously successful. enormously significant. ve
very
very significant.
in other words, that way of singing seeing things and how often
and and by the way, there's
you know
there's
i
i would say say there's a serenity prayer. the serenity prayer is god
give me the serenity to accept that which i can't control
and give me the power to control that which i can and the wisdom to tell the difference.
okay. and so to how you approach these things, we're talking about reflection. you ask me reflection.
okay? if you can reflect in that quality way, then you deal with anything.
and i've
i've dealt with
uh
the worst possible thing.
um
i lost a son.
okay? and i would have rather died.
i would have rather lost everything to lose my son.
so it's the worst possible thing. and and then to see what it did
you know
the damage and the harm from family terrible.
okay. then to go through that with meditation with reflection and so on
uh
was invaluable and people have their own challenges
but to be able to do it that way
i i really urge your audience
i urge you to
uh
to learn that
that's very helpful. how
how did that tragedy change your your perspective and your your principles
in any way
on life on
on happiness
on success
on all these things that you've written about? well,
it's again
i
you know
i go above it
and
um
you reflect on the life arc
and i realize at that higher level that that's what the life arc is like.
you
you'll in in all my books there's this ar
um
arcing
this arcing
here's a bigger version of it
uh
yeah
there's this arcing
okay
i don't know if you're camera sees that
whatever it is
and that's what life and evolution is like to me
meaning you make advances
you will have setbacks
okay
if you reflect well,
and you learn how reality works
and how you will deal with it, you will get past that and go on.
and that's just what it is. that's just the way life is. and if you do that
well, then that's your best possible life.
are you religious? are you a religious person? i'm not religious, but i'm spiritual. okay. the dalai lama
who i had the pleasure of meeting told me u and i i agree with
um
that religions are typically
a mix between superstitions and spirituality.
there's half of it is that element that nobody knows
but there is the way people should deal with each other. there is karma.
okay. all religions
there's the part of them that says do unto others as you would have them do unto you
or what goes around comes around and then you get to the particulars.
okay. and it is true that if we work well together
that even little things i can do to help you can make a big difference in your life
and little things that you can do to help me make a big difference in our lives.
and so it's practical and it is also joyous.
okay, that creates a relationship.
and we talked earlier about how that meaningful relationship is like the source of great happiness.
but when you have a community and you do that, you have a better society.
and almost all religions will tell you that there'll be elements of those.
and when i believe in spirituality, what i also mean is
uh
we're all part of this greater hole.
okay? we're all part of the greater hole.
and if you could see yourself as part of the greater whole and love the greater whole
uh
and whatever that is
spirituality
really
okay
and so i will go through my life arc
and i will die and i'm comfortable with that
okay in that
okay
it's all part of the greater whole
you know
na nature and whatever it is
that's true
i can't tell you about other things
but i do believe in the things i just told you when it comes to living a successful life
we've talked about having dreams
and understanding your nature and aspiring for things and then understanding reality
which transcendental meditation is a great mechanism and vehicle to do
um
and in your
in your book about a successful life
you talk about
plus determination
hard work
if i want to be a successful man
or woman, how important do you think hard work is? well, gives you power.
it's very important, right? some people
some people,
you know,
i'm not saying they want to choose it, but the ir
the irony of things is there are first order consequences and there are second order consequences.
this is like a rule of life, okay? and most of the time
the first order consequences
whether they're likable or not
has the opposite second quarter
second order consequences.
what i mean by that is like eating or exercising.
okay, eat the foods you like. second order consequence is probably not going to be good.
um
you know i don't want to exercise
second order consequences won't be as good. okay. working hard
which gives you strength.
where does strength come from?
i mean strength comes from working hard.
so working hard will will give you power.
power will make things easier and make things better.
that's just the way it is.
and being open-minded while you do it. something that was openminded to you. yeah.
i say
uh
the importance of being open-minded and assertive at the same time.
um
i
i watch people becoming so tied to their own opinions
like this is the greatest tragedy of mankind. the greatest transgen of mankind
because it so easily can be fixed
is holding a strong opinion that is wrong
that you could have made right better if you were open to learning more.
if you would said, " i want to be stress tested.
i want my thinking to be stress tested. i want to make sure that i'm making the better decision
and so i'll be challenged.
but a lot of people view that challenging like a fight. it's not a fight.
if somebody holds a different opinion, it should prompt a curiosity.
you know, i don't know.
am i wrong
or is they wrong?
there's a 50 % chance.
i don't know.
maybe i'm wrong.
so, it should prompt curiosity
and in exchange to try to make sure that you're seeing the whole picture and so on.
but subliminal instincts are i'm going to stick with it and i'm going to have a fight.
that's a problem
because there's too much on the line for so many people to
it's subliminal.
it's
it just goes back to the mind thinking that the intellectual challenge is a fight and it's egotistical.
you know,
ego,
i must be right.
as an as an investor and entrepreneur, that's obviously particularly important
because you're constantly dealing with your information and feedback, which you need to be flexible.
that was one of the two things that changed my
uh
my
my whole direction and made me successful. i i can explain it if you want.
please. 19
and 80
i had calculated
that american banks had lent more money to foreign countries
that they were going to be able to pay back
and that we were going to have a debt crisis.
very controversial point of view.
in august of 1982, mexico defaulted on its debts
and over the next decade, many other countries did and it caused bank problems.
however, at that time, i thought things were going to get bad
and that was the exact bottom in the stock market, august 1982.
so, i couldn't have been more wrong.
i lost money for me.
i lost money for the clients.
i lost money.
i was so broke
that i had to borrow $ 4, 000 from my dad to help to pay for family bills
because i was faced with the choice.
what am i going to do?
and and do i do
i go back to work on wall street, get a uh tie, get on the train,
and go back that
which is again not in my nature or whatever.
and and two things changed me. okay, reflection.
first of all,
um,
i learned what we were just talking about.
i learned humility and fear of being wrong and open-mindedness.
so, i wanted the smartest people who could i could find to stress test my opinions
because i'm always realized i could be wrong.
and then i learned how to diversify my bets so
that i could dramatically reduce my risk without reducing my returns.
okay, that was the bottom.
okay,
from that point all the way over that
following those principles took me to the biggest hedge fund in the world, the most successful
and so on
because i applied it to the markets, applied it to what we did
and so on. so that notion of reflection
and then how do you deal with what reality is like
and then you know
okay
the learn
learn
radical open-mindedness in other words
and like there's a principle in the book you have to take in before you put out or that
um
decision making is a two-step process
first take in then decide.
okay. so, yes, open-mindedness. you don't doesn't in any way minimize your ability to decide.
so, you still have the freedom to decide, but it's crazy not to be open-minded.
you recognize that the biggest threat to good decision-m is harmful emotions.
and that two-step process is first learn and then make the decision.
which is funny
because it sounds simple, but
when you said it, i think about all the worst decisions i've ever made in business.
and i missed step one. i forgot
to
i forgot to take a minute and do the evidence gathering or the like information gathering process.
yeah, just smart people who care about your decision
say
stress test me.
why don't we do that? that ego and also instinct that that's a fight.
is there any advice you would give me on becoming a better decision maker? so i have a fund, i have many businesses.
is there any sort of practical simple foundations of becoming a better decision maker
that we haven't talked about? get smart people to interrogate my thinking.
um, be open-minded. i think we've talked about almost all of them. um,
i think then you have to then know about how to leverage yourself. okay.
in other words, as you do more and more, uh,
how do you do more and more when your brain has a capacity limit, okay,
and there's only certain number of hours in the day or the week,
okay, you have to know how to do that. is that focus
or is that something?
no, no,
no.
it's knowing how to do it through others. okay. it's knowing how to pick others and orchestrate.
well, it's like
uh
running a symphony or whatever.
okay. get the best players. okay, when i say
uh
you know
um
good character and good capabilities and orchestrate them well and then provide that
that leverage
like
uh
um
when i was doing the most
i had 30 direct reports
whatever the number is.
so
uh
it
the process is how to get more out of a minute
or a day, not how to work harder, okay? it's how to leverage yourself.
and you're going to leverage yourself by picking the right people who you can trust.
they're not going to screw you.
they're going to operate in your interest and they're going to be capable.
and so a lot of people what you can do is you can deal with them
and then you can say
like i i would deal with them on this 30 reports.
i'd have maybe um an hour meeting with them once every two weeks
and and they go off and do things. and when you do that
you can even find people who are much better at things than you would be if you did them.
because if you have these different things, okay, you better
because otherwise you don't have the capacity.
you have these two key challenges to to overcome as an entrepreneur, which is find these great capable people
that have great character
and then
like
bind them with the right culture to make sure that they do the best work, right?
and and in other words, it's meaningful work and meaningful relationships through radical truthfulness and radical transparency.
radical truthfulness and transparency.
okay.
first, if you can have um meaningful work and meaningful relationships, the people are on the mission with you.
wow, that's fantastic.
but you
you better be truthful and transparent. that'll show that you're honest and you better
because you have to get a truth
including what people are bad at and how to deal with all those things
and
and most people hide them. they don't bring them out into the open. okay,
they
everybody's worried about hurting each other's feelings
or you know
uh
that
and then
so they're not honest with each other and and they're
that's the barrier
you
we talked about
the barrier of disagreement
there's
it's like that
okay
um
you know
uh
i don't know
are you good at that
or you're striking out
if you're striking out and what is it
how do we deal with it
you better talk about that clearly
because you need to have an a team of players
you know you have to work yourself
so your team is an a team of players who are tight.
how did you do that at bridgewater?
how did you make people honest? oh, well
uh
f
first of all
um
i had a policy talk behind another person's back
critically.
that happens three times, you're out.
and then i would have radical transparency so everybody could see everything.
so you could see why i'm making decisions and i would reflect.
but the main thing is you know you know if it's happening or not.
okay.
and i made that comfortable because that's ordinarily uncomfortable.
we talked about the fact that there's an intellectual you and there's an emotional subliminal you.
okay. i made them understand like if i had a team
a football team and so on that this is going to be better for the team.
is going to be better for you and you'll have your evolution
because what do you want to have dishonesty?
do you want people to think one thing about you
and really say something different? how is that going to work?
so there's an intellectual
okay
we believe it
and then also by having the meaningful relationships. i mean i'm not
i don't force them.
i create a culture of meaningful relationships so that they have known each other for a long time.
they go go to each other's parties or they go to each other's there are funerals.
there are baby showers. there are these things. not that anybody's f
i created uh clubs. i said, " any club that you want to create that has more than uh
20 people
um
whatever it is
up to $ 500 per half. " so, so i don't care what it is.
if it's play softball
or play chess
or whatever it is that you're enjoying each other's company
or you want to go to ball games or something, i don't care what it is.
i'll pay for half up to that
up to $ 500.
so i to nobody has obligations to or something
but if i have that kind of meaningful relationships
so you can talk honestly with each other
uh
i found that very helpful and you've built a famously built an idea
meritocracy
which in my understanding means where the best idea ends up winning in the company versus just your idea
because you're the most powerful person in the business
right
i mean i want what do i want
i want the best idea to win
this sounds simple
but but again
it's
it's not how businesses operate.
one of the fascinations i've always had is that
when businesses get bigger and they have more intellectual horsepower by
i mean if you just added up how many brains they had
they sometimes get less innovative
and it it feels like the the ceo well
because they become more more bureaucratic and more fragmented. yeah. okay. there's
um
i found it to be true
and it's wellestablished fact that if you get a group of people past a certain size
which is 75 to 100 people
um
they don't know each other. okay,
they
they start to become different
and then you lose those relationships. you lose a lot and so on.
i found it because
uh
um
at the holiday season every year,
what i would do is i would write everybody notes, long notes in their cards
and i would pick an individualized holiday gift for them.
and when it got to be to 67 people, i remember the year, it broke my back.
i mean, i i just couldn't do it. okay.
and i realized that at that point i was going into another frame.
okay. and so it's a organizational reality that you can keep that group
and then what you have to do is then you have different
those different areas and you have to create cohesiveness between those different and cohesiveness
common mission
and how do you do that between that. so, like
for example,
when we would have our holiday party where it used to be
everybody would be, you know, sort of go in and you have a holiday party and everybody together,
what i found out is we had a big arena that we would uh
go to and i'd have both. i'd have okay
um
that department is in that area and whatever
and then they come out and they all mingle together and so on.
so there's an organizational thing that you've got to realize in terms of culture and and management of that.
it's like villages in a city
i guess
like
yeah
you basically keep build the villages and then good example city. interesting.
okay. yeah.
our media company's at that exact point now. it's at
it's at that
90 odd people. okay. there you are.
so when you said 75 to 100
i was like ah
interesting.
yeah.
i was thinking about all the things i should be doing now to counteract some of those adverse effects of the culture splintering
or relationships breaking down.
but i guess you've described it there. uh
interesting.
and i have to say one of the things i found to be most
i'm 33 years old. i just turned 33 last week.
it's crazy how how often people say that hiring is the most important thing.
yet
when you look at how what entrepreneurs are spending their time on, it's usually like the product, the marketing, etc.
and it's maybe like one or two hours in some cases if they're lucky on finding truly exceptional people.
they often just outsource it to someone else, the recruitment team.
when you think back through your career, how important was it to find truly exceptional people? of course.
well, i systemized it first of all.
um
i think that anything i do or one does can be systemized.
so i would think what are the personalities, what are the backgrounds of the people
that i'm hiring, what are the choices,
how do i specify it? and i've and i got it
by also maintaining a lot of data with people.
there's um
there's a ted talk i did that
uh
explains how like data
everybody's going around and they're operating in a certain way.
so i know what people are like.
if you know what people are like, you know what you can expect of them.
and then i would then say uh
in a very data way,
those people who are successful in these jobs have the following attributes
that would create a job specifications for that type of job.
so i i knew
that in that type of job there would be that type of person i'm looking for.
okay.
what works
they work
okay
data
and then i would find that would be my job spec
and and so we had the systems
and then we had some people who are responsible for doing that
because you're right
it takes time
how can i interview all those people and so on
but who can you trust and you're operating that way
and then evaluation process doesn't stop when you hire them
okay
the valuation process continues from that moment
and you still learn more about what they're like and you do that same process and still think
would
i still have hired them and and if i wouldn't have hired them
you know
in the first place
then they shouldn't be there
and so i have a process and people
people in process
do people change after a certain point
so if you've hired someone in six months and 12 months and they haven't changed
is it worth giving them another year
is it worth a performance review
i found out that for me the big question
mostly there were two big questions
but um
the big question is how do you adapt to my culture
and that would take about 18 months to find out like
can you speak honestly about what can we have thoughtful disagreement
do you like this evolutionary process where you're challenged and all of this kind of thing
that culture that'take about 18 months and then roughly speaking
then learning about the people
their strengths and weaknesses would take 18 months
two
two years
maybe something along those lines
and so then you know
you could pretty much decide
but always being open every day by day
so nobody's surprised that you're always talking about things
you know
how's it going
make sure you keep what i'm about to say to yourself
i'm inviting 10, 000 of you to come even deeper into the diary of a ceo.
welcome to my inner circle.
this is a brand new private community that i'm launching to the world.
we have so many incredible things that happen that you are never shown.
we have the briefs that are on my ipad when i'm recording the conversation.
we have clips we've never released. we have behind the scenes conversations with the guest
and also the episodes that we've never ever released
and so much more.
in the circle, you'll have direct access to me.
you can tell us what you want this show to be, who you want us to interview,
and the types of conversations you would love us to have.
but remember, for now, we're only inviting the first 10, 000 people that join before it closes.
so, if you want to join our private closed community, head to the link in the description below
or go to daccircle.
com.
it's a really interesting time to be leading a business.
new skills are constantly being invented
and ones that didn't exist a few months ago are now all of a sudden essential.
our team at flight story thrives on staying ahead of emerging tech and innovation.
so whenever we need to plug into those skills of the future like vibe coding, ai agent development, generative engine optimization, all of the technical things we've talked about on the show before, we always go to the same place, which is fiverr,
our show sponsor, and the place
where that future focused talent quietly shows up before the rest of the world catches on.
their freelancers are reliable, high performing, and also highly vetted.
and you'll find them in over 750 categories.
fiverr isn't just for quick jobs.
we use their talent more on complex long-term projects, ones that require an expert to take charge.
and you can tap into tomorrow's talent at fiverr. com / diary.
and for 10 % off your first order, use code diary.
ai is
um
a bit of an alien that seems to have entered the room um
and has is going to change more
almost every every industry. great.
yeah.
i can't tell if you're being sarcastic. no.
truly,
if you are
um
working with it, controlling it, if it's a good partner to be able to get a lot of leverage, it's truly fantastic.
as i said in almost everything i did, we had the criteria, we had the systemized.
would you do that? would you not do that? how do you know
how does reality work? what are the principles? and and so it's a fantastic leveraging
like i described. you know, i would make the decision-making model
like the computer chess game that would make it. well, now it's better than uh
ever those those resources.
so it leverages you enormously. what about having a strong middle?
we talked about having the strong sort of economic political middle.
political middle. yeah. yeah. is it going to drive inequality? yes.
it's going
that's like all good
like all things. going to be
um
it has good things and bad things and we were talking
let's say first about managing and doing that
i think in managing and knowing what people are like and how they're all
it's going to be very valuable
mostly very valuable in terms of changing
um
there'll be
uh
a limited number of winners and a bunch of losers and
um
i think it's going to create much greater polarity
which
as we're seeing um through the system
the ways that we talked about
you know that top 1 to 10 % benefiting a lot and that you know
so that will be a dividing
uh force
i think it's got to got to pose the question with robotics accelerating at the speed of of light
with optimist and tesla
and all the things they're doing
and all these other companies
humanoid robots
and then with artificial intelligence
having trillions of dollars plowed into it and accelerating. we're in this crazy boom at the moment.
with these two things combining, you're going to be able to have a humanoid robot who
that can navigate human spaces, but is also smarter than i am.
lawyers, accountants,
uh
lots of people in the medical profession. why would you
why would one need them if we had a humanoid robot that is smarter than all of us
and has a phd and everything?
well, we will not need a lot of those jobs for the reasons that you're saying.
okay. and then the question is what our society does
and what do you think we do in such a world? i think we fight over about what we do unfortunately.
um
but as i say i i don't think we have escaped a world
where most people to have a healthy society
most people have to be productive and prosperous. i don't
i
i think people need to be now
certainly there
and there certainly needs to be a redistribution policy.
i don't think that's just a redistribution of money policy
because uselessness and money may not be a great combination.
so i think that you have that has to be figured out
and the question is whether we're too fragmented to figure that out and agree on it
and i'm worried about that.
interesting times. is there any historical precedence for this in your view? someone that knows history.
is there any historical precedence for something like ai and robotics converging?
well,
um
through um evolution, we have gone from a period of time
which was called the dark ages or the agricultural age
in which
um
basically there was land.
it's agricultural and so on
and people were treated
they were essentially like oxen
most people
and then there were the landowners
who were the nobles
and then there were the royalty
who
uh
were the families that control most things
and so on
and then in history
with the uh invention of the printing press
there became more knowledge
um
uh
more intelligence
and we see an evolution in which
um
you start to see new ages emerge and thinking emerge and power change
and i won't take you through the whole history
but you start to see that individuals can be clever enough to earn money
that
so you begin the age of exploration and the industrial revolutions in which machines replaced people
and it's almost like they first replaced them physically
that
um
in other words they didn't have
they were not like oxen doing the thing
so you get a tractor or something
and and it's almost like from the body up in terms of the mind
and so you've seen that evolution through time and the rise of intelligence in its various forms
go through this arc of rising in intelligence
and now you see that intelligence matters more than anything.
okay? it matters more than money.
it matters more than anything
because intelligence will attract people among those with money to invest in them in the development of that.
and so we have seen this arc through history develop in that way, right? and we've seen people replaced.
now the question is as we get higher
and higher in thinking, okay, whether we've run out of capacity to shift
or whether we're just going to be totally replaced. our muscles have been totally replaced, but okay,
as this is happening, our best thinking may be totally replaced
and we're going to have to deal with that question.
are you hopeful? i'm excited.
i'm
i think it all comes down to human nature.
okay.
i'm excited in that. fast forward, make the most of it, jump on it.
woo
!
you know,
i'm excited.
i've also watched
uh
the evolution of species.
almost all species have come
and gone for certain reasons
and they uh one of the reasons that they come have come and gone is
because almost their strengths are not in all respects
great strengths.
you can use these things, intelligence to your detriment.
and i believe that
um
the things that these technologies and so on bring us while very important,
it extends life expectancy
and all of that is not import as important as human nature.
and so if you were to go back in time
and we're at different societies, do you have happier societies? is the well-being greater? okay.
so you can go 50 years ago and you might say the well-being is greater
50 years ago.
not in all ways, not in in many ways
the technologies and the consequences of those are much better, but you may have had a better life.
and it's human nature of how people are going to deal with each other.
so i think the real question is can people rise above this
and
and which it goes back to the spirituality question.
can people then rise above it so that they think of the collective good and they think of you
know
collectively
how do we make the best and also karma
you know
in other words
um
the realization
that if i help you in ways
that can be so simple for me to help you make such a big difference in your life
and you do the same and we have win-win relationships
it'll be good
but if we don't do that
and i worry about human nature
and i worry about this process, especially when you've got geopolitical tensions. and it's because of human nature.
i've had a lot of conversations on the podcast about ai
and i just can't seem to get to my own solid conclusion about this
because when i look at human nature, as you say,
i see greed, i see power, hunger, status.
yeah.
some problems
you just just accept the fact
that you may not be able to be confident about a prediction in the future.
so, it'll always be a question
and just get on with the fact of using it for yourself in the best way
that works for you.
that's what i'm doing.
we have a closing tradition on this podcast
where the last leaves a question for the next not knowing who they're leaving it for.
you know this person
um
because i've seen you with them.
the question they left for you is what is a book
or books that you've recommended or gifted more than others
and why? can't say your own but right
um
there are three books
there's a book on evolution
written by richard dawkins
uh
river from eden
i think it's called
then
a book by um will and ariel durant
which are the maybe the greatest historians in time
and it's called lessons from history
it's a very short book.
i think it's 104 pages. they wrote massive amounts about 5, 000 years of history and so on.
and they sort of condense their lessons, lessons from history. and then um
joseph campbell's the hero's journey. is it the the hero with a thousand faces?
yes, that's it.
hero with a thousand faces.
and why dawkins book?
why did you say that one? oh, he understands evolution.
everything is evolving. okay. all species.
man is one of 10, 000 species.
i mean, and they're and they're all structured similarly. there's a structure. they
they
you know,
like
um
two eyes, a brain that has a structure to it. um
that and the same parts of the brain. there's the cereum,
the cerebellum, the prefrontal cortex. there's this structure that makes you think differently
and and so on. there's evolution. there's all evolution.
so, it's not just limited to um
human evolution or what humans are like.
it's the force of evolution. man is only
um
mankind's only about 200, 000 years old. that's in history
that's short.
okay.
and and the species and all species evolve. okay. and it's very interesting.
so that's and you know that's what his books are about
and you know i think they're very good
and joseph campbell's the hero's journey
the hero
with
it's
about human nature and and the evolution of life and the life journey that we're talking about.
what i find so interesting ray is how you draw on principles from other domains
whether it's from nature or biology
as you were talking about there to tie into your work in business
and investing and everything else and life and happiness.
and it really says something to me about being more eclectic
and be broadly curious in order to be successful in my more narrative.
yeah. i just see i i don't
is that to me
maybe too much of a specialist kind of mentality
but the world is being interrelated to these things if you want to understand how reality works.
um
you can't say i'm going to be just a specialist.
i mean these are all affected by each other.
thank you so much for write writing these books. they are iconic
and
uh
the youtube videos that explain these
these books are iconic.
i don't know who you have on your team that makes the animations and pulls it all together.
but not only is the content so important
because they are principles, so they're enduring through time, but they're so unbelievably accessible to all people of all ages.
and if
if you
if people haven't read this book, i'd be shocked. but
um
all of these books are fantastic. the this book, principles by ray dalia,
which i'm going to link all of them below for anyone that wants to read them.
i suggest you read them all, um
will be formative in your life, even if you're not interested in business or investing
because as as it says on the book, they're principles and the
the economy affects us all in ways that we might not understand.
we're all trying to be successful or happy in our own right.
and that that's interwoven into all of these books.
so, thank you.
i hope you write more books.
well, and thank you because yeah, i'm at a stage in my life, this is a symbiotic relationship
otherwise we wouldn't be here. okay.
and my
um
my benefit is that i want to pass along these things and we're doing it together.
and i have found
and it's joyous to me to know that these things have made a big difference in people's lives.
people come up to me and they say, " thank you for the difference you've made.
" and you know, at this stage in my life, that's what i want to do.
i think that's an understatement.
i think it's had a profound impact.
in fact, every person i know, all of my best friends have taken something from your work
which has had a profound impact on their decision-m which has led them to be happier in some way.
and
when i told my friends
that i was interviewing you, i'm interviewing 16 people while i'm in new york over the over the next month.
when i told my friends, my best friends in the world,
that i'm interviewing you, all of them were telling me to pass on a message of thanks
because there's something in one of these books that's helped them.
and they're all young people in that first season of their life.
and there's there's something in all of these books that's um pushed them closer to their success
and their happiness.
so, thank you for on behalf of me because you've had a profound impact on me.
but thank you. thank you for giving me that joy.
you know that. thank you. i really really mean that. thank you so much, ray.