Bill was always obsessed.
I remember him distinctly saying this in the '90s,
he said, "There's only one category in software.
It's called information management.
You got to schematize people,
places and things, and that's it."
The problem is people are messy.
Do people have loyalty to a model
or do they have loyalty to an AI brand?
You want an ensemble of models.
You have agents intermediating that ensemble
so that it meets your needs.
Will everyone's preference
not just be for more intelligence?
Like, I'll go into the picker
and manually select o3
for like, "Where should I go get ice cream," query?
It's like a rite of passage for certain software companies
to try to take on Excel.
Why is it so durable?
We sort of don't give it enough credit.
It's like, "I can make it
do anything." I think the world's
most approachable programming environment.
100%.
And Pieter here is who?
Pieter is Pieter Levels.
He's like an indie— Oh, yes, I know him.
Yeah, you know Pieter Levels.
I know him, yeah. Course yes.
You're so online.
See, Satya knows who Pieter Levels is.
This is why Microsoft is like an $14 trillion company.
Was there anything good to see at the data center?
Or is like— There's always—
"That's a lot of racks."
It's the most fun place to go, man.
Yeah.
Satya Nadella took over as Microsoft CEO in 2014,
but he's been with the company
for more than 30 years and has seen a lot.
Microsoft has grown by 10X
in the time that Satya has been running it.
And he's credited with Microsoft's success
first in cloud and now in the AI boom.
Cheers, John. This is great.
So what should people be excited about at Ignite?
The Ignite Conference for us, more than anything else,
is about making sure that AI is getting diffused
inside of the enterprise, right?
I mean, if there is one thing,
it's more about, hey, what does it mean
not to just admire somebody else's AI factory or AI agent,
but how to build your own AI factory.
So organizing the data layer
turns out to be probably the most complicated thing,
which spans the enterprise
such that it can meet the intelligence.
And so that's the stuff
that I think we'll probably do a lot of.
We still don't really have Deep Research
in a corporate context.
We do, that's what Copilot is about.
But most people day-to-day do not have this.
So are they just underusing AI that exists?
Yes, and in fact, it's interesting you brought that up
because to me that is the killer feature, right?
So the biggest thing we did was we took this graph
that is underneath what is what I think
is the most important database in any company, right,
which is underneath your email,
your documents, your Teams calls, what have you.
It's the relationships that...
By the way, people are not working in an ad hoc fashion
in an unstructured way, but you know,
they're all doing it in relation of some business event.
Yes.
That semantic connection
is in people's heads and it's lost.
And for the first time,
there's much better recall of that.
Why do you think this is underpenetrated
than the enterprise?
Because I feel like people are using lots of, you know,
LLM tools.
They are uploading individual documents maybe,
but I don't think most companies
have the all singing, all dancing,
all of the company's context
is plugged into their everyday AI.
Yeah, in fact, I would say there are two sets of things.
One, it's starting, right?
I mean, you know, what I always say,
at least compared to anything we have done
in terms of all the office suites over our history,
this is the fastest in that sense,
because it's change management, right?
At the end of the day, you've got to get it in,
people have to use it.
Oh, by the way, in the enterprise setting,
it has got to mean all the discovery has to work.
All of the data governance has to work.
We have had to plumb this purview into Copilot
such that anytime I'm trying to retrieve something
that's confidential, it's labeled confidential,
it's IRM'd and so on.
So there's been significant amount of work,
and that I think is where we're starting to see the uplift.
The other thing I'd say is,
you know, it's one thing to have it work
across the Microsoft 365 graph, right?
But then the next thing is, oh, what about your ERP system?
The connectors kind of work,
but they don't really
because they're two thin straws, right?
You just need a much better data architecture
where you have to essentially semantically embed
all of these into one layer.
Okay.
There's been a vision for decades
of your company's data at your fingertips.
My favorite example of this
is I read like the book "Softwar" on, you know,
the history of Oracle,
and it talks about Larry Ellison doing EBCs,
I think they're talking about one in Japan, in the 1990s.
So it's the late 1990s.
And he is pitching executives
on all your company's data in one place.
Part of the reason this is an evergreen pitch
is because companies don't actually
have all their data at their fingertips.
Companies do not eat their data infrastructure vegetables.
And, you know, the pitch to executives is always,
"You can go answer your questions yourself
at the touch of a button,"
as opposed to sending a request to an analyst
who goes and does an investigation for you.
Will we finally this time eat our data plumbing?
You can push back on the premise, but that's my question.
No, I think that, in fact, I think, if I'm not mistaken,
Bill coined this term, information at your fingertips,
at a COMDEX speech, I think in the '90s.
I think that's right, yeah.
And that is kind of where it, you know,
and for the longest time, Bill was always obsessed
about, like, he felt, in fact,
I remember him distinctly saying this in the '90s,
which I picked up in one of the reviews I was in
as a junior guy sitting around,
and he said, "There's only one category in software.
It's called information management.
You got to schematize people, places and things,
and that's it.
You don't have to do anything anymore
because all software..."
And that was the dream Bill always had,
which is he wanted, like for example, he hated file systems
because they were unstructured.
He would've loved it if everything was a SQL database
and he could just do SQL queries
and program against all information.
Like, that to him was like a elegant solution
to information at your fingertips.
The problem is people are messy,
and even if data is structured,
it sort of is not truly available in one index, right,
or one SQL query that I can run against all of that.
So that has been the fundamental challenge
of the old world, I would say.
I would've not thought, none of us thought
that somehow this AI thing
and a deep neural network at some scaling
will suddenly become the thing
that figures out the patterns, right?
Not some schematized data model, right?
In fact, for the longest time
we used to always obsess about, oh, how complex
do the relationships have to be,
or the data model needs to be
to capture the essence of an enterprise, right?
And it turns out it's lots of parameters
in a neural network with a lot of compute power.
Dwarkesh talks about this really smart remote employee
who started five minutes ago, getting at the point
that the models can be arbitrarily smart
and they can do RAG and they can have access
to everything in your enterprise,
but it's not quite the same
as the model actually knowing something as a model.
And so the models, unless you train custom models
inside your company, cannot actually get smarter
at what it is that you do and, you know,
the thousandth query is not any smarter than the first.
Where do you think that goes?
I think there're two things there,
I mean, I think if I understand his thing,
it's all about in context learning
or continual learning, right?
I mean, that's sort of the ultimate thing.
And it sort of speaks to the thing I was saying,
which is if you kind of have the models cognitive core
separated from its knowledge,
then you have essentially the continual learning, you know,
formula, so to speak, or the algorithm,
and then you just unleash it.
At least there are three things to me
that are outside of the model at runtime
that I think you kind of have to crack, right?
One is memory, and all forms of memory, right?
Short, long, right?
Even like these big challenges of, you know,
humans are great at long-term credit assignment, right?
Which is how does intuitively, like somebody said to me,
"Hey, the day, you know,
AI models can both reward and remember
that you, you know, how to punish
for some mistake because they have the ability
to do long-term credit assignment,
that's when you'll know that you have real memory."
But in any case, memory is one.
The second one is entitlements, right?
So, which is they have to really respect
all of the permissioning system at runtime, right?
Because this is where we put their roles,
what access do I have,
and so the model needs to meet that.
And then the action space all has to work.
So if you bring those three things,
because after all, that's the environment.
So if I have actions, entitlements, and memory
with these models, and they by definition
have to be outside of the model,
but be built into the model.
And so for example,
in Copilot today, you use OpenAI models,
you use even Claude, right?
I need the system to work across both of those.
And that I think is where the frontier has to move to.
Yes, yes.
I have many more AI questions,
but I want to ask you some questions
about your way of working.
So, what does your day-to-day look like?
And in particular, how are you managing by walking around?
What virtual corridors are you wandering,
to just get a sense for what's going on in Microsoft?
What do your customer engagements actually look like?
Just for a normal day, not earnings
or not a board meeting or something.
Interestingly enough, my normal day,
it's the two ends of it, right?
Which is the customer stuff,
so there's not a day that I would say I'm not having...
Many of them are remote.
I mean, there's Teams calls for me most of the day,
at least two or three of them with some customer.
It's sort of the most helpful way
for me to stay most grounded, I would say.
So I have at least one or two of those each day.
And then I would say
there is a lot of meeting time.
You know, as a CEO, one of the things I've recognized
is there are two types of meetings, right?
One meeting is where I'm just supposed to convene
and, you know, keep my mouth shut
because convening was the real thing, right?
It is like, don't over perform and just sit,
because all the work would've either happened
or will happen after.
So that's kind of one.
And then the other meeting, which are the important meetings
where I do need to learn or I need to make a decision
or communicate something.
So meetings is another spot.
Then I must say, it's kind of like all over for me,
Teams channels, right?
I am lingering around Teams channels
and they're most helpful.
In fact, if anything, I learn the most there,
I meet most people that...
So wandering the halls,
I wish I could tell you that, you know,
that is the form.
No, but I think Teams
is the new wandering the halls, right, you know,
lurking around those channels.
100%, and then I meet...
So the most beautiful thing
is for me to be able to...
That's where I make the most connections, right?
I get to know, wow, here's the person
working on Excel agent,
or that's the eval that they're looking...
I mean, I learn so much out of it
than anything else I've done.
So are Teams at Microsoft
just working away on their product
and then Satya pops up and, you know,
has a question on their product?
Some of it, like, I wish—
They give a little yelp. I wish—
Yeah, well, I wish, you know,
sometimes I feel like we are way too permissioned too.
You know, I wish I had more access sometimes.
In fact, my biggest complaint
is that I can't drop in everywhere I want to.
But, yes, it's fun to be able to just go in there
and it sort of normalizes it.
And then people are also, like today's workforce
is not shy of sharing their opinion with you.
I've noticed, yeah.
You are famous, at least in small corners of the valley,
speaking of being methodical, for staying very connected
to what's going on in tech here.
And I remember you came and visited the Stripe office.
Remember that one in the Mission, yeah,
when we were a pip-squeak company.
I mean, it was probably
right after you took over as CEO, I'm guessing.
But Stripe was very small and Microsoft was very big.
Actually before,
I think the first time I came to your offices
was when I was running Azure first.
Okay. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, so it was even before that.
So that would've been very early in Stripe's journey.
Why do you think you do this much more than most other CEOs?
Because other CEOs should want to meet all the startups too.
I've always grown up, in some sense, I grew up,
even in a Microsoft, which had...
I have that developer relations evangelism
sort of gene in me, I kind of approach,
I think a lot of it
as, hey, if you don't follow developers...
There are two sort of things that are ingrained in me.
One is if you don't follow where developers are going,
it's hard to sort of be relevant in terms of tech platforms.
And then you really need to understand the new workload
in order to build a tech platform.
Those are the two things that at least I've kept.
And so therefore, the only way,
if you're not following startups, it's very hard
to know what is either the platform or the workload.
So that's sort of a thing that I've indexed towards.
The other thing is it's just, you know,
I derive so much energy out of it, right?
I mean, I've always thought
founders are just magical people
who create something from nothing.
I mean, it's just sort of feels like a magic trick.
So I always like, "How the heck does one do that?"
Yeah, no, it is funny you say that
about following what the startups are doing.
We always conceived of what Stripe was building
as it was important to build for startups
both because today's small startups
are tomorrow's public companies.
And we've seen that again and again on Stripe.
But we just felt at an intuitive level
and we felt this before we could prove it,
that what the startups were interested in
were often better product experiences.
And so if the startups want stablecoins
or usage based billing or what have you,
we should build for those needs.
Not just 'cause we'll have a good startup business,
but the enterprises will come around.
And it took us, I would say, many years
to kind of prove out that model.
But now we're really seeing—
Yeah, in fact, I think you guys
are a bit of a gold standard on that.
In fact, one of the things that I learned from you guys
was rediscovering at some level
what Microsoft was very good at,
which is following the developer,
being where the startups are.
And so that's what sort of led me even to GitHub
and NAT and all of the rest,
which is to some degree the GitHub asset, right?
Obviously it is a great asset.
We needed to, one, be good stewards
of an open source ecosystem.
But it also the place where every startup,
like the one thing that everybody does have
is their repos in GitHub.
And I felt like, hey, being in that loop
was important for us.
Not just "oh it's strategically great
to have some position there," to learn simply
and to build better product, I think, is sort of well said.
Because you lose sometimes the aesthetic
of what is required,
what's that friction-free way to deliver
because the least amount of patience is there
and the time to value, for example, has to be maximized.
Is Microsoft thinking about generated UIs
that are personalized to...
Like, when you think about it,
software is stuck in the old paradigm of, you know,
we write a bunch of software and it goes to Gold Master
and as you know, goes out on discs
and now that same kind of software,
it's delivered in the cloud,
but the UI you want is probably, you know,
we can render that exact UI in real time.
Is that a direction you guys are going?
I think that, for sure, like at some level
what's happening is on one side our ability to generate.
I mean, if you sort of say you can generate all code,
so therefore you can generate some UX scaffolding
around anything that's a lot more custom, right?
So especially, in fact for the longest time,
one of the things at Microsoft
was what's the difference between a document,
a website and an application, really?
And so, to some degree, yeah, exactly.
So you can generate any one of those
at any time depending on what format you want to present it.
But, interestingly enough for all the talk
of, hey, all these apps go.
Take even our good old IDEs,
in some sense IDEs are back, right?
Whether it's Excel or VS Code.
Because the reality is AI generates output,
I need to make sense of that output.
In fact, I need a fantastic editor
that lets me do diffs and iterations on it with AI.
So I think the IDE, I think in fact
one of the most exciting things
is new classes of highly refined IDEs
that have even a sort of a telemetry loop
with the intelligence layer, but also
they kind of act more like heads up displays, right?
I have thousands of agents going off.
How am I going to make sense
of the micro steering of thousands of agents.
And that is what IDEs/inboxes
and messaging tools will be, right?
Which is, I'm not messaging one, you know,
or dealing with triage the way I deal with it today,
but it's going to be different.
Okay, interesting.
So you think right now
programmers spend all their time in an IDE,
but they're one of the few professions that does that.
And your vision is the accountant IDE,
the lawyer IDE, and—
What is the metaphor
of how I will work with agents, right?
So it's kind of like massive macro delegation, right?
So there's lots of agents
I go give a bunch of instructions to and they go off
and work sometimes for hours, days, let's say, you know,
as the models get better, but they are checking in
and so it's macro delegation, micro steering.
So if you take that,
how does one do micro steering with context, right?
It can't come back like my...
It can't be in the next notification hell, right?
Which is, it sort of notifies me.
It has like five words.
I don't know exactly what the real context is
or what have you.
That I think is where,
and that has to be multi app like, right?
So that's where I feel like all software finally,
when it grows up, it looks like an inbox
and a messaging tool
and a canvas with a blinking screen.
Except this time around a lot of work got, you know,
went and happened.
Is that one app, is that 10 different apps?
Like, it's kind of interesting
if you think about the productivity speech that emerged,
there was, you know,
three big apps in Word, Excel, and PowerPoint.
But it's interesting that that number
was not 1 and was not 40, it was 3.
And so how do you think about this in the—
I think that that's right.
I mean, to me, it will be a few, I think.
And in fact, the reductionist, you know,
in me, it says, "Man, they'll be the same things."
Except the job they do is going to be different
because I think, you know,
a table, at least at the human level, right?
Because we can all talk about,
like what tools will agents use
to communicate with each other, right?
That's a different thing, right?
Right now for the RL loop,
they are simulating our production environment,
but they will ultimately be more efficient
in creating their own production environments
to kind of RL themselves, so...
But let's just leave that aside.
But in order to communicate with us,
I feel like we have discovered
some good things that we like.
We like spreadsheets and tables
and we like documents in sort of linear form.
We like inboxes or messaging tools.
So these are like reasonable UIs,
except the question I think you asked
is how does this thing have, when it shows up
in an IDE with like a set of changes,
you have to help me more than just say, "Okay,
now here is a file, go to that file."
Like, that directed plan, not just to execute,
but for me to do my workflow.
And like, one of the things
that we are experimenting with
is mission control and GitHub Copilot is that.
The idea is you go have five, six different branches
in which you fire off all these autonomous agents.
They all do their work, they come back
and then your ability to do PR triage
is where I think the next IDE is born.
I'm struck by in technology
how frequently you see the pattern of excitement for,
and a vision around a technology being so much earlier
than the technology actually being ready.
Like the movie "2001: A Space Odyssey,"
which is in the '60s,
like that was a voice activated AI
with tool use, you know, capabilities.
It's true. And, you know,
it just took 50 years
and then, you know, people were excited about the idea
that you could speak to your computer and, you know,
text to speech, speech to text.
People were excited about that in the '80s.
And like only now, I don't know if you use superwhisper
or anything like that, but it's finally really good.
But like it wasn't good three years ago, you know,
40 years after the vision.
Yeah, it's crazy that you bring that up.
In fact, I used to have an apartment
right next to the Microsoft campus, that old campus,
and I was working on Interactive Television.
This was in '94.
The information superhighway.
That's right.
You know, and there were multiple things that were stunning.
My management chain was Rick Rashid and, you know,
who reported to Craig Mundie,
who reported to Nathan Myhrvold
and there was Bill Gates
and I was saying, "Man, that's a lot of IQ .
And of course we all missed the internet.
That was the only thing that happened.
But I had interactive television,
switched ATM, I think, to my home in my apartment.
So I remember doing this demo,
one of the high stakes things I did
as a young guy at Microsoft
was a demo of our first redundant file system,
which was a video server
where John Malone was the one who came
and Bill was sort of saying,
"Hey, here's the future of interactive television."
And guess what?
It's even great because the disc can go, you know,
haywire and still stream.
And so my job was to remove the disc drive
and have the stream continue.
But we built essentially a distributed file system
and a streaming server
and had an ATM switch network to the house.
And I had like five movies I could watch.
And I watched them all multiple times.
Okay, so I want to ask you about this,
'cause I've thought a lot about this
and you're the perfect person to ask,
which is, Microsoft saw the internet future
that was coming in the '90s,
and in particular the famous Bill Gates
Internet Tidal Wave memo
said, "The internet is the one big thing
Microsoft needs to focus on."
It wasn't like, "We're not thinking about the internet."
It wasn't that it was priority number 7 of 15.
It was like, "Hey, guys, listen up.
The only thing Microsoft should be thinking about
is the internet."
But the vision for the internet at the time
was this information superhighway,
which was subtly different from the internet
because the thinking was, and it was very sensible thinking,
no one has internet to the computer in their home.
Like, a lot of people don't have a computer in their home.
So what people do have is a TV
and what they have is cable,
which is a high bandwidth connection.
And so we're going to do these set top boxes on the TV
and that is how people will use the internet.
Like, paying a huge amount of attention to this coming wave.
Pretty sensible, well thought out solution,
and yet not the right approach.
And so obviously bring that up
in the context of the giant AI.
Like, what should one take away from that?
It's great one.
See, if I look at even my interpretation,
it'll be actually interesting.
I've not spent as much time talking to Bill about that era.
But I felt there were at least...
As someone, as a sort of an entry level employee
at that time even,
my reading of history
was that we kind of got the internet,
but we didn't.
Because we wanted to deliver, remember the quality...
Like, I don't think we believed that TCP/IP would work.
I mean, at some level the information highway,
when I look at what we were trying to do
was, man, this quality of service is a thing.
This TCP/IP just is not going to work.
And so therefore we were competing against AOL, on dial up
and even that sort of...
You remember like MSN was an X.25 network.
Yes, yes. The first version of it.
Yes. And so then...
But that's when Bill like pivoted, right?
So the thing that Bill did was in '95, I guess...
In fact, it's funny that, right,
Windows 95 was launching,
and then he says, "You know what?"
It's all going to change."
So I feel between '92,
which is when I think all of us,
maybe who'd got our first demo,
right, '93, November is when Mosaic...
Right? Yeah, that's right.
I think something like that.
And so we all, you know,
were kind of dancing around it.
So from '93 to '95,
there was that two year period where it was unclear
whether this was going to be the protocol
and the stack emerged.
And by '95 it was clear, and then we pivoted.
Interesting.
Okay, so just at that time it wasn't actually clear
that the open internet would win.
Yes.
And in fact, there's one more lesson that...
You know, the interesting thing that I've always watched,
and because I think we can parlay this into AI,
one is to get the paradigm right.
Then, it's not clear, even if you get the paradigm right,
that you may not get what is the killer app
or even the business model,
like, that's always been the case, right?
Which is, you know, with the internet,
who would've thought that, you know,
for the open web, an organizing layer
would be one proprietor
or one network effect search engine, right?
Because the organizing layer of the web,
you know, I always say like, "There's no such thing
as the open web, there's the Google web."
And just because they just dominated it.
Should one reflect on the fact
that maybe there was some motivated thinking
around our proprietary solution, you know,
the Liberty Media, Microsoft joint venture will win?
Whereas the open web is what won
and you should maybe caution organizations
where if they're following two possibilities, you know,
our information superhighway proprietary system
or the open web, companies will somehow
have happy thinking towards the proprietary solution.
It's an interesting one, I think the way, you know,
when I look back again, it's interesting, right?
So AOL and MSN kind of, you know,
lost out, let's call it, to the open web,
except they were replaced by new forms of AOL and MSN.
They're called search engines.
They're called app stores.
Like, the mobile web in fact is fascinating.
Yeah, the open web was a moment in history.
A moment in history, and then...
And so the thing that, maybe the meta thing for me
is organizing layers will always emerge
even in an open ecosystem
and a lot of the category power
moves to that organizing layer.
And it's always unclear, like the last paradigm
or this last time it was search engines,
today it's chat bots.
How long lasting is that?
No one knows, but it's definitely,
today, I mean, ChatGPT's success cannot be denied
in terms of what it means as an aggregation point.
Marketplaces/app stores have been a thing.
What comes next, you know?
What happens to e-commerce
in an agentic marketplace or an agent e-commerce?
I think these are the interesting things
that need to be litigated.
Well, I want to talk about that
and I want to talk about commerce, but actually first,
while we're on the topic of, while we're still in the '90s,
everyone is making comparisons
to the dot-com bubble right now, it's almost a cliche.
And I think it's actually a reasonable comparison.
You know, it's a cliche for a reason,
which is, it is a very CapEx intensive build out
for a new paradigm that is in fact a big deal
and yet there's an awful lot of CapEx.
You were there at Microsoft during the 2000 dot-com bubble
and it really was, you know,
Microsoft's share price peaked
in the late '90s, early 2000s,
and then didn't surpass it until 2016, I want to say.
What did it feel like in 1999?
In particular, did you know you were in a bubble?
Or was it like, "Oh, this time it's different."
It's interesting. Yeah.
Yeah, in fact, I remember, I think, you know,
we probably became the largest market cap company in 2000,
we crossed GE, I remember that.
Yeah, we were capital-light, let's say, right?
That time around, it was like...
I guess I was more like Sam at that time,
which is somebody else's capital was being spent.
It is, quite honestly, when I look back at it,
at that time too, the financial cycle aside,
it was clear, the secular trend was clear
that this is going to.
Because even by then,
the business models were also emerging.
Even for Microsoft, the biggest lesson at that time
was, oh, my God, like even our first order play,
or, oh, we got to build a browser,
we got to build a web server.
We've got to, you know, have internet protocols everywhere.
You know, we had a website builder
inside of office with front page.
We did all the obvious things,
but we realized that just doing the obvious things
didn't make sense.
We needed to reinvent what we were doing,
plus what are the new business models, was clear.
So in an interesting way,
that cycle kind of came out of nowhere.
I mean, it came out of, you know, what was just, you know,
whatever rational exuberance or what have you,
but the correction in some sense
washed away a bunch of stuff.
But I would say the ideas persisted.
Totally. Right?
And so, to me, I think about what's happening here.
I mean, there are two things, right?
The infrastructure itself that's getting laid out,
I think it's got a lot more immediate.
Like, it's not like even the, you know, the gestation period
of okay, I built up, you know, dark fiber,
and you know, some internet company will first scale
to a billion users and use.
This time— There are lines
out the door to buy this stuff.
Exactly, and so this time around,
quite frankly, we are behind, right?
Like when I look at our infrastructure build, right,
and demand today.
That's the thing that when people say
it's all a, you know, there's a bubble.
Like, when I look at my earnings, I can have...
Like, I mean, that was the last time
I was so supply constrained on PowerShells.
I haven't heard that comparison before,
which is, let's not forget that the dot-com bubble,
which again was a telecoms bubble,
it was a fiber bubble in a big way.
Like, it was dark fiber, the clue's in the name,
it was dark, it was not lit up yet.
And this is anything but dark fiber.
Yeah, it's not like any one of us is sitting there
and saying, "Hey, I have all the GPUs wired up
and nobody's using them."
I don't have a utilization problem.
I may have a PUE, like, I mean,
I want higher utilization
because it's mostly because it's memory bottleneck
or what have you, but that is a different...
But like there is not a thing
that I have that's not sold out.
In fact, my problem is I got to bring more supply.
And in that, will we perfectly get it?
No one does, right?
There's no supply chain operation
that perfectly matches demand and supply.
But this time around the build out, you know,
given the long lead, like for example,
one of the things we study a lot is,
even when we talk about our capital,
we try to describe it even to the Street.
Hey, you got to remember these assets.
Some of these assets are 20 years.
Some of these things are four years or five years.
And in fact you kind of have to make the decisions
on those things differently, right?
Having a cold shell that's unused is nothing, right?
Yeah. it's kind of like having a campus with five buildings.
It's not sort of going to be a problem
on Microsoft's balance sheet.
What is a real problem would be,
hey, not having warm shells
that we can kind of light up.
Where is the bottleneck these days?
Like, is it electricians, is it shells?
Is it turbines. Yeah, I mean, so...
Yeah, the product that is the bottleneck
is just a bunch of powered up shells.
So if I don't have enough shells that are powered,
that I can then roll in my racks
and then make them operational.
And that's the long lead part, right?
Which is you kind of have to have the land permits,
the power permits, get all that done in time.
And by the way, location, right?
So I think one of the things that's glossed over,
of course stateside, United States, we are building a lot,
but we have to build all over the world.
And there are data regulations, in fact, more every day.
People care about sovereignty in a major, major way.
And so therefore for us, we have to make sure
that the fleet is a global fleet,
a fleet that kind of can deal with all types of workloads,
training to DataGen, to inference.
And so it's sort of a complex, multi-variable thing.
Who should care about data sovereignty?
Where, you know, Ireland has a bunch of data centers
but is not particularly wound up on the idea that, you know,
data should only be in Ireland.
And I don't think it should be super wound up
about that fact, but, well, I guess,
do you guys just go with whatever the country wants
or do you try to advise
on whether you should want data sovereignty or not,
and who should?
Yeah, so I think it's obviously a topic that's top of mind
for pretty much every country,
every policy maker, and they care.
And there's obviously real legitimate reasons.
The thing that I would say, in the AI age,
I'm now thinking a little bit differently
even about sovereignty.
What I mean by that is the ultimate sovereignty question
is more of what's the future of a corporation, right?
Like, I mean, if you sort of start by, you know,
if you go to the core of the Coase theorem,
you say, "Wow, what the heck?
You know, if the model is the thing that knows everything,
why do I even...
Like, I'm supposed to have some tacit knowledge
that makes the transactional costs inside my organization
lower than just being in the marketplace."
So that's a mind bender.
So in fact, one of the ways I think
is the sovereignty that matters
is your company's sovereignty
in a age where there are continual learning,
increasing returns to a model.
So I'm increasingly thinking that hey, company's ability
to have that intelligence layer that's a scaffold
or even weights embedded in the model.
Like, so it's not somebody else's foundation model.
It's about do you have sovereignty in your foundation model?
So my new concept is the future of a company
is that company has its own foundation model
that captures essentially that passive knowledge
that makes the transactional costs
of how knowledge gets accrued and diffused
inside the organization faster.
So that's sort of a long speech on sovereignty.
Well, there's two versions of...
That's very interesting, the idea that AI
maybe just changes the nature of companies.
And you are saying that if companies,
some companies are already collections of IP, right?
You know, Disney, we just had Dave Ricks
from Eli Lilly here, that is an IP company in a big way.
And some companies are already collections of IP.
But right now that IP is in all the emails and documents
and people's heads most importantly.
Whereas maybe the IP could be in a single model over time.
Where I thought you were going to go with that
is just maybe the, you know, people point out a lot
that current companies are modeled after, you know,
manufacturing companies and Alfred Sloan type stuff,
despite the fact that, you know,
we're doing knowledge work today
and not running a little manufacturing line.
And do you get more just weird looking companies,
do you get the, you know, the famous,
really tiny billion dollar company?
Do you get more highly distributed internet companies?
Do you get some DAOs?
I thought that's where you're going to go with that.
I think that those are also possibilities.
So the structure itself could change
and it's going to be more possible for, you know,
whatever the few, you know,
the one person billion dollar company, what have you, right?
Make that happen or DAOs could happen.
But the interesting question, at least for me is,
where does tacit knowledge reside, right?
Clearly it resides in people's heads
and it's the classic knowhow that accrues in compounds.
I think it will also reside
and compound as weights in some LoRA layer
that is unique to your company.
So that's kind of my...
So in fact, I feel like, hey, you know,
the new intellectual property at Eli Lilly or at Microsoft
or at Stripe at some point
can be also be besides all the humans,
besides all the other artifacts we have,
I think we'll also say, "Oh, they are in some embedding."
Yes. Well, okay.
It's funny you say this because Stripe,
Stripe is interesting 'cause it does not really
have strong network effects as a company.
You know, when we started building up Stripe,
it was very much a single player API experience
and we make it easy to start using Stripe,
but ultimately you'd never know
that anyone else was using Stripe.
What's happened as we've scaled up
is we now just have a trust network
where we can prevent fraud by virtue of the fact
that we've seen most internet users.
And so we have a knowledge for what good and bad looks like.
And even the fact that we haven't seen you before
is inherently a little bit suspicious
because we've seen most people
and so it becomes a reputation network,
kind like reCAPTCHA for Google
simply became kind of a reputation network.
Anyway, what we're now doing
is training a payments foundation model
where we're using all the data that we have
in the Stripe network
and you have a much larger, more capable model
taking into account...
So anyway, we are trying to do exactly what you're saying.
And so one of the questions for all of us,
then how do you protect that
from sort of essentially leaking over
to the base foundation model?
Is it just like one capability hop away
because it learned how to even do fraud detection?
Is it just some other multidimensional or not?
And that I think is the key question, right?
To me, I think, there are two arguments, right?
One argument is it's that, you know,
argument that, hey, the models are going to eat the world.
You can kind of easily see, oh yeah,
after all, everything is just a pattern
and I'll learn it all and what have you, so.
But then the thing though is,
you could, to your point about Stripe
can take multiple models,
build this unbelievable sort of, I'll call it
fraud detection layer that is, you know, model forward.
And then there is this memory and tools use
and action space that's all unique to Stripe.
That to me is the future of a corporation.
Whether it's a pharma company, a payments company,
or a software company.
That I think is the work that we all are doing
and will do, and I think that that's, to me,
that is sovereignty, right?
Alright.
Oh, man.
Woo. Wow.
Okay, this could be a new high score.
And 4, 74.
So, new high score. There you go.
I'm still thinking about this discussion
we're having about
the IDE for people who aren't software engineers.
And again, I feel like there could be a product
in the next 10 years for finance people
where, in hindsight, it is obviously the correct UI,
but just like the spreadsheet
kind of came out of nowhere as a UI,
it may feel like it came out of nowhere at that time.
I'm really struck by that.
Speaking of the spreadsheet,
it's like a rite of passage for certain software companies
to try to take on Excel
and it's seems to be doing pretty well
40 years in or what have you.
Why is it so durable?
Yeah, it's unbelievable, right?
I mean, at some level, you know,
the idea that a tabular for...
I mean, I think it's the power of lists and tables.
It's just a perfect,
and the malleability of software, right?
That was I think the combination.
So I think that's where the, what's the durability of a,
that's why a blinking canvas, right?
It's sort of like it's always going to be there.
We may add lots of bells and whistles to it.
And the same thing with spreadsheets.
The other thing about the spreadsheet is,
it's Turing complete, right?
I mean, that's the other, you know,
Yeah, We sort of don't give it enough credit.
It's like I can make it
do everything. I think it's the world's
most approachable programming environment.
100%, I mean, it's kind of like, you know,
and you get into it without even thinking your programming.
And that is the other beauty, right?
Which is like, you know, like AI still, we're mystified it.
You and I talked about, oh, my God,
we need change management.
When spreadsheets came,
nobody talked about change management.
They were just using it.
And that to me is the other thing which is...
You know, like somebody was describing to me,
I was meeting the CEO of Generality,
he joined Generality during the fax machine era
and he was managing all their insurance agents
and he said to me like, "Look,
I still remember the day when emails showed up,
Excel showed up and the entire workflow
of how things happen completely were upended
and evolved and changed ground up."
And so to me, I think that that's, to your point,
what are those things of this era that will discover,
that'll allow the ground up relitigation of the work,
the work artifact and the workflow.
It's such an interesting time to be in software.
I mean, compared to, you must feel this,
like, it's just a much more interesting time now
than 5 or 10 years ago.
You know, it is interesting, right?
Which is what happened was we were like, you know,
Cloud, Cloud, Cloud.
And, you know, if you had to ask me
what is the hottest thing in, you know, 2019,
we had built this fantastic multi region
or regionless database that was multi-format, right
Cosmos DB, which was like, ah, we had, you know,
basically a JSON database.
We had a SQL in there,
it was the everything database and we were thinking,
oh, and it's regionless and blah, blah, blah.
And then the pandemic happened
and then Cloud went into another hyper drive.
I mean, Teams, thank God, just became like the thing.
So that was the exciting thing,
and lo and behold, you come out of it
and you sort of say, "Oh, I thought, oh, after the pandemic
we're going to get to some stable state."
In fact, I remember a forecast of the Cloud, you know,
we were saying, "What do we do?
We overbuilt during the pandemic,"
and there was a good eight months
where we were, "Oh, what..."
And then this thing now has come to.
There's a lot of charts of the shape at Stripe.
I don't know if it was this way at Microsoft,
where obviously March 2020
you saw this discontinuity, right?
Much more eCommerce activity happening
and we saw the rate of online business creation.
'Cause, you know, you had businesses that were offline only
saying, "Oh, you know, we got to switch to selling online."
And it just stayed at that elevated level forever
obviously since, it's gone up from there.
But there was no matching decline
as people went back to, you know,
into physical offices and things like that.
It was just a step change
and then it stayed at the elevated level forever.
I'm sure you saw some of the things
in Azure and things like that. Yeah, 100%.
It never came down.
We're talking about commerce, so we might as well
talk about what we're working on together.
So we are very excited about it.
I mean, I think the idea that has always been there is,
which is what's the best way
for a merchant friendly set of rails
and what is a customer friendly set of rails, right?
Is there a perfect matching?
Conversational sort of commerce
is a thing that people have talked about.
And now I think with the work that you all have done
and others have done,
we kind of can really bring the merchant and the end user
and have this agentic sort of experience.
So it's early days, it has to be tastefully done,
it has to be done in a way that you earn the user's trust.
And so I'm very excited about it.
Yeah, we see two differences here
because there have been previous attempts as, you know,
buying on Twitter, buying on Instagram
and, you know, these kinds of things.
But what's different here is one, you have AI,
so all the integrations for the merchant are much easier.
It's much less of a lift than previous times
when things like that just have been tried.
But then secondly, I just think the experience
is so compelling as an end user.
We're already seeing this in the early data
from the super early customers that we have.
You know, we launched a few weeks back in ChatGPT as well
that just, it has to work.
And again, the data's already bearing that out,
because it's so much easier as an end customer.
Yeah, I've been talking about it like, you know,
I'm a bit of a cricket nut so I kind of,
I'm always searching for something and, you know,
the problem is, you know,
whether it's Amazon or Walmart or what have you,
the search experience sometimes is hard on the site.
So interestingly enough,
these chat experiences first are fantastic, right?
And the fact that they point back to the catalog,
I mean, the catalog is still king.
But now if I can marry the checkout and the catalog
and that to me is where I think the seamlessness.
Well, and do you have any experiences,
I've found versions of this,
I'm curious if you've had experiences
where for product research,
using an AI app is so much better
than, you know, keyword based search.
It's amazing that up to last year
we thought keyword based search was an acceptable way
to hunt for anything. Yeah, in fact, that's...
Yeah, and the seller, like the bottom line
is it's kind of like it is creating
a custom catalog for you, right?
I mean, the response is not like a SERP, right?
No, we were buying furniture in our house
and we were just saying, "Oh, yeah,
we have this much space available in this spot.
What do you think is a good, you know, piece
that would look good in that spot
that meets these dimensions," and things like that.
But it's crazy that we weren't doing that
previously, you know what I mean?
And so all this kind of customization,
being able to give vibes, general aesthetics,
"I'm looking for like something slightly higher end
but not super fancy."
You know, it's crazy that you weren't able to...
By the way, that's just the other crazy, crazy thing.
I know my wife's who's an architect
and so she sort of has this notebook, you know,
Copilot notebook in which she has all these
architectural pictures and so on.
And you can ask it quite high level reasoning questions
on what I should put in there.
It's able to take an architectural sketch,
a drawing, and then take a public catalog of furniture
and put those things together and reason about it.
And that type of stuff is pretty magical.
Like, our view on this, we are, as you know,
really AI pilled when it comes to commerce at Stripe.
And we think a huge amount will move here.
And all the merchant conversations we're having
are bearing that out.
And the way I think about it
is that if you are doing open-ended discovery,
"Oh, I'm interested in an outfit to buy for this occasion,
don't know exactly what I want,"
AI will be so much better at helping you with that
than the current experiences where, you know,
you're clicking through a list of search results
or something like that.
And then if you're doing targeted search
where I'm looking for a specific object
that meets these needs,
"I want this component for my bike."
Then also being able to specify with AI
the exact parameters of the search you have,
will be much better.
You're like, "Wait, if you're taking
all of the undirected discovery
and if you're also taking all of the highly directed search,
isn't that just like all the commerce
that happens on the internet?"
I think the only thing that's left
that's out of that is like recurring staples.
"I need to order more pet food."
That feels to me like the least affected.
Though, of course you have to discover the brand
of pet food at some point originally.
But yeah, that's kind of how we're thinking about it.
And again, Etsy has been an awesome first partner
because all the products are custom, right?
There's no...
Yeah, that makes a ton of sense to me.
I mean, the discovery part,
which obviously people like Instagram
and others have done a great job.
So the question is what's the discovery layer.
We have, like, that's one of the, you know,
obviously personalized discovery layer inspiration
for a product, you know,
what Pinterest has done is interesting.
So some layer like that
married with this conversational interface.
Well, and of course it'll be a rising tide
that lifts all boats
where part of what we're doing with this
is making merchant's product catalogs remotely discoverable
and inventory and everything like that.
And then remotely purchasable
where you don't necessarily
have to go through the whole flow on their side
and everything like that.
You can just do it inside the magic wand Copilot experience.
And so that is at like the raw nuts and bolts level
what we are doing and what we're wiring up.
I think then what's exciting is that, again,
Pinterest played with commerce quite a few years back,
maybe 10 years back.
It hasn't taken off as a huge thing.
But now if you have all the merchants
who are offering their product catalogs
as part of this protocol, then social sites like, you know,
Pinterest and Instagram and Twitter
get another run at this kind of commerce experience
because you've way more merchant support and adoption for it
than you had the first time around.
Yeah, and we have a project called the NLWeb
and the idea is that,
and which is to really take every catalog of every merchant
and give it like essentially a website,
an NLWeb interface,
that then an agent can talk to, to be able to interrogate
and get the deep search, so to speak.
Yes, yes, yes. Because today in some sense,
one of the biggest challenges is the quality of the catalog
and the ability to use reasoning to do a deep search.
And if you can solve that, then to your point,
every product will find its query.
Yes, so we're building out this platform
in agentic commerce where we have, you know,
some open source protocols
like our agentic commerce protocol.
We obviously have the regular Stripe products, you know,
people are using us for, you know,
and it's particularly kind of tricky
from a payments point of view
because you're looking to have an AI app
do payments on behalf of other people
across all these different sites on the web
without probably sharing all your payment details
like all across the web.
It's interesting payment things that we're doing.
Anyway, we're looking to build a platform business
in agentic commerce.
You guys seem to know a thing or two.
What advice would you have for us
as we build in this very nascent space,
but when there clearly is product market fit?
I mean, I think...
I mean, you have done that, right?
Which is one of the things
that I would think is what does it mean
to participate in this agentic workflow, right?
For every merchant, right?
Like, so every merchant now
will have to sort of come to someone like Stripe
and say, "Hey, I have a catalog, I have a checkout,
please get me to meet agents,"
in the most friction-free way.
And that's done tastefully is why
I would think I would hire Stripe for.
And I think the merchant onboarding,
because I'm assuming the long tail of merchants
being able to click and say, "Hey,
enable me for agentic commerce,"
is going to be the thing that's going to drive.
Because the good news here is there is going to be multiple,
I mean, obviously ChatGPT is the big one,
but there's going to be, I mean, you know,
Google's going to be there, we're going to be there,
Meta will be there, Perplexity,
there's going to be a lot of competition.
There's going to be a lot of front doors
as aggregators. Yes.
But the more interesting thing is they themselves,
will on their website or on their mobile app,
will want to support natural language queries.
And so all of that being enabled for,
or my own agents will go interrogate those things.
So I think that that's the key thing
to be challenged, you know, or rather really solve well.
Because going to a small merchant
and saying, "Hey, you go stand up an MCP server,
do this protocol, that protocol," what's the easy button?
I think the other thing that's we're going to see is,
and you're probably seeing this already,
a merging of a bunch of the agentic experiences.
So we're talking about agentic commerce here.
And we had Des Traynor from Intercom,
they're now doing customer service AI mediated
and just like replacing humans,
doing customer service with AI.
But what they're seeing obviously
is a huge amount of induced demand
where people initially come for the help desk type queries
and it's like, "Wow, this is honestly a much better way
to navigate the website."
And it's almost like a command line for...
Anyway, it can't quite take as much actions now
as it will be able to.
But I also wonder how much all these experiences merge
where like, we're doing the buying stuff over here
that is growing and expanding and, you know,
maybe there's some discovery and things like that.
They're doing the customer service stuff over there.
It's universal.
Yeah, that's a good point.
When does it become a command-line application?
Like, again, my example of this
is I find the fashion space interesting
where, how incredibly poor the tech is
with a lot of websites out there where people are trying
to do this very aesthetic vibe space.
"I'm looking for something like that,
but like a little more fancy," you know, whatever.
And it's all keyword based search
and manual tagging and things like that.
And things like that feel to me perfectly set up
for having an interactive AI based experience where, again,
like your Midjourney prompts,
you're like, "No, the image wasn't quite right.
Change it in this way."
Just doing that with commerce, I think,
will be really interesting. Makes sense.
And I also think intuitively like, I mean, all of us
our inside sales is also, or rather customer service
is also inside sales.
Exactly. Yeah, yeah.
And so intuitively that makes sense, you know,
and definitely in the agentic world,
you can stitch these things together
so that the seams are not like to what they are today.
Maybe what we're describing
is a bunch of swim lanes have been established
by random accidents of software and org charts
and everything like that.
You do customer service, when people come with a query
is of a non-commercial nature, you are an SDR.
That's right. You know, you do whatever.
And all those distinctions
are probably going to get thrown away.
We're talking lot about kind of the AI apps that people use
and Copilot and ChatGPT and Gemini
and all these kind of things.
There's a debate about how much model quality matters
and is it the case that people pick a brand and, you know,
they've been drinking, you know, Coke for the longest time
and even if Coke's, I mean, Coke's a bad example,
because there was a revolt about the change in the formula.
But, you know, even if they change the formula, you know,
people, they still have a preferred brand.
You know, I use o3, my wife uses GPT-5.
I'm always horrified 'cause I'm like, you know,
"You deserve more intelligence than that."
And, you know, you can take o3 from my cold, dead hands.
Where do you stand on the debate
of do people have loyalty to it?
And there was also the revolt
when they tried to take away
4.0, was it? Yeah, that's right.
And people were really attached to that model.
Do people have loyalty to a model
or do they have loyalty to an AI brand?
And how does this affect your business strategy?
I think that in the consumer products,
this was the first time we saw that, right?
When you changed models, they're not sort of uniform changes
and they impact people differently, right?
And personality is one such thing
or style or what have you.
And so it just sort of is a new dimension.
So in other words, it's also an argument
that, "Oh, wow, this is a new dimension
of perhaps differentiation," right?
People will, you know,
it's sort of, there's the IQ side of it,
there's the EQ side of it,
and then there is all these style points.
And maybe that's kind of one of the things
that people will steer things towards.
But long term, for me,
I think you have to kind of make sure
that the models are most capable
for the hardest high value tasks.
And then you continuously optimize,
after you have access to that,
for what the task had had is, right?
So as a product builder for us,
and my thing is have the model drop
which is the most capable,
but then what's in production is multiple models.
And my favorite, like, new thing in GitHub for example,
is auto, which is I want to keep, you know,
people still obviously love sonnet whatever,
they want to use it.
But at the end of the day, I really want the model picker
and it just can't be a dumb model router, right?
It has to basically have the intelligence
to know that this task deserves this kind of cogs
or this type of intelligence
and this is my complexity of my repo or my PR task.
That ultimately is where, you know,
the future of agents would be, right?
And so therefore you want the model,
in fact, you want an ensemble of models
that then, you know, you have agents
intermediating that ensemble so that it meets your needs.
And then you'll have preferences.
Will everyone's preference
not just be for more intelligence?
Like, I'll go into the picker and manually select o3
for like, "where should I go get ice cream" query?
Like I always want the most—
That's habit, don't you think?
But that is, you know— Maybe.
But it's also an important considered decision.
But it is true.
I mean, like, it's very hard for any of us
to take our, that's why defaults matter
and we love our defaults.
We don't love the cheese to be moved.
You know, even the model selection stuff, you know,
it's kind of like, wow,
if you now took away the model selection, you know,
it's a problem and so therefore you got to be careful.
But I do think in the long run, if I can trust,
that's another one, right?
Which is if I can trust something
to always do something for me while it's making a selection
that somehow is delightful,
then that's when I'll hand off.
Okay, and so you think that's what you need to get to,
is me trusting that you'll pick an appropriate model?
Exactly. Yeah. Yeah.
And then, I mean, my mental model of Microsoft
is that you just play at every part of the stack
in that there's the, you know,
you have Copilot, you have your stake in OpenAI,
you have, well, we can get to vertical applications in AI.
You have the Azure layer, you have chips, everything.
I leaving out a whole bunch of stuff.
Are some more important to you than others?
What is the must win?
Will you do verticals?
Yeah, I mean, at some level— What's the nuance to that?
Yeah, well, at the core,
the way I kind of conceptualize it
is our infrastructure business.
We have to be fantastic at building
what I'll call the token factory, right?
This is the tokens per dollar per watt.
Really being super efficient in that.
Then I'll say we have another layer of it,
which is the agent factory.
And the difference between the token factory
and the agent factory is use the tokens most efficiently
to drive a business outcome,
or a consumer preference outcome, which is about—
That's the value per token or something?
Yeah, the value per token.
And as evaled by sort of the specific domain
that people care about.
And that is, to your point, it has tooling around it.
It has a whole host.
It's kind of the new app tier
or the app server, right?
Every new platform has always had,
there was the web and there was a web server.
This is the AI server in some sense, or the AI cloud.
Then we will definitely want to build our own,
I'll call it systems of intelligence or AI systems,
that is the family of Copilot, right?
Whether it's for information work,
that's kind of what we have done.
For coding or software development,
that's the GitHub Copilot.
Security's another domain
where we are absolutely going to be a primary.
Those would be the three horizontal.
We will also have business applications.
The other one that is,
we're doing a lot in health and science.
So in health the, you know, we had bought nuance
and now we have something called DAX Copilot
and this is the notetaking diarization
for physicians, right.
So the ability to be able to have a doctor
spend more time with their patients
and then the AI do everything else
in terms of everything from coding to taking the notes.
So that's one place we are, you know,
have a great close partnership with Epic.
It's embedded part of Epic.
So that's kind of what we are doing in health.
And then we are also doing stuff in Copilot
for consumer health that sort of docks to it.
But the other one is science.
And the science, it turns out it's a big domain
for what I'll call the outer loop orchestration, right?
Which is the scientific method in some sense
requires you to create the hypothesis,
then run these multiple experiments in silico,
come back, refine and so on.
So that to me is another tool chain.
It's kind of like we're trying to discover some combination
of the GitHub Copilot meets
Microsoft 365 Knowledge work,
if you will, for the scientist
where they have the authoritative sources of knowledge.
They have even the interfaces tools used
could even be, hey, the MCP server
for the wet labs, so to speak.
Can I interface with it?
And then how do you orchestrate all of this
such that the scientific loop can go faster.
As a platform company, you always have decisions
around when should you try and bundle products together,
when should you try and staple them
and mandate they be used together and when should you not.
And, you know, I think the classic example
for some reason that everyone talks about,
despite it being quite minor,
is the fact that Apple originally
only let you use an iPod with a Mac
and try to use it to drive Mac sales
and then gave up and, you know,
shipped iTunes for Windows.
And my understanding reading the "Apple in China" book
is it was like a totally random decision
that someone just made it, you know, one day.
But it's often held up as one of these examples.
Obviously Microsoft, the entire history
is full of these interesting examples.
I don't think people realize how open Microsoft was
in the early days where in 1985
most of Microsoft's revenue was from Macintosh applications.
And then for the Microsoft operating systems,
most of the applications were third party, you know,
like Lotus 1-2-3 and things like this.
And so it was like a fully open strategy.
And then you had the Windows era of the tight coupling
between Office and Windows
and those kind of mutually reinforcing each other.
Then early on, I get the sense
Azure and Cloud was, you know,
oh, it's a place you can run your SQL server.
And then fully embracing Linux later on
and things like that.
I'm curious just to, 'cause again,
we think about this as a platform company
and we've been of late embracing much more modularity
where Stripe Radar, you can use it
even if you're not using Stripe for payments
and things like that.
How do you in general think about your framework
for when products should be coupled
versus when you sell them independently?
That's a great point. And then, I have
AI specific versions of that question.
So the way I reason about it is,
I think we overstate many times
how many of these battles are quote, unquote, "zero sum."
So at some level, one of the pieces of analysis
that I think that you want us to be sharp at is,
what are by definition going to be multiplayer.
Like Cloud is a classic example, right?
Which is, I remember even back in the day
when I got started, and obviously
Azure got started much later than AWS,
people would tell me, "Oh, God, isn't AWS so far ahead?"
Whereas is there a room for a second Cloud?
And having competed against Oracle and IBM
on all the middle tier servers and so on,
I felt like, no, this enterprise customer
and commercial customers by and large
are going to demand sort of a multiple.
And so that was the structural understanding
that drove us to even just be at it.
And the rest is history.
So a little bit of, to me, if you over package things,
you might in fact sort of reduce your TAM,
and not compete.
Like for example, if we built Azure,
in fact Azure's, you know,
we just called Windows Azure, right?
Oh, well, that's a problem.
Because Azure makes no sense just for Windows.
It's sort of got to support Linux as first class.
It's got to support MySQL and Postgres as first class.
And so that's what sort of allowed us to make sure
that you have to actually
have to do a great job with SQL Server.
But you got to do as bang of a job as like, you know,
Amazon would do with Postgres or MySQL.
And so it was driven primarily by, hey, that's the TAM.
That's what customers expect us.
And we are going to have tough competition.
But, so to me that's kind of
how I define my modularity, right?
What's the thing
that maximizes my stack's market opportunity,
then yes, we are a firm,
and the reason we we're not a conglomerate.
And so therefore there should be a theory
of some integration benefits
and platform effects.
And so therefore, what is that
and how do we do a great job of it?
But each layer of the stack,
right, even in, let's say in Azure, the token factory,
somebody should be able to come
and say, "I just want to use Azure
for its bare metal services.
I just need Kubernetes, you know, clustered all over,
but I just need to you to do the management part
and I'll bring all my software."
No problem, we got to win that workload.
Maybe then after that we'll at least have a shot someday
when it becomes a real pain
to manage sort of your multi-region database on your own
that you'll say, "Oh, let me just use Cosmos."
But it's a separate decision.
But isn't there always a debate
between if we have Linux and Azure, we'll sell more Azure.
But then the Windows people say, "Yeah,
but you're a hamstringing, you know, Windows server."
And there are some places like you're describing
where Microsoft's open, there are other places, you know,
Microsoft Flight Simulator is not available
on the PlayStation, it's available on the Xbox.
And that makes sense, you know, it feels kind of natural
to be integrated that way.
I know this might be a bit of a stretch, but, you know,
Teams Chat and Teams Video are not sold separately.
They're just part of one thing, and that makes sense.
It makes the bundle more compelling.
And so don't you always end up in these debates
as to does the bundling cost outweigh the bundling benefits?
Yeah, and I think some of those, like for example,
Teams thing is, it's a classic one,
which is Teams was born as a product
that brought those four things, like Outlook, right?
Outlook was brought, you know, there was a PIM before,
there was an email client
and calendaring was separate.
And Outlook was the first scaffolding
that said, "Hey, we bring these three things
to get a job done," right?
So that was, and same thing with Teams, right?
We brought chat and channels and video
and what have you into one.
So the bundling was the product to some degree, right?
That was the product scaffolding.
And so then of course you can then say, "Hey,
that needs to have an open marketplace
and it needs to integrate with other things,"
or what have you.
So the modularity has to be thought through
in ways that make sense at the atomic level.
Then you don't want to overthink about the synergies
or sort of integration effects
and you're not competitive, right?
A classic thing would be
if you built an unbelievable public cloud,
except it only ran Windows workloads or SQL workloads,
that'll be essentially a very small sliver of the market.
So it was in our sort of interest
and definitely in the interest
of meeting the customer needs.
And so being able to sort of really click in the AI stack,
that's kind of how I look at it, right?
We have an infra business, we have an app server business,
and we have an apps business.
It's just simplifying.
I want those three things to stand
for them
on their own merits.
We ourselves of course want to have the feedback loop
across these three layers,
but customers and partners will choose
which door they enter through.
This impression I have
is that when you took over Microsoft,
you shifted the culture from a highly bundled,
you'll buy your Windows machines
and they're running Microsoft Access
and you know, they're a SQL server
and everything is like neatly packaged together
in this Microsoft life to moving towards
more of an open and interoperable strategy.
I think that the way I would say
is my thing was to go back even
to the Microsoft of the '80s perhaps, right?
Because most of what happened was really in the '90s
there was Microsoft.
and there was pretty much nothing else.
And so there was sort of a lot more
of our things coming together,
whether it was on the client or on the server.
The '80s were like to your point, right?
You know, we built Office on the Mac.
Windows came later.
In fact, the concept that Bill had
when he started Microsoft was it's a software factory.
I'm not in love with any one category.
I'm just like going to build the best software factory
and it's going to churn out whatever,
flight sim— Interpreters.
Flight sim, you want, you know,
a basic interpreter.
No problem, we have one.
You want an operating system, we have one too.
So in some sense that was the idea.
And at what point we got into a lock
between four or five parts of that, that became the Windows
and Windows NT and client server and what have you.
And so I sort of realized that when, you know, I became CEO
and even when I was running our Cloud business,
that, hey, this is a time where, you know,
the market's going to be a lot bigger and a lot different.
And we didn't, like, we didn't have the mobile platform
at that time and so therefore we really needed to make sure
we would stay relevant in the largest markets
that we could address
by bringing our products together in configurations
that made sense.
So it is actually a lot more less dog...
There was not that much dog...
In fact, I would say, you know,
if it was not in the core DNA of the company,
I don't think just because I showed up as a CEO
and I said, "I want to do this," we would've executed well.
It was in the core DNA of the company
that we can in fact take our software to every platform.
Yes, speaking of the core DNA of the company,
there's the famous cartoon of, you know,
Microsoft with all the guns pointing at each other.
How much cultural tweaking did you have to do?
And how do you actually do that
when you get down to brass tacks?
'Cause you can see all the nice things,
the all hands and things like that,
but ultimately culture comes down to
what you will and won't tolerate
and how decisions are made and things like that.
Yeah, I mean, I'd say there are two things
that I learned from that entire episode
because I always say, look,
I'm a consummate insider, right?
Anything good and bad about Microsoft
of the last 35 years,
I lived through them all and I'm part of it, right?
So I can't deny any of it.
The thing that I felt was, a little bit of that
was just we lost our own belief
because we lost the narrative.
That cartoon is a great example of someone else
defining what became the cultural narrative
more so than reality, right?
The people started to identify with the cartoon.
That's right, I mean, that's kind of one of the...
I think that one of the fundamental issues
of today's social media and the zeitgeist
is you can absolutely lose narrative.
It's reflexive Yeah,
it's completely reflexive.
Like, so one of the interesting things is,
of course all of these things have signal, right?
So this doesn't mean, oh, wow, we were all perfect divisions
and we were all sort of, you know, in greater harmony.
That is not the case.
But you know, in some sense,
some of these divisional tensions are real issues
that need to have tension, right?
You can't have...
Like, social cohesion is not a goal,
Winning in the marketplace is a goal,
but at some level you have to orchestrate
these large organizations.
In fact, you may even have two competing teams
by design.
And just because somebody sort of said, "Hey,
I'm going to read the New Yorker
and there's going to be a cartoon,"
like, that's the type of stuff
that I think leaders,
and how to communicate in today's world
where your employees read about you outside
and form opinions about you
is one of the toughest leadership challenges, I think.
Which is how do you earn the trust?
How do you really make sure
that they can in fact feel the reality, shape the reality?
Like the other thing is everybody thinks it's the system.
It's that guy at the top or, you know, my VP
and they have all the power and I have none.
The reality is the power is a lot more diffused
and distributed and so therefore
how do you really help people
especially get hold of that and reshape.
Like, you know, one of the other famous things
people say is, "Hey, I never leave companies,
I leave managers."
And, you know, I believe that, right?
And so it's kind of micro cultures and they can be shaped.
In fact, when I look back at my Microsoft career,
I was lucky to fall into these people
who created these unbelievable environments
in the company, right?
And that's kind of why I stayed
and that's how I thrived.
And so to some degree, you know,
I feel that the more culture...
You need at the top, a narrative
that you have to live and be consistent, right?
So that's where this growth mindset
or learn-it-all versus know-it-all
has been super helpful for us as just a frame
because nobody thinks of it as my dogma, right?
Thank God it's not, you know,
it's a well understood child psychology thing
that appeals to people outside of work.
And so cracking something like that and then living it,
but also somehow I would say the challenge
for all of us in today's world is,
let the social media memes not define us.
What's that inner strength that is there in an organization
that can in fact resist the social meme?
That I think is the key.
How many people is Microsoft?
I think around 200,000.
Okay, so rough number is, you know,
Microsoft is 200,000 people, Stripe is 10,000 people.
Maybe there's someone who's listening to this
who runs a company that's 500 people or something like that.
A lot of the things that we do
are probably fairly scale independent
where you're trying to make sure
that you're talking to customers,
you're holding a leadership offsite.
We're looking at the numbers for '26.
We want the revenues to be a bit higher
and the cost to be a bit lower.
You know, there's a lot of activities in companies
that are kind of the same regardless of the size.
That said, there's also probably things
that only show up at the, you know, 200,000 person,
you know, city state size
that, you know, I wouldn't be aware of
at the 10,000 person size.
What effects only show up when you're that big?
There are two things I would say.
Quite honestly, having only worked at Microsoft,
it's not that I'm like an expert.
But the one thing I would say, taking over for a founder,
you know, Steve and Bill built the company,
I mean, Paul and Bill started
and Steve and Bill scaled it
and I was the sort of the first, quote unquote,
"non-founder person."
The thing I realized quickly, or in fact I got into the job
and I realized that I need a team.
And just to have the ability to manage the scope.
But then, you know, that A.G. Lafley thing
that we put out there, which I think is a great one.
Like what is this, being clear about
what does the CEO clearly need to do though in that, right?
Which businesses are you in?
Which businesses are you out synthesizing the outside,
having the standards, setting the standards for culture,
and then the ability to your point
about having that performance culture
that you can't say, "Hey, I'm only about the long term,
or I'm only about the short term."
You've got to deliver both.
Getting a real grip of the four or five things
that only you can do.
And then building the team, building the team.
You'd say, "Even at a 500 person, that's what you do."
But quite frankly,
you can keep in your working memory, right,
growing up as a developer, right?
There was a set of things everybody would talk about.
How many lines of code do you know, right, personally?
At some point you sort of say, "Oh, that's the person
who knows that module or that library."
That becomes more, like,
and everybody starts where they know every line of code.
At some level then you have to get to the person
who knows, "Oh, I know the person who wrote that."
And I think that that modularity
and team building
and the cohesiveness is, I think they most important.
So am I understanding you correctly
that maybe at the Stripe scale
or at a smaller scale,
you can still reason about the product as a product
and know everything
that you're shipping and everything like that—
But I also think founders are unique in that sense.
because the founders are, you know,
that's kind of what is singular about them, right?
Because they've grown up with it from day one.
See, it's kind of hard
to take the working memory of a founder
and say, "Oh, let me take it and imprint it."
Sort of a professional CEO.
It just doesn't work
because the...
You know, even for me,
I joined the company in '92,
I was not there in the early '80s, right, you know?
And so to some degree it was a continuous scale
that only the, quote unquote, "the founder, CEO"
or the founders see it.
And so that's why I think having respect
for what founders can do uniquely
and founders having respect for whoever comes next,
that they can't be like we're doing exactly
the same thing that they did, right?
So that's why I think this founder mode thing
is interesting, which is that clearly there is, you know,
the culture personality of a founder is unbelievable, right?
And you use it, maximize it.
Then mere mortal CEOs like us
have to sort of also be, you know,
you can sort of be in the refounder mode
but don't think you are a founder.
And that nuance I think is an important one.
Last question, because we're running up against time,
as we talk about cultures and building them,
what's going on in the water in Hyderabad where, you know,
the school that you went,
also Shantanu went there, Ajay Banga went there.
A bunch of good chess players are similarly from there
and southern India more broadly and things like that.
But do you have any theory on the local outperformance?
Yeah, the high school we went to in fact, yeah.
Until I would say NVIDIA and Jensen,
because Jensen has it now covered for all of us.
Yeah, between me and Ajay and Shantanu.
In fact the CEO of Procter & Gamble today
is also from my high school.
See, it's cabal.
It's kind of a cabal.
I would say one of the fascinating things
growing up in Hyderabad and going to that school
in the middle of nowhere at that time in the late '70s
and the early '80s, I would say,
I think it gave us a lot more space.
If you look at even each of us, right?
Academics was a thing,
but quite frankly, we, mostly all of us
had things which we excelled at
a lot of other things beyond academics in fact.
That was a pretty rare thing at that time in that country.
And so I attribute it a lot to my high school
because I feel that it is a place
where it gave us a lot more space and room
to follow what really became your passion.
But you were able to take your time to discover it
versus sort of feeling that, "Hey,
I had to join some kind of a race."
It wasn't as tracked. That's right.
Yeah. That's right.
What was your passion in high school?
Cricket.
In fact, this, by the way, the Samuel Beckett.
Yeah, so I want to know the story.
Sure, you know who...
So if you asked the question,
who is the one sports person
who played actually professionally?
I guess he played one or two matches
for I guess the Dublin University
and he played first class cricket.
And so he's the only person who played professional cricket
and won a Nobel Prize.
Really?
That's really funny.
So you can have it all is the—
There you go.
The chess, boxing of its day or something, you know,
merging the— A Nobel Prize winner
and he's a professional cricketer.
That's awesome.
Well, you know, you, you came close
but in another life, you know, that could have been you.
Alright. Thank you so much.
Thanks, Satya. It's such a pleasure.