Maybe after the Industrial Revolution, this is the biggest thing.
But at the same time, I'm a little grounded in the fact that this is still early innings.
If you're a model company, you may have a winner's curse.
You may have done all the hard work
done unbelievable innovation, except it's kind of like one copy away from that being commoditized.
We didn't want to just be a host star for one company and have just a massive book of business with one customer.
That- that's not a business.
You can't build an infrastructure that's optimized for one model.
If you do that, you're one tweak away from some MoE
like, breakthrough that happens when your entire network topology goes out of the window.
Then that's a scary thing.
Our business, which today is an end user tools business
will become essentially an infrastructure business in support of agents doing work.
The thing that you have to think through is not what you do in the next five years
but what do you do for the next 50?
Today, we are interviewing Satya Nadella, we being me and Dilin Patel
who is founder of SemiAnalysis.
Satya, welcome.
Thank you.
It's great.
Thanks for coming over to Atlanta.
Yeah.
Thank you for giving us the tour of
uh, the new facility.
It's been really cool to see.
Absolutely.
Satya and Scott Guthrie, Microsoft's EVP of Cloud and AI
give us a tour of their brand new Fairwater 2 data center
the current most powerful in the world.
We try to 10X the training capacity every 18 to 24 months.
And so this would be effectively a 10X increase
10X from what GPT-5 was trained with.
And so to put it in perspective, the number of optics
the network optics in this building, is almost as much as all of Azure across all our data centers two and a half years ago.
It's kind of, what, five million network connections.
You've got all this bandwidth between different sites in the region and between the two regions.
So is this like a big bet on scaling in the future that you anticipate in the future there's gonna be some huge model that needs to require two whole different regions to train?
Uh- The goal is to be able to kind of aggregate these FLOPs for a large training job
and then put these things together across sites.
Right.
And the reality is, you'll use it for
uh, training  and then you'll use it for data gen
you'll use it for inference in all sort of ways.
Yeah.
It's not like it's going to be used only for one workload forever.
Fairwater 4, which you're going to see under construction nearby- Mm-hmm.
.
..
yeah, will also be on that one peta- petabits network.
Yep.
So that we can actually link the two at a very high rate.
And then basically, we do the AI WAN connecting to Milwaukee
where we have multiple other Fairwaters being built.
Literally, you can see the- the model parallelism and the data parallelism.
And it's kind of built for, um
essentially the training jobs, the pods, the super pods
across this campus.
And then with the WAN, you can go to the Wisconsin data center
and you literally run a training job with all of them getting aggregated.
And what we're seeing right here is this is a cell with no servers in it yet
no racks.
How many, uh, racks are in a cell?
We think about, uh, we don't necessarily share that per se
but- but we- we.
..
Let me- That's the reason I asked.
No, no, no.
Uh, you'll see upstairs.
I'll start counting.
You can start counting.
We'll let you start counting.
How many cells are there in this building?
That part also I can't tell you.
Division is easy, right?
My god, it's kinda loud.
Are you looking at this like, "Now I see where my money is going"?
It's kind of like, "I run a software company.
Welcome to the software company.
" How big is the design space once you've decided to use GB200s and NVLINK?
How many other decisions are there to be made?
There is coupling from the model architecture to what is the physical plan- Yeah.
.
..
that's optimized.
And it's also scary in that sense, which is
A, there's gonna be a new chip that will come out.
Yeah.
Which obviously, I mean, you take Vera Rubin Ultra.
I mean, that's gonna have power density that's going to be so different
but with cooling requirements that are going to be so different.
Right.
Right?
So you kind of don't want to just build all to one spec.
So that goes back a little bit to I think the dialogue we'll have
which is you want to be scaling- Yeah.
.
..
in time.
Yeah.
As opposed to scale once- Yeah.
.
and then be stuck with it.
Yeah.
When you look at all the past technological transitions
whether it be, you know, railroads or the internet or
you know, replaceable parts, industrialization, uh
the cloud, all of these things, each revolution has gotten much faster in the time it goes from technology discover to ramp- Yeah.
.
and pervasiveness through the economy.
Many folks who have been on Dark Ashes podcast believe this is sort of the final
uh, technological revolution or transition, and that this time is very
very different.
Um, and at least so far in the markets
it's sort of, you know, in three years
we've already skyrocketed to, you know, hyperscalers are doing $500 billion of CapEx next year
which is a scale that's un- unmatched to prior revolutions in terms of speed.
And the end state seems to be quite different.
How- how do you.
..
Your- your framing of this seems quite different than sort of the
I would say, the AI bro, who is-  .
..
who is quite, um, you know, AGI is coming.
And, you know, I- I'd like to understand that more.
Yeah, I mean, look, I- I start with the excitement that I also feel for maybe after the Industrial Revolution
this is the biggest thing.
Um, and so therefore, I- I- I- I start with that premise.
Uh, but at the same time, I'm a little grounded in the fact that
uh, this is still early innings.
Uh, we built some very useful things.
We're seeing some great properties.
The scaling laws seem to be working.
Um, and I'm optimistic that they'll continue to work
right?
Some of it is, um, you know
it does require real science breakthroughs, but it's also a lot of engineering and what have you.
But that said, I also sort of take the view that
you know, even what has been happening in the last 70 years of computing
uh, has also been a march, uh
that has helped us move, um, you know
with, as I said, you- you know
I- I like one of the things that Raj Reddy.
..
. uh, has as a metaphor for what AI is
right?
He's a, he's a Turing Award winner out of
uh, CMU, um, and he's always .
..
And he had this even pre-AGI, uh
but he had this metaphor of, uh
AI should either be a guardian angel or a cognitive amplifier.
I love that.
Uh, it's a simple way to think about what this is.
Ultimately, what is its u- human utility?
It is going to be a cognitive amplifier
uh, and a guardian angel.
And so if I sort of view it that way
I view it as a tool.
But then you can also go very mystical about it and say
"Well, this is, you know, more than a tool.
It does all these things which only humans did so far.
" But that has been the case with many technologies in the past.
Only humans did a lot of things, and then we add tools that did them.
Mm.
I guess, uh, we don't have to get wrapped up in the definition here
but maybe one way to think about it is like may- maybe it takes five years
10 years, 20 years.
At some point, eventually a machine is producing Satya tokens
right?
And the Microsoft board thinks that Satya tokens are worth a lot.
How much, how much are you wasting of this
uh-  .
..
of, of, like, economic value by interviewing Satya?
I could not afford the API cost of Satya tokens.
Um, but so, you know, whatever you wanna call it is that
are the Satya tokens a tool or an agent
whatever, um, right now if you have models that cost on the order of dollars or cents per million tokens
there's just an enormous room for expansion, uh
a margin expansion there where Satya to- a million tokens of Satya are
like, worth a lot.
Um, and where does that margin go
and what level of that margin is Microsoft involved in is the question I have?
So I think, um, in, in some sense this goes back again to essentially what's the
uh, economic growth picture gonna really look like.
Um, what's the firm gonna look like?
What's productivity gonna look like?
Yeah.
And that to me is where, again
if the Industrial Revolution created after, whatever
70 years of diffusion is when you started seeing the economic growth
right?
It took .
..
That's the other thing to remember is, um
even if the tech is diffusing fast, uh
this time around, for true economic growth to appear
it has to sort of diffuse to a point where the work
the work artifact and the workflow has to change.
And so that's kinda one place where I think
uh, the change management required for a corporation to truly change I think is something we shouldn't discount.
So, I think going forward, do humans and the tokens they produce
uh, get higher leverage, right?
Uh, whether it's the Dwarkesh or the Dylan tokens of the future.
I mean, think about the amount of technolo- would you be able to run SemiAnalysis or this podcast without technology?
No chance.
Yeah.
Right?
I mean, the f- scale that you would be able to achieve
no chance.
So the question is what's that scale?
Is it gonna be ten x-ed with something that comes through?
Uh, absolutely.
Uh, and therefore with it you'll ramp to some revenue number
or you'll ramp to some audience number or what have you.
And so that I think is what's going to happen
right?
Yeah.
I mean, the, the point is, uh
that s- whatever, what took 70 years
maybe 150 years for the Industrial Revolution may happen in 20 years
25 years.
That's a better way to f- Like, I would love to compress what happened in 200 years of the Industrial Revolution into 20-year period
if you're lucky.
Mm.
So Microsoft historically has been perhaps, you know
the greatest software company, the largest software as a service company.
You know, you've gone through a transition in the past where you used to sell Windows licenses and discs of Windows or Microsoft
and now you sell, you know, subscriptions to 365 or
um .
..
A- as, as we go from sort of
you know, that transition to wh- where your business is today
um, there's also a transition going after that
right?
Uh, software as a service, incredibly low incremental cost per user.
Uh, there's a lot of R&D, there's a lot of customer acquisition cost.
This is why, not Microsoft, but the SaaS companies have m- underperformed massively in the markets because the cogs of AI is just so high.
Yeah.
And that just completely breaks how these business models work.
H- how do you as a, as
as a, as perhaps the greatest software company
um, software as a service company transition Microsoft to this new age where cogs matters a lot
um, and, and the incremental cost per users is different
right?
Because right now you're charging, "Hey, it's 20 bucks for Copilot.
" Yeah.
So I think that this is a .
..
it's a great question because in some sense
the business models themselves, I think the levers are gonna remain similar
right?
Which is if I look at the, the
if, if you look at the menu of models
uh, starting from, like, say, consumer all the way
right, there will be some ad unit
uh, there will be some transaction, there will be some device gross margin for somebody who builds an AI device.
Um, uh, there will be subscriptions, consumer and enterprise.
Uh, and then there'll be consumption, right?
So I still think that that's kinda how .
..
Those are all the meters.
To your point, what is a subscription?
Up to now, people like subscriptions because they can budget for them
right?
They are essentially entitlements to some consumption rights that come encapsulated in a subscription.
So that, I think, is what .
..
In some sense it becomes a pricing decision.
Uh, so how much consumption is en- you are entitled to is .
..
If you look at all the coding subscriptions
that's kinda what they are, right?
Yeah.
And they kinda have the pro tier, the standard tier
and what have you.
And so I think that's how the pricing will ha- uh
you know, and the margin structures will get tiered.
Um, the interesting thing is having .
..
At Microsoft, the good news for us is we kinda are in that business
uh, all, in across all those meters.
In fact, at, at a, as a portfolio level
uh, we pretty much have consumption, subscriptions
uh, to all of the other consumer levers as well.
Um, and then I think time will tell which of these models make sense in what categories.
Um, one thing on the SaaS side
since you brought up, which I think a lot about is .
..
Uh, take Office 365 or Microsoft 365.
I mean, man, having a low ARPU is great because h- here's an interesting thing
right?
During the transition from server to cloud, one of the questions we used to ask ourselves is
"Oh my God, if all we did was just basically move the same users who were using
let's call it, our office licenses and our servers at that time
office servers, right, to the cloud.
".
..
and we had cogs, this is going to basically not only shrink our margins
uh, but we'll be fundamentally a non-profitable or even less profitable company.
Except what happened was the move to the cloud expanded the market like crazy
uh, right?
I mean, we sold a few servers in India
didn't sell much.
Whereas in the cloud, suddenly everybody in India also could afford fractionally buying
uh, servers.
The IT cost.
I mean, in fact the biggest thing I had not realized
for example, was the amount of money people were spending buying storage underneath SharePoint.
In fact, EMC's biggest segment may have been storage servers for SharePoint.
All that sort of dropped in the cloud because nobody had to go buy
in fact it was working capital, I mean
basically it was cash flow out, right?
And so it expanded the market massively.
So this AI thing will be that, right?
So if you take coding, um, lit- what we built with GitHub and VSCode and over whatever
decades, uh, suddenly the coding assistant is that big in one year.
And so that, I think, is what's going to happen as well which is the market expands massively.
Mm.
I guess there's a question of the market will expand but will the parts of the revenue that touch Microsoft expand?
So Copilot is an example where if you look
uh, early this year, I think, uh
I guess according to Dylan's numbers, um
the Copilot revenue, GitHub Copilot revenue, was like 500 million or something like that.
And then, uh, there were like no close competitors.
Whereas now you have Claude Code, Cursor
and Copilot with around similar revenue, around a billion.
And then Codex is catching up around 700
800 million.
And so the question is across all the services that Microsoft has access to
what is the advantage that Microsoft's equivalents of Copilot have?
Yeah.
By the way, I love this chart.
You know, I love this chart for so many reasons.
One is we're still on the top.
Um, second is all these companies that are listed here are all companies that have been born in the last four
five years.
Yeah.
That to me is the best sign, right?
Which is if you have new competitors, new existential problems when you say man who is it now?
Oh, Claude's going to kill you.
Cursor's going to kill you.
Yeah.
It's not boring, right?
So thank God.
Like that means we are in the right direction.
But this is it, right?
The fact that we went from nothing to this scale is the market expansion.
So this is like the cloud-like stuff.
This, uh, fundamentally this category of coding and AI is probably going to be one of the biggest categories
right?
It is a software factory category.
Yeah.
In fact it may be bigger than knowledge work.
So I kind of want to keep myself open-minded about
I mean, we want to have tough competition.
I think that's your point- Yeah.
.
which I think is a great one.
Uh, but man, like I'm glad we have
we parlayed, uh, what we had into this and now we have to compete.
And so in the compete side, uh
even in the last quarter, we just fin- we did our quarterly announcement
I think we grew from 20 to 26 million subs
right?
So I feel good about our sub growth
uh, and where the direction of travel on that is.
But the more interesting thing that has happened is guess where all the repos of all these other guys
uh, who are generating lots and lots of code go to?
They go to GitHub.
So i- GitHub is at an all-time high in terms of repo creation
PRs, everything.
So that, in some sense, we want to keep that open by the way.
That means we want to have that, right?
Because we don't want to conflate that with our own growth
right?
The, interestingly enough, we're getting one developer joining GitHub a second or something.
Mm.
That is the stat I think.
And then 80% of them just fall into some GitHub Copilot
uh, workflow just because there are.
And by the way many of these things will even use some of our coding
uh, code review agents which are by default on just because you can use it.
So we'll have many, many structural shots at this.
The thing that we're also going to do is what we did with Git
Git, the primitives of GitHub whether starting with Git
to issues, to actions, these are powerful lovely things because they kind of are all built around your repo.
So we want to extend that.
At EA- last week at GitHub Universe that's kind of what we did
right?
So we said Agent HQ was the conceptual thing that we said we are going to build out.
This is where, for example, you have a thing called Mission Control and you go to Mission Control and now I can fire off
sometimes I describe it as the cable TV of all these AI agents
because I'll have essentially packaged into one subscription Codex
Claude, um, you know, cognition stuff
anyone's agents, Grok, all of them will be there.
So I get one package and then I can literally go issue a task
steer them so they'll all be working in their independent branches.
Uh, I can monitor them, uh, so I literally have
because I think that's going to be one of the biggest places of innovation
right?
Because right now I want to be able to use multiple agents
I want to be able to then digest the output of the multiple agents
I want to be able to then keep a ha- a handle on my repo so if there's some- some kind of a heads up display that needs to be built and then for me to quickly steer and triage what the coding agents have generated.
That to me between VSCode, GitHub, and all of these new primitives we'll build
uh, as mission control I think, uh
with a control plane observability, I mean think about everyone who is going to deploy all this
will require a whole host of observability of what agent did what at what time to what code base.
So I feel that's the opportunity, uh
and at the end of the day your point is well taken which is we better be competitive and innovate and if we don't
yes, we'll get toppled but I like the chart at least as long as we're on the top even with competition.
The key point here is sort of that GitHub will keep growing irregardless of whose coding agent wins but that
that market only grows at, you know
call it 10, 15, 20% which is way above GDP.
It's a great compounder but these AI coding agents have grown from you know call it $500 million run rate at the end of last year which was basically just GitHub Copilot to now the current run rate across
you know, GitHub Copilot, Claude Code, Cursor
Cognition, Windsurf, Replit, uh, Codex, OpenAI Codex
that's, that's, that's run rating at five
$6 billion now.
..
. um, for the, for the Q4 of
of this year.
That's a 10X, right?
And, and when you look at, hey
what's the TAM of, of software agents?
Is it, is it the $2 trillion of wages you pay people
or is it, is it, is it something beyond that
uh, because every company in the world will now be able to- Absolutely.
.
you know, develop software more?
No question Microsoft takes a slice of that
but you've gone from near 100% or certainly way above 50% to
you know, sub 25% market share in just one year.
What is the sort of confidence that people can get that Microsoft will be- No
no, I mean, there's no.
..
Again, I- it goes back a little bit
Dylan, to sort of there's no birthright here that we should have any confidence other than to say
"Hey, we should go innovate.
" And knowing the, the lucky break we have in some sense is that
uh, this category is gonna be a lot bigger than anything we had high share in.
Let's, let me say it that way
right?
Mm-hmm.
In some sense, you could say, well
we kind of had high share in VS Code.
We had high share in the repos for
with GitHub.
Uh, and that was a good market
but the point is even having a decent share in what is a much more expansive market
right?
I mean, you could say we had a high share in client server
server computing.
We are much lower share than that in hyper-scale
but is it a much bigger business?
By orders of magnitude.
So at least there's existence proof that Microsoft is doing okay
uh, even if our share position has not been as strong as it was
uh, as long as the markets we're competing in are creating more value
uh, and there are multiple winners.
Uh, so I think that's the stuff.
But I w- I, I take your point
that ultimately it all means you have to get competitive
so I watch that every quarter.
And so that's why I think we're.
..
I'm very optimistic that, uh, what we're going to do with GitHub HQ and
uh, or Agent HQ, turning GitHub into a place where all these agents come.
Uh, as I said, we'll have multiple shots on goal on there
right?
It need, it need not be that
hey, some of these guys can succeed along with us
uh, and so it n- doesn't need to be just one winner
uh, and one subscription.
Hmm.
I, I guess the reason to focus on this question is that it's not just about GitHub
but fundamentally about Office and all the other software that Microsoft offers
which is that one vision you could have about how AI proceeds is that
look, the models are c- going to keep being hobbled
and you'll need this direct, visible, um
observability all the time.
And another vision is over time, these models can.
..
now they're doing tasks that take two minutes.
In the future, they'll be doing tasks that.
..
Next they're gonna be doing tasks that take 10
30 minutes.
In the future, maybe they're doing days worth of work autonomously
and then the model companies are charging thousands of dollars maybe for access to
uh, really, a coworker, which could use any UI to communicate with their human and
uh, so forth and migrate between platforms.
So w- if we were getting closer to that
why aren't the model companies that are, uh
just getting more and more profitable the ones that are taking all the margin?
Why is the, the place where the scaffolding happens
which becomes less and less relevant as AIs become more capa- capable
gonna be that important?
And that goes to, you know, Office as it exists now versus coworkers that are just doing knowledge work autonomously.
And so- I think that's a great point.
I mean, I think that's a gr-.
..
I mean, for example, I mean, this is where
you know, does all the m- value migrate just to
uh, the model, um, and, uh
or does the mo- you know, the.
..
does it get split between the scaffolding, um
and, uh, the model and what have you?
I, I think that, uh, time will tell
but my, my fundamental point also is the incentive structure gets clear
right?
Which is if you take, um.
..
let's take, uh, let's take information work
or take even coding.
Um, already, in fact, one of the favorite settings I have
uh, in GitHub Copilot is called Auto
um, right, which will just optimize.
In fact, I buy a subscription, the Auto one will start picking and optimizing for what I am asking it to do
uh, and it could even be fully autonomous
and it could sort of arbitrage the tokens available across multiple models to go get a task done.
So if that is the.
..
that, that mean, that.
if you take that argument, the commodity there will be models.
Uh, and especially with open source models
you can pick a checkpoint, and you can take a bunch of your data
and you're seeing it, right?
I think all of us will start u- whether it's from Cursor or from Microsoft
uh, we will start seeing some in-house models even
uh, which will.
..
and then you'll offload most of your, uh
tasks to it.
So, I think that one argument is if you win the scaffolding
uh, which today is dealing with all the hobbling problems or the
uh, the jaggedness of these intelligence problems
which you kind of have to.
Um, if you win that, then you will vertically integrate yourself into the model just because you will have the liquidity of the data and what have you
and there are enough and more checkpoints that are gonna be available.
Uh, that's the other thing, right?
So structurally, I think there will always be an open-source model
uh, that will be fairly capable in the world that you could then use as long as you have something that you can use that
uh, with, which is data, uh
and a scaffolding, right?
So I can make the argument that, oh
my God, uh, if you're a model company
you may be, uh, you may have a winner's curse.
You may have done all the hard work
done unbelievable innovation, except it's kind of like one copy
uh, away from that being commoditized, and then the person who has the data for grounding and context engineering
um, and the liquidity of data can then go take that checkpoint and train it.
So, I think the argument can be made both ways.
Un- unpacking sort of what you said, there's two views of the world
right?
One is that models.
..
there's so many different models out there, open source exists.
There will be differences between the models that will drive some level of
you know, who wins and who doesn't
but the scaffolding is what enables you to win.
Yeah.
The other view is that actually models are the key IP
and yes, we're in a very.
..
everyone's in a tight race, and there's some
you know, "Hey, I can use Anthropic or OpenAI
" and you can see this in the revenue charts
right?
Like OpenAI's revenue started skyrocketing once they finally had a code model similar capabilities to Anthropic
although in different ways.
Um-.
..
th- th- there's a view that, like
the model companies are actually the ones that garner all the margin
right?
Because, you know, if you look across this year
at least on Anthropic, their gross margins on inference went from
you know, well below 40% to north of 60
right- Yeah.
.
by the end of the year.
Um, the- these- the margins aren't- Yeah.
.
expanding there despite, hey, more Chinese open-source models than ever.
Yeah.
Hey, OpenAI's competitive.
Hey, Google's competitive.
Hey, xGrok is now competitive, right?
All these- all these companies are now competitive.
And yet despite this, the margins have expanded at the model layer significantly.
Yeah.
Um, h- h- how do you think about the.
..
It's a gr- it's a great question.
I mean, it- it- I- I think the- the one thing is perhaps a few years ago people were saying
"Oh, I can just wrap a model and build a successful company.
" Uh, and that, I think, is- probably gotten debunked just because the model capabilities
uh.
..
and the tools used in particular.
But the interesting thing is there's no- like when I look at Office 365
let's take even this little thing we built called Excel Agent.
It's interesting, right?
Excel Agent is not a UI-level wrapper.
It's actually a model that is in the middle tier.
Uh, in this case, because we have all the IP from the- the GPT family
uh, we are taking that and putting it into the core middle tier of the Office system to both teach it what it means to natively understand Excel
everything in it.
So it's not just, hey, I just have a pixel-level understanding.
I have a n- full understanding of all the native artifacts of Excel
uh, both when I see it- like because if you think about it
if I'm going to give it some reasoning task
right, I need to even fix the reasoning mistakes I make.
And so that means I need to both not just see the pixels.
I need to be able to see, oh
I got that formula wrong, and I need to understand that.
And then- so to some degree, that's all being done not at the UI wrapper level with some prompt
but it's being done in the middle tier by teaching it all the tools of Excel
right?
So I'm giving it even- essentially a markdown to teach it the skills of what it means to be a sophisticated Excel user.
So it's a weird thing that- it goes back a little bit to AI brain
right?
Which is you're building not just Excel.
You are now business logic in its traditional sense.
You're taking the Excel business logic in the traditional sense and wrapping essentially a cognitive layer to it using this model which knows how to use the tool.
Mm-hmm.
So in some sense, Excel will come with an analyst bundled in and with all the tools used.
That's the type of stuff that'll get built by everybody.
So even for the model companies, they're allowed to compete
right?
So if they price stuff high, uh
guess what?
If I'm a builder of a tool like this
I'll substitute you.
I may use you for a while, and so as long as there's competition
there's always a winner-take-all thing, right?
If there's going to be one model that is better than everybody else with massive distance
yes, that's a winner take all.
As long as there's gonna be competition where there's multiple models
just like hyperscale competition, and there's an open-source check
uh, there is enough room here, uh
to go build value on top of models.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, but at Microsoft, the way I look at it and say is
uh, we are going to be in the hyperscale business which will support multiple models.
We will have access to OpenAI models for
uh, uh, you know, seven more years which we will innovate on top of
so royalty f- uh, essentially, I think of ourselves as having a frontier-class model
uh, that we can use and innovate on with full
uh, flexibility.
And we'll build our own models, uh
with MAI, um, and- and so we will always have a model level.
And then we'll build these, whether it's in security
whether it's in knowledge work, whether it's in coding
or in signs, we will build our own application scaffolding- Mm-hmm.
.
..
which will be model-forward, right?
Mm-hmm.
It won't be a wrapper on a model
but the model will be wrapped into, uh
the application.
I have so many questions about th- the other things you mentioned.
But before we move on to those topics
um, I still wonder whether this is
like, not forward-looking on AI capabilities, where you're imagining models like they exist today
where, yeah, I can- you have this
like- it takes a screenshot of your screen
but it can't, like, look inside each cell and what the formula is.
And I think the better m- mental model here is
like, look, a human- just imagine that these models actually will be able to actually use a computer as well as a human.
100%, yeah.
And a human knowledge worker who is using Excel can look into the formulas
can, you know, use alternative software, can migrate data between Office 365 and another piece of software if the migration is necessary
et cetera.
So what is- That's kind of what I'm saying.
So what- what- But if that's the case
then the integration with Excel doesn't matter that much- No
no, no.
because then- And- and don't worry about the Excel integration.
After all, Excel was built as a tool for analysts.
Great.
So whoever is this AI that is an analyst should have tools that they can use.
Uh, that they have a computer, right?
That- that- just the way a human can use a computer
that's their tool.
The- the- the- the tool is the computer.
Right.
Right, so that- so all I'm saying is I'm building an analyst as- as essentially an AI agent
uh, which happens to come with a- an a priori knowledge of how to use all of these analytical tools.
Uh, but is- is it something- well
maybe just- just to make sure we're talking about the same thing
um, is it a thing that a hu- like me using Excel as a podcaster.
No, no, no, no.
I'm not proficient in Excel, but like.
..
It'll be an auton- a completely autonomous.
So just imagine I work- like so we should now maybe sort of lay out how I think the future of the company is
right?
Yeah.
Uh, the future of the company would be the tools business which I have a computer.
I use Excel.
And in fact, in the future, I'll even have a copilot.
Right.
Uh, and that copilot will also have agents
right?
That still I am- I- you know, it's still me steering everything.
Yeah.
And everything is coming back.
So that's kind of one world.
Yeah.
Then the second world is the company just literally provisions a computing resource for an AI agent.
And that is working fully autonomously.
Yeah.
That fully autonomous agent will have essentially embodied set of those same tools- Right.
.
..
uh, that are available to it, right?
So this AI tool that comes in also has not just a raw computer
uh, because it's gonna be more token-efficient to use tools to get stuff done.
In fact, I kinda look at it and say our business
which today is an end-user tools business, will become essentially an infrastructure business in support of agents doing work.
Okay.
..
. is another way to think about it
right?
So if one of the things that you'll see us do .
..
In, in, in fact, like, all the stuff we built underneath the M365 still is going to be very relevant.
Uh, you need some place to store it
some place to do archival, some place to do discovery
some place to manage all of these activities
e- even if you're an AI agent.
Mm-hmm.
So that's .
..
So it's kind of a new infrastructure.
S- so just to make sure I understand
you're saying, like, look, theoretically, a future AI that has actual computer use
which is .
..
all these companies are working on, model companies are working on right now
could use, even if it's not partnered with Microsoft or under our umbrella
could use Microsoft software.
But you're saying we're gonna give them .
..
if, if you're working with our infrastructure
we're gonna give you, like, lower-level access that makes it more efficient for you to do the same things you could have otherwise done anyways.
100%.
I mean, so the entire thing in
in fact, the way th- you know
like, what happened is we had servers
then there was virtualization, and then we had many more servers.
So that's another way to think about this
which is, hey, don't think of this .
..
the tool as the end thing.
What is the entire substrate underneath that tool that humans use?
And that entire substrate is the bootstrap for the AI agent as well because the AI agent needs a computer.
That's kind of one.
Like, you know, so in fact, one of the fascinating things we are seeing a significant amount of growth is all these guys who are doing these o- office artifacts and
and what have you as autonomous agents and so on want to provision Windows 365
right?
They really want to be able to provision a computer for these agents.
Uh, and so .
..
absolutely, and that's where I think we're gonna have essentially an end user computing infrastructure business
which I think is going to just keep growing because guess what?
It's going to grow faster than the number of users.
So in fact, that's kind of one of the other questions people ask me
is, "Hey, what happens to the per-user business?
" At least the early signs may be the way to think about the per-user business is not just per user
it's per agent, and if you sort of say it's per user and per agent
the key is what's the stuff to provision for every agent?
A computer?
Um, a set of security things around it?
An identity around it?
Uh, and all those things, our observability and so on
are the management layers, and that's, I think
all going to get baked into that.
The way to frame it, at least the way I currently think about it
and I'd like to hear your, you know
your view, is that, uh, these model companies are all building environments to- Yep.
.
..
train their models to use Excel- Yep.
.
..
or Amazon shopping or whatever, whatever it is
book flights.
Um, but at the same time, they're also training these models to do migration from .
..
because that, that is probably the most immediate
uh, valuable thing, right?
Converting mainframe-based systems to- Yep.
.
..
standard cloud systems, converting, um, Excel databases into real databases- Yep.
.
uh, with SQL.
Yep.
Right?
Or, or converting, um, you know
w- what is done in Word and Excel to something that is more programmatic and more efficient in a classical sense- Absolutely.
.
that can actually be done by humans as well.
It's just not cost-effective for the software developer to do that.
That seems to be what everyone is going to do with AI for the next
you know, few years at least to massively drive value.
Um, h- h- how does Microsoft fit into that if the models can utilize the tools themselves to migrate to something?
And yes, Microsoft has, you know, a leadership position in databases and in storage and
and in all these other categories, but the use of
say, a office ecosystem is going to be significantly less just like potentially the use of a mainframe ecosystem could be potentially less.
Now mainframes have grown for the last two decades actually
even though no one talks about them anymore.
They've still grown.
100%.
I agree with that.
How does that, how does that flow forward?
Yeah.
I mean, at the end of the day
this is not about sort of, hey
um, there is going to be a significant amount of time where there's going to be a hybrid world
right?
Because people are gonna be using the tools that are gonna be working with agents that have to use tools
and by the way, they have to communicate with each other.
What's the artifact to generate that then a human needs to see?
So, like, all of these things will be real considerations in any place.
So the outputs, inputs.
So I don't think it'll just be about how I migrate it off
right?
But the bottom line is I have to live in this hybrid world.
So let .
..
but that doesn't fully answer your question because there can be a real new efficient frontier where I stress agents working with agents
uh, and completely optimizing.
Mm-hmm.
And even when agents are working with agents
what are the primitives that are needed?
Uh, do you need a storage system?
Uh, does that storage system need to have e-discovery?
Does that e-discover- uh, do you need to have observability?
Do you need to have an identity system that is going to use multiple models with all having one identity system?
So these are all the core underlying rails we have today for what our office systems or what have you
uh, and that's what I think we will have in the future as well.
You talked about databases, right?
I mean take .
..
you know, man, I would love all of Excel to have a database backend
right?
In fact, I would love for all that to happen immediately.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, and that database is a good database.
I mean, databases in fact will be a big thing that will grow.
Uh, in fact, if I think about all of the office artifacts
uh, being structured better, the ability to do the joins between structured and unstructured better because of the agenting
well, that'll grow the underlying what is infrastructure business.
It happens the consumption of that is all being driven by agents.
You could say all that is just in time generated software by a model company.
That could also be true.
If we .
..
we will be one such model company too.
Uh, and so we will build in .
..
so the competition could be, uh, that we will build a model plus all the infrastructure and provision it
and then there will be competition between a bunch of those folks who can do that.
Hmm.
Um, I guess speaking of model companies
you say, okay, we will also be one of the .
..
not only we'll have the infrastructure, we'll have the model itself.
Right now, Microsoft AI's most recent model that was released two months ago is 36 in Chatbot Arena and there's a q- I mean
you obviously have the IP rights to OpenAI
so there's a question of .
..
. first, to the extent you agree w- that l- it seems to be behind
why is that the case?
Especially given the fact that you could, um
you theoretically have the right to just, like
fork OpenAI's mono repo or distill on their models.
Um, y- yeah, es- especially if it's a big part of your strategy that we need to have a leading model company.
Yeah, I mean, f- so first of all
we are g- absolutely going to use the OpenAI models
uh, to the maximum, uh, across all of our products
right?
I mean, that's, I think, the core thing that we're gonna continue to do all the way for the next seven years.
Uh, and not just use it, uh
but then add value to it.
That's kinda w- where the analyst and this Excel agent
and these are all things that we will do where
you know, we'll do r- you know
RL fine-tuning, we'll do some mid-training runs on top of a GPT family where we have unique data assets and build capability.
Um, the MAI model, the way I think we're gonna think about it is the
the good news here, in fact, with the new agreement
is even we can be very, very clear that we're gonna build a world-class superintelligence team and go after it with high ambition.
But th- at the same time, we're also gonna use this time to be smart about how to use both these things.
So that means we will, on one end
be very product-focused or, on the other end
be very research-focused.
In other words, uh, because we have access
aha, to the GPT family, the last thing I don't want to do is use my flops in a way that is just duplicative and doesn't add much value.
So I want to be able to take
uh, the flops that we use to generate a GPT family and maximize its value while my MAI flops are being used for.
..
Let's take the image model that we launched
which I think this launched, uh, is a number nine in the
uh, image arena.
You know, we're using it, you know
both for cost optimization.
It's on Copilot, it's in Bing, and we're gonna use that.
We have a, a audio model in Copilot
which really it's got personality and what have you.
We optimized it for our product.
So we will do those.
Even on the LM arena, we started on the text one
I think it was, it debuted at night 13.
And by the way, it was v- it was done only on
whatever, 15,000, uh, H100s?
And so it was a very small model.
And, uh, so it was, again
to prove out, uh, the core capability
the instruction-following and everything else, which b- you know
we wanted to make sure we can match what was state-of-the-art.
And so that shows us, given scaling laws
what we are capable of doing if it gave more flops to it
right?
So the next thing we will do is an omni model where we will take sort of the work we have done in audio
what we have done in image, and what we have done in text.
That'll be the next pit stop on the MAI side.
So when I think about the MAI roadmap
we're gonna build a first-class superintelligence team.
We are gonna continue to drop and do on
in the open some of these models.
They will either be in our products being used because they're going to be latency-friendly
cogs-friendly, or what have you, or they'll have some special capability.
And we will do real research in order to be ready for some next five
six, seven, eight brea- breakthroughs, uh
that are all needed on this march towards superintelligence.
So I think that's.
..
And while exploiting the advantage we have of having the GPT family that we can work on top of as well.
Mm-hmm.
S- say we roll forward seven years, uh
you no longer have access to OpenAI models.
What does one get confidence, or what does Microsoft do to make sure they are leading or have a leading AI lab
right?
Today, you know, it's, it's all OpenAI has developed many of the breakthroughs
whether it be scaling or reasoning, or Google's developed all the breakthroughs like Transformers.
Uh, but, but it- it is also a big talent game
right?
You know, you've seen Meta spend, you know
north of $20 billion on talent, right?
Uh, you've seen Anthropic pr- uh, poach the entire Blueshift reasoning team from Google last year.
You've seen Meta poach a large reasoning and post-training team from Google more recently.
These, these sorts of talent wars are very capital-intensive.
They're the ones that, you know, arguably
you know, if you're spending $100 billion on infrastructure
you should also spend, you know, X amount of money on
on the people using the infrastructure so that they're more efficiently making these new breakthroughs.
What, what confidence can one get that
you know, hey, Microsoft will have a team that's world-class that can make these breakthroughs?
And, you know, once you decide to turn on the money faucet
you know, you're, you're being a bit capital-efficient right now
which is, which is smart, it seems
uh, to not waste money d- doing duplicative work.
But once you decide you need to, you know
how, how can one say, "Oh, yeah
now you can shoot up to, we're the top five model"?
Well, look, I mean, at the e- eh
the end of the day, we are gonna build a world-class team
and we, uh, already have a world-class team that's beginning to be sort of a sample
right?
With Moustafa coming in, we have Karen
we have Amar Subramanian who did a l- lot of the post-training at Gemini
Tufai, who's at Microsoft, Nando, who did a lot of the multimedia s- work at DeepMind is there.
And so we're gonna build a world-class team.
And in fact, I think later this week
even Moustafa published some, you know, a little more clarity on what our lab is going to go do.
Um, I think the thing that I want
uh, the world to know, perhaps, uh
is we are gonna build the infrastructure that'll support multiple models.
Uh, you know, uh, we.
..
Because from a hyperscale perspective, we wanna build the most scaled infrastructure fleet that's capable of supporting all the models the world needs
whether it's from open source or whether it's obviously from OpenAI and others.
And so that's kinda one job.
..
. second is in our own model capability
we will absolutely use the OpenAI model in our products
and we'll start building our own models.
And we may, like in- in GitHub Copilot
Anthropic is used, so we will even have other frontier models that are gonna be wrapped into our products as well.
So, I think that that's kind of how at least each time
at the end of the day, the eval of the product as it meets a particular task or a job is what matters.
And we'll sort of back from there into the vertical integration needed
uh, knowing that as long as you're a service
you know, you're serving the market well with the product
you can always cost optimize.
Mm.
Th- th- there's a question going forward.
So right now, we have models that have this distinction between training an inference
and one could argue that there's, like
a s- smaller and smaller difference between the different models.
Um, going forward, if you're really expecting something like human-level intelligence
humans learn on the job.
H- you know, if you think about your last 30 years
wha- what makes Satya tokens so valuable?
It's the last 30 years of wisdom and experience you've gained at Microsoft.
Um, and w- we will eventually have models
if they get to human level, which will have this ability to continuously learn on the job
and that will drive so much value to the model company that is ahead
at least in my view.
Because you have copies of one model broadly deployed through the economy
learning how to do every single job, and unlike humans
they can amalgamate their learnings to that model.
So, there's this sort of continuous learning sort of exponential feedback loop
um, which almost looks like a sort of intelligence explosion.
Uh, if that happens and Microsoft isn't the leading model company by that time
doesn't then the s- uh, you know
you were saying, well, we substitute one model for another
et cetera, matter less, 'cause it's just
like, this one model knows how to do every single job of the economy.
The other long tail don't.
Yeah.
No, I think that your point about if there's one model that is the only model that's most broadly deployed in the world and it sees all the data and it has continuous learning- Yeah.
.
that's game, set, match- Yeah.
and, you know, you're such sharp, right?
I mean, the- the reality, at least I see
um, is the world, even today, for all the dominance of any one model
it's not the case.
Um, a- is t- take any.
..
take coding.
There's multiple models.
In fact, every day it's less the case
where there is not one model that is getting deployed broadly.
In fact, there's multiple models that are getting deployed.
It's kind of like databases, right?
You- it's always the thing is, like
hey, can one database be the one that just is used everywhere?
Except it's not.
Uh, there are multiple types of databases that are getting deployed
uh, for different use cases.
So, I think that there is going to be some network effects of continual learning or data
y- you know, I'll call liquidity, that any one model has.
Uh, is it gonna happen in all domains?
I don't think so.
Is it gonna happen in all GOs?
Is it gonna happen in all segments?
I don't think so.
It'll happen in all categories at the same time?
So therefore, I feel like the design space is so large
uh, that there's plenty of opportunity.
But your fundamental point is having a capability which is at the infrastructure layer
model layer, and at the scaffolding layer
and then to be able to compose these things not just as a vertical stack
but to be able to compose each thing for what its purpose is
right?
You can't build an infrastructure that's optimized for one model.
If you do that, what if you go fall behind?
In fact, all the infrastructure you built will be a waste
right?
You kind of need to build an infrastructure that's capable of supporting multiple sort of families and lineages of models.
Otherwise, the capital you put in, which is optimized for one model architecture
you- that means you're one tweak away from some MOE-like breakthrough that happens with somebody else and your entire network topology goes out of the window.
Then that's a scary thing, right?
So therefore, you kind of want the infrastructure to support whatever may come
in fact, in your own model family and other model families
and you got to be open.
If you're- if you're serious about the hyperscale business
you got to be serious about that, right?
Um, if you're serious about being a model company
you've got to basically say, "Hey, what are the ways people can actually do things on top of the model so that I can have an ISV ecosystem?
" Unless I'm thinking I'll own every category.
That just can't be.
Then- then you won't have an API business
and that by definition will mean you'll never be
uh, a platform company that's gonna be successfully deployed everywhere
right?
So therefore, the industry structure is s- such that it will
uh, really force people to specialize, and that.
..
in that specialization, a company like Microsoft should compete in each layer by its merits
uh, but not think that this is all about all a road to game
set, match where I just compose vertically all these layers.
That's- that just doesn't happen.
So, according to Dylan's numbers, there's gonna be half a trillion in AI CapEx next year alone
and labs are already spending billions of dollars to snag top researcher talent.
But none of that matters if there's not enough high quality data to train on.
Without the right data, even the most advanced infrastructure and world-class talent won't translate into end value for the user.
That's where Labobox comes in.
Labobox produces high quality data at massive scale
powering any capability that you want your model to have.
It doesn't matter whether you need a coding agent that needs detailed feedback on multi-hour trajectories or a robotics model that needs thousands of samples on everyday tasks
or a voice agent that can also perform real world actions for the user
like booking them a flight.
To be clear, this isn't just off-the-shelf data.
Labobox can design and launch a custom production scale data pipeline in 48 hours
and they can get you tens of thousands of targeted examples in weeks.
Reach out at labobox.
com/dwarkesh.
All right, back to Satya.
So, last year, Microsoft was o- on path to be the largest infrastructure provider
uh, by far.
You were the earliest in '23, so you
you went out there, you acquired all the resources in terms of leasing data centers
starting construction, securing power, everything.
You guys were on pace to beat Amazon in '26 or '27.
Um, but certainly by '28, you were gonna beat them.
Um, since then, you, you know
in, let's call it the second half of last year
Microsoft did this big pause, right, where they let go of a bunch of leasing sites that they were gonna take
which then Google, Meta, um, Amazon in some cases
Oracle, uh, took these sites.
We're sitting in one of the largest data centers in the world
so obviously it's not everything.
You guys are expanding like crazy, uh
but there are sites that you just stopped working on.
Hmm.
Wh- why, why did you do this
right?
Yeah, I mean, the fundamental thing we .
..
This goes back a little bit to what is the hyperscale business all about
right?
Which is one of the key decisions we made was that if you're gonna build out Azure to be fantastic for all sort of stages of AI
uh, from training to mid-training, to data gen
to inference, we just need fungibility, uh
of the fleet.
Um, and, and so that entire thing caused us not to basically go build a
a whole lot of capacity with a particular set of generations.
Uh, because the other thing that you got to realize is having actually for up to now 10Xed every 18 months enough training capacity for the various OpenAI models
uh, we realized that, um, the key is to stay on that path.
But the more important thing is to actually have a balance to not just train
but to be able to serve these models all around the world.
Because at the end of the day, the rate of monetization is what then will allow us to even keep
uh, funding.
And then the infrastructure was going to need us to support
as I said, multiple models and what have you.
So once we said that that's the case
since then, we just course corrected to where .
..
the path we are on, right?
If I look at the path we are on is we are doing a lot more starts now.
Uh, we are also buying up as managed capacity as we can
whether it's to build, whether it's to lease
or even GPUs as a service.
But we are building it for where we see the demand
uh, and the serving needs and our training needs.
And we didn't want to just be a host stop for one company
uh, and have just a massive book of business with one customer.
That, that's not a business, right?
That is sort of, uh, you know
you should be vertically integrated with that company.
Yeah.
Uh, and so given the, the thing that OpenAI was going to be a successful independent company
which is fantastic, right?
I think it makes sense, right?
And even Meta may use third-party capacity, but ultimately they're all going to be first party
uh, for anyone who has large scale
they'll be, you know, they'll be a hyperscaler on their own.
And so to me, was to build out a hyperscale fleet and our own research compute.
Uh, and that's what the adjustment was.
Um, you know, and then, and so I feel very
very good.
Oh, by the way, the other thing is I didn't want to get stuck with massive scale of one generation.
I mean, we just saw the, the GB200s.
I mean, the GB300s are coming, right?
And by the time I get to Vera Rubin
Vera Rubin Ultra, guess what?
The data center is gonna look very different because the power per rack
power per row is gonna be so different.
Uh, the cooling requirements are gonna be so different.
And that, that means I don't want to just go build out like a whole number of gigawatts that are only for a one generation
one family.
And so I think the pacing matters and the fungibility and the location matters.
Uh, the workload diversity matters, customer diversity matters
and that's what we're building towards.
The other thing that we've learned a lot is
um, every AI workload does require not only the AI accelerator
but it requires a whole lot of other things
right?
And in fact, a lot of the margin structure for us will be in those other things.
And so therefore, we want to build out Azure as being fantastic for the long tail of the workloads because that's the hyperscale business while knowing that we've got to be super competitive starting with the bare metal for the highest end training.
And, but that can't crowd out the rest of the business
right?
Because we're not in the business of just doing five contracts with five customers
being their bare metal service.
That's not a, a Microsoft business.
That may be a business for someone else
and that's a good thing.
What we have said is we are in the hyperscale business
which is at the end of the day
a long tail business, uh, for AI workloads.
And in order to do that, we will have some leading bare metal as a service capabilities for a set of models
including our own.
Uh, and that I think is the balance you see.
The, another sort of question that comes around this whole fungibility topic is
okay, it's not where you want it
right?
You would rather have it in a good population center like Atlanta as you're- we're here.
Um, there, there's, there's also the question of like
well, how much does that matter if as the horizon of AI tasks grows?
Well, actually- It's a great question.
.
..
you know, 30 seconds for a reasoning prompt or
you know, 30 minutes for a deep research or
you know, it's gonna be hours for software agents at some point
um, and days and so on and so forth
the time to human interaction.
Why does it matter if it's- Yeah.
.
if it's- It's a great, it's a great question.
..
uh, location A, B, or C?
That's exactly right.
So in fact, that's one of the other reasons why we want to think about like
hey, what does an Azure region look like and what is the
in fact the networking between Azure regions?
So this is where, uh, I think as the model capabilities evolve
and I think the usage of these tokens
whether it's synchronously or asynchronously evolves, and in fact you don't want to be out of position
right?
Then on top of that, by the way
what are the data residency laws, right?
What, where do I .
..
Like, I mean, the entire EU thing
uh, for us where we literally had to create an EU data boundary
uh, basically meant that you can't just round-trip a call to wherever
even if it's asynchronous.
And so therefore you need to have maybe regional things that are high density and then the power costs and so on.
But you're 100% right in bringing up that the topology as we build out
uh, will have to evolve, one, for tokens per dollar of a watt.
Uh, what are the economics?
So, overlay that with what is the usage pattern
um, usage pattern in terms of synchronous
asynchronous, but also what is the compute storage because the latencies may matter for certain things.
Uh, the storage better be there.
If I have a Cosmos DB close to this for session data or even for an autonomous thing
then that also has to be somewhere close to it
and so on.
So I think that all of those considerations is what will shape
uh, the hyperscale business.
Mm-hmm.
You know, prior to the pause, you were- you were- you're
you know, versus, you know, what we had forecasted for you by '28
you were going to be, like, 12
13 gigawatts.
Yeah.
And now we're at, you know, nine and a half or so
right?
But, you know, something that's even more relevant
right, and it's- it's, you know, I just want you to
like, more concretely state that this is the business you don't want to be in.
But, like, Oracle's going from like one-fifth your size to bigger than you by end of 2027 and while it's not a Microsoft level quality of return on invested capital
right?
They're still making 35% gross margins, right?
So sort of the question is like does it- is it- isn't it- is it- is it
you know, hey, it's not Microsoft's business to maybe do this
but you've created a hyperscaler now- Yeah.
.
by refusing this business, by giving away the right of- Look
I- I- .
..
first refusal, et cetera.
I'm not.
..
First of all, I don't, I don't want to take away anything from the success Oracle has had- Yeah.
.
..
uh, in building their business, and I wish them well.
And so the thing that I think I've answered for you is
it didn't make sense for us, uh
to go be a host, uh, for one model company
uh, with limited time horizon RPO.
Let's- Yeah.
Let's just put it that way, right?
The thing that you have to think through is not what you do in the next five years
but what do you do for the next 50?
Uh, because that's kind of what I- we made our set of decisions
um, I feel very good about our OpenAI partnership and what we're doing.
We have a decent book, book of business.
We wish them a lot of success.
In fact, we are buyers even of Oracle capacity
we wish them- Yep.
.
success.
But, you know, at this point, I think the industrial logic for what we are trying to do is pretty clear
which is, it's not about, like, chasing.
..
I mean, first of all, I track
by the way, your, uh, things
whe- whether it's the AWS or the Google and ours
which I think is super useful.
Uh, but doesn't mean I got to chase those.
Yeah.
Uh, I have to chase them for not just
uh, the gross margin that they may represent in a period of time.
You know, does Mi- what, what is this book of business that Microsoft uniquely can go clear which makes sense for us to clear?
And that's what we'll do.
I, I, I guess I have a question
even stepping back from this, of, okay
I, I take your point that it's a better business to be in
all else equal, to have a long tail of customers you can have higher margin from
right?
That when you're serving bare metal to a few labs.
But then there's a question of, okay
which way is the industry evolving?
And so if we believe we're on the path to smarter and smarter AIs
then why isn't the shape of the industry that the OpenAIs and Anthropics and DeepMinds are the platform which the long tail of enterprises are actually doing business with
where they need bare metal, but, like
they are the platform?
What is the long tail that is directly using Azure
um, 'cause, you know, you, you want to use the general cognitive core- But those models are gonna be available on Azure
right?
So any workload that says, "Hey, I want to use
um, you know, some open source model and an OpenAI model
" like, I mean, if you go to Azure Foundry today
you have all these models that you can provision by PTUs
get a Cosmos DB, get a SQL DB
get some storage, get some compute.
That's what a real workload looks like.
A real workload is not just, "Hey
I called in an API call to a model.
" A real workload needs all of these things to go build an app
uh, or instantiate an application.
In fact, the model companies need that
right, to build anything.
It's just not like, "I have a token factory.
" I have to have all of these things.
That's the hyperscale business.
Uh, and it's not even any one model
but all these models.
And so if you want Grok plus, let's say
uh, OpenAI plus an open source model
come to Azure Foundry, provision them, build your application
here is a database.
That's kind of what the business is.
Uh, you, there is a separate business called just selling raw bare metal services to model companies and that's the argument about how much of that business you want to be in and not be in and what is that.
..
It's a very different segment of the business
which, uh, we are in and we also have limits to how much of it is going to crowd out the rest of it.
Uh, but that's kind of at least the way I look at it.
So, so there's, there's sort of two questions here
right?
Like, why, why couldn't you just do both is one
and then the other one is, um
given, you know, our, our estimates on what your capacity is in 2028 is three and a half gigawatts lower
sure, you could have dedicated that to OpenAI training and inference capacity
but you could have also dedicated that to
hey, th- this three and a half gigawatts is actually just running Azure
it's running Microsoft 365, it's running GitHub Copilot.
It doesn't actually.
..
I could have built it and not given it to OpenAI.
Or, or I may want to build it in a different location.
I may want to build it in UAE
I may want to build it in India
I may want to build it in Europe
right?
So one of the other things is, as I said
like, where we have real capacity constraints right now are
given the regulatory needs and the data sovereignty needs
we got to build all over the world.
Uh, it's, first of all, state-side capacity is super important and we're going to build everything.
But one of the things is, when I look out to 2030
uh, I have a sort of a global view of what is Microsoft shape of business by first party and third party.
Third party segmented by the Frontier labs and how much they want versus the inference capacity we want to build for multiple models
um, and our own research compute needs
right?
So that's all what's going into my calculus versus saying
"Hey," uh, I think you're rightfully pointing out the pause
but the pause was not done because we said
"Oh my God, we don't want to build that.
" We realized that, oh, we want to build what we want to build slightly differently
uh, by both workload type as well as geo type and timing as well.
Like, we'll keep ramping up our gigawatts and the question is
at what pace and in what location and in what sort of
how do I write even the Moore's Law on it
right?
Yep.
Which is, do I really want to overbuild three and a half in '27 or do I want to spread that in '27
'28, knowing even.
..
One of the biggest learnings we had even with NVIDIA is their pace increased
uh, in terms of their model mi- I mean
their migrations.
So that was a-.
..
a big factor.
I didn't want to go get stuck for four years
five years of depreciation on one, uh
generation.
And I wanted to just basically buy like
in fact, Jensen's a- advice to me was two things.
One is, "Hey, get on the speed of light execution.
" That's why I think even the execution in this Atlanta data center
I mean, like, in 90 days, right?
Right, between when we get it and do a handoff to a real workload
that's sort of real speed of light execution on their front.
And so I wanted to get good on that.
And then that way, then I'm building this each generation and scaling.
Uh, and then every five years, then you have a much more balanced.
..
So it becomes really literally like a flow
uh, for a n- large-scale industrial operation like this
where you suddenly are not lopsided, where you built up a lot in one time and then you take a ma- massive hiatus because you're stuck with all this
to your point, in one location, which may be great for training
may not be great for inference.
Because I can't serve even if it, like
is all asynchronous, but Europe ain't gonna let me round trip to U- Texas.
So that's all of the things.
How do I rationalize this statement with what you've done over the last few weeks?
You've announced deals with Iris Energy, um
with Nebious, um, and Lambda Labs, and there's a few more coming as well.
Uh, you're, you're going out there and securing capacity that you're renting from the neo-clouds
um, rather than having built it yourself.
What was the, what was- I think it's f- it's fine for us because we now have it
you know, when you have line of sight to demand
which can be so where people are building it
it's great.
In fact, we'll even have, I would say
you know, we will take leases, we will take build-to-suit
we'll take even GPU-as-a-service where we don't have capacity
but we need capacity and someone else has that.
Uh, and by the way, I would even sort of welcome every neo-cloud to just be part of our marketplace.
Uh, because again, g- guess what?
If they, if they go bring their capacity into our marketplace
that customer who comes through Azure will use the neo-cloud
which is a great win for them, and we'll use compute storage databases
all the rest from Azure.
So I'm not at all thinking of this as just a
you know, "Hey, I should just go gobble up all of that myself.
" Hmm.
Um, uh, so you mentioned the co- how
the, you know, you're depreciating this asset that's five
six years, and this is the majority of the
you know, 75% of the TCO of a data center
and Jensen is taking a 75% margin on that.
So what all the hyperscalers are trying to do is develop their own accelerator so that they can reduce this overwhelming cost for
um, uh, equipment to increase their margins.
Yeah.
And then, and then like, you know
when you look at where they are, right?
Google's way ahead of everyone else, right?
They've been doing it for the longest.
They're gonna make something like five to seven million chips
right?
Of their own TPUs.
You look at Amazon, they're trying to make three to five million.
Uh, but when we look at what
you know, Microsoft is, is ordering of their own chips
it's, it's, it's way below that number.
Um, you've had a program for just as long
what's going on with your internal chips?
Yeah.
That's a good question.
So, so the couple of things, one is the thing that is the biggest competitor for any new accelerator is kind of even the previous generation of NVIDIA
right?
I mean, in a fleet, what I'm going to look at is the overall TCO.
So the bar I have even for our own
and which by the way, you know
just looking at the data for Maia 200
which looks great, um, e- e- except that one of the things that we learned even on the compute side
right?
Which is we had a lot of Intel
then we introduced AMD, and then we introduced Cobalt.
And so that's kind of how we scaled it.
And so we have good, um, sort of existence proof of at least in core compute on how to build your own silicon and then manage a fleet where all three are at play in some balance.
Uh, because by the way, even Google's buying NVIDIA and so is
uh, Amazon.
And it makes sense because NVIDIA is innovating and it's the general-purpose thing.
All models run on it, uh, and customer demand is there
because if you build your own vertical thing
you better have your own model, uh
which is, you know, either going to use it for training or inference
and you have to generate your own demand for it or subsidize the demand for it.
So therefore, you want to, uh, make sure
um, you scale it appropriately.
So the way we are going to go do it is
um, have a closed loop between our own MAI models and our silicon because I feel like that's the re- that
that's what gives you the birthright to really do your own silicon
right?
Where you literally have, uh, designed the microarchitecture with what you're doing
and then you keep pace with your own models.
Um, in our case, the good, the good news here is OpenAI has a program
uh, which we have access to.
Um, and so therefore, to think that Microsoft is not going to have something that's sca- What level of access do you have to that?
All of it.
You just get the IP for all of that?
Yeah, yeah.
So the only IP you don't have is a consumer hardware?
That's it.
Oh, wow.
Okay.
Yeah.
Interesting.
Oh, and by the way, we gave them a
a bunch of IP as well to bootstrap them
right?
So this is one of the reasons why they had a mass.
..
Because we built all these supercomputers together, uh
rebuilt it for them, and they, uh
benefited from it, rightfully so.
And, uh, and now as they innovate even at the system level
we get access to all of it.
Uh, and, uh, we first wants to in- e- want to instantiate what they build
uh, for them.
Uh, but then we'll extend it.
And so to think that we don't have.
..
And so if anything, the way I
I think about to your question is,  uh
Microsoft wants to be a fantastic, I'll call it
speed of light execution partner for NVIDIA, because quite frankly
that fleet, uh, is life itself.
I'm not worried about.
..
I mean, obviously, Jensen's doing super well with his margins
but the TCO has many dimensions to it
and I want to be great at that TCO.
Uh, on top of that, I want to be able to sort of really work with the OpenAI lineage
uh, and the MAI lineage, and the system design knowing that we have the IP rights on both ends.
Hmm.
Um, uh, sp- speaking of rights, one thing
you know, you had an interview a couple of days ago
uh, where you said that we have rights to the
the, the new agreement you made with OpenAI
you have rights to, the exclusivity to-.
..
the stateless API calls that OpenAI makes.
And we were sort of confused about if there's any state whatsoever.
I mean, you were just mentioning a second ago that all these complicated workloads that are coming up are gonna require memory and databases and storage and so forth.
And is that now not stateless?
Or ChatGPT is storing stuff, run sessions- No
but that's the reason why.
So the, the thing, the business, the strategic decision we made
and also accommodating for the flexibility OpenAI needed in order to be able to procure compute for.
..
Essentially, think of O- OpenAI having, um
a PasS business and a SaaS business.
SaaS business is ChatGPT, their PasS business is their API.
Yeah.
That API is Azure-exclusive.
The SaaS business, they can run it anywhere.
And they can partner with anyone they want to to build SaaS products?
They, so if they want a partner
and this partner wants to use a s- a stateless API
then Azure is the place where they can get the stateless API.
I- it seems like there's a way for them to make you
you, you know, build the product together and
and it's a stateful thing.
No, even that, they'll have to come to Azure.
Okay.
So if it is any partner.
..
And so, so fundamentally, you know, so l- again
this is done in the spirit of, what is it that we valued as part of our partnership?
And we made sure while at the same time we were good partners to OpenAI
given all the flexibility they need.
So, so for example, Salesforce wants to integrate OpenAI.
It's not through an API.
They actually work together, train a model together
deploy it on, let's say, Amazon now.
Is that, is that allowed?
Or, uh, or do they have to use your- No
for any custom agreement like that, they will have to come run it.
There, there are some few exceptions to US government and so on that we made
but other than that, they'll have to come to Azure.
So as Satya explained, as AI agents get more capable
you're gonna need more and more observability into what they're doing.
You're gonna need to catch them when they're making mistakes
you're gonna need high-level summaries of what they're doing
and you're gonna need a picture of how everything that they're doing fits together.
This is exactly what CodeRabbit provides.
You just make a normal pull request and CodeRabbit automatically reviews the PR.
It generates a summary of changes so you can understand exactly what the PR's author was intending
and it uses the context from your full code base to provide line-by-line feedback on how things could be improved.
This is helpful whether you're viewing a PR from a coworker or an agent.
In either case, CodeRabbit will write up its thoughts and flag any issues so that your teammate or your agent can go fix them.
I've noticed that when I'm coding with agents
CodeRabbit catches a lot of mistakes that the models make by default.
For example, the models have a bad habit of using old versions of libraries.
So in one session, I watched CodeRabbit catch a call to a
an old model, figure out what the new version was
and then suggest that improvement.
Go to coderabbit.
ai/thwarkash to learn more.
Stepping back, a question I have is
you know, when we were t- uh
w- walking back and forth, uh, at the factory
one of the things you were talking about is
you know, uh, Microsoft, you can think of it as a software business
but now it's really becoming an industrial business.
Uh, there's all this capex, there's all this construction.
And if you just look over the last two y- t- um
two years, your sort of capex has
like, tripled.
And maybe you extrapolate that forward, it just actually just becomes this huge industrial
uh, explosion.
U- Other hyperscalers are taking loans, right?
Meta's, Meta's done a $20 billion loan at Louisiana.
They've taken, they've done a corporate loan.
It s- seems clear everyone's free cash flow is going to zero.
Um, which is, which is, I'm sure Amy is
like, gonna beat you up for-  .
..
for even, if you even try to do that.
But, like, uh, what- what- what's happening?
I mean, I think, uh, I think the structural change
um, is what you're referencing, which I think is massive
right?
Which is, I, I describe it as we are now a
a capital-intensive business and a knowledge-intensive business.
And in fact, we have to use our knowledge to increase the ROIC on the capital spent
right?
Because that's gonna.
..
You know, look, the hardware guys have done a great job
uh, of marketing the Moore's Law, which I think is unbelievable and it's great.
But if you even look, I think some of the stats I even did in my earnings call
which is for a given GPT family, right?
Uh, the improvement, software improvements of really throughput in terms of tokens per dollar per watt that we're able to get
uh, y- you know, quarter over quarter
year over year, is massive.
Uh, right?
So it's 5X, 10X, maybe 40X in some of these cases
right?
Just because how you can optimize.
That's s- sort of knowledge intense- Yeah.
.
..
intensity coming to bring out capital efficiency.
So that, at, at some level, the
that's what we have to master.
What does it mean?
Like, so many people ask me, "What is the difference between
uh, you know, a classic, old-time host
uh, and a hyperscaler?
" It is software.
So yes, it is capital-intensive, but as long as you have systems
know-how, software capability to optimize by workload
by fleet.
That's why I think when, when we say fungibility
there's so much software in it.
It's just not about the fleet, right?
It's kind of the ability to evict a workload
uh, you know, and then schedule another workload.
Can I, like, manage the, that algorithm of scheduling around?
Uh, that is the type of stuff that we have to be world-class at.
And so yes, so I think we'll still remain a software company.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, but yes, this is a different business.
Um, and we're gonna manage.
Look, I think at the end of the day
uh, the cash flow that Microsoft has allows us to have
um, both these arms firing on, you know
uh, well.
Mm.
I- it seems like in the short term
you have more sort of, um, credence on things taking a while
being more jagged.
But in the, maybe in the long term
you think, like, the people who say
talk about AGI and ASI are correct.
Like Sam, Sam will be right, but eventually.
Um, and I, I have a broader question about what makes sense for a hyperscaler to do
given that you have to invest massively in this thing which depreciates over five years.
So s- uh, so if you, if you have 20
40 timelines for the kind of thing that somebody like Sam anticipates in three years
um, you know, what- what is a reasonable thing for you to do in that world?
There needs to be an allocation, uh
to I'll call it research compute.
..
Mm-hmm.
. that needs to be done like you did R&D.
Yeah.
Right?
So, that's the best way to even account for it
quite frankly.
We should think of it as just R&D expense.
And you should say, "Hey, what's the research computing or how do you want to scale it?
" Yeah.
Um, and let's even say it's an order of magnitude scale
um, in some period.
Pick your thing.
Yeah.
Is it two years?
Is it 16 months?
What have you, right?
So, that's sort of one piece, which is kind of
that's kind of table stakes.
That's R&D expenses.
And the rest is all demand driven, right?
I mean, ultimately you can, you don't have to build ahead of demand
but you better have a demand, uh
uh, plan, uh, that doesn't go completely off-kilter.
Do you buy.
..
So, these labs are now projecting revenues of 100 billion in '27
'28, uh, and they're projecting, you know
revenue keeps growing at this rate of, like
3X, 2X a year.
So there's lo-.
..
In the marketplace, right, there's all kinds of incentives right now and
and rightfully so, right?
I mean, what, what do you expect an independent lab that is sort of trying to raise money to do
right?
They have to put some numbers out there such that they can actually go raise money so that they can pay their bills for compute- Yeah.
.
and what have you.
And it's, and it's good thing.
I mean, someone's going to take some risk and put it in there
and they've shown traction.
Yeah.
It's not like it's all risk without seeing the fact that they've been performing.
Whether it's OpenAI, whether it's Anthropic, so I feel great about what they've done.
Uh,  and we have massive book of business with these chaps.
Yeah.
So, therefore, uh, that's all good.
But overall, ultimately, there's two simple things.
One is you got to allocate for R&D.
You brought up even talent, you got to sp-.
..
Like, the talent for AI- Yeah.
.
..
is at a premium.
You got to spend there.
You got to spend on compute, so in some sense
researcher to GPU  ratios have to be high.
Uh, that is sort of what it takes to be a leading R&D company in this world
uh, and that's something that needs to scale
um, and you have to have a balance sheet that allows you to scale that long before it's conventional wisdom and so on.
So, that's kind of one thing.
But the other is all about sort of knowing how to forecast.
A- as we look across the world, right
America has dominated many tech stacks, right?
Um, the US owns Windows, right, through Microsoft
which is deployed even in China, right?
That's the main operating system.
Um, of course, there's Linux, which is open source
but, you know, Windows is deployed everywhere in China on personal computers.
Um, you look at, you look at Word
it's, it's deployed everywhere.
You look at all these various technologies, it's deployed everywhere.
The thing that is quite unique and, and
and Microsoft and other companies have grown elsewhere
right?
They've built, they're building data centers in Europe and in India and then
and then all these other, you know
in Southeast Asia and in LATAM and Africa
right?
All of these different places you're building capacity
but this seems quite different, right?
You know, t- today the political aspect of technology
of comput-.
..
You know, you know, the, the US administration didn't care about the dot-com bubble
right?
Um, it seems like the US administration as well as every other administration around the world cares a lot about AI.
And the question is, you know, we've.
..
we're in a sort of a bipolar world
at least with US and China, but Europe and
and India and all these other countries are
are saying, "No, actually, we're going to have sovereign AI as well.
" How does Microsoft navigate, you know, the difference of the '90s where it's like there's one country in the world that matters
right?
It's America.
And we do.
..
Our companies sell everywhere, and therefore Microsoft benefits massively
to a world where it is bipolar, where
hey, Microsoft can't just necessarily have the right to win all of Europe or India or
you know, Singapore.
There's actually sovereign AI efforts.
What, what is your thought process here?
That's a great- How do you think about this?
It's, it's, I think, a, a super
you know, critical, um, piece
which is.
..
Um, I think that the key, key priority for the US tech sector and the US government is to ensure that we not only do leading innovative work
but we also collectively build trust around the world on our tech stack
right?
Because I always say the United States is just an unbelievable place
it's just unique in history, right?
It's 4% of the world's population, 25% of the GDP
and 50% of the market cap, and I think you should think about those ratios and
uh, really,  and reflect on it.
That 50% happens because, quite frankly, the trust the world has in the United States
whether it's its capital markets or whether it's its technology and
and its stewardship of what matters at any given time in terms of leading
uh, sector.
So, if that is broken, uh, then that's not a good day for the United States.
And so, if we start with that
which I think the, you know, President Trump gets
the White House, David Sachs, everyone, uh
really, I think gets it.
Uh, and so therefore, I applaud anything that the United States government and the tech sector jointly does to
quite frankly, for example, put our own capital at risk collectively as an industry in every part of the world
right?
So, I would like, in fact, the USG to take credit for foreign direct investment by American companies all over the world
It's kind of like, uh, least talked about but the best marketing  that the United States should be doing is.
It's not just about all the foreign direct investment coming into the United States
but the most leading sector, which is these AI factories
are all being created all over the world by whom?
By America, uh, and American companies.
And so you start there, and then you even build other agreements around it
which are around their continuity, their legitimate sovereignty concerns around whether it's data residency
whether it's even what happens, um, uh-.
..
uh, for them to have real agency and guarantees
uh, on privacy and so on.
And so the.
..
In fact, our European commitments, I think
are worth reading, right?
So we made a series of commitments to Europe on how we will really govern our hyperscale investment there
uh, such that really European, uh, Union and the European countries have sovereignty.
We're also building sovereign clouds in, in France and in Germany.
We have something called Sovereign Services on Azure
which literally give people key management services along with confidential computing
including confidential computing in GPUs, which we have done great innovative work with NVIDIA.
Um, and so I think.
..
I feel very, very good about being able to build both technically
and through policy, this trust in the American tech stack.
Mm-hmm.
H- and how do you see this shaking out as
you know, you do have this, uh
network effect with continual learning and things on the model level
maybe you have equivalent things at the hyperscaler level as well
and do you expect that the countries will say
"Look, it's clear that one model or a couple models are the best and so we're gonna use them
but we're gonna have some laws around, well
the weights have to be hosted in our country.
" Or do you expect that there will be
uh, this push to have.
..
it has to be a model trained in our country?
Maybe an analogy here is like people would l- uh
you know, semiconductors are very important to the economy and people would like to have their sort of sovereign semiconductors
but, like, TSMC is just better and so semiconductors are so important to the economy that you will just go to Taiwan and buy the semiconductors.
You have to.
Will it be like that with AI or is there.
..
Um, ultimately, I think what matters is the use of AI in their economy to create economic value
right?
I mean, that's the, uh, the diffusion theory which is ultimately.
..
it's not the leading sector, but it's the ability to use the leading technology to create your own comparative advantage.
Yeah.
Right?
So that, I think, will fundamentally be the core driver.
But that said, they will want continuity of that
right?
So in some sense, that's one of the reasons why I believe there's always going to be a check
a little bit, to sort of some of your points on
hey, can this one model have all the runaway deployment?
I- that's why open source is always gonna be there.
There will be, by definition, uh, multiple models.
That'll be one way.
Like, it's kind of the, you know.
..
that's one way for people to sort of demand continuity and not have concentration risk
is another way to say it.
Yeah.
It is, right?
Um, and so you say, "Hey, I want multiple models and then I want an open source.
" So I feel, uh, as long as that's there
every country will feel like, okay, I don't have to worry about deploying the best model and broadly diffusing
because I can always take, uh, what is my data and my liquidity and move it
uh, to another model, whether it's open source or on
uh, from another country or what have you.
Mm-hmm.
So concentration risk, um, and sovereignty, right?
Which is really agency.
Those are the two things I think that'll drive the market structure.
The, the thing about this is that this doesn't exist for semiconductors
right?
Exactly.
You know, all refrigerators, cars have chips made in Taiwan.
It didn't exist until now.
Until now, everyone is now.
..
like, you know, like- Even, even then
right?
America, you know, if Taiwan is cut off
there is, there are no more cars
there are no more refrigerators.
TSMC Arizona is not replacing any real fraction of the production.
Like, they're.
..
it is, it, it.
they're.
..
the sovereignty is a bit of like a
a scam if you will, right?
I mean, it's, it's worthwhile having it
it's important to have it, but it's not a real.
..
it's not real sovereignty, right?
And we're a global economy.
We don't.
..
we.
I think it's kind of like Dylan saying
"Hey, at this point, we've not learned anything about sort of
uh, res- what resilience means and what one needs to do
" right?
So it's kind of.
..
Any nation state, including the United States
at this point, will do what it takes to be more self-sufficient on some of these critical supply chains.
So I, as a multinational company, have to think about that as a first-class requirement
right?
If I don't, then I'm not respecting what is in the sort of policy interests of that country long term
And I'm not saying they won't make practical decisions in the short term
right?
Absolutely.
I mean, the globalization can't just be rewound
right?
I mean, all these capital investments cannot be made
uh, in, in a way, at the pace at which.
..
But at the same time, you have to kind of.
Like, if I.
..
l- like, think about it, right?
If somebody showed up in Washington and said
"Hey, you know, you know what?
We're not gonna build any semiconductor plants.
" They're gonna be kicked out of the United States.
Um, and, and the same thing is gonna be
uh, true in every other country too.
Uh, and so therefore, I think we have to
as companies, respect what the lessons learned are
um, you know, whether it's, you know
you could say the pandemic woke us up or whatever.
But.
..
and nevertheless, people are saying, "Look, globalization was fantastic.
Uh, it helped supply chains be globalized and be super efficient.
But there's such a thing called resilience and we are happy.
..
you know, we want resilience.
" And so therefore, that feature will get built.
At what pace I think is the point you're making.
It can't be like you can't snap your fingers and say
"All the TSMC plants now are all in Arizona and with all of the capability.
" They're not going to be.
But is there a plan?
There will be a plan.
And should we respect that?
Absolutely.
And so I, I feel that's the world.
..
I wanna meet the world where it is and what it wants to do going forward
as opposed to say, "Hey, we have a point of view that doesn't respect your view.
" Mm-hmm.
So j- just to make sure I understand
th- the idea here is each country will want some kind of data residency
privacy, et cetera, and Microsoft is especially privileged here because you have relationships with these countries
you have expertise in setting up these kinds of sovereign data centers
and.
..
therefore, Microsoft is uniquely fit for a world with
um, more sovereignty requirements?
Yeah, I mean, like, I, I
I don't wanna sort of describe it as somehow we are uniquely privileged.
Yeah.
Uh, I would just say I think of that as a business requirement- I see.
.
that we have been doing all the hard work all these decades- Yeah.
..
and we will plan to.
And so my answer to Dylan's previous question was
I take these re-.
..
you know, whether it's in the United States
quite frankly, or, or when, you know
when the White House and the USG says
"Hey, we want you to allocate more of your
" I don't know, "wafer starts to, uh
uh, fabs in the US.
" We take that seriously.
Uh, or whether it is data center in the EU boundary
we take that seriously.
Yeah.
So to me, um, ma- respecting what I think are legitimate reasons why countries care about sovereignty- Yeah.
.
and building for it as a software and a physical plant is what I
I would say we are going to do.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, a- and as we go to
like, the bipolar world, right?
US, China- Yeah.
.
..
um, there is, there is a lot around
you know, American tech does not.
..
you know, it's not just you versus Amazon
um, or you versus, you know, Anthropic
or you versus Google.
Yeah.
There is a whole host of competi- com- competition.
How does, how does America rebuild the trust?
Great point.
What do you do to rebuild the trust to say
"Actually, no, American companies will be the main provider for you?
" Um, and how do you think about competition with up-and-coming Chinese companies
whether it be, you know, ByteDance and Alibaba
or DeepSeek and Moonshot?
And this is ju- just to add to the question
one concern is, look, we're talking about how AI is becoming this sort of industrial CapEx race
uh, where you're just rapidly having to build quickly across all those supply chain.
When you hear that, at least up until now
you just think about China, right?
This is, like, their comparative advantage.
Very much.
And especially if we're not gonna m- moonshot to ASI next year
but we.
..
it's gonna be this decades of build outs
and infrastructure- It's a great point.
.
and so forth, how do you deal with Chinese competition
and are they privileged in that world?
Yeah, so it's a great que-.
..
I mean, in fact, you just made the point of why I think trust in American tech is probably the most important feature.
It's not even the model capability, maybe.
It is, like, can I trust you
the company?
Can I trust you, your country, and its institutions- Mm-hmm.
.
..
to be a long-term supplier may be the thing that wins the world.
I think it's a good note to end on.
Yeah.
Satya, thank you for doing this.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Yes.
Thanks.
Such a pleasure.
Yeah.
It's awesome.
It's like, man, you two guys are
like-  .
..
quite the team.
Hey, everybody.
I hope you enjoyed that episode.
If you did, the most helpful thing you can do is just share it with other people who you think might enjoy it.
It's also helpful if you leave a rating or a comment on whatever platform you are listening on.
If you're interested in sponsoring the podcast, you can reach out at dwarkesh.
com/advertise.
Otherwise, I'll see you in the next one.