Let's be honest.
It's the boring  that makes you rich.
And the most unbelievable way for generating wealth and long-term economic security is.
..
And then, once you do that, you can become a super tax avoider.
That sounded awful.
Scott Galloway, one of the world's leading voices in business and finance is back.
His mission is to help millions of people build incredible wealth and live a life of economic security.
If you're trying to build wealth, you wanna lean into your advantages.
Your advantages in your 20s are flexibility and time.
So take risks, find your talent, not your passion
it has a 90-plus percent employment rate.
Or become an owner, not an earner
and develop an army of capital that goes out and kills for you at night
and then invest it.
What if you're not young?
Focus on the things you can control.
One thing that is within your control is spending.
But 98% of us will spend everything we get our hands on.
It is very hard to have the discipline to take money that is within your grasp and invest it.
And we don't appreciate the power of investing and compound interest.
My team brought a bucket of sand to illuminate the power of compounding interest.
This is investing £1,000 a month over the course of 12 months
starting at the age of 25.
If you left it and kept investing at that rate
by the age of 65, it would look like this.
And the young man who says, "I have £500.
I gotta wait till I have a million before I start investing.
" The way you get a million pounds is by investing that 500.
And this notion that it's too late for me
I'm in my 40s, I'm gonna ignore finances
ah, bull.
So what is the set of steps?
Let me make it easy.
First thing .
..
Congratulations, Diary of a CEO gang.
We've made some progress.
63% of you that listen to this podcast regularly don't subscribe
which is down from 69%.
Our goal is 50%.
So if you've ever liked any of the videos we've posted
if you like this channel, can you do me a quick favor and hit the subscribe button?
It helps this channel more than you know.
And the bigger the channel gets, as you've seen
the bigger the guests get.
Thank you, and enjoy this episode.
Scott, you've written a book on wealth
money, finance.
Why?
And why does it, why does it matter?
Uh, this is kind of a memo to my 25-year-old self.
I've been rich three times.
And the first two times, I lost it.
And I didn't grow up with a lot of money.
It's been very important to me.
I think America, and mostly in Europe
but especially America, America becomes more like itself every day.
And that is, it's a generous, loving place if you have money.
It's a rapacious, violent place if you don't.
I think economic security is really important.
And I think there's a series of habits and character traits that
uh, can help you get to economic security.
You know that study that you become the average of your five closest friends?
Same body mass index, same politics, same sports team
same neighborhood?
Uh, what they don't talk about is that amongst those five people
even if they're all making about the same amount of money
one will end up much more economically well-off than the other four.
And I'm trying to understand the behaviors of that one person who becomes economically secure by the time they're my age without making a lot more money than their colleagues.
Do you think we're taught about money?
W- where d- where did those people, that one in five
where did, where did they learn about money?
Yeah, that's a really interesting question.
I think .
..
So, th- the honest answer is, I don't know.
What I would say, uh, sociologically is that rich people talk about money
and it's considered taboo for employees and middle class and lower class and women to talk about money.
Like, you're told not to talk about your salary at work.
Asymmetry of information will always benefit the person that has symmetry
that knows the information.
The boss of a company knows what everyone's making
but he tells his or her employees not to discuss their salary because Lisa might find out that Bob is making 30% more for doing the same work.
So there's a bit of a zeitgeist that tells people not to talk about money
that it's like talking about porn or that it's vulgar.
And I think you need to start talking about money and maintain a certain level of financial literacy from a very early age.
Because Roger Federer talks about tennis.
If you wanna be good at anything, most people wanna be good at money
and to be good at something you need to understand it
and to understand it, you need to talk about it.
So I'm very transparent with how much money I make
what I do with it.
But talk to your friends about mortgage rates
talk to your friends about how much money they make
what they're doing with it, where they lost money.
And people aren't transparent about it, especially
I think, about men.
We're supposed to be just, like, accidentally wealthy.
And to ever talk about our financial problems is to admit that we're not ballers or that we're not masculine.
And so I encourage people from a young age to start talking about money and understand it and be transparent about it.
Where did you learn about money?
W- 'cause I think about my own life
and I think there's key moments of, quite frankly
luck.
Yeah.
Where I was exposed to information because I was invited into a room
physically, literally into a room, or I was
through no decision of my own, someone came into my life.
Yeah.
Um, or in my case, maybe one of the biggest blessings I ever had is when I went off
dropped outta university and pursued entrepreneurship- Yeah.
.
..
my brother decided to go be an investment banker for 11 years in London.
Yep.
And then, when I had my first exit
he messaged me one day and said, "Hey
I'll manage your money, and I'll quit my job and come work with you full-time.
" And that's my older brother.
So, like, life gave me the greatest gift anyone could ever have been given.
I- i- i- th- that, that, that rings so true.
So I think of three things as you said that.
The first is, the smartest thing I ever did was being born a white heterosexual male in California in the '60s.
Because it gave me unfair advantage.
It gave me access to free education in the University of California
and access, 76% admissions rate when I applied to UCLA.
The admissions rate this year is 9%.
I came of professional age in the '90s when the internet was coming online.
So I sorta had these winds at my back.
And also, uh, just to be blunt-.
..
everyone who was raising capital looked, smelled
and felt like me.
They were all White heterosexual males.
And I didn't even realize at the time what privilege or unfair advantage I had.
So w- the first is just, just sheer luck.
The second is environmental.
I grew u- I was raised by a single immigrant mother who lived and died a secretary.
And people who don't grow up with mony- people who grow up with money just can't really truly empathize with what it's like to grow up without money.
I felt as if there was this ghost following me and my mom around
constantly whispering in our ear, "You're not worthy.
Your mom fucked up, which means y- you aren't worthy.
" And so I very early decided that I was
that economic security was really important to me.
And I wanna be clear, you can't make a decision to be wealthy
a lot of it is luck.
But I was gonna be very committed.
My goal in life from zero to 45 wasn't to be a good person
it wasn't to save the whales, it wasn't to
to have strong relationships, it was to get economic security.
So I started connecting the dots around money pretty early.
And then along the lines of what you were talking about
um, my mom had a boyfriend and
um, and people don't talk about this
you know how in certain dramas they reference a second family where a guy has an entirely other family despite the fact he's married?
My mom and I were that second family.
Her boyfriend for seven years was a wonderful man named Terry
really nice to me, spent every other weekend with us
super generous to me.
Uh, he was also married with another family
so we were that second family.
But he was a good man and he was
he was actually a good role model for me.
And one weekend I was asking him, "What is a stock?
" And I was 13.
And he said, "Here's $200.
" He gave me two crisp $100 bills and said
"Walk down to one of those stock brokerages
those fancy stock brokerages in Westwood Village, and buy some stock and if you don't buy it by Monday afternoon or by the time I'm back next weekend
I'm taking my money back.
" So at 13 I marched down to Merrill Lynch Pierce Fenner Smith
was in the lobby, I was ignored
I got intimidated, I walked across the street to Dean Witter Reynolds
another brokerage, and this young guy named Si Cerro came walking out and said
"Hi, I'm Si Cerro," and he gave me my first lesson in the markets.
And I bought 14 shares of Columbia Pictures.
At 13 he gave you a lesson in the markets?
Yeah, at 13.
And every day, every weekday for the next three years from Emerson Junior High pay phone booth I put two dimes in and called Si and he would say
"'Close Encounters of the Third Kind' is a hit
which means that Columbia, uh, Studios is gonna make a lot of money
so people are buying more stock.
" And then I'd go into his office
I didn't, I didn't have a ton of friends
and so I would just swing by Dean Witter and he would always give me a lesson in the markets.
Had those two men not shown such generosity to you with their time and with that $200 bill
have you ever played out in your mind where you might be?
I think we all do that, like Sliding Doors
that movie, you know, things are s- th- eh
it's like, life is such a series of.
..
You know, I, I promised myself I was gonna approach this strange woman at the Raleigh Hotel in the middle of the day who was sitting by the pool
who was sitting there with another woman and another guy
and without the benefit of alcohol it's not easy to open
you know, a conversation with a strange woman.
And I walked out to get my car and I said
"I promised myself I was gonna speak to her
" I was very drawn to her, a beautiful woman.
So I went back in, I just rolled right up and I said
"Hi, I'm Scott, where are you guys from?
" And this was at the Raleigh Hotel.
Long story short, 18 months later our first son's middle name is Raleigh
right?
And what I tell people is that unless you're willing to take an uncomfortable risk
nothing wonderful is ever gonna happen to you.
I mean, a really uncomfortable risk.
What you're doing here is an uncomfortable risk
it's public failure if it doesn't work.
This podcast platform you're starting, you know
this, most people aren't willing to take these risks.
And a lot of this, not to get existential
a lot of this comes down to a huge unlock for me has been atheism.
I think I have a very solid grasp of the finite nature of life.
You're a young man, you're gonna be my age in an instant
and the thing you're gonna recognize is that
okay, in 30 or 40 years, everyone whose opinion you are worried about is gonna be dead.
And I have found that has been an enormous unlock for me
knowing that I'm gonna at some point sooner than I'd like look into my kids' eyes and know our relationship is coming to an end
so I'm comfortable expressing my emotions, or more comfortable.
I'm comfortable taking uncomfortable risks knowing that if I call someone and ask them to invest
if I approach a strange woman in a bar and introduce myself
if I call a, an employee who I would never think would consider working for me
I'm not afraid of rejection because I realize everyone I'm worried about being shamed by is gonna be dead soon and so am I.
And so why wouldn't you live out life.
..
w- wh- why wouldn't you live out loud?
Why wouldn't you squeeze so much juice from this
you know, uh, uh, lemon called life?
It's really been an enormous unlock for me
'cause the reality, Steve, is that most people are not willing to take uncomfortable risks that might result in public shaming.
It's embarrassing to get rejected by a pote- to express interest in someone and be sort of rejected.
It's embarrassing to try and raise money and be rejected.
It's embarrassing to start a business and not have it work.
The majority of people aren't willing to take those uncomfortable risks.
And the reason why you get outsized return as an entrepreneur
the reason why you get outsized returns when you're willing to approach strangers and ask for mentorship
friendship, express romantic interest, is because you are willing to endure rejection.
The most overcompensated people in any organization are the salespeople.
In terms of how hard and how smart they are
how hard they work and how smart they are relative to their compensation
hands down the most overcompensated people that everyone resents are the salespeople because they are willing to get out a big spoon and eat shit.
"Do not call me again.
Okay, so what you're saying is I should follow up in a couple weeks.
" Right?
That type of rejection, that type of risk
that type of public failure, 99% of people are not willing to endure.
I ran for sophomore, junior, and senior class president in high school.
I lost all three times and based on my track record I decided I should run for student body president where I went o- went on to
wait for it, lose.
And it never really got in the way of my confidence
you know.
And that's the key.
If you want.
..
And unfortunately, young men are told, you know
"Don't try hard," or they feel like a loss of agency
or especially romantically, they're told, "Be careful in terms of expressing romantic interest.
" And if you don't know the difference between expressing interest and asking someone out for coffee and harassing them
you've got bigger problems.
But I think a lot of young men have feel like their agency has been taken away
they feel like the game is rigged so they're not trying
and quite frankly, they're spending much too
too much time on a screen or in their homes
so they're not putting themselves in a position to have something wonderful happen to them.
And then on a very basic level, I'm almost entirely sure that I can guarantee you that nothing really wonderful
I mean, really wonderful, is gonna happen to you inside of your home on a screen.
Your success is a function of your ability to endure rejection and increasingly
how much time you spend outside of your house off a screen.
What if you're not young?
Because what you described there, that h- all of that was me at 18.
Mm-hmm.
I had just dropped out of university after w- going to only one of the lectures.
And I had these four credit cards which had about
I think, combined about £1,000 on them.
Mm-hmm.
I'd maxed them all out.
My parents weren't speaking to me.
I'm three hour, three hours away from home
roughly, up in Manchester.
More than that, six-hour round trip in Manchester.
And I'm 18, I've got no kids
no mortgage, no nothing and I'm in- Mm-hmm.
.
this room that I can't afford to pay for.
So in.
..
I was so clearly at the bottom with nothing to lose- Mm-hmm.
.
..
that every roll of the dice was a potential win.
Yeah.
So I was rolling that motherfucker.
But you kept rolling them.
Over and over and over- Yeah.
.
and over again.
Yeah.
But, but I, I, I wonder sometimes
'cause there's probably gonna be someone listening that's
you know, 47- Yep.
.
..
three kids, mortgage- Yep.
.
..
comfortable job, just about cutting it every month
one holiday a year, experiencing the same dissatisfaction with their life
but- Yeah.
.
..
they can't roll like I could when I was 18.
Look, the reality is when you have kids
everything changes.
The, I think the, probably the darkest moment for me
maybe personally or professionally other than losing my mom
was the moment that was supposed to be the happiest and that was when my first son was born.
And you think that when this child, when you
you know, this child's introduced to the world
it's gonna be bright lights and angels singing.
For me, if, I felt humiliation and shame and fear because I had made a lot of money
but I had gone all in, and this is a lesson from the book
The Power of Diversification.
I'd gone all in on this one company
Red Envelope, which went public in 2002.
It was an e-commerce company I started.
And I thought and had been taught by the venture capital community that if you throw yourself at something and you're talented
and I thought, "I'm a baller, I'm really good at what I do
" you gotta go all in, and I kept investing every spare dollar I had and threw myself at this thing.
And then a strike at the port, a software glitch
and the credit crisis.
In 2008, our stock went from seven bucks to Chapter 11 in
like, three weeks.
And I ended up not being worth 10 or 12 million
but being worth, worth negative two million
'cause I was one of those idiots that borrowed against their stock to buy more stock.
Ah.
And then my child has the poor judgment
my oldest, to come marching out of my girlfriend
and the first thing I felt was failure on a massive level.
Like, my first emotion when my son was born was
"I have failed to live up to my core responsibility as a man
and that is to take care of my child.
" And it was just, it was just a really ugly emotion.
And that's a lesson in the book, and that is
the moment you aggregate anything resembling some sort of n- uh
decent amount of capital, you wanna look at it and you wanna diversify like crazy.
Because if I'd just taken a little bit of money off the table and invested in index funds or in real estate or bonds
I would've been so much better off.
But everyone's told, "You can have it all
you can, you, you know, y- y- you can be successful if you just go all in
never give up.
" Well, actually, the market will trump individual performance every time.
And last week, my, the investment I was most excited about
this healthcare tech startup, great CEO, tier one investors
elbowed my way into the deal.
I put five million bucks in.
I found out last Friday it's a zero.
It just didn't work.
Zero, shutting down.
But here's the thing.
I never invest more than 3% of my net worth now in any one thing.
So while it hurt, I have Kevlar in the form of diversification.
So I took a bullet to the chest
knocked me off my feet, I get up
I was bummed out for an hour, that was it
because I never go all in on something.
And people are taught, especially young people
especially men who are more risk aggressive, go all in on something because the people who are the wealthiest people in the world kind of went all in on something.
And what they don't tell you is the moment they have capital
they start diversifying like crazy.
So you wanna diversify.
You don't need to find the needle in haystack.
You can buy the whole haystack.
And especially, unfortunately, in the American economy
not as much in the UK economy, it continues to be up and to the right.
And the S&P and the NASDAQ are sort of self-filtering mechanisms because they kick out companies that aren't great and they bring in new ones.
They kick out Kodak and they bring in Salesforce.
If I had learned that diversification when I was a younger man
I would've saved myself.
..
Uh, not only would I be, have saved myself a lot of economic harm
I would've saved myself a lot of mental anguish.
So diversification, and that's one of the key components of my algebra of wealth
diversification, people don't recognize how powerful it is 'cause it sounds boring.
And you have people like Bill Ackman saying
"It's not concentration, it's conviction," you know
and then they beat on their chest, like
"Check out my shit.
" No, diversify and get rich slowly, because here's the thing
life goes so goddamn fast, "Wow, life has gone slowly
" said no one ever.
Now, back to your person who's 40
45, they're gonna live another 40 years-They're probably gonna work another 30.
You wanna lean into your advantages.
Your advantages in your 20s are flexibility, you wanna workshop careers
find sone- find your talent, not your passion.
Start saving a little bit of money.
A little bit of money when you're young is a lot when you're older.
Try and develop that savings muscle.
A hundred bucks a month, a thousand bucks a month
oh my God, 25 hundred bucks a month
if you can do that in your 20s
you're gonna be fine when you're my age.
Even if you don't go double platinum or sell a book or be a baller in business
you're fine.
Your plan B is all set.
That's your advantage when you're in your 20s
is time.
When you get to your 40s, your advantage is the following.
One, hopefully you're in a relationship with a partner you can align with around financial
um, e- objectives, your approach to spending
your approach to earning.
Y- you can see the runway, "All right
I'm gonna retire in 30 years.
I need 15 to 25 times my, my nut to be in the bank to retire.
I spend about $120,000 a year, that 20 times that I would need 2.
4 million, I'm not.
..
" Now, work backwards.
How much would I need to save over the next 30 years to get to 2.
4 million, assuming 8% a year?
The landing lights are on, you can start to plan your life.
"I'm not gonna get there.
I can't save this much.
I got kids in college.
" Okay.
When do your kids go to college?
Can you take that burndown to 80 grand by moving to Mexico City or Costa Rica or to St.
Louis?
But you have the advantage of knowing your path.
Ideally, you have a career where you can make some money and start saving a little bit.
Ideally, you have a partner where you can get alignment around working together to get that financial security.
But most people in their 40s are under the impression their life is over.
I mean, they're probably gonna live to be over a hundred
and i- it's so, okay, so you don't have 80 years
you only have 60 years left, but you still probably got another 30 years working and making money
and you kinda know what you need, right?
Uh, so I think there's advantages at every age
but this notion that it's too late for me
I'm in my 40s, I'm gonna ignore finances
no, bullshit.
You just need to have an adult conversation with yourself.
Do you think it makes sense then to go kind of risk on when you're young and then go diversified once you're older
'cause you just wanna highlight that for people that are
you know, uh, like I was when I was 18
to kinda go all in and to make those big bets when you have nothing to lose
and the minute you have something to lose
whether that's your mortgage, y- you know
you got children to take care of or now you've got wealth
to then go risk off.
Is that the kind of approach you would suggest to life?
I, I think generally speaking, you can't be as risk-aggressive when you have kids.
Um, when you're younger, look, if you screw up here
y- you're, you're, you're likable enough that you can probably find couches to live on f- for two years- .
.
..
if you needed to.
If you like just got in over your skis
uh, you could find a way to dan- when you're young
you can dance between the raindrops.
I lived in New York, I had two
two roommates.
When I started my business, my girlfriend paid our rent
and I, because I didn't, I didn't have kids or dogs
there's just a certain level of responsibility and things you gotta take care of as you get older.
When you get a little bit older, don't go all in on anything.
If you're gonna start a business, use other people's capital
ring-fence it, don't get seduced into.
..
The worst thing that can happen in your 30s and 40s is you start a business and you start failing slowly
you just don't know.
The worst type of business is one that gives you just enough green signals that you keep investing more time and more money.
The red envelope, people, that's what people know me for
that's the worst thing that can happen to somebody
'cause it failed slowly.
It failed over 11 years.
I started an e-commerce incubator in New York backed by Goldman Sachs
Maveron, um, JPMorgan, it was out of business in eight months 'cause of the dot-com meltdown.
That's a blessing.
The best thing that can happen is success
the second-best thing is fast failure, the worst thing that can happen to you is slow failure.
You can't have slow failure when you're 30s and 40s.
So, you wanna make sure that if you go in on something
you ring-fence it, "I'm leaving my job
I'm gonna try and start my own business
I'm gonna spend two years doing it.
A certain amount of capital, no more than maybe 10
20% of my capital," because hitting a wall and failing at 50 is
is much more devastating than hitting a wall or failing at 25 or 30.
You can get up again.
You're fine.
You can press the restart button a bunch of times
so you wanna take advantage of that in your 20s and 30s and workshop a bunch of things.
I'm not saying hop around.
I'm not saying, "Well, oh, I don't love this
it's not my passion," no, that probably means it's just work
but if you're not making progress, if you're not making money
if you're not getting roles in films, if you're not
if everything's just really hard, really hard
you're in a position at that age to say
"You know what?
I'm gonna leave Milan and move to Munich or I'm going to Dubai.
" You have flexibility when you're young, you have geographic flexibility.
Lean into your advantage.
It's a heck of a lot easier right now to make money in Dubai than it is in Curaças
right?
You'd rather be good in a great economy than outstanding in a mediocre economy.
You have geographic flexibility.
Lean into your advantages, your flexibility, your ability to recover
your ability to workshop.
What would you do if one of your sons said to you
how many sons have you got now?
I got two.
You got two sons, right?
That I know of.
that you know of.
One of your sons comes to you and says
"Dad, I would like to be a
I've read your book, um, all of your books
and I think they're great, but Dad
I'd love to be a professional actor-" Yeah.
.
and then your other son came to you and said
"I wanna be a musician.
" I don't wanna crush anybody's dreams.
Uh, I'd go for it, I'll be supportive
um, but this industry, let's just look at the economics.
Musician and acting has a 99% unemployment rate
so you gotta be in the 1%, and I want you to set up benchmarks for determining what it means to be in the top 1%
right?
80, uh, the most talented actors in the world are in a union called SAG-AFTRA.
And by the way, it's not easy to get your union card.
You gotta be in a Broadway play, you gotta be recognized.
That's a big moment.
It's like getting your PGA golf tour card
right?
You get your SAG-AFTRA card, it means you're one of the 180
000 most talented creatives in the world.
Last year, 83% of them didn't have health insurance 'cause they didn't make more than $23
000.
So, you not only need to be in the top 17% just to have health insurance
you probably need to be in the top 10%
realistically the top 1%.
I know a lot of working actors.
If I said, "This is the guy from this show
" you'd be like, "Oh my God, that guy's amazing?
" He's not making a lot of money.
I mean, everybody talks about Tom Cruise.
The majority of working actors, you would say
"Oh, I know that woman, I know that man.
They're great.
" They make an okay living.
If they had achieved that level of excellence in almost any other industry
they'd be, they'd own a house and a second house in Ibiza.
So, if you wanna be an athlete
an actor, a model, an artist, open a restaurant
open a nightclub, have a jewelry line
be a fashion designer, I don't wanna crush anyone's dreams
but let's have a sober conversation that if you aren't getting bright green lights that you're in the top 1% really quickly
and we put some guardrails on it, we're gonna do this for two years
three years, can't pay your rent in two or three years
Dad's gonna stop paying your rent at some point
or maybe I'll continue to pay your rent
but I need you to start workshopping another career.
Because here's the thing, people of- young people oftentimes mistake their hobbies for their passions.
And what I would suggest is, and what I can guarantee you
is being successful at anything, passion comes from mastery.
Mastery comes from being a ninja at something.
I'm renovating a house and there's this guy installing our soapstone
who's the soapstone guy.
He's an Iraqi immigrant, dropped out of high school.
He knows everything about so- soapstone.
He can talk to you about the vein in the soapstone and which quarries.
And, and he makes.
..
I've been very open with him.
I've talked about it in my book, he made 1.
3 million pounds last year.
He's the soapstone guy.
I can't imagine when he was a kid
he and I bonded over football.
I would bet, I don't know this
I would bet he dreamt of being a football star and playing for Iraq in the World Cup at some point.
I doubt at the age of 17, he thought
"My.
..
I'm hoping in 15 years I'm installing soapstone and renovations for American douchebags in Marylebone.
" I can't imagine that was his dream
right?
But here's the thing.
He has an amazing life, he takes care of his kids
he takes care of his parents, he gets to take amazing vacations with his wife
which makes him passionate about soapstone.
So yeah, go be a fashion designer.
But let's be honest, if you're not making enough money to pay your rent within two years
and you're not making enough money to say
form a family in five years, we're gonna workshop something else.
This requires such a mindset shift in the current world
because obviously the slot machine, the casino
the Las Vegas of validation is Instagram and TikTok.
That's right.
Now, if I announce on Instagram that I'm a tax lawyer
for the next f- 10 years- Not a great Instagram page.
.
it's not gonna increase my chance of getting laid either.
But if I say that I am, I don't know
if I say that I'm part of Chelsea Football Club
I'm in the, you know, the Junior Academy- Yeah.
.
..
or if I say that I'm starting a business
I'm probably gonna get laid more in the next 10 years.
Well, the only pushback I would get is that you have to be one of the 10 best soccer players in the world that year to play for Chelsea.
That is really hard.
That is really.
..
That means you're the best player in Senegal
and then you go.
..
I mean, you just have to be godlike talented.
The best 10% of tax lawyers, that's tens of thousands of them
fly private and get laid more than you think
because they fly private and they can afford.
..
They can find someone and give them a wonderful life.
So, uh, I mean, look, in a capitalist.
..
I'm not saying this is how the world should be.
I'm saying this is how the world is.
Economic security provides you with all sorts of opportunities for experiences
for relationships, for romantic opportunities, and it is sexy to be great at anything and get economic security from anything.
And I can't tell you, I love taking care of my kids 'cause at one point I was worried about my ability to take care of my kids
and not worry about it, and this is where happiness comes from.
It's great to be in a prestige industry and be a baller.
I get reward from some of the fame I have right now.
I'm sure you get reward from it, but the thing that is really rewarding as you get older is I can lean into my relationships with my sons and I don't have that economic fear I had the first time my son came marching out on my girlfriend.
That is so rewarding.
I can take care of my dad.
I don't have to worry about it.
My, my dad's 90, gonna be 94 in a few weeks
and he lives in a really nice home
and he has a full-time kind of health aide
and it's about a quarter of a million dollars a year to take care of my dad.
And if you look at, okay, that's post-tax
there's no tax credit for it, so it's about $400
000 in pre-tax income.
My sister, who does really well, but not as well as me
we have a great partnership.
She handles it logistically, I handle the money
and being able to do that and not have it be a source of stress in my life
and know that my dad is taken care of well
okay, i- i- uh, it'd be great to be a football player
trust me, when you get to my age
that feels really good.
That feels really nice.
And the m- the, the, the means to the ends
the means.
..
Money is a means.
It's really important.
It's hard to be happy in a capitalist society with economic stress.
The standing blood- the resting blood pressure of kids in low-income homes is higher than kids in middle and upper mid because they sense the anxiety from Mom and Dad.
I remember, you know, losing my jacket when I was in the eighth grade and it was gonna be just a horrible day 'cause I had to go home and tell my mom jackets cost 33 bucks
all in my head, very upsetting.
..
. the ability to take care of your kids
your parents, do wonderful things.
Money a- affords you so many wonderful things that getting to a certain level of economic security is the means.
But the ends, the reason you get to economic securities is so you can free up and be free of anxiety and have some additional time so you can focus on the ends.
And the ends is deep and meaningful relationships.
I spend the majority of my money on travel and experiences with my family and friends.
I spend a shit ton of money, and I absolutely love it.
There's no reason to hoard money.
Once I hit my number, I hit my number seven years ago
and I started thinking, "I could be a billionaire.
" What was your number?
Uh, my number was 100 million.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, by the way, my number when I got out of college was a million
and then by my 30s, I thought
"Well, if I had 10 million, I'm done.
" And then things got so expensive and my greed glands kept going
and my number was 100 million.
Why have a number?
Why did, why do people listening need to create a number?
What's the value of having that sort of line in the sand?
Well, you need a goal, and you need to be thoughtful about how much money you're gonna need.
So if you figure out I'm gonna need a
I'm gonna need 80,000 pounds a year to live.
Uh, uh, the definition of rich is having a ton of shit and impress your friends.
The definition of wealth is knowing that the passive income that you would get from growth from your stocks or dividends or incomes or rental income is greater than your burn.
So you work, you work out of d- out of
uh, a option, or you work because you want to
not 'cause you need to.
That's the definition of wealth.
So having a number is just backward integrating into
okay, um, I want to have at least $3 million a l- a year to live the life I wanna live.
All right?
Assuming a 4% return, that means I need $75 million.
So I round it up to 100 million
right?
I got exceptionally lucky to get there.
By the way, see above.
In 2008, I was broke.
I was broke at the age of 42
43.
That did not feel good.
I got very lucky, started a company
bull market the last 16 years, right place
right time, exceptionally lucky.
But you should be able, you should have a number.
You should say, "This is the amount of money I need
and once I get to this number, enjoy it and start giving it away.
" We, we really need to.
..
'Cause I'm thinking about.
The lens that I kind of think about this conversation through is
like, different stages in my own journey and the advice that I would have wanted from you at different steps in my journey.
And I, I just flashed back to working in those call centers
where I was making just about enough money to.
..
Well, to be fair, if I'm being completely honest
I did have disposable income.
But I, when I was poor, I was reckless with my money.
Mm-hmm.
So I would get the 500 pound disposable income on payday
leave the call center, go and buy a 400- Magical.
.
pound TV- Yeah.
..
flat-screen TV, and put it in a room where the TV was as big as the wall of my room.
Right.
And I, I'm trying to, I'm really trying to zoom in on that person who is so far away from nine figures- Yeah.
.
and they're like, "Okay, Scott, I wanna be Scott Galloway.
" Yeah.
So what is the set of steps or the mindset
the fishing rod I need- Got it.
.
in my mind to become Scott Galloway, nine figures?
Well, the first is, the first is
some of it is luck.
A l- again, a lot of my success in.
..
If I had been born in Europe, I don't think I'd have that number.
Europe's not as forgiving of entrepreneurs that have failed.
I've had a lot of failure.
If I lived in China, I think there's a decent chance I'd be in jail.
So the smartest, again, the smartest thing I've ever done was being born in California in the '60s.
So you're saying to move?
Does that matter?
What's that?
Should I move city?
Like- Oh, if you're young, the first thing you want to do is to get to one of 20 supercities.
If you're.
..
I'm just talking about someone who wants to be an economic animal
right?
Uh, you might-  Who doesn't?
Okay, but it's, uh, some people might say
"Scott, it's your way or it's not the right way.
I wanna teach, coach football in my little village outside
uh, in the Amalfi Coast.
I can make 55,000 euros working, running a small bakery and have a really nice life.
" Or- I don't think they would have clicked.
More power to you.
That's not the majority of the people I hang out with.
Majority of the young people I hear from realize that capitalism
that wealth equals relevance and love in a capitalist society
and they wanna be economically very secure.
The easiest thing, the best piece of advice is
one, get credentialed.
We live in a LinkedIn economy.
What you did, your success is especially impressive because on average
people who get a college degree earn 50 to 100% more over the course of their life.
There's an entire set of industries that are off-limits to people that don't have credentialing.
I went to work for Morgan Stanley.
We not only didn't hire people without college degrees
we didn't hire people that didn't go to one of eight universities when I applied.
Eight.
You had to g- not only go to college
you had to go to one of eight colleges to get a job at Morgan Stanley at that time.
So if you can, get credentialing.
The second thing, not everyone's cut out for college.
I get that.
The second thing is get to a supercity.
Two thirds of all economic growth over the next 30 years is gonna take place in one of 20 cities.
So if you're really in that small town in Italy
you wanna get to Milan as quickly as possible
and then, if you can, you wanna get to London as quickly as possible or Munich or a bigger city.
And then, quite frankly, if you have total geographic agility and flexibility
ignoring the ridiculous INS of the US, you wanna get to New York or San Francisco
because to be good in San Francisco is much better than being amazing in Stuttgart.
The amount of economic.
..
Here's the thing.
I'm, I'm a mediocre, I'm a mediocre surfer.
I've even, actually even given it up.
But when I was young and I used to go to Hawaii and the waves were perfect
I started believing I was a good surfer.
Or I go to Aspen after a fresh coat of snow and I'm like
"I'm a decent skier.
" No, you're not.
The snow and the waves are fucking amazing.
Anyone could be a good skier in this shit.
Get to where the waves and the snow are amazing
and that's, generally speaking, in cities.
And when you're young, you can be in a city 'cause you can live in a 400-square-foot apartment.
You can be out of the house all day.
You can dance between the raindrops and make money.
But when you are in a city.
..
You know how when you play tennis, if you play with someone much better than you
it elevates your game?
Mm-hmm.
When you're in a city, you're playing against Serena Williams every day.
Everyone is smart.
Everyone is well-dressed.
Everyone is working hard.
Everyone is taking chances, and you are surrounded by people who are very successful
and you are gonna bump off professional and personal opportunity every day.
Do it while you're young, 'cause when you start collecting dogs and kids
as I did in my 30s, I could no longer afford to stay in New York.
So I had to move to Delray Beach in Florida.
When I say have to, we had a wonderful life down there.
There's not a fraction of the opportunities in Delray Beach for someone in their 20s and 30s.
Now, I already had professional momentum, but Sunday to Thursday night
I was commuting to New York, 'cause that's where the action was.
So one, credentialing, but two, absolutely get to one of 20 supercities.
When you say 20 supercities, I- I thinking now
we're having this conversation in a world where AI seems to be the biggest topic of conversation.
Yeah.
It seems to be ripping up m- many industries.
But, uh, I also reflect on that and I go
where is the AI opportunity gonna be?
If that is the biggest wave coming into shore in terms of opportunity
um, should I be playing my sort of geographical
um, decision-making based on artificial intelligence?
'Cause everyone's raving about how big of an opportunity that is.
And technology generally over the next 10 years seems like it's really gonna eat up a lot of
uh, industry.
Yeah.
I don't, I don't know if it'd be possible to determine geography based on AI.
What I would say is, okay, you know
every.
..
Literally, uh, a third of my class
NYU, they get on a plane for San Francisco the day they graduate.
There's just, uh, within a seven-mile radius of San Francisco International Airport
there's been more wealth created I think in the last six months than
than Germany's created in the last decade.
NVIDIA is worth more than the entire UK stock market.
NVIDIA is, they make the, they're basically
they make the brains for artificial intelligence.
They make a GPU, which is essentially a microchip that powers all of AI right now.
And no one can buy them fast enough.
Now, they have 30,000 people.
I would bet 10 or 15,000 of them are worth at least $10 million now.
Right?
Because?
Because the 30,000 employees got stock options.
And when a company goes from, from 300 billion to three trillion
it means everyone is getting rich.
That doesn't happen that often in Dortmund.
It doesn't happen that often.
It doesn't happen.
I'm being kind.
Right?
You grow up in Ingolstadt, you either go to work for Audi
nothing wrong with that, make a good living.
But if you're young and you think, "I really want to get in front of the biggest waves
" you wanna go to one of several cities.
You wanna have the winds at your back.
So if you're young, what do you have?
You have agility geographically.
But going back, you initially asked me
"What's the algorithm?
What are the steps?
" And I tried to.
..
Uh, the book's called The Algebra of Wealth.
I tried to distill it down to a
uh, a small number of, of features.
The first is focus.
Go all in on something.
Once you find, you workshop in your 20s
once you find something you're really good at
that you could be in the top 1% at
and here's the key part, as we referenced before
that has a 90-plus percent employment rate.
And 90% of industries have that.
But if you can be in the top 10% of an industry that has a 90-plus percent employment rate
you're gonna make really good money.
First thing, focus.
Try not to have side hustles.
If you have a side hustle, it means your main hustle isn't working.
Use side hustle to workshop new main hustles.
But once you find something you're really good at
go all in on it.
Can I pause there just as we keep going?
'Cause I want to just provide counterarguments just in case that certain people are objecting in their own minds.
Uh, I think about me in the Southwest of England as I grew up
and I was in Plymouth working in a McDonald's.
I worked there for two days.
Mm-hmm.
But I worked in retail and shops and stuff.
What I had at that moment, I
in hindsight, was a void of information.
So.
..
M- I could only work at, like
a clothing store and a McDonald's because I didn't have any other information.
And if a kid hasn't gone to university or if someone listening to this haven't
hasn't got the information and they've stumbled across
across this podcast, but they're working in
I don't know, like a equivalent of a Wendy's or a Burger King
for example- Mm-hmm.
.
..
and they just, like, "How do I get out of this Burger King
Scott?
I'm a cashier at Burger King.
" Yeah.
Look, I, I don't.
..
Uh, I, I want to be clear.
I think there is a certain downside to the notion that we live in a meritocracy
and it creates a lot of rage and shame among young people
and that is the notion that, in America especially
anyone can be anything.
Well, not really, boss.
'Cause the problem with thinking we live in a meritocracy is that if you don't make it
you fucked up.
It's your fault.
Yeah.
And there's dignity in every work.
What I would say to someone working at a Burger King or in fast food that wants something bigger
work really.
..
I was on the board of Panera Bread
which is a fast food chain or quick service.
They call it QSR.
They don't like the term f- Someone who is hardworking and showed up at work every day on time and worked with their colleagues and acted like they owned the place
probably within two years could be managing the place and making 60 or 80 grand a year.
Now, I'm not suggesting you go all
all in on food, but there's always dignity in work.
There's always opportunity for people who work hard and act like owners and are good people and try and look out for other people and are good managers.
That might just be for you a means to an end
where you're workshopping other stuff to say, "How do I get to
to school?
How do I get to training?
How do I find a better job?
How do I save for a one-year apprenticeship program to become an electrician?
How do I start meeting people?
" You gotta pay your bills.
There's dignity in all work.
I coach a lot of young men, and the first thing I say is
"You gotta start making some money.
" And they're like, "I'm not gonna work at CVS or at McDonald's.
" I'm like, "Yeah, you are, 'cause you need a taste for flesh.
" The best way to make a lot of money is to start making a little bit of money.
But have a plan.
"I want to be the assistant manager of this McDonald's.
I want to save enough money so I can go back to school.
I want to save enough money so I can move to Dubai or move to London and get a job there that might be higher paying.
" Is there anything about the CVS or the Burger King or the whatever that I should be looking at to check that it has room for me to grow there?
Is there anything that.
..
You know, if we're starting by making a little bit of money- Yeah.
.
..
is there any good place to make a little bit of money versus a bad place to make a little bit of money?
Well, growth sort of solves all problems.
So if you're working at a Chipotle-Doug McMillon
who is the CEO of Walmart, started st-
uh, loading trucks.
He worked in the loading docks.
But he was also working for the retailer that grew faster than any retailer in history.
So is your company growing?
Uh, first thing, growth kind of solves all problems
right?
If you were mediocre at Google, you did a lot better than if you were great at General Motors the last 20 years
because one was growing, one wasn't.
So is it growing?
Two, is more situational.
Do I have someone who is emotionally invested in my success here?
Is the manager of the store like me and saying
"Keep doing this, I'm gonna get you an assistant manager job at the store down the street?
" Am I learning, right?
Am I getting skills that challenge me?
Is this a little bit hard?
That's okay.
Is it stressful?
That's okay too.
You don't want stress?
Go be a security guard in a parking lot.
No stress, no upside.
The market is really good at trading up.
The more stressful and intense, and like
"God, I can't keep up here," that probably means you're learning
that probably means you're gonna make more money.
So am I learning?
Do I have senior level sponsorship?
Am I at a company that's growing?
Am I in a city where there's economic vitality?
Do I have flow?
Flow of interesting people, flow of interesting friends that I might start another business with
flow of potential rem- One in three relationships begin at work
and every HR has hairs on fi- HR manager's hair is on fire right now.
One in three relationships begin at work.
We don't talk about that.
A third of all relationships begin at work
and 99% of them are consensual, right?
Young people have to find a place to
to find other mates, if you will.
But there's a ser- And then, more importantly
I think than all of this, is assembling a kitchen cabinet of people that will
you can be really honest with.
"I'm working at Burger King, I think I'm doing pretty well there.
They wanna make me.
..
" Managers at In-N-Out Burger make about 110
$120,000 a year in, in the US
and they're even given a chance to participate in profit sharing.
And I'm not suggesting being in fast food the rest of your life
but have a plan.
And then you gotta have a kitchen cabinet.
Put together a group of three, four people who know you
who you trust you, and you can be totally transparent
"This is how much money I'm making.
These are my opportunities.
These are, this is what I'm good at
what I'm not good at.
What do you think I should do?
" And who are those people in terms of
are they people that are ahead of you in
in the race of life?
Or are they.
..
First off, don't approach someone and say
"I find you h- I want you to be my mentor
" right?
'Cause that's a high bar and a lot of people are really busy.
It's like, "Hey, uh, I- I'm
uh, y- I think you're really impressive.
" A neighbor, someone who's made.
..
Uh, it doesn't have to be a baller
but someone who's living a virtuous life, who seems smart and nice to you.
"Can I get some advice from you?
Can I, would you mind?
I just have questions.
Can we do a call?
Can we have a coffee?
" There are a lot of people out there who want to help younger people and take it as a compliment.
"Can I get your advice?
" Ask them for advice.
Don't make big decisions without talking to other people.
It is really hard to read the label from inside of the bottle
really hard, right?
Check in with people.
Save, save yourself from yourself.
So that kitchen cabinet.
And if you're like, if you're a young woman working at a Burger King
and yo- hopefully you meet some people and say
"Hey, uh, can I just get some advice from you?
" And by the way, it might be someone else working at Burger King
and you're like, "This person has her act together.
This person just has her act to- She's just smart.
" We all know those people.
Mm-hmm.
We meet them and we work with them
like, "You know, this person just-" Yeah.
.
..
"kind of switched on.
They just seem to have better judgment around certain issues.
" So, uh, what I would say is
have a plan, don't be afraid to make changes
put together a kitchen cabinet, realize there's dignity in all work.
And any company, even something that seems low-brow
like fast food, those organizations need talented people to go up the ranks and make money
because the turnover is enormous.
Mm-hmm.
So I think there's opportunity and dignity in any work.
You said something really interesting, which I
I don't think I've ever had anybody talk about before
which is, you said, "Don't ask someone to be your mentor.
" And I frank- I get asked to be someone's mentor several times a week
as I'm sure you do.
Yeah.
And I've never given people advice on why that isn't the right
right approach.
But you said there that you don't think that's the right approach
so I wanted to just pause and ask you why.
Well, you don't go up to a strange person and say
"Do you wanna have sex?
" You go up and say, "Do you wanna have a con- Do you wanna have a conversation?
Do you wanna have another drink?
Do you wanna grab coffee?
Do you wanna go to the movies?
Can I ask you a question?
Can I get some advice from you?
" You ease into the relationship.
Yeah.
Because to ask someone to be your mentor is just very intimidating.
The person has to go, "Do I wanna meet with this person every month for the next five years and then break up with them if it
you know, if I'm not enjoying this relationship?
" So you don't need to say, "Will you be my mentor?
" That sounds like a lot.
Just, "Can I get your advice on something?
I really respect you.
I, I think you're so smart about this stuff.
I'm, I'm facing some issues in my life
some questions.
I'd love to just get your advice.
Can we grab coffee or can we do a five or 10 minute call?
" If someone emails me and says, "I'm thinking of.
..
" I get a lot, "I'm thinking about starting a business.
I'm thinking about going to business school.
Can I get some time?
" I try to say yes, and I say
"I can do, I can do a 15-minute Zoom call with you.
" If someone asks me to be their mentor
there's just no way.
I don't, I don't have time to.
..
You know, I can barely mentor me right now.
I do the, the.
..
I just don't have time to commit to being someone's mentor.
But if someone emails me and says, "I need advice around this specific issue
" and then what happens?
You hear that they're, you know, raised by a single mother like me
they're a good person, they're struggling, their sister's got an eating disorder and they're struggling with it
and they're trying to, they're thinking about starting a business and you're like
"Oh, no, no, don't do that right now.
You've got a good job.
" Like, you just make some, you just help them with some common sense decisions.
Common sense.
And then what happens?
You become emotionally invested in their success and then they email you a month later and you're like
"What's going on?
" And you wanna do another call.
You know, ease into it.
So anyways, I think it's much easier to just ask someone for help and for advice
and I think there's a lot of people out there.
..
It doesn't have to be a baller like Steven Bartlett.
There's a lot of smart people out there that can give you good advice.
'Cause I think this is really important, I
I don't think I've, as I said
I don't think I've had anyone talk about this
but you get a lot of messages.
Have you been able to figure out exactly why some of them perk your interest
so much so that you give them 15 minutes on a Zoom call?
Is there, is there a sort of psychological formula that gets to you?
Well, the first is, okay, first off
brevity.
When I get like a long, you know
a novel, I'm just not gonna get through it.
Uh, obviously, and this is hard to control
but they reference someone you know, or they w- they
they make a connection, "We're both graduates of Berkeley
" or, "I met you, I came up to you and said hi to you at Cannes
" or, "We have a mutual friend," or
"I too was raised by a single.
..
" They make some sort of personal connection
and they make the ask very crisply, "I'm writing 'cause I'd love some advice around this.
" "I'm writing 'cause I'd like an introduction.
" "I'm writing 'cause I'm applying for your position for managing editor for Prop G Media.
" Just like get to the point, what's the ask
and try and make some sort of personal connection.
And the other thing I would say, although I hate
you know, and I don't wanna encourage people to do this
be persistent, 'cause a lot of times I get an email and I think
"Oh, that's a good kid.
I should really set up a call or something
" and then I go on to the next 85 emails I have
and I don't even remember getting that email.
So, I would say don't be afraid to hit again and just say
"Hey, just putting it in the top of your inbox.
Know you're busy.
If I can grab 10 minutes of your time
I'd be really appreciative.
" And also, don't get discouraged if they don't get back to you.
That's okay.
It's not a reflection on you.
Go onto the next.
Just don't.
..
Write it off.
That's okay.
D- don't worry about it, don't worry about it.
I have a, I have a bubbling thesis on this that
um, if you just taught kids, you know
your kids, my k- future kids how to ask for things in life
the impact that that would have on their long-term trajectory is unbelievably profound.
Because I c- if I think back through my life
when I was 18 years old stealing those pizzas in Manchester
or every step along the way, some of my big
pivotal moments in my trajectory were sending an email.
Yeah.
And yeah, pretty, like, yeah, pretty much all of them started with sending an email.
But we don't teach people how to send an email
and you're- Right.
.
..
you're on the receiving end of thousands of emails every month
or, or whatever, so you can see bad and good from a bird's-eye view.
And the things you've just said there, I completely agree with
the, the size of the, the message
um, s- being specific in the ask
as you said, um, playing to ego in some way
letting them know that you've read something you've done
or you're interested in them- Yeah.
.
..
or you know someone, all those things
has such a big, such a big impact.
And I think if you think about your life and you go
"Okay, I'm gonna live for a h- I'm gonna live 100 years
and I'm probably gonna ask for things 10
000 times," if I can increase my success rate of those asks by 10% because I'm just more thoughtful in how I ask for things
my life could end up in a completely different place.
Mm-hmm.
Kind of like what you said about you only need a couple of wins to really be successful in life
you only need, if you send 10 e- 10 emails
you only need like one person to say
"Yes, I'll invest.
" That's it.
And, and be willing to endure the rejection of the nine.
I had a kid, this young kid come up to me
I was just in Cannes, um, "I'm a big fan.
Can I take a picture with you, a selfie?
" "Yeah.
" Boom, 10 seconds, take a selfie.
Sent me an email yesterday with a picture of the selfie and said
"We met.
We didn't have a chance to say hi.
I'm struggling with.
..
" Um, and he was quite vulnerable.
He told me about some of the stuff he was going through and said
"I'm struggling.
" And, uh, "Would you mind doing a 10 or 15-minute call with me?
" And he includes a picture of me and him.
How the fuck am I gonna say no to that
right?
Anyway, there, you know, there's all sorts of tricks and trades
but the willingness to take that risk, the willingness to reach out to strangers
that's the key to success.
That's, I mean, it's the reason I have kids.
It's the reason I'm wealthy.
Um, nothing wonderful is gonna happen to you without
um, uh, taking an uncomfortable risk.
So, I think about this with my boys.
I used to force them or ask them to speak to a stranger every time we were outside of the house.
My oldest one has no problem, my youngest one doesn't like it.
Really hard.
"Okay, we just sit outside the door for 10 minutes.
Just go ask them what breed their dog is over there.
Just go over there, just ask them about their dog.
" 'Cause he, I think a good strategy
especially for young men who, uh, for some reason seem to be sequestering and becoming much more isolated
whenever you're in a line, talk to the person in front of you and behind you.
Just talk to them.
Just get used to opening.
Just get used to eye contact.
Just get used to being friendly and having a conversation.
'Cause I think people are spending so much time indoors and behind screens
they're losing the ability to establish professional and personal connection
so I think a certain cognitive behavior or
or training around how to be friendly and how to endure rejection.
One of the most revealing things I've, I've noticed about you as a person is what you just said about that kid that emailed you yesterday.
Mm-hmm.
Because as you said it, I could see the emotion in your face.
Yeah, look, what do you want?
As a species, you wanna feel certain things
right?
You wanna feel.
..
You know, the most rewarding things are sensations and feelings.
And I get really moved by these kids sometimes
you know, you relate to them.
I relate to young men who are struggling 'cause I was one of them.
And so this stuff really, sometimes, i- you know
y- what you want in life is a
a group of people who are emotionally invested in your success
and then as you get older, the most rewarding thing is to let other people let you be emotionally invested in their success
right?
I want my boys to love me, but what is the most rewarding thing is that they let me love them.
That's the most rewarding thing, right?
They are these vessels that I get to pour this like
affection into.
That's the most rewarding thing as you get older.
So yeah, I think about this stuff a lot
and I get- Why did he move you?
Well, just the picture.
And I, I, I don't wanna divulge
but he's struggling.
He's really going through some issues, uh
uh, with addiction and self-harm.
..
. and depression.
And, and also, by the way, is obviously a very talented kid
is very smart, is working in.
..
You know, has a high-profile job, and is struggling with addiction and self-harm.
I mean, and, and you think, "Jesus
this shit is real," right?
"This is really, really tough for this kid.
" And, uh, you just realize, I think so many young people
we're raising.
..
My colleague at NYU wrote this book that's
this is the book we wish we'd written.
Uh, The Anxious Generation, Jonathan Haidt.
Oh, yeah.
It's literally the most inf- he's now the most influential scholar probably globally.
And the takeaway is we're raising, despite our prosperity in the US
we're raising the most anxious, depressed, obese
and addicted generation in history.
And you can just sense it.
There's so many young people out there that are really struggling
that aren't happy, that don't have the opportunities that my generation had
and then 200 time- 210 times a day
they're reminded that they're not doing well as someone else vomits their faux success and experiences all over them.
That, "Oh wait, I didn't make, I didn't
I didn't make a million dollars in NVIDIA and I'm not partying in Saint-Tropez
I'm a failure?
" Right?
And there, there are opportunities for professional and romantic success are going down.
People aren't dating.
One out of three men under the age of 30 has a girlfriend.
Yeah, I mean, there's just so many.
..
You can just tell young people are really
really struggling.
And I think about that a lot, and
uh, you know what?
It moves me because a few fortunate decisions
a few random emails, you know, things could have been much different for me.
And I, I, so I really, I do relate to these
especially the young men.
I relate to the struggles they're facing.
You s- you talked about making decisions in The Algebra of Wealth.
Um, I get asked this a lot
um, uh, kids come up to me at the end of a talk that I do or some other event and will ask me about decisions
like- Yeah.
.
..
jump-off points in their life.
As you zoom out on life, is there anything that I can know about how to be a great decision-maker over the context of 50 years of life?
Yeah.
Is there anything about how to make a decision?
Greatness is in the agency of others.
You're, you're not.
..
This bus- the business you built is not gonna get beyond a certain point unless you have the ability to attract and retain really talented people.
Great decisions are in the agency of others.
We have some weird notion of leadership.
I used to think leadership, when I was a younger man
was quickly assessing the situation, deciding what we should do
and then advocating for my course of action.
That was leadership.
And it was more important to be, to be right than effective
or to get people to agree with my decision than to make the right decision.
What you want is you wanna get to the correct decision that has the best outcome for everybody and be open to change and evolving.
And the way you do that, I don't make a big decision now without speaking to at least three people.
So you wanna make better decisions?
Then slow the process down, you're slow and fast thinking
and get the benefit of other people and expertise.
Is there any decision that I should make slow versus fast?
Is there a framework for how to know what.
..
You know, sometimes I think, I find in business that the cost is the time I waste trying to make the decision.
And then sometimes in business, the cost is the outcome of the decision.
Well, yeah, there's been books written about this
but basically every day there's thousands or hundreds of decisions you have to make instantly.
Like, do I go on the red light?
Do I not go?
Do I.
..
You know.
There's a ton of things you have to do
saying "Thank you," "Pardon me," whatever.
There's a ton of decisions you have to make every day.
So we get into a framework of sometimes where we don't slow down and have the luxury of making a good decision.
The other thing is, that I've tried to do
is I try to screen out unimportant decisions.
And this is a luxury, but as I've gotten a little bit of money
I don't make decisions around anything.
I mean, this sounds weird.
I don't order, when I'm in a restaurant
I don't order.
I basically ask the waiter to order for me.
I have a uniform at work.
I don't pick out my own clothes.
I have a group of people who manage.
..
You know what I'm saying?
You're in charge of all decisions here.
I try to focus only on the decisions I can bring a lot of value to so I can spend a lot of time being really thoughtful about them.
Um, but generally speaking, for a young person that's not in a position of outsourcing a lot of decision-making
what I would say is get a kit- again
goes back to the notion of a kitchen cabinet.
Get a group of people who will.
..
You might end up at the same place
but they'll say, "Have you thought about this?
" Or, "Why wouldn't you just do.
..
Why wouldn't you just have, you know
do X, Y, or Z?
" Or I think, you know, who have the leadership skills and know you well enough to go
"You know, Steven, I think you're making a mistake here.
" When I was 26, I started a company called Prophet Brand Strategy
a strategy firm.
Six years later, when I was 33
I was offered 55 million for it, uh
from SapientNitro and another firm called Cyient.
55 million.
I owned 60, 70% of the company.
So I would've been done, but I was under the about
"No, this is the internet.
It's gonna be huge.
Uh, we're gonna be worth a billion.
" I, if I just had a board
if I just called a couple people, they would
I know they would've said, "What the fuck are you thinking?
" I was doing three million a year in consulting
and this firm offered me $55 million.
If I had just talked to someone, they would kind of go
"Let me get the.
..
Okay, so Scott, you've been offered 18 times revenues for a small strategy services company?
" Also, around relationships, right?
When I talk to some of my friends or younger men I know who are really upset with their spouse
I'm like, "Be clear.
Yeah, this is an issue, but you're not bringing a lot of generosity and forgiveness to the relationship.
And if you don't bring those things, your marriage to this person or anyone else is not gonna survive.
" I didn't figure this out till I was older.
But you will always naturally inflate your own contribution to the relationship and some- and
and diminish theirs.
..
. and the relationship is never gonna be in perfect harmony or balance
so in those periods of deficit, you've got to bring forgiveness.
You've gotta bring patience.
Otherwise, no long-term relationship is gonna survive.
And also, be pretty clear, if you split up right now
just know you're gonna lose 70% of your net worth
maybe 60 but plan on 70.
You split everything, and then the cost of lawyers.
..
And I can guarantee you, if you have to sell a house
that'll be the exact wrong moment to sell it.
It's just karma.
Just karma.
So, just keep in mind, there's a lot of good reasons to stay together in a marriage and try and figure it out.
Is marriage good for wealth?
Oh, yeah.
Really?
'Cause I don't wanna lose 50, 70% of my money or whatever.
Well, you'll have that guy on, who's on TikTok all over the place saying it's a failed technology.
The majority of really wealthy people, uh
have long-term relationships and are in a monogamous relationship.
They're married because the team is a fantastic way to build wealth.
But if, if the stats are true and
you know, 50-whatever, 50-whatever percent of people are getting divorces
doesn't that mean if I'm building wealth there's a 50-odd percent chance that I'm gonna lose half of it if I'm married
or more?
Well, first off, if you have wealth going in
get a prenup.
Yeah.
But what I would say is, um.
..
And first off, that number's a bit misleading because marriage is becoming a luxury item.
Two, uh, it used to be 95% of wealthy people got married and 85% of middle class and poor people got married.
It's dropped to less than half among poor people.
The bottom line is no one wants to mate with poor men
and, uh, wealthy people attract a lot of mates.
And generally speaking, really wealthy people.
..
I mean, there's all this, you know
there's all these.
..
It's fun to do TikToks about Jeff Bezos on a
on a yacht with his new girlfriend and everything
but the majority of wealthy people are actually
uh, uh, stay married, and the team is really powerful.
You know, we're both working together.
We're both making a lot of money.
That is really powerful in sharing one set of expenses.
You're gonna focus on the logistics of our life or our family
and my wife's the professional baller, right?
The team, the team is powerful.
So this notion that you shouldn't get married or.
..
I'm not s- I'm not suggesting that marriage is for anybody or stay
stay married no matter what.
I'm not suggesting that at all, but there's just no getting around it.
The team is much more powerful than the individual
and if you, if you break down the numbers of people who are wealthy
they, generally speaking, invest a lot in their relationships.
Wealth is a whole-person project.
There's a myth that rich people are bad people.
The Elizabeth Warren, Bernie Sanders, that billionaires crawled over other people to get there.
It's just not true.
What you generally find among wealthy people, especially people who've made their own money
is that the rea-.
..
One of the reasons they're wealthy is they've collected allies along the way.
And just as compounding is so powerful with small investments when you're young
bringing some generosity to people when they need help
being a good friend, occasionally checking in
"How are you doing?
" Helping people find jobs when they lose a job
being kind.
Those little investments you make as a young person really add up
and you're gonna find this.
I have all these great friendships now with people who I was never great friends with.
But because we made small investments in each other over 20 or 30 years
just checked in, "How you doing?
Congrats on how you're doing this.
Congrats on your wedding.
" Maybe not even close friends.
You wake up in your 50s, and you have millions of dollars in terms of a relationship.
You feel close to these people.
You feel like a real nice sense of comity with them.
You really.
..
Uh, a- and, and this is very true of wealthy people.
You want to be put in a room of opportunity
even when you're not there.
So Google did a study.
When they put out a job opening for a product manager
they'll get 200 resumes within a few hours.
They invite the 20 best in.
80% of the time, the offer that's made is made to somebody who has a evangelist/advocate friend in the company.
So this is who you need to be.
You need to be that person who's like
"Oh, there's a job opening here?
I have this woman who would be great
" and then connects them.
You need to be in a room.
You wanna be a, a successful professionally
be successful personally.
Go out.
Make friends.
Be kind.
Invest in them.
Help them when there's no obvious reason to help them
and those investments pay off.
And generally speaking, and this isn't.
..
Not a popular narrative, the majority of very wealthy people I have met
and I've met a lot of them, are kind.
They're generous, very civic-minded, very good mates.
So this trope of, you know, of Monty Burns lighting cigars with the $100 bills and owning the
the nuclear power plant and pouring, you know
radioactive waste into the river, that's a cartoon.
The majority of self-made people who are really wealthy are good
kind people, because you have to have allies along the way to be really successful.
Can anyone start a, a company, in your view?
Can anyone become a successful entrepreneur?
Oh, no.
Y- There's, there's certain attributes that most people don't have.
What are those traits?
First and foremost, you have to be really risk-aggressive and have that willingness to fail.
You're willing to take huge risks.
I speak to people all the time who say
"Well, I'm gonna go get a job at Google or JP Morgan for a few years
and then I'll have the credibility to start a business.
" I'm like, "You're not an entrepreneur.
" Most entrepreneurs.
..
70% of entrepreneurs are immigrants that don't have access to corporate Britain or corporate America.
By the way, if you have access to Google.
..
All these kids come to my office hours.
When I say kids, I mean students
and they wanna ask.
..
They don't wanna talk about brand strategy.
They wanna talk about careers, and they say
"Oh, I have an offer from JP Morgan or Google
but I'm thinking about starting my own business
and I know you've started a lot of business.
" And they think I'm gonna say, "Go for it.
" I'm like, "Don't be a fucking idiot.
Go to work for Google.
"On a risk-adjusted basis, the most unbelievable platform for generating wealth and opportunity and long-term economic security is the American corporation.
These are unbelievable platforms to get rich with some certainty slowly and sometimes quickly in the tech community.
If you have access to those platforms, unless you hate it and are terrible at it
you should go that way.
The majority of entrepreneurs are immigrants.
And why, why is that?
Because they didn't have any choice.
They didn't have access to corporate America.
They had to open a dry cleaner.
They had to start a soapstone company.
Entrepreneurship, you have to be risk-aggressive, willing to take risks.
Two, to be really successful at it
you have to be, um, a great salesperson.
You have to be willing to convince people to invest
buy your products.
You have to be willing, most importantly
to sell people on your vision and believe that you're a good person
and that if you're successful, they're gonna be successful.
What's the best way to train that muscle
if I'm young?
Gosh, I don't know.
For me it was, um .
..
Look, I, I think the core competence you would want any kid
your kid to inherit, if I could give my kids any skill.
..
I remember in the toniest preschools and, or I'm sorry
high schools, they had Mandarin.
And that was just stupid.
Or computer science.
I believe that replacing history and civics class with computer science
you get Mark Zuckerberg, you get these mendacious fucks who are billionaires but don't care about the health of the commonwealth.
The greatest skill you can develop or that you would want your kids to have that will stand the test of time is storytelling.
The ability to craft a narrative and then convince people
get people engaged in your narrative and think
"Oh, your company makes sense.
" You're not gonna come in and say
"I'm starting a software company.
" You're gonna say, "This is the technology.
This is the marketplace.
This is why society needs this.
These are our unique skill set.
" And you can craft it into a story that is compelling
right?
It's the key, it's the key to scoring above your weight class romantically
Communicating a plan, communicating kindness, communicating empathy
communicating, um, humor, right?
Any industry, Jeff Bezos' 1997 shareholder letter
you read that letter, you just wanna buy stock.
I don't care how overvalued it is.
When you listen to Jensen Huang talk about the future of AI and biology and healthcare
you're like, "Well, maybe I should buy it even though it's trading at 110 times earnings.
" If you wanna be a great CEO
you gotta be a great s- .
..
I don't care if you're Maya Angelou, Rishi Sunak
or you know, Jensen Huang, the core competence of any really successful person or the core competence that's gonna get you real influence and economic security is storytelling.
So, uh, th- the, it's so interesting because
um, I completely agree with everything you've said about how at the very heart of wealth creation as an entrepreneur
but, but more generally in life, whether you wanna be a president or prime minister or a philanthropist
is this idea to craft narrative, but
um, the average, how does the average person develop that skill when they don't
they're not a lecturer, they don't have students that they can speak in front of
they don't have a podcast necessarily that people are gonna listen to?
But if we both agree that it's such an integral skill
a transformative life skill.
Oh, there's a million ways.
The f- w- the first thing I assign my students
my kids in the class is, pick a medium.
It can be Instagram.
Mm-hmm.
It can be X, it can be threads
it can be Pinterest, LinkedIn, public presentations
speaking, radio podcasting.
Identify what it would mean to be in the top 1%.
You can go online.
What are the top 1% of followers on Instagram?
How many followers do you need to be in the top 1% on Instagram?
By the end of this semester, you need to be a top 1% storyteller on a medium.
I'm really good at this.
You're really good at podcasting.
I'm really good in front of a large crowd.
I'm not very good on the phone.
I'm pretty terrible one-on-one.
Hmm.
I come across as aloof yet insecure at the same time
which isn't easy to do.
So I know the medium, I'm not good on the phone.
I'm, I've become a proficient writer.
I, I aspire to be a great writer.
I'm good now.
Someday I'll be great.
But I know my mediums and I practice storytelling every day.
I'm either writing, I'm either speaking, I'm either podcasting.
If you're young, oh my God, the mediums
are you good on TikTok?
Get a smartphone, get a, you know
iMovie, start editing, and every day make small iterations and changes and commit to being a s- great storyteller.
And the wonderful things about these mediums in the economy and these technologies is you can be a great storyteller anywhere
from any background and from any location.
I'm not suggesting that you, that everybody has the same opportunities
but the opportunities, the reason why Hollywood is struggling
the reason why the writers for striking for four months only got a 5% increase in pay
is that there are 1.
7 billion people on TikTok, and 850 million of them are creators
which is a fancy term for storyteller.
And assume 1% of them are outstanding storytellers
all of a sudden, eight and a half million new storytellers have come into the media market
and the half a million in LA who think their work is so fucking precious and are trying to figure out why their industry is in decline
like, you're competing against eight and a half million new storytellers that aren't asking for pet bereavement leave or for a trailer with catered food.
The ability to tell, craft a narrative
find your medium and then say, "I'm gonna be in the top 1%.
" What is the algebra to storytelling, if there had to be one?
If you, I know you've not had time to think about this.
Oh, that's really interesting.
I'm thought about that.
I think of it as, one, you just have to be a compelling.
..
I mean, it sounds terrible, but y- I
I have a handsome voice.
Mm-hmm.
I was, I have a face for podcasting.
I've had five TV shows.
They've all been canceled within like four weeks.
Podcasting is my medium.
Television is, television is not.
You've done really well.
..
. on podcasting and video, right?
That says something.
I would say that more than anything, it's tapping into people's emotions.
Like, how do you make someone feel something?
I mean, you wanna be smart, you wanna say interesting things
but how do you really connect with someone and make them feel something?
The white space I'm trying to occupy is
I'm trying to be a white heterosexual male in his 50s who's open about his emotions.
That's a white space.
Guys my age don't talk about their failures
they don't talk about the way they feel about their kids
they don't talk about, you know, how devastated they were when their mother died.
That shit's just not talked about among men of my demographic.
That's the white space I'm occupying.
So you need to say, okay, what am I gonna make people feel that other people aren't spending a lot of time evoking
getting people to understand those emotions?
It's, uh, I think the specific crowds out the general
you wanna focus on a niche, own something.
All right, I'm gonna be in the top 1% of this medium
and I'm gonna develop domain expertise.
I'm gonna be the person that understands Ethiopian cuisine
and I'm gonna bring romance and make people feel something
and I'm gonna connect it to family, and I'm gonna connect it to African culture
and I'm gonna connect it to maternal love and c- whatever it is.
But think about it, what emotions do you want people to feel?
And then every day, it's just hand-to-hand combat
every day.
You know, w- before when we were off mic
you said we were both kind of.
..
In the last two years, both of our careers have sort of hit a tipping point.
I feel like I've worked my ass off for 35 years
and all of a sudden, I'm an overnight success.
And you said, "What was the one thing?
" And I can't point to any one thing.
It was a series of little things.
It's kinda the Mr.
Beast secret sauce.
It's iteration.
Every day, they test things.
They make things just a tiny bit better.
So commit to excellence.
You put out a podcast, you put out a Medium post
you put out a PowerPoint presentation lever- about AI
whatever it is, try and find a mechanism for feedback and commit to just being a little bit better the next time you do it.
I'm gonna let you in on a little secret.
What is in the Diary of a CEO cup
this cup that sits in front of me when I interview these people
sometimes for three hours, and sometimes three people a day?
And the answer is this, Perfecta.
I invested in the company on Dragons' Den
and since then, they've gone from an idea to the fastest-growing energy drink in the UK.
It is a matcha energy drink, and it is absolutely delicious.
But that's not why I choose to drink it on this podcast.
The reason I choose to drink it is because it gives me what I call all-day energy.
It.
..
I don't get the same crashes that I used to get with other energy drinks.
If you're in the middle of a conversation or you're in the middle of a talk on stage or in the boardroom
the last thing you wanna do is have a crash.
You don't want jitters and you need focus.
And that is why they now sponsor this podcast.
Not only is it delicious, but it gives me a significant competitive advantage.
If you haven't tried it, go down to a Tesco
go to a Waitrose, or go online and use the code DIARY10 at checkout
and you'll get 10% off.
And when you do try it, let me know how you get on.
I'm very keen to understand how you invest your money.
So say I'm, uh, I'm working at McDonald's
like, m- or Burger King, or whatever
and I say these places not to sort of diminish the
the value of the work, because I worked four or five years of my life in places like call centers and the McDonald's
et cetera.
But just as that's the, the jump-off point for many people
I get up to manager or position, I have a little bit of disposable income now.
Mm-hmm.
Should I be going all in on crypto?
Or my friend has this company, he said it's gonna work
should I be betting my money there?
Over the, uh, long-term time horizon, where have you invested your money and made the most returns
and where should I?
Well, just do as I say, not as I do.
I always went all in on things.
And when you go all in on something
if it hits the ground or blows up
you're kinda done, and you don't have any capital
and you can end up.
..
I ended up broke at, uh.
In '99, I was looking at jets.
By 2000, after the dot bomb ex- implosion
I was broke, crawled my way back
was wealthy again by 2007, all in on tech.
By the end of 2008, I was broke again.
And what I have learned since then is
I've crawled my way back, gotten very lucky
the markets have boomed, but now I diversify like crazy
and the- What does diversify mean?
You're never more than a certain amount of your net worth in any one thing
and you try and make sure those things aren't correlated to each other.
It's harder when you're young because you may have to go all in on a house.
You may have to put every penny you have to buy your first home.
When you start a business when you're young
you don't have the luxury of diversifying.
You have to.
..
I bet you kinda went all in on this business at some point.
But as soon as you have the opportunity to diversify.
..
I'm about to put money in an aircraft maintenance company in El Salvador.
I love it.
It's totally different than anything I do.
That way, if my world goes to shit again in tech
I have someone making money fixing planes in El Salvador.
I do a bunch of just different weird businesses that aren't related
because over time, because of demographics and technology
productivity does grow up in our economy and the markets go up.
The best advice I can give any young person
in terms of the actual investment, is a low-cost ETF.
You don't want fees to eat up.
You don't want to day trade.
80 to 95% of people who day trade lose money.
You wanna be in a low-cost diversified, um
ETF.
What's an ETF?
Exchange-traded fund.
So they basically say, "Okay, we're gonna create a synthetic of the entire market and all healthcare stocks.
" So like I could, I could invest in a tech E- ETF or a solar ETF or- That's right.
.
or a, I don't know, a AI ETF?
Let me make it easy.
Go to Vanguard.
Um, I don't have a relationship with Vanguard.
SPY, that's the index that tracks the S&P 500.
Mm-hmm.
And so people.
..
The email I get most is from young men looking for guidance and mothers looking for guidance for their
for their sons.
The second most frequent email is the following
"Is it too late to invest in Nvidia?
"And the honest answer is, I don't know.
I can imagine a scenario where it gets cut by 80%.
I can c- imagine a scenario where it triples.
So this is what you do.
You invest in SPY, because about 20% on the dollar will go into the Magnificent Seven
because they're about 20% of the market cap of the S&P.
SPY is, again, a basket of different stocks.
It's, it's a index fund that mimics the S&P.
So there are 500 companies in the S&P.
NVIDIA's probably 3 or 5% of the total value of the S&P
so five cents on your dollar goes into NVIDIA.
Mm.
Right?
About 20%.
..
Is that right?
24, 25% is the Magnificent Seven, the tech companies we talk about.
25 cents on your dollar will go to them.
So assume those companies double, great, you participate.
But assume the other 493 companies finally get their time in the sun and those companies go down a half
you're still fine.
You're still fine.
Again, you don't need to find the needle in the haystack and stop believing
in a very American way, that you can figure it out.
I know the brightest people in finance, and what I
the, the, my net conclusion is that none of them have any fucking idea.
Some have a little bit more of an idea
but if you look at the entire alternative investments industry
hedge funds, private equity funds, mutual funds
anyone on CNBC, if you took all of their returns and aggregate
they're less than the S&P by the amount of their fees.
It's one of the greatest grifts in the modern economy
is believing that some guy who looks old and unhappy and has suspenders and went to Harvard knows more about the markets than you.
All you need to know is diversification, right
SPY, start saving young, and then the next best piece of advice is
if you can, if you can, forced savings.
98% of us will spend everything we get our hands on.
It is very hard to have the discipline to take money that is within your grasp and invest it.
Forced savings plan.
Find out at work if they have profit-sharing or IRAs or Roths
whatever the, the.
..
I forget what it's called here, where if you put some money aside
the government matches it.
Pensions?
Well, not only pensions, but there's something here
I forget what it's called.
If you save 5,000 pounds through your work
the government, I think, will match it
uh, put in 1,000 pounds.
There's all sorts of saving schemes at work.
Acorns, the apps that round up to the nearest dollar and then immediately shoot it into SPY.
Try as hard as you can to put yourself in a position where you invest despite your best efforts not to.
'Cause the majority of us will get that money and go buy a flat-screen TV.
And when you're saying investing, I think
because it can s- sometimes sound complicated from someone that's so far away from it
there's apps on our phones now- Yeah.
.
where we can, in a couple of minutes
invest in the exact thing you've just said.
From, we can make ac- an account in a couple of minutes that'll probably ask for our passport
take a photo of our passport.
There's so many different apps where you can go in and invest in the S&P 500.
You don't need- That's right.
.
to call someone or know someone.
And you can invest.
What's the minimum you can invest, $50?
A dollar.
Public, go to public.
com.
Y- I mean, start with a basic
a basic low-cost ETF or index fund.
S- SPY if you wanna get, take a little bit more risk and you wanna be in tech
there's all sorts of ETFs and index funds around tech.
Uh, uh, you're gonna, every young person
especially a young man, is under the impression they're smarter than they are and that they can beat the market.
So okay, take 30% of your money
have some fun, buy Starbucks, NVIDIA, Unilever
Novo Nordisk, whatever you think you have insight into
so you can learn a life lesson that over the long term you don't know what you're doing
and just put it in an index fund.
'Cause the marvelous thing about the human race is we become more productive
and the Western economies, generally speaking, over the medium and long term are up and to the right.
And again, and I'll go back to my algorithm
or equation, focus.
Find something you could be good at, maybe great
that has a 90-plus percent employment rate.
Stoicism, we haven't talked about that.
Realize there's some things you can't control.
Focus on the things you can control.
One thing that is within your control is spending.
Try and find a partner.
Try and gamify spending.
I spent $78 a week my summer between my junior and senior year
including rent, because I needed $3,300 to go back to school.
I partnered with five other guys in my fraternity and we gamified who could spend the least amount of money.
Find a partner who's aligned with you around spending and saving
right?
Realize no one's as impressed or thinking about your shit as much as you are
F- try and find reward from exercise, from relationships
not from signaling wealth with kind of stupid shit
right?
I call that stoicism.
It's really more about discipline.
Develop a savings muscle.
One, an appreciation for time and how fast it's gonna go.
I was stupid.
I remember my best friend, Lee Lotus
picking me up to go to the beach when I was college
and he was scrambling to find $2,000 to put it into something called an IRA Roth
where his company, a bank he was working for
he was just outta college, if he found $2
000, they would match it with another 2
000.
I thought, I said to him these exact words
"If 2,000 bucks means anything to me when I'm older
shoot me.
" I have made so much more, much more money than Lee Lotus
and he is a multimillionaire now.
So am I.
But I've endured a lot more risk and a lot more ups and downs
'cause he was that lame guy scraping together $2
000 when he was 23.
I went out and spent my first bonus check at Morgan Stanley.
I got $28,000 my first year out of college
Morgan Stanley, $28,000 check.
I go out and I buy a $35
000 BMW, hung swim goggles from the rear view mirror thinking that would impress people.
I don't know what I was doing.
I figured out if I had bought a Hyundai for 9
000 bucks, which you could get in 1987 or whatever it is
and invested the other 20 in SPY, never looked at it again
I would have enough money now to buy 11 Ferraris
including that new electric Ferrari that for some reason appeals to me
which makes no sense, an electric Ferrari.
Anyways-You're gonna love this.
I tell the people who work for me that I drive up in a Ferrari and I say
"If you work really hard, someday, someday I'll have two Ferraris.
"   Anyways.
Uh, I don't have a Ferrari, by the way.
I- I- my other joke about a Ferrari is
Ferrari is like having a long consistent erection.
I don't have a Ferrari.
Anyways,  anyways, where were we going?
Uh, realize people aren't as impressed with your shit as you are.
Recognize the power of time.
And then the thing where I really screwed up
Steven, diversification.
Take some money off the table.
Invest in.
..
I'm hearing from employees in Nvidia, we talked about this
diversify.
You get.
..
it's such a bulletproof Kevlar for your mental health.
You get risk-free return.
Nobody knows, anything can happen.
Amazon 1999, again, lost 90% of its value.
Do you know the kind of mental anguish when you go into a stock like Amazon and you lose 90% of your
of your investments?
So if you want to have some fun
ring fence it to 30% of your, of your savings
pick some stuff, and it'll be a good life lesson for you.
You may get lucky.
More power to you.
Over time, you're going to realize nothing beats over the long term.
..
Warren Buffett, what, the third wealthiest man in the world?
I'm giving you the same answer he gives.
If someone has 10,000 bucks, how do they invest?
And he's like, low-cost index funds.
It's a two-and-a-half-hour conversation.
That concludes it.
Put it in the S&P 500.
Low, low-cost index fund.
I know, it's, it's the boring shit that makes you rich.
Yeah.
It's also, I, I, I buy a lot of CEOs.
It's the boring incremental stuff that moves shareholder value.
Mm-hmm.
No, it's so true.
So one of the things that stopped me when I was young from doing exactly what you just said is
I didn't think that the $500 I had or the 500 pounds that I had was enough to get started.
So I said to myself, in my head
I thought, "Okay, when I get a million
I'll become an investor.
" And I think a lot of people actually listen to these kind of conversations and go
"Okay, once I've, once I've got 5
000 pounds disposable income a month, then I'll do what Scott said.
But there's no point in doing it with a small amount of money.
" No.
I wanted to use this little bucket of sand here as an analogy for this because
um, my team brought a bucket of sand to illuminate the power of compounding interest when you invest in these S&P 500 companies.
And this glass represents investing 1,000 a month in the S&P 500 over the course of 12 months
starting at the age of 25.
Right.
But if you left it and kept investing at that rate
by the age of 65, it would look like this.
You have Zuma Beach.
Zuma.
Ah.
Oh, my God.
Thank God that's you.
Jesus Christ.
It would look like that.
And this is really what you're saying when you're talking about ETFs?
Well, when you asked that question about the young man who says
"I'm gonna wait till I get.
..
I have 500 pounds, I'm gonna wait till I have a million before I start investing.
" The way you get a million pounds is by investing that 500.
We don't believe we're gonna get old.
We don't recognize how fast time is gonna go.
We don't appreciate the power of compound interest.
Don't focus on your investments.
Put it in low-cost, low-energy ETFs.
Start early.
You have ti- Your advantage when you're young is time
and you're gonna get that bucket of sand.
By the way, this right here isn't a lesson in investing.
This is a lesson in storytelling.
A bucket of sand?
I mean, who thinks of this?
Oh, my gosh.
I'm moving it out the way.
No, but it is, it is.
Uh, uh, I've, I, um, I discovered the art and the science of compounding interest too late in my life.
Yeah, most people do.
And I just wish someone had slapped me in the face with it at 18.
Yeah, it's crazy.
Honestly, I probably started at 28.
That's still earlier than most people, but it goes to the notion of back to the advice for a young person.
Most young people don't have the discipline to invest any money they get their hands on
'cause the capitalist economy is a.
..
The, the smartest people in the world with the most godlike technology are presenting you with amazing
irresistible offers to upgrade from economy to economy comfort
to add, to add flourless chocolate cake to your order from Balthazar boulangerie in one minute or less.
I'm like, "Oh, my God.
Oh, wait, there's three other people looking at this room
this hotel room, and it's going on sale
and I better bu-" It's so difficult to hold onto any money.
You want to find ways of forced savings.
A house is forced savings to a certain extent
'cause people don't want to be evicted from their house.
Going to work for a company and getting options and getting equity that grows tax deferred
that's sort of forced savings.
But you want to, as a young person
try and find as many ways as possible to have forced savings.
An app that, that rounds up to the nearest dollar and then invests no matter what
that is forced savings.
It is very difficult to take money that is in
ever comes through your hands, and invest it.
So, uh, find forced savings mechanisms that are taken out of your check.
Find out if your company offers any sort of investment or savings schemes that they match or that the government matches.
And most corporations offer something.
Real estate.
I've had a lot of guests talk to me like Morgan Housel and others that have a sort of mixed view- Yeah.
.
..
on whether real estate is a good investment.
What's your thoughts on it?
Should I be investing in real estate?
Well, you know, my brother said something to me when I was 25.
He said, "Steve, if everybody is playing the game
the returns probably aren't great from it.
" Goes back to sex appeal.
Too much capital going in.
L- look, uh, K Schiller, the brightest people in real estate will say if you really account for maintenance and upkeep
that real estate has not outperformed other asset classes.
The reason I like real estate is that
one, in the United States it's very tax advantaged.
There are very few asset classes you can lever up four to one.
20% down payment?
I can't buy Apple.
..
I can't buy $100 worth of Apple stock for 20 bucks.
So it's h- it's a huge leverage.
The interest on that is tax deductible.
In addition, if you sell a home
and this is true in the US, I own in the US
uh, I don't know, in the UK
if you buy a home and sell it after
hold onto it for at least two years
you get a $250,000 tax deduction, 500
000 for married.
So if you have, for example, any ability
get to know the, the homes in your area
find a nice home or a rental unit that you can maybe rent out or
or upgrade, maybe you're handy, to do that every few years and take advantage of the tax deduction and then roll into something bigger
and that is for savings.
You know that mortgage payment is coming every month.
Actually, the majority of savings for Baby Boomers right now is in their homes.
It's the equity in their homes.
Now, unfortunately, that's, there's some bad things
we haven't improved housing permits as quickly as we should
which has made it more expensive for entrants.
Young people can't afford homes, the average home's gone from 290 to 420 through the pandemic in the US
and if you look at interest rates, it means the average mortgage payment's gone from $1
100 to $2,300.
So it used to be 2/3 of America could afford a home
now it's 1/3.
I- I.
..
a whole other talk show, but I just did a TED Talk on the war on the young
economically, but real estate is a very tax advantaged industry.
It is for savings.
Also, there is some, I think, psychic value
which I think is important to, to a home.
You start investing in it, fixing it up
it feels like, I don't know, it's just there's something rewarding about it.
But to what your brother said, when everyone's trying to buy homes in an area
that usually means it's probably getting overvalued, and like any other asset class
uh, it can lose money.
But the reason I like it is because it is a form of forced savings.
People, generally speaking, will make that mortgage payment or try and figure out a way.
Now you want to make sure that not more than 40% of your income goes into a house
otherwise it's just gonna be your anchor, it's just gonna be a source of stress for you
and I think a lot of people grow up thinking
"I have to have a home," and so they just become over levered in their home and they become kind of house poor.
They own a house and that's it, and they can't afford to do anything else.
And they mightn't be able to, able to move then
and you talked about geographical opportunity when you're young.
That's right, you get tied.
Yeah.
You get tied down, especially if your home goes down in value.
But I still think it's a, in the US at least
real estate's the most taxed advantage, and if you own commercial real estate in the US
you can depreciate it 2% or 3% a year.
You can't depreciate a stock 2% or 3% a year.
Is there someone that should and shouldn't buy a home then
in your view?
Is there a certain demographic or age or s- person with a certain talent that should and shouldn't buy a home?
I would say in general if it's a home
if you think that you're not gonna be able to hold onto it for at least seven years
if you hold onto a home for seven years
you should be able to ride out most economic cycles or e- economic down cycle.
Um, I think there's some wonderful things about renting.
You can slam your keys down and leave if you're planning to move.
Um, if you don't have somewhat reliable sources of income
um, a mortgage is probably a tough thing.
I don't know, I think o- I think home ownership
I- I'm talking my own book a little bit here because I've made good money in real estate and I've really enjoyed it
but I think it's situational, and it goes back to that notion of having a kitchen cabinet of people who can advise you on
on, on that asset class.
Unfortunately, that asset class has become so expensive that the
quote unquote, "American dream of owning a home
" has become somewhat of a hallucination, if you will
or a fantasy for a lot of young people.
The other thing I, I came to learn as I got money
and I, it was almost like someone pulled the curtain back for me
is how wealthy individuals play the tax game.
Oh my gosh.
And it's a tax game that the average person has no idea is going on.
Got to talk about money.
Tax avoidance is a key skill to building wealth.
And by the way, people, we don't talk about
I, I speak openly about my, I won't call it tax avoidance
but my tax strategies.
If you're, you know, it's like they said
if you're a prisoner of war, you have an obligation to escape.
If you're trying to build wealth, you have an obligation to pay as little tax as possible.
Do it legally.
But Apple will issue their IP to Apple International in Ireland
and then they will use Apple Ireland, they will license their IP to America
charge them tens of billions of dollars, thereby increasing the income of Apple Ireland at a lower tax rate and decreasing the income in the US
thereby lowering their overall tax rate.
That is pure tax avoidance.
Every organization, every corporation does this to the hilt
and so should you.
By the way, I will vote for people who have an alternative minimum tax.
We have to raise taxes on corporations.
The 25 wealthiest Americans pay between 6% and 8% tax rate.
What are the tax games they're playing?
Oh.
This, the rich people?
There's a bunch of them.
First and foremost, it's you buy stocks
you never sell them, you borrow against them.
Okay, explain that to me like I'm a 10-year-old.
So- Sure.
You own $100 in Amazon stock.
Yeah.
You need money to buy something.
Instead of selling the stock, and let's say it's gone up 50%
let's say it's doubled, you would have to realize a capital gain and pay long-term capital gains on that $50 gain.
No, just borrow against it and let the stock continue to grow
and you pay a little bit of interest
hopefully from your current income, but basically it's invest
borrow against it, and die.
Put it into a, a trust and then pass it on to your kids.
There's a lot of, um, state arbitrage.
Jeff Bezos just moved to Florida to spend more time with dad.
Isn't that sweet, Steven?
Isn't that nice?
No, it has nothing to do with his father.
Give me a fucking break.
He aggregated $160 billion in wealth.
He would pay about another 8% or 10% in state taxes in Washington because he's got to leverage the public school system
the University of Washington, the Seattle-Tacoma Airport
the hospital system.
But in the US, you're allowed to peace out to Texas or Florida and pay no income tax.
So all the people shitposting California or New York-Show me someone who's crit- all of a sudden can't handle San Francisco politics
I'm gonna show you someone who needs to recognize a capital gain and has all of a sudden decided they like Texas politics.
It's really not very, it's very disingenuous.
There's, uh, the tax loophole I've leveraged.
In the US there's something called 1202, or Qualified Small Business.
So when I started L2- What's L2?
L2 is my analytics company.
I started it.
I invested a small amount of money, um
uh, because it was a business worth fi- fi- less than 50 million
your business would qualify in the US as QSB small business.
If you hold onto that stock in that company for longer than five years
when you sell it, the first 10 million
or 10 times the basis, are tax-free.
So the first 10 million out of L2 was tax-free
zero.
That makes no sense.
If that sounds like we're screwing the middle class
trust your instincts.
I invested in a company, brought a company out of bankruptcy.
I invested two and a half million.
The first 25 million got very lucky, the company got sold for a lot of money
the first 25 million were tax-free.
These are, the tax code has gone from 400 pages to 4
000, and that extra 3,600 pages are to turn rich people into super rich people.
Now, the myth around taxes is the following
that rich people don't pay their taxes.
Actually, the sort of rich pay a disproportionate amount of taxes.
So if you make all of your money from current income
that is salary, and you make a lot
you're actually paying more taxes than anyone.
So mom's a baller.
She's a partner in a prestigious law firm making a million bucks a year.
Dad's a chiropractor, has three people working for him.
He makes 600, $1.
6 million a year, total ballers.
In order to make that kind of money
they probably have to live in a urban center in a blue state
where at that level they're paying 45, 48
sometimes 52% tax rates.
But if Dad decides to raise capital and buy a bunch of chiropractic clinics and they become investments
and he sells them for $50 million, his tax rate plummets.
So you don't wanna be a super earner
you wanna earn enough money to invest so you can become a super owner.
The top 25 wealthiest Americans pay about 8% in tax
right?
So actually, the bottom half pay almost no tax.
They pay a lot of consumption taxes, but it's the super earners that get screwed
what I call the workhorses.
But once you make the jump to light speed and you own things and you make your money from buying and selling assets
your tax rate plummets.
The really sort of actionable thing there for the average person as well is probably the
the first point where you said a lot of what rich people do is they'll buy a stock.
So I'll, I'll spend 10K on Amazon stock
and then I go to a bank and the bank give me a $5
000 loan against my Amazon stock tax-free- Right.
.
..
and I just hold the Amazon stock.
Now I've got 5,000 c- tax-free.
If the Amazon stock goes to twe- uh
$20,000 in value, then I can
I can go to the bank and say
"It's gone up now, give me another $5
000.
" Far more.
And I just spend and live off that money.
Now, if the Amazon stock collapses, I'm fine because the loan was against the stock.
So they'll sell the stock at a certain point as it's collapsing to get their money back.
Yeah, I mean, you don't wanna get into too much trouble
but, uh, leverage is how smart people go broke.
But the idea is that one of the great tax schemes in history is that stocks grow.
Think of yourself as a stock.
You, you go up in value a million bucks a year.
You're making a million dollars a year doing a very successful podcast.
Every year, the government in the UK is gonna take 40 cents of that
40% of it.
If you own a million dollars in stock and it goes to two million
you don't get taxed on it till you sell it.
Yeah, so just never sell it.
Never sell it.
And that's what Elon's doing with his company.
People say he's got, you know, $200 billion
whatever.
In fact, he's borrowing tax-free against those companies.
And then when he finally needs to sell it to pay off some of those loans
he moves to Texas, despite the fact he built all his wealth in California.
Smart.
I think, uh, one of the great advantages of life is
um, a- as it relates to wealth creation
is really getting good tax advice, 'cause I've sat here over and over again with people that have great tax advice and some people who didn't have any at all.
And the outcomes are quite frankly, um
shocking.
The variance in outcomes are quite frankly shocking
from one person going bankrupt to the other person becoming a multi-billionaire.
And it comes down to, some of it comes down to their tax strategy and how they thought about tax.
And how, you know, being around a lot of people now that are masters in tax
it was like- Yeah.
Yeah, I describe it as someone pulled back a curtain that I never knew was there
and all these people were doing magic behind this curtain
and no one ever told me that curtain existed- That's right.
.
..
and it's called tax.
Well- We don't all pay the same tax.
.
because we're not supposed to talk about it.
Yeah.
Again, not talking about it is rich people trying to keep poor people down.
Because rich people talk about their taxes all the time.
Brightest woman in my entire professional universe is a woman named Lucy Lee
who is my tax Yoda, who works at a big law firm
that I pay 1,800 bucks an hour to
to figure out the smartest.
..
When I set up a company, I talk to my tax person.
When I'm about to get a big payment for my podcast distribution company
I talk to my tax person first.
This is, it is everything, but the key when you're young is to become an owner
not an earner.
You're an earner.
You want to bust a move out of earning and develop an army of capital that goes out and kills for you at night.
500 bucks is a lot of money when you're 21.
500 bucks when you're 21 is 10,000 when you're my age
right?
Mm-hmm.
And it's gonna go really fast.
So just start, and then once you become a super owner
you have 10,000, 50,000, 100
000, a million dollars in assets, then
then you can become a super tax avoider.
That is so bad.
That sounded awful, didn't it?
Yeah.
Sounded awful.
That sounded awful.
Sitting here with your bucket of sand.
Oh, my God.
Our budget melinas.
That's right.
Talk about, "This is how we fuck the middle class
Stephen.
This is how we really screw over the little guy.
"  We have a cl-  We have a closing tradition on this podcast- Oh
there we go.
.
..
where the last guest leaves a question for the next guest.
Yeah.
Not knowing who they're leaving it for.
What is the last thing you learned how to do just because you wanted to learn how to do it?
Hm.
That's really interesting.
Um, you know, it sounds.
..
Oh, this is gonna sound so trite
but my boys and I are, uh
uh.
..
You know, when you get.
When you're a dad, you, you, you.
..
I- If you're an e- egomaniac like me.
I just assumed my kids were gonna be super into World War II history and CrossFit
because I thought, "Oh, they would think I was such a hero that they'd w- get.
..
" But you realize if you wanna be a good dad
you have to be engaged in what your kids are engaged in.
Otherwise, you're just not gonna engage.
I have no interest in sports.
I have become a massive fan of Premier League football because my kids are so devoted to Chelsea and to Tottenham.
So I've taken up Arsenal so we can have a lot of fights in the house.
But what have I learned?
I've learned to love football.
And the moment my sons are out of the house
I will learn to not care about it again.
So, I've learned to love Premier League football
'cause it's a way I engage with my boys.
Well, next year, we'll go.
Yeah.
I'm a Manchester United fan, so, uh
you know.
Man U?
Yeah, yeah.
How fucking predictable.
Literally, Man U.
About to be another podcast .
You're such a poser.
You're such a- Cut there.
Cut there.
Oh, wait.
You, you grew up in Manchester, right?
Half my family did.
Okay, then- So, half my siblings were born there.
Yeah, yeah.
Then the only thing worse than that would have been Man City
but you have- Yeah.
Okay, you have Man U rights then if you're from Manchester.
Yeah.
I have to tell people this all.
..
They're like, "Wha-" Like, they.
'Cause you get roasted, and then you have to indicate that the f-.
..
Like, for me, the first place we lived in the UK was Manchester
so my older siblings were all born there
and then we moved to Devon in the Southwest
which, countryside, but.
..
One of the strongest brands in the world.
My, my six-year-old son has a friend coming.
They're gonna take the train up just to do a tour of the stadium.
Oh, really?
How many times do you do that?
So I- When will they be coming?
Uh, I think it's in a few weeks.
We're going.
..
But, I mean, we're going to Germany for the European Championships.
Ah.
We're going to the World Cup.
Our whole family, our activity, is we explore Europe
we follow, uh, we go, you know
see FC Barcelona play.
I mean, this is a position of privilege.
Mm-hmm.
But football, for us.
..
When I stopped playing sports, uh, uh
as a college student, I didn't think about sports again for 25 years
and now we're just all in on footb-.
..
They, we plan our lives on.
Not, not around football, but every week we go to a game.
It's wonderful.
I'm convinced it's one of the few safe places that men can demonstrate emotion.
Yeah.
It's one of the few places men are allowed to hug each other
feel sad, feel joy.
100%.
But it's.
..
I've been to, because I'm in the corporate world
amazing sporting event, the best sporting events in the world
the Olympics, the Super Bowl.
Nothing matches Premier League football.
Mm-hmm.
Nothing.
It really is special.
That's what I learned to do.
Hey, man.
Hey, man, well, it's super interesting because I'm.
..
I read in your work about, like
buying, people buying football clubs and stuff like that
and then they're never gonna make money, but the
the asset is basically valuable because someone else wants to buy it off you.
The greater fool theory.
And I'm getting loads of those offers now to
like, get involved in football clubs and stuff.
And, and actually, based on your thesis about men- Yeah.
.
..
it is act-.
For me, there's, there is a thesis there.
Well, the thesis is that there's.
..
The real thesis is that the number of billionaires in the US has gone from 500 to 2
500.
They're men who are in a massive mid-life crises.
The way to become the most interesting person in Cleveland is to buy the Cavaliers or the Browns.
Overnight, you're the sexiest man in Cleveland.
If you're worth $50 billion, why wouldn't you spend $5 billion to Yu- buy the Washington Commanders or
you know, to buy.
..
I think Tottenham's up for sale right now.
Yeah.
I've thought.
..
I got together the wealthiest, most famous Scottish people in the US
which is about 14 of us, and said
"Let's go buy Rangers.
" Rangers FC, it's a publicly traded company.
I had it all figured out, £10 mill- million convertible note.
I'm like, "We.
..
" And then this  guy, my friend of mine's a famous historian
a Scottish.
..
He's like, "You'd be the most hated person in the United Kingdom.
" He goes, "They would hate you.
You knew nothing about football.
You'd be some American idiot over there.
" And I'm like, "Yeah, you're right.
" He's like, "Just go to Rangers games.
"   Yeah, yeah.
He's like, "What are you thinking?
" Yeah.
There's a pain equation with buying sports teams because you're buying a tribe.
Yeah.
And the chances are you won't win most of the time.
And then you have to deal with, like
Dave from, I don't know, Southampton- Oh
yeah.
whose entire life is that football club that you've just bought
and he is pissed.
And unless you win trophies from day one
you've screwed up.
And who does?
Yeah, nobody does.
So it's a horrible pain sport.
But anyways, Scott, we're done.
I am a big Manchester United fan.
My travel all over the world.
One of the big lifesavers for me, as someone that never misses a game ever
regardless of where I am in the world
is NordVPN, because NordVPN allows me to watch the game in territories and in countries where it's often not available for a variety of different reasons.
But it's not just about football.
It's websites, movies, that I can access
and it helps me navigate those geographical blockers.
And that's why NordVPN are both a sponsor of this podcast
but a lifesaver for me.
And it costs the same as a cup of coffee per month.
And not just that, when I'm accessing Wi-Fi networks around the world
it gives me a lot of security, which is something that I think we don't think about enough.
If you wanna check out NordVPN for a limited time only
head to nordvpn.
com/doac, and you can access our exclusive deal which gives The Diary of a CEO listeners a huge discount
plus four extra months when you sign up to a two-year plan.
And there's no risk with Nord's 30-day money-back guarantee.
So give it a try.
That's nordvpn.
com/doac, or check out the episode description link below.