- What happened during World War II was
that once the Germans started to run out
of manpower, they created foreign legion groups.
But because those people were not
Aryans, they couldn't be trusted.
So they were put under the command
of Heinrich Himmler under command of SS,
and became known as SS Waffen units,
and one of such units was created in Ukraine.
- The following is a conversation with Serhii Plokhy,
a historian at Harvard University
and the director of the Ukrainian Research Institute,
also at Harvard.
As a historian,
he specializes in the history of Eastern Europe
with an emphasis on Ukraine.
He wrote a lot of great books on Ukraine
and Russia, the Soviet Union, on Slavic peoples in general,
across centuries on Chernobyl and nuclear disasters,
and on the current war in Ukraine,
a book titled The Russo-Ukrainian War,
The Return of History.
This is the Led Fridman podcast, to support it,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Serhii Plokhy.
What are the major explanations
for the collapse of the Soviet Union?
Maybe ones you agree with and ones you disagree with?
- Very often people confuse three different processes
that were taken place in the late eighties
and early nineties, and the one was the collapse
of communism as ideology.
Another was the end of the Cold War,
and the third one was the end of the Soviet Union.
All of this processes were interrelated, interconnected,
but when people provide ideology as the explanation for all
of these processes, that's why I disagree,
because ideological collapse happened on the territory
of the Soviet Union in general.
Soviet Union lost the Cold War, whether
we are talking about Moscow, Leningrad,
or St. Petersburg now, or Vladivostok.
But the fall of the Soviet Union is about a story in which
Vladivostok and St. Petersburg
ended up in one country, and Kyiv, Minsk,
and (speaks foreign language)
ended in different countries.
So the theories
and explanations about how did that happen for me,
this really very helpful theories
for understanding the Soviet collapse.
So the mobilization from below, the collapse
of the center, against the background of economic collapse,
against the background of ideological implosion.
That's how I look at the fall of the Soviet Union
and that's how I look at the theories
that explain that collapse.
- So it's a story of geography, ideology, economics,
which are the most important to understand of
what made the collapse of the Soviet Union happen?
- The Soviet collapse was unique,
but not more unique than collapse of any other empire.
So what we really witnessed,
or the world witnessed back in 1991,
and we continue to witness today
with the Russian aggression against Ukraine, is a collapse
of one of the largest world empires.
We talked about the Soviet Union,
and now talk about Russia as possessing plus, minus,
one sixth of the surface of the earth.
You don't get in possession of one sixth of the earth
by being a nation state.
You get that sort of size as an empire.
And the Soviet collapses continuation of the disintegration
of the Russian Empire that started back in 1917,
that was arrested for some period of time by the Bolsheviks,
by the communist ideology,
which was internationalist ideology,
and then came back in full force in the late eighties
and early nineties.
So the most important story for me, this is the story
of the continuing collapse of the Russian Empire
and the rise of not just local nationalism,
but also rise of Russian nationalism that turned out to be
as a destructive force for the imperial
or multi-ethnic, multinational state,
as was Ukrainian nationalism or Georgian
or Estonian for that matter,
- Well you said a lot of interesting stuff there in 1917,
Bolsheviks, internationalists, how that plays with the idea
of Russian Empire and so on.
But first, let me ask about US influence on this.
So one of the ideas is that, you know, through the Cold War,
that mechanism, US had made your interest
to weaken the Soviet Union,
and therefore the collapse could be attributed to pressure
and manipulation from the United States.
Is there truth to that?
- The pressure from the United States,
this is part of the Cold War
and Cold War part of that story,
but it doesn't explain the Soviet collapse.
And the reason is quite simple.
The United States of America didn't want
the Soviet Union to collapse and disintegrate.
They didn't want that at the start of the Cold War in 1948.
We now have the strategic documents.
They were concerned about that.
They didn't wanna do that,
and certainly they didn't wanna do that
in the 1991, as late August of 1991,
the month of the coup, in Moscow,
president Bush, George HW Bush travels from Moscow
to Kyiv and gives famous,
or infamous speech called Chicken Kyiv speech,
basically warning Ukrainians against going for independence.
The Soviet collapse was a huge headache
for the administration in the White House
for a number of reasons.
They liked to work with Gorbachev.
The Soviet Union was emerging as a junior partner
of the United States on the international arena.
Collapse destroyed all of that.
And on the top of that, there was a question
of the nuclear weapons, unaccounted nuclear weapons.
So the United States was doing everything humanly possible
to keep the Soviet Union together in one piece
until really late November of 1991, when it became clear
that it was, it was a lost cause
and they had to say goodbye to Gorbachev
and to the project that he introduced.
A few months later,
or a year later, there was a presidential campaign,
and Bush was running for the second term
and was looking for achievements.
And there were many achievements.
I basically treat him with great respect,
but destruction of the Soviet Union
was not one of those achievements.
He was on the other side of that divide.
But the politics, the political campaign,
of course have their own rules and they produce
and give birth to mythology with which we still,
at least in this country, we live till now, till today.
- So Gorbachev is an interesting figure in all of this.
Is there a possible history
where the Soviet Union did not collapse
and some of the ideas that Gorbachev had for the future
of the Soviet Union came to life?
- Of course, history, on the one hand, there is a statement.
It doesn't allow for what-ifs.
On the other hand, in my opinion, history is full of
what-if, that's what history is about.
(Lex laughs)
And certainly there are scenarios,
how the Soviet Union
would continue beyond, let's say Gorbachev's tenure.
And the argument has been made that the reforms
that he introduced, that they were mismanaged
and they could be managed differently,
or there could be no reforms
and there could be continuous stagnation.
So that is all possible.
What I think would happen one way
or another is the Soviet collapse in a different form
on somebody else's watch at some later period in time.
Because we're dealing with not just processes
that happening in the Soviet Union,
we're dealing with global processes
and the 20th century turned out to be the century
of the disintegration of the empires.
You look at the globe at the map of the world in 1914,
and you compare it to the map at the end
of the 20th century in 1991, 1992.
And suddenly you realize that there are many candidates
for being the most important event,
the most important process in the 20th century.
But the biggest global thing
that happened was redrawing the map of the world
and producing dozens, if not hundreds of new states.
That's the outcome of the different processes
of the 20th century.
Look, Yugoslavia is falling apart around the same time.
Czechoslovakia goes through
what can be called a civilized divorce, a very,
very rare occurrence in the fall
of multinational states.
So yeah, the writing was on the wall,
whether it would happen under Gorbachev
or later, whether it would happen as the result of reforms
or as the result of no reforms.
But I think that sooner
or later, that would happen.
- Yeah, it's very possible.
Hundreds of years from now,
the way the 20th century is written about
as the century defined by the collapse of empires.
You call the Soviet Union the last empire.
The book is called The Last Empire.
So is there something fundamental about the way the world is
that means it's not conducive to the formation of empires?
- The meaning that I was putting in the term the Soviet
Union as the last empire was that
that was the Soviet collapse, was the collapse of the
last major European empires, traditional empires
that was there in the 18th century, 19th century,
and through most of the 20th century,
the Austria Hungary died in the midst
of World War I, the Ottoman Empire disintegrated,
the Brits were gone and left India.
And there was the successor
to the Russian Empire called the Soviet Union,
was still hanging on there.
And then came 1991.
And what we see even with today's Russia,
it's a very different sort of policies.
The Russian leadership tried to learn a lesson from 1991,
so there is no national Republics
in the Russian Federation that would have more rights than
the Russian administrative units.
So the structure is different.
The nationality policies are different.
The level of unification is much higher.
So it is in many ways already a
post imperial formation.
- And you're right about that moment in 1991,
the role that Ukraine played in that
seems to be a very critical role.
Can you describe just that
what role Ukraine played in the
collapse of the Soviet Union?
- History is many things,
but it started in a very simple way
of making notes about on the yearly basis
what happened this year at that.
So it's about chronology.
Chronology in the history of the collapse
of the Soviet Union is very important.
You have Ukrainian referendum on December 1st, 1991,
and you have dissolution of the Soviet Union
by the leaders of Russia.
Ukraine and Belarus respond a week later,
and the question is why?
Ukrainian referendum is the answer.
But Ukrainians
didn't answer their referendum question
of whether they want the Soviet Union
to be dissolved or not.
They answered very limited in terms of,
it's been in question whether you support the decision of
(speaks foreign language) of your parliament
for Ukraine to go independent,
and the rest was not on the ballot.
So why then one week later, the Soviet Union is gone?
And President Yeltsin explains to President Bush around
that time, the reason why Ukraine was so important.
He said that, well, if Ukraine is gone,
Russia is not interested in this Soviet project
because Russia would be outnumbered
and outvoted by the Muslim republics.
So there was a cultural element,
but there was also another one.
Ukraine happened to be the second largest Soviet republic
and then post-Soviet state in terms of population, in terms
of the economy, economic potential, and so on and so forth.
And as Yeltsin suggested, close culturally, linguistically
and otherwise to Russia.
So with the second largest republic gone,
Russia didn't think that it was in Russia's interest
to continue with the Soviet Union.
And around that time, Yegor Gaidar
who was the chief economic advisor of Yeltsin,
was telling him, well, we just don't have money anymore
to support other republics.
We have to focus on Russia.
We have to use oil
and gas money within the Russian Federation.
So the state was bankrupt, imperial projects,
at least in the context of the late 20th century,
they costed money.
It wasn't a moneymaking machine
as it was back in the 18th and 19th century,
and the combination of all these factors led
to the processes in which Ukraine's decision
to go independent, spelled the end to the Soviet Union.
And if today anybody wants to restore,
not the Soviet Union,
but some form of Russian control over the post-Soviet space,
Ukraine is as important today
as it was back in December of 1991.
- Lemme ask you about Vladimir Putin's
statement that the collapse of the Soviet Union is one
of the great tragedies of history.
To what degree does he have a point?
To what degree is he wrong?
- His formulation was that this is
the greatest geopolitical catastrophe
or tragedy of the 20th century.
And I specifically went and looked at the text
and put it in specific time when it was happening.
And it was interesting
that the statement was made a few weeks
before the May nine parade
and celebrations of the victory,
a key part of the mythology
of the current Russian state.
So why say things about the
Soviet collapse being
the largest geopolitical tragedy
and not in that particular context, the Second World War?
My explanation at least is that the World War II,
the price was enormous,
but the Soviet Union emerged as a great victor
and captured half of Europe.
1991, in terms of the lives lost at
that point, the price was actually very, very low.
But for Putin, what was important that the state was lost.
And he in particular was concerned about the division
of the Russian people,
which he understood back then,
like he understands now in very, very broad terms.
So for him, the biggest tragedy is not the loss
of life, the biggest tragedy is the loss
of the great power, status,
or the unity of those whom he considered
to be Russian nations.
So at least this is my reading, this is my understanding of
what is there, what is
on the paper and what is between the lines.
- So both the unity of the sort of quote Russian Empire
and the status of the superpower.
- That's how I read it.
- You wrote a book, The Origins of The Slavic Nations.
So let's go back into history.
What is the origin of Slavic nations?
- We can look at that from different perspectives.
And we are now making major breakthroughs
in answering this question with the very interesting,
innovative linguistic analysis, the study of DNA.
So that's really the new frontier.
We're getting into a prehistorical period
where there is no historical sources.
And from what we can understand today,
and that can of course change tomorrow
with all these breakthroughs in sciences, is that
the Slavs came into existence somewhere in the area
of Pripyat marshes, northwestern part
of Ukraine, southwestern part of Belarus,
eastern part of Poland.
And that's is considered to be historical homeland of Slavs.
And then they spread,
and they spread all the way to the Adriatic.
So we have Croats,
we have Russians spreading all the way to the Pacific.
We have Ukrainians, we have Belarusians, Poles.
Once we had Czechoslovaks, now we have Czechs and Slovaks.
So that's the story of starting with the eighth
and ninth century.
We can even a little bit earlier, we can already follow
that story with the help of the written sources,
mostly from Byzantine, then later from Western Europe.
But what I was trying to do, not being a scientist,
not being an expert in linguistics
or not being an expert in DNA analysis,
I was trying to see what was happening in the minds
of those peoples and their lives in particular,
whom we call today
not Slavs, but Eastern Slavs, which means Russians,
Ukrainians and Belarusians.
How they imagine themselves, how they imagine their world.
And eventually I look at the
so-called nation building projects.
So trying to answer the question of how we arrived
to the situation in which we are today,
where there are not just three East Slavic nations,
but there are also three East Slavic states, Russian,
Ukrainian, and Belorussian.
So this is the focus of my book.
And admittedly in that particular book
I end on the 18th century before the era of nationalism.
But then there are other books like Lost Kingdom
where I bring the story all the way up to today.
- So what aspects of the eighth
and ninth century, the East Slavic states
permeates to today that we should understand?
- Well, the most important one is that the existence
of the state of Kyivan Rus
back during the medieval period
created a foundations for historical mythology,
common historical mythology.
And there are just wars
and battles over who has the right, or more right
for Kyivan Rus.
The legal code that was created at
that time existed for a long period of time, the acceptance
of Christianity from Byzantium, that became a big issue
that separated then eastern Slavs from their Western
neighbors, including Czechs and Poles.
But united in that way to let's say Bulgarians
or Serbs and the beginning of the written literature,
beginning in Kyiv.
So all of that is considered to be part of heritage.
All of that is being contested.
And this debates that were academic
for a long period of time,
what we see now tragically have been being continued
on the battlefield.
- What is Kyiv, what is Rus that you mentioned?
What's the importance of these?
You mentioned them as the sort of defining places
and terms, labels at the beginning of all of this.
So what is Kyiv?
- Kyiv became a capital
or the outpost of the Vikings
who were trying to establish control over the
trade route between
what is today's Western Russia and Belarus
and Northern Ukraine.
So the forest areas and the biggest
and the richest market in the world that existed at
that time, which was in Constantinople, in Byzantium.
So the idea was to get whatever goods you can get in
that part of Eastern Europe.
And most of those goods were slaves.
Local population put them on the ships in Kyiv
because Kyiv was on the border with the step zones.
Step zones were controlled by other groups,
(speaks foreign language) and so on.
And you name it.
And then staying
on the river being protected from attacks of the moments
to come to the Black Sea
and sell these products in Constantinople.
That was the idea.
That was the model.
Vikings tried to practice that sort of
business model also in other parts of Europe
and like in other parts of Europe, they turned out to be,
by default creators of new politics, of new states.
And that was the story
of the first Kyivan Dynasty
and Kyiv as the capital of that huge empire
that was going from the Baltics to today, central Ukraine,
and then was trying to get through the southern Ukraine
to the Black Sea.
That was a major,
major European state kingdom, if you wanna call it,
of medieval Europe with a lot, creating a lot
of tradition in terms of dynasty, in terms of language,
in terms of religion, in terms of, again,
historical mythology.
So Kyiv is central for the nation building myth
of a number of groups in the region.
- So in one perspective
and narrative, Kyiv is at the center of this Russian empire,
at which point does Moscow come to prominence
as the center of the Russian empire?
- Well, the Russian Empire is a term
and really creation of the 18th century.
What we have for the Kyivan,
and we call it Kyivan Rus.
Again, this is a term of the 19th century.
They call themselves Rus,
and there was metropolitan of Rus
and there was Rus principalities.
So very important to keep in mind that Rus is not Russia,
because that was a self name for all multiple groups on
that territory.
And Moscow doesn't exist at the time when Kyiv
emerges as the capital.
The first reference
to Moscow comes from the 12th century when it was founded
by one of the Kyivan Princes, and Moscow comes
to prominence really in a very different context
and with a very different empire running the show
in the region.
The story of Moscow and the rise of Moscow.
This is the story of the Mongol rule
over former Rus lands and former Rus territories.
The part of the former Rus eventually
overthrows the Mongol control with the help
of the small group
of people called Lithuanians,
which had a young state and young dynasty
and united this lands,
which were mostly in today's terms,
Ukrainian and Belorussian.
So they separate early.
And what is today is Russia, mostly Western Russia,
Central Russia, stays under the Mongol control up
until late 15th century.
And that was the story when Moscow rises
as the new capital of that realm replacing
the city of Vladimir
as that capital for those who ever went
to Russia, they familiar with, of course,
Vladimir as the place of the oldest
architectural monuments, the so-called
the Golden Ring of Russia, and so on and so forth.
Vladimir is central.
And there were so many architectural monuments there,
because before there was Moscow there was Vladimir,
eventually in this struggle over control of the territory,
struggle for favors from the Mongols
and the Tatar horde, Moscow emerges as the center
of that particular realm under Mongols,
after the Mongol rule is removed,
Moscow embarks on the project that historians,
Russian historians of the 19th century called the gathering
of the Russian lands, using Russian now for Rus.
And trying to bring back
the lands of former Kyivan Rus,
but also the lands of the former Mongol empire.
The Russians get to the Pacific
before they get to Kyiv, historically,
and really the quote-unquote gathering of the
quote unquote Russian lands.
And only in 1945 when the Soviet Union
bullies the Czechoslovak government into turning
what is today's Ukraine to the Soviet Union.
It is included in the Ukrainian Soviet socialist republic.
So that's the moment when that destiny, the way
how it was imagined
by the 19th century Russian historian was
eventually fulfilled.
Moscow was in control of all this lands.
- So to what degree are the Slavic people one people?
And this is the theme that will continue throughout,
I think, versus a collection of multiple peoples,
whether we're talking about the Kyivan Rus
or we're talking about the 19th century Russian
empire conception.
- Well, a number of ways to look at that.
One, the most obvious, the most clear is language.
And there is no question that
Poles speak a separate language in their Slavs.
And there is no question for anyone
going to Ukraine,
and hearing Ukrainian realizing that this is not Russian,
the level of comprehension can be different.
You can understand certain words
and you don't understand others.
And the same would be with Polish,
and the same would be with Czech.
So there is this linguistic history
that is in common, but languages very clearly indicate that
you're dealing with different people.
We know that language is not everything,
Americans speak a particular way of English.
Australians speak a particular variant of English.
But for reasons of geography history,
we pretty much believe that despite linguistic unity,
these are different nations and different peoples.
And there are some parts
of political tradition more in common.
Others are quite different.
So the same when it comes to language,
the same when it comes to political tradition,
to the loyalty to the political institution applies
to Slavic nations.
So again,
there is nothing particularly unique about the
Slavs in that regard.
- You wrote the book, the Cossack Myth,
History and Nationhood in the Age of Empires,
it tells the story of an anonymous manuscript
called the History of the Rus.
It started being circulated in the 1820s.
I would love it if you can tell the story of,
this is supposedly one
of the most impactful texts in history, modern history.
So what's the importance of this text?
What did it contain?
How did it define the future of the region?
- In the first decay of the 19th century,
after Napoleonic Wars, a mysterious text emerged
that was attributed to a orthodox arch bishop
that was long dead,
which was claiming that the Cossacks of Ukraine
were in fact the original Rus people,
and that they had the right
for a particular place for central place
in the Russian Empire.
And it tells the history of the Cossack.
It's the era of romanticism,
full of all sorts of drama.
There are heroes, there are villains,
and the text captivates the attention of
some key figures
in the Russian intellectual elite
in St. Petersburg, people like (speaks foreign language)
who was executed for his participation in 1825 Uprising
writes poetry on the basis of this text.
Pushkin pays attention to it as well.
And then comes along the
key figure in Ukrainian national revival
of the 19th century Ukrainian National Project.
(speaks foreign language) and reads it as well,
and they all read it very differently.
Eventually by the beginning of the
mid 20th century, some of the Russian
mostly nationalist writers called this text
the Quran of Ukrainian nationalism.
So what is there?
The story, it's very important in a sense that
what the authors,
and that's what I claim in the book, what the authors
of the text were trying to say.
They were trying to say that the Cossack elite
should have the same rights as the Russian nobility,
and brings the long historical records to prove
how cool the Cossack were over the period of time.
But at the beginning of the 19th century,
they put this claim already, they used new arguments,
and this arguments are about nation and nationalism,
and they're saying that the Cossack are a separate nation,
and that's a big, big, big claim.
The Russian Empire,
and this is a very, very good argument in historiography,
that Russian empire grew
and acquired this one sixth of the Earth,
by using one very specific way of integrating those lands.
It integrated elites, it was making deals with their elites,
whether their elites were Muslim
or their elites were Roman Catholic,
as the case was with the Poles,
elites would be integrated,
and the empire was made based on that estate,
the state loyalty and the state integration.
But once you bring in the factor of nation
and nationalism and language, then once in a sudden
the whole model of the integration of the elites,
irrespective of their language, religion,
and culture starts falling apart.
And the Poles were the first who really
produced this sort of a challenge
to the Russian empire by two uprisings in the 19th century.
And Ukrainians then followed in their footsteps.
So the text, the importance of the text is that
it was making claim on the part of a particular estate,
the Cossack officer class, which was
that empire could survive.
But it turned it, given the conditions
of the time into the claim for the special role of
Cossack as a nation,
creating that this is a separate nation, a Rus nation.
And that is the challenge of nationalism
that no empire really survived.
And the Russian Empire was not an exception.
So there's a turning point when the discourse switches from
loyalty based on the integration of the elite
to the loyalty based
on attachment to your nation, to your language,
and to your culture and to your history.
- So that was like the initial spark, the flame
that led to nationalist movements.
- That was the beginning and the beginning,
that was building a bridge between the existence
of the Cossack state in the 17th and 18th century.
That was used as a foundation for the Cossack mythology.
Ukrainian national mythology went into the Ukrainian
national anthem and the new age
and the new stage where the Cossack were not there anymore,
where the professors, intellectuals, students, members
of the national and organizations.
And it started of course, with romantic poetry.
It was started with collecting folklore,
and then later goes to the political stage
and eventually the stage of mass politics.
- So to you, even throughout the 20th century under Stalin,
there was always a force within Ukraine
that wants it to be independent.
- There were five attempts for Ukraine
to declare it's independence
and to maintain it in the 20th century,
only one succeeded in 1991.
But there were four different attempts before.
And you see the Ukrainian
national identity manifest in itself
in two different ways, in the form of national communism
after the Bolshevik victory in Bolshevik controlled Ukraine,
and in the form of radical nationalism in the parts
of Ukraine that were controlled by Poland and Romania.
And part of that was also controlled by Czechoslovakia
and later Hungary.
So in those parts outside of the Soviet Union,
the form of the national mobilization, the key form
of national mobilization became radical nationalism in
Soviet Ukraine, it was national communism
that came back in the 1960s and 1970s.
And then in the 1991, the majority
of the members of the Ukrainian parliament who voted
for independence were members of the Communist Party.
So that spirit on a certain level never died.
- So there's national communism and radical nationalism.
Well, let me ask you about the radical nationalism,
because that is a topic that comes up in the discussion
of the war in Ukraine today.
Can you tell me about Stepan Bandera, who was he?
This controversial far-right,
Ukrainian revolutionary?
- The right list two Stepan Banderas.
One is the real person
and another is mythology that really
comes with this name.
And the real person was a young student,
nationalistically oriented student in the late 1920s
and the early 1930s in the part of Ukraine
that was controlled by Poland, who belonged
to the generation who regretted
that they were not born in time for the big struggles
of the World War I
and revolution at that time, they believed
that their fathers lost opportunity for Ukraine
to become independent and that a new ideology was needed,
and that ideology was radical nationalism
and new tactics were needed.
So Bandera becomes the leader
of the organization
of Ukrainian nationalists in Ukraine at the young age
and organizes a number of assassinations
of the Polish officials
or members of the Ukrainian community
who this young people in their
17, 18, 19 considered to be collaborators.
He is arrested, put on trial.
And that's where the myth of Bandera starts
to emerge because he uses the trial
to make statement about the
Ukrainian nationalism, radical nationalism and its goals,
and suddenly becomes a hero among
the youth, Ukrainian youth at that time,
he's sentenced for execution, for death.
So when he delivers his speech, he knows that
he probably would die soon.
And then it was the sentence was commuted to life in prison.
Then World War II happens,
the Polish state collapses under the pressure coming,
of course from Nazi Germany.
And the Soviet Union, Bandera walks away
and presides over the act of the split over the organization
of Ukrainian nationalists into two groups.
The most radical one you called Revolutionary,
they call themselves Revolutionary, is led by Bandera.
They worked together with the Nazi Germany at that time,
with the hope that Nazi Germany would deliver them
independent Ukraine.
First days of the German attack,
Nazi attack on the Soviet Union.
The units formed on the basis of organization,
Ukrainian National march into the city of Lviv,
and declare Ukrainian independence.
That was not sanctioned by the German authorities,
that was not in German plans.
So they arrest Bandera, members of his family, his brothers,
leaders of the organization.
So his two brothers go to Auschwitz, die there.
He was sent to Sachsenhausen for
most duration of the war until 1944,
refusing to revoke declaration of Ukrainian independence,
which again, contributes further
to his mythology after the war.
He never comes back to Ukraine.
He lives in exile in Munich.
So between 1930 and his death in 1959,
he spent in Ukraine maybe up to two years,
maybe a little bit more,
but most of the time was either in the Polish prison
or in the German concentration camp or in exile.
But the myth of Bandera lived,
and all the members of the organization
of Ukrainian nationalists
and then the Ukrainian insurgent army
that fought against the Soviets all the way into the early
1950s, they were called Banderites.
They were called Banderites by the Soviet authorities.
They were known also in that way to the local population.
So there was a far away leader that barely was there
on the spot, but whose name was attached
to this movement for really liberation
of Ukraine at that time.
Again, the battle that failed.
- The fact that he collaborated with the Nazis sticks.
For one perspective
he's considered by many to be a hero of Ukraine, fighting
for the independence of Ukraine.
From another perspective, coupled with the fact
that there's this radical, revolutionary extremist flavor
to the way he sees the world.
That label just stays, that he's a fascist, he's a Nazi.
To what degree is this true?
To what degree is it not?
- Nazi, this label is certainly promoted by, first,
by the Soviet propaganda
and then by Russian propaganda.
It works very nicely.
If you focus on the years of collaboration,
those were the same years when Joseph Stalin
collaborated with Hitler.
Right?
So we have the same reason
to call Stalin Nazi collaborator as we have
the reason to call Bandera Nazi collaborator.
We look at the situation in the Pacific,
in Indonesia and other places, the leaders
who worked together with Japanese, with the idea
of promoting independence of their countries
after the Japanese collapse, become leaders of the empire.
So the difference with Bandera is
that he never becomes the leader of empire
and immunity that comes with
that position certainly doesn't apply to him.
But there are other parts of his life,
which certainly put this whole thing in question.
The fate of his family,
his own time in the German concentration camp,
certainly don't fit the propaganda
one-sided image of Bandera.
In terms of him being a hero, that's a very,
very interesting question
because he is perceived in Ukraine today,
not by all, and probably not by the majority,
but by many people in Ukraine as a symbol
of fighting against the Soviet Union
and by extension against Russia and Russian occupation.
So his popularity grew
after February 24th, 2022, as a symbol
of that resistance.
Again, we are talking here about myth and mythology,
because Bandera was not leading the fight against
the Soviet occupation
in Ukraine, because at that time he was just simply
not in Ukraine, he was in Germany.
And you can imagine that geography mattered at
that time much more than it matters today.
- There's a million questions to ask here.
I think it's an important topic
because it is at the center of the claimed reason
that the war continues in Ukraine.
And so I would like to explore
that from different angles.
But just to clarify, was there a moment where Bandera chose
Nazi Germany over the Red Army when the war already began?
So in the list of allegiances,
is Ukraine's independence more important
than fighting Nazi Germany, essentially?
- The Ukrainian independence was their goal,
and they were there to work with anybody
who would support and in one way
or at least allow the Ukrainian independence.
So there is no question that
they're just classic nationalists.
So the goal is,
nationalism is the principle according to which,
or at least one definitions is according
to which the cultural boundaries coincide
with political boundaries.
So their goal was to create political boundaries
that would coincide with the geographic boundaries in the
conditions of the World War II.
And certainly making deals with whoever
would either support, as I said,
or tolerate that project of theirs.
- So I would love to find the line between nationalism,
even extreme nationalism and fascism and Nazim.
So for Bandera the myth and Bandera the person,
to what degree, let's look at some of the ideology of Nazis.
To which degree did he hate Jews?
Was he anti-Semitic?
- We know that basically in his circle, there were people
who were anti-Semites in a sense that, okay,
we have the texts, right?
We know that.
We don't have that information about
or that sort of text
or that sort of evidence with regard to Bandera himself.
In terms of fascism, there is very clear
and there is research done
that in particular Italian fascism
had influence on the thinking of people in
that organization, including people at the top.
But it is also very important to keep in mind
that they called themselves
nationalists and revolutionaries.
And despite the fact that in 1939 and 1940
and 1941, it was very beneficial for them
to declare themselves to be Ukrainian fascists
and establish this bond with, not just
with Italy, but with Nazi Germany.
They refuse to do that,
and then they refuse to recall their independence.
So influences, yes,
but clearly it's a different type of a political project.
- So lemme fast forward into the future
and see to which degree the myth permeates.
Does Ukraine have a neo-Nazi problem?
- My understanding is there are Nazis in Ukraine
and there are supporters of white supremacy theories,
but also my understanding is that they're
extremely marginal
and they're more marginal than the same sort of groups
are in central Europe,
maybe in the US as well.
And for me, the question is
not whether the Ukraine has it,
but why even in the conditions of the war,
the radical nationalism and extremism
and white supremacist is such a marginal force
when in the countries that are not at the war, this is this,
you look at France, you look at, again,
it's not exactly national,
but really right, radical right
is becoming so important.
Why Ukraine and the conditions of the war
is the country that
manages relations between different ethnic groups
and languages in the way that strengthens political nation.
So for me, as a scholar,
and a researcher, what I see is that in Ukraine,
the influence of the far right
in different variations is much lower than it is
among some of Ukraine's neighbors
and in Europe in general.
And the question is why, I don't know, I have guesses.
I don't know answer.
But that's the question
that I think is interesting to answer.
How Ukraine ended up
to be the only country in the world outside of Israel
who has a Jewish president, who is,
my at least understanding,
is the most popular president in history in terms of
how long his popularity goes after the election.
So this are the really, from my point of view,
interesting, interesting questions
and again, we can certainly debate that.
- So just for context,
the most popular far right party won 2.15%
of the vote in 2019, this is before the war.
So that's where things stood.
It's unclear where they stand now.
It'd be an interesting question whether it escalated
and how much, what you're saying is that war in general
can serve as a catalyst for expansion of extremist groups
of extremist nationalistic groups,
especially like the far right.
And it's interesting to see to what degree they have
or have not risen to power sort of in the shadows.
- So no nationalist
or nationalistic party actually crossed the barrier
to get into the parliament.
So Ukraine is the country where there is no right
or far right in the parliament.
We can't say that about Germany,
we can't say that about France.
So that's just one more way
to stress this unique place of Ukraine in that sense.
And the year 2019 is the year already of the war.
The war started in 2014 with the annexation of the Crimea.
The frontline was near Donbas.
All these groups are fighting there.
So Ukraine, maybe not to a degree that it is now,
was already on the war footing.
And yet, the right party couldn't get more than 2%.
So that's the question that I have in mind.
And yes, the war historically
of course puts forward
and makes from the more nationalist views
and forces turn them from marginal forces
into more central ones.
We talked about Bandera
and we talked about organization of Ukrainian nationalists.
They were the most marginal group in the political spectrum
in Ukraine in the 1930s that one can only imagine.
But World War II comes
and they become the most central group
because they also were from the start, go, they knew
they had the organization.
Violence was basically one of their means.
They knew how to fight.
So historically, war did produce those results.
So we're looking at Ukraine, we're trying
to see what is happening there.
- So Vladimir Putin in his interview with Tucker Carlson,
but many times
before said that the current goal for the war in Ukraine
is denazification, that the purpose
of the war is denazification.
Can you explain this concept of denazification
as Putin sees it?
- Denazification is the trope
that is accepted quite well
by the former Soviet population and Russian population.
In particular, the most powerful mythology,
Soviet mythology that then was basically passed as part
of heritage to the Russian Federation
was World War II, was fighting against fascism.
So once you use terms fascism and Nazi
and denazification,
suddenly people not just start listening,
they just stop analyzing.
An as a propaganda tool this is
of course very, very powerful tool,
in terms of to what degree this is the real goal or not,
we discussed the importance of the far right
in Europe and in Ukraine.
So if that's the real goal of the war,
probably the war would have to start not against Ukraine,
but probably against France
or some other country if you take this at face value.
- Well, there's something really interesting here,
as you mentioned that's spoken to a lot of people in Russia,
and you said analysis stops,
in the West, people look at the word denazification
and look at the things we've just discussed
and kind of almost think, this is absurd.
When you talk to people in Russia,
maybe it's deep in there somewhere, the history
of World War II still reverberates through the,
maybe the fears, maybe the pride,
whatever the deep emotional history is there.
It seems that the goal of denazification appears
to be reasonable for people in Russia.
They don't seem to see the absurdity or the complexity
or the even the need for analysis, I guess in this kind
of statement, word of denazification .
- I'll say this is broader.
The war that started under the banner that Russians
and Ukrainians were one and the same people
and produces that sort of casualty,
really goes against also some, any sort
of logical thinking.
But the Russia is a place
where the free press doesn't exist already
for a long period of time.
Russia is the place where there is
an echo chamber to a degree.
And as war started first in 2014,
and then all out war in 2022,
I came across a lot of people on the personal level,
but also in the media reporting
that they really can't find common language
with their close relatives in Russia, people
who visited Ukraine, who know that it is not taken over
by nationalists and is not taken over by Nazis.
But the media around them, the neighbors around them,
the people that they work basically say one
and the same thing.
And we as humans in general, whatever our background,
we are very, very, our mind is really,
it's relatively easy to manipulate it
and to a degree that even even family connections
and even family ties don't sometimes help
to maintain that ability to think
and to analyze on your own, to look at at the facts.
- So Putin has alluded
to the Yaroslav Hunka incident in the Canadian parliament
September, 2023.
This man is a veteran
of World War II on the Ukrainian side,
and he got two standing ovations in the Canadian parliament,
but they later found out that he was part of the SS.
So can you explain on this, what are your thoughts on this?
This had a very big effect on the narrative, I guess
propagated throughout the region.
- Yes.
What happened during World War II
was that once the Germans started to run out
of manpower, they created
sort of foreign legion groups.
But because those people were not Aryans,
they were created for fighting
on the battleground
because they were not Aryans, they couldn't be trusted.
So they were put under the command of Heinrich Himmler
under command of SS
and became known as SS Waffen units.
And one of such units was created in Ukraine
with great difficulties
because Nazis didn't consider Slavs to be generally
worthy of even even that sort
of foreign legion formations.
But they made an exception
because those people were coming from Galatia,
which was part of Austria Hungary,
which means part of Austria,
which means somehow were open to the benevolent influence
of the Germanic race
and called the Division Galatian, or Galatia,
part of Ukrainian youth joined the Galatian division.
The one of the explanations was
that they were looking at the experience of World War I
and seeing that the units,
the Ukrainian units in the Austrian army then played a very
important role in the fight for independence.
So that is one of the explanations.
You can't just use one explanation
to describe motivations of everyone
and every single person who was joined in there.
So they were sent to the front,
they were defeated within a few short days
by the Red Army.
And then were retreating through
Slovakia where they were used to fight
with the partisan movement there
and eventually surrendered to the British.
So that's the story.
You can personally maybe understand
what the good motivations were
of this person or that person.
But that is one of the best, one of the very tragic
and unfortunate pages
in Ukrainian history.
You can't justify that as a phenomenon.
So from that point of view, the celebration
of that experience as opposed to looking at that, okay,
that happened.
And we wish that tho those young men
who were idealistic
or joined the division for idealistic purposes had
better understanding of things or made other choices.
But you can't certainly celebrate it.
And once that happened, that of course became
a big propaganda item in the current war,
we're talking about about 10
to 20,000 people in the division,
and we're talking about two
to 3 million Ukrainians fighting in the Red Army.
And again, it's not like Red Army's
is completely blameless in the way how it behaved
in Prussia in Germany and so on and so forth.
But it's basically, again,
we are going back to the story of Bandera.
So there is a period of collaboration
and that's what propaganda tries to define him by.
Or there is a division Galatian by 20,000 people
and somehow it makes irrelevant, the experience of two
to 3 million people.
- I mean, just to clarify,
I think there's just a blunder on the Canadian parliament
side, the Canadian side of not doing research of, maybe,
correct me if I'm wrong,
but from my understanding, they were just doing
stupid shallow political stuff.
Let's applaud, you know, when Zelenskyy shows up,
let's have a Ukrainian veteran, let's applaud a veteran
of World War II, and then all of a sudden you realize, well,
there's actually complexities towards, we can talk about,
for example, a lot of dark aspects on all sides
of World War II, the mass rape at the end of World War II
by the Red Army.
When they say martial German, there's a lot
of really dark complexity in it on all sides.
So, you know, that could be an opportunity
to explore the dark complexity that some
of the Ukrainians were in the SS,
or Bandera, the complexities there.
But I think they were doing not a complex thing.
They were doing a very shallow applaud,
and we should applaud veterans, of course.
But in that case, they were doing it for show,
for Zelenskyy and so on.
So we should clarify that the applause wasn't knowing,
it wasn't for the SS, (laughs) it was for a Ukrainian,
it was for World War II veterans, but the propaganda,
or at least an interpretation from the Russian
side, from whatever side is
that they were applauding the full person standing
before them, which wasn't just a Ukrainian veteran,
but Ukrainian veteran that fought for the SS.
- I don't have any particular insights,
but I would be very much surprised if even one person
in the parliament, I mean the members
of the parliament actually knew the whole story.
I would be very surprised.
- Yeah, the whole story of this person,
and frankly the whole story of Ukraine and Russia
and World War II period.
- Yes, yes.
- Nevertheless, it had a lot of power
and really reverberated in support of the narrative
that there is a neo-Nazi, a Nazi problem in Ukraine.
- This is the narrative that is out there,
and especially powerful in Russia,
it's especially powerful in Russia, given that there are
really the atmosphere
that has created really is not conducive
to any independent analysis.
- Well, I wonder what is the most effective way to respond
to that particular claim?
Because there could be a discussion about nationalism
and extreme nationalism and the fight for independence
and whether it isn't like Putin wrote, one people,
but the question of are there Nazis in Ukraine seems
to be a question that could be
analyzed rigorously with data.
- That is being done on the academic level.
But in terms of the public response
and public discourse, the only response
that I see is not to focus
on the questions raised and put by the propaganda,
because you already become victim
of that propaganda by definition.
But talk about that much broadly
and talk about different aspects,
or if it is World War II, about different aspects
of World War II, if it's about issue
of the far right in Ukraine, let's talk about US,
let's talk about Russia, let's talk about France.
Let's compare.
That's the only way how you deal
with propaganda, because propaganda is not necessarily
something that is an outright lie.
It can be just one factor
that's taken outta the context
and is blown out of proportion.
And that is good enough.
- And the way to defend against that is
to bring in the context.
Let us move gracefully throughout, back
and forth through history.
Back to Bandera, you wrote a book on the KGB spy
Bogdan Stashinsky.
Can you tell his story?
- This is a story of the history of the organization
of Ukrainian nationalists and Bandera as well already
after the end of the second World War,
because what you got
after the second World War, so imagine May of 1945,
the red banner is all over Riksdag.
The Red Army is in control of half of Europe,
but the units of the Red Army are still fighting the war,
and not just behind the Soviet lines,
but within the borders of the Soviet Union.
And this war continues all the way into the early 1950s
up to almost up to Stalin's death.
The war is conducted by the organization
of Ukrainian nationalists,
which have a Ukrainian insurgent army.
And the government tries to crush that resistance.
So what it does is basically recruits local people
to spy on the partisans on the underground.
And Bogdan Stashinsky is one of those people.
His family is supporting the resistance.
They provide food.
His sister is engaged with one of the local
commanders of this underground unit.
And they know everything about Stashinsky's family
and they know everything about him
because he is also collecting funds for the underground.
So they have a conversation with him saying that, okay,
that's what we got.
And you and your family can go to to prison
or you help us a little bit.
We're interested in the fiance
of your sister, and we wanna get him.
And Stashinsky says yes.
And once they round up the fiance,
he basically betrayed a member
or almost member of his family.
He is done.
He can't go back to his village.
He can't go back to his study.
He was studying in Lviv at that time.
So he becomes, as I write in my book,
the secret police becomes his family.
And he is sent to Kyiv.
He is trained for two years, sent to East Germany,
into Berlin and becomes an assassin.
So they sent him across the
border to Western Germany, to Munich,
which was the headquarter of different
organizations, anti-Soviet organizations, Ukrainian
and Russian and Georgian and so on and so forth.
And he kills two leaders
of the organization of Ukrainian nationalists, one editor
of the newspaper, and eventually he kills Bandera.
He does that with the new weapon,
a spray pistol that eventually makes it into the Bond
novel, The Man With The Golden Gun.
And that whole episode is a little bit reshaped,
but it's not in the film, but it's in the novel itself.
And then later has a change of mind under the influence
of his German fiance and then wife.
They decide to escape to the west.
And while they're doing that, they discover that their
apartment was bugged, and probably the KGB knows
all of that.
so a long story short, his son dies
in Berlin, the KGB doesn't allow him to go there,
but his wife has a nervous breakdown.
So they allow him to go there to just calm her so
that there would be no scandal.
And two of them, one day
before their son's burial,
because after that they would be sent to Moscow.
They jumped the ship
and go to West Berlin, two hours
before the Berlin Wall was being built.
So if they would stay for the funeral,
probably the KGB would not let them go.
But also if they would stay,
the border would be there.
And he goes to the American intelligence
and says, okay, that's who I am,
and that's what I did.
And they look at him and they say, we don't trust you.
We dunno who you are, you have documents in five names.
You say you killed Bandera.
Well, we have a different information.
He was poisoned and probably by someone
in his close circle.
A spray pistol?
Did you read too much Ian Fleming,
where does this come from?
He insists, they said, okay,
you insist, if you committed all those crimes,
we're giving you to the German police.
And German police will be investigating you.
And then the trial comes.
And if he takes back his testimony,
the whole case against him collapses, he can go free.
But he knows that if he goes free, he is a target
of his colleagues from the same department.
So his task at the trial is to prove that he's guilty,
that he did that.
And then he disappears and nobody knows where he goes.
And there are all sorts of cover stories.
And I was lucky to interview a commander, former chief
of the South African police, confirmed to me that
Stashinsky was in South Africa.
- He fled.
- The West German intelligence thought
that it was too dangerous for him to stay in Germany.
They sent him under a different name
to South Africa.
So that's the story of Stashinsky himself.
But going back to Bandera, of course, the fact that
he confessed and it became known
that KGB assassinated Bandera, that added to the
image and to general mythology about Bandera.
- What a fascinating story
of a village boy becoming an assassin who killed one
of the most influential revolutionaries of the region
in the 20th century.
So just zooming out broadly then in KGB,
how powerful was the KGB?
What role did it play in this whole
story of the Soviet Union?
- It depends on the period.
At the time that we just described, late fifties
and early sixties, they were not powerful at all.
And the reasons for that was that
people like (speaks foreign language)
were really concerned about the secret
police becoming too powerful.
It became too powerful in their mind under Stalin.
And it was concern about
Beria's power as a secret police chief that led to the
coup against Beria and Kryuchkov come into power
and Beria was arrested and executed.
And what Kryuchkov was trying to do
after that was trying to put
since '54, the name was already KGB,
KGB under his control.
So he was appointing the former council leaders
as the heads of the KGB.
So the people who really,
really owned everything to him, that sort of position
and the heads of the KGB were not members of (indistinct),
it changed in the seventies with Andropov where KGB
started to play again, very important role
in the Soviet history
and let's say decisions on Afghanistan
and the Soviet troops marching into Afghanistan were made
apart from Beria, by the trio of the
people who are not,
would be called today, (speaks foreign language)
or not all of them were (speaks foreign language)
but one of course was Andropov, the head of the KGB.
Another was the Minister of Defense.
And then there was secretary in charge
of the military Industrial Complexity,
Minister of Foreign Affairs.
So, the head
of the KGB became really
not just the member of (speaks foreign language)
but the member of that inner circle.
And then the fact that Andropov
succeeds Beria is also a manifestation of the power
that KGB acquired really
after Kryuchkov in the 1970s
and then going into the 1980s.
- Who was more powerful, the KGB
or the CIA during the Soviet Union?
- The CIA, it's the organization that
is charged with the
information gathering
and all sorts of operations including assassinations
in the fifties and sixties abroad.
The KGB was the organization that really
had both the surveillance
over the population within the Soviet Union
and also the operations abroad.
And its members,
its leaders were members of the inner circle
for making decisions.
Again, from what I understand about the way
how politics and decision work
and decisions are made in the United States,
the chief of the CIA is not one
of the decision making group
that providing information.
Yes.
So I would say it's not day and night,
but their power, political influence,
political significance, very different.
- Is it understood how big the KGB was,
how widespread it was, given its secretive
and distributed nature?
- Certain things we know, others we don't
because the Stasi archives are open
and most of the KGB,
especially in Moscow, they're not.
But we know that the KGB combined not only the
internal sort of a secret police functions at home
and counterintelligence branch
and intelligence branch abroad,
but also the border troops, for example.
Right?
So really institutionally
it was a huge, huge mammoth.
And another thing that we know, we can sort
of extrapolate from what we know
from the Stasi archives, that the surveillance at home,
the surveillance was really massive.
The guess is, the soviets were not as effective
and as meticulous and as scrupulous
and as methodical as probably as Germans were.
But that gives you a basic idea
of how penetrated the entire society was.
- What do you think is important to understand
about the KGB?
If we want to also understand Vladimir Putin,
since he was a KGB foreign intelligence officer
for 16 years.
- From my research, including on the Stashinsky,
what I understand is that
in KGB, and it was a powerful organization, again,
less powerful in fifties and sixties,
but still very powerful organization.
There was on the one hand the understanding
of the situation in the country
and abroad that probably
other organizations didn't have.
They had also first pick in terms of selection,
the work in the KGB was well paid
and considered to be very prestigious.
So that was part to the degree
of the Soviet elite in terms of
whom they recruited.
And they had a resentment over the party leadership.
They didn't allow them to do James Bond kind of things
that they would wanna do because there were political risks
after this scandal with Stashinsky,
at least on many levels, the KGB stopped
the practice of the assassinations,
political assassinations abroad
because it was considered politically
to be extremely, extremely dangerous.
The person who was in charge of the KGB at the time
of Bandera assassination, Shelepin,
was one of the candidates to replace Kryuchkov
and Brezhnev used against him that scandal abroad
eventually to remove him from (speaks foreign language)
so the KGB was really looking at the party leadership
strategically as ineffective, corrupt
and who was on their way.
And from what I understand, that's exactly
the attitudes that people
like Putin and people of his circle brought
to power in Kremlin.
So the methods that KGB use they can use now.
And there is no party
or no other other institution actually stopping
them from doing that.
And the thing about, my understanding
the operations abroad about foreign policy in general in
terms of the KGB mindset of planning operations
and executing particular operations and so on and so forth.
So I think a lot of culture that
came into existence in the Soviet KGB now became part
of the culture of the Russian establishment.
- You wrote the book, the Russo-Ukrainian War,
The Return of History, that gives the full
context leading up to the invasion
of Ukraine by Russia in February, 2022.
So can you take me through the key moments in history
that led up to this war?
So we'll mention the collapse of the Soviet Union.
We could probably go much farther back,
but the collapse of the Soviet Union mentioned 2014.
Maybe you can highlight key moments
that led up to 2022.
- The key moments would be first
the (speaks foreign language)
known as Oragne Revolution in Ukraine,
and then in 2014, known as the Revolution of dignity.
Both were the revolts against something that
by significant part of Ukrainian population was considered
to be completely,
completely unacceptable actions on the part
of the government and people in the government at that time.
So the Orange Revolution of 204
was a protest against falsified presidential elections
and rejection of a candidate that was supported
by Russia, publicly supported by Russia.
I remember being in Moscow at that time
and couldn't believe my eyes when in the center of Russia,
I saw a billboard with Yanukovych.
The trick was that there were a lot of Ukrainians
in Russia and in Moscow in particular,
and they had the right to vote.
So, and it led to the election of
Ukrainian president, Viktor Yanukovych,
who put on the agenda the issue
of Ukraine's membership in NATO.
So it was very clear pro-Western orientation.
And the second case was the Revolution of Dignity
2013 with some of the same characters
including Yanukovych who at
that time was already president of Ukraine.
And there, the question was of the government
promising the people for one year at least
to sign association agreement with European Union
and then turning over almost overnight
and saying that they were not going to do that.
And that's how things started.
But then when they became really massive
and why something that was called revolution,
Euro revolution became Revolution of Dignity
was when the government police
beat up students in downtown Kyiv,
who judging by the reports were basically already,
almost ready to disperse, almost ready to go home.
And that's when roughly half
of Kyiv showed up on the streets.
That sort of, the police behavior, that sort of,
was absolutely unacceptable in Ukraine.
Still in elections
and falsification of elections was unacceptable.
That's where, around that time
and around 204, the president of Ukraine at that time,
Leonid Kuchma, writes a book called
Ukraine is Not Russia.
And apparently the term comes from
his discussion with Putin.
When Putin was suggesting to him quite strongly
to use force against people on the square in Kyiv.
And Kuchma allegedly said,
"You don't understand.
Ukraine is not Russia,
you can't do things like that.
You get pushback."
And that's this two events 204
and then 2013 became really crucial point in terms of the
Ukraine direction, the survival of Ukrainian democracy,
which is one of very few countries in the post-Soviet space
where democracy survived the original flirt
between the government leaders
and democracy of the 1990s.
It was the whole Soviet story in Russia,
everywhere else there was high democratic expectations,
but they came pretty much to an end
by the end of the decade.
Ukraine preserved the democracy
and the orientation of Ukraine
toward integration in some form, into Western
and European structures, that
Ukrainian democracy plus Western orientation was something.
And in Russia, we see the strengthening
of the autocratic regime under Putin, that
if you look deeper, these are the processes
that put two countries on the collision course.
- So there's a division, a push
and pull inside Ukraine on identity of whether they're part
of Russia or part of Europe.
And you highlighted two moments in Ukrainian history that
there's a big flare up where the statement
was first Ukraine is not Russia,
and essentially Ukraine is part of Europe,
but there's other moments.
What were the defining moments
that began an actual war?
- The war started in February of 2014,
with the Russian takeover of Crimea
by military force, right?
The so-called Green Man.
And the big question is why,
and it's very important to go back to the year 2013
and the start of the protests
and the story of the Ukraine signing association
agreement with European Union.
So from what we understand today,
the Ukrainian government under President Yanukovych,
did this suicidal sharp turn
after one year of promising
association agreement saying that, okay,
we changed our mind under pressure from Moscow.
And Moscow applied that pressure
for one reason, at least in my opinion,
the Ukraine signing an association agreement
with European Union would mean
that Ukraine would not be able to sign association agreement
with any Eurasian union in any shape or form.
That was, at that time in the process of making,
and for Vladimir Putin, that was the beginning of his,
or part of his third term, one of his
agenda items for the third term was really a consolidation
of the post-Soviet space and Eurasian space,
and not membership in NATO,
not membership in European Union,
but association agreement with European Union meant that
that post-Soviet space would have
to exist under Moscow's control,
but without Ukraine,
the second largest post-Soviet Republic,
the republic on whose vote depended the
continuing existence of the Soviet Union
and whose vote ended
in many ways the existence of the Soviet Union.
So that is broadly background,
but also there are of course personalities,
there are also their beliefs,
the readings of history.
And all of that became part of the story.
But if you look at that geopolitically,
the association agreement is
putting Ukraine outside of the Russian sphere of influence.
And the response was an attempt
to topple the government in Kyiv that clearly was going
to sign that agreement to take over Crimea
and to help to deal with a lot
of issues within Russia itself
and boost the popularity of the president.
And it certainly worked in that way as well.
And once Ukraine still,
after Crimea continued on its path,
then the next step started the
so-called hybrid warfare in Donbas.
But again, unlike Crimea from what I understand,
Russia was not really looking forward to taking possession
of Donbas, Donbas was viewed as the way
to influence Ukraine,
to stop if from drift towards the west.
- Maybe you can tell me about the region of Donbas.
- I mentioned that nationalism
and principle of nationalism is the principle of
making the political borders to coincide
with ethnic and cultural borders.
And that's how the maps of
many East European countries had been drawn in the
19th and 20th century.
On that principle, Donbas,
where the majority constituted by the beginning
of the 20th century were Ukrainians was considered
to be Ukrainian and was claimed
in the middle of this revolution and revolutionary wars
and civil wars by Ukrainian government.
But Donbas became a site, one
of the key sites in the Russian empire
of early industrialization,
and its mining industry with mythological industry.
So what that meant was that people from other parts of,
not Ukraine, but other parts
of the Russian empire congregated there,
that's where jobs were.
That's how Kryuchkov
and his family came to Donbas, the family
of Brezhnev overshoot a little bit.
They got to the industrial enterprises in the city
of Kaminsk,
the city that was called. (speaks foreign language)
So those were Russian peasants moving into the area
looking for the job.
And the population became quite mixed.
Ukrainians still constituted the majority of the population,
but not necessarily in the towns and in the cities.
And culturally, the place was becoming more
and more Russian as the result of that moment.
So apart from the Crimea,
Donbas was the part of Ukraine
where the ethnic Russians were
the biggest group.
They were not the majority,
but they were very, very big and significant group.
For example, in the city of Mariupol, that was all
but destroyed in the course of the last two years,
the ethnic Russians constituted over 40%
of the population, right?
So that's not exactly part of Donbas,
but that gives you general idea.
Now the story of Donbas
and what happened now is multidimensional.
And this ethnic composition is just one part of the story.
Another very important part of the story is economy.
And Donbas is a classical rust belt.
And we know what happens with the cities that were part
of the first or second wave
of industrialization in the United States and globally,
know about social problems that exist in those places.
So Donbas is probably the most dramatic
and tragic case of implosion of the rust belt
with the mines not anymore producing the sort of,
and at the acceptable price, the coal that they used
to produce, these people losing jobs
with the politicians looking for subsidies as opposed
to trying very unpopular measures of
dealing something and bring new money
and new investment into the region.
So all of that become part of the story
that made it easy for Russia,
for the Russian Federation to destabilize the situation.
We have interviews with Mr. Girkin
who is saying that he was the first
who pulled the trigger
and fired the shot in that war.
He became the Minister of Defense in
the people's republic.
You look at the prime minister, he is another person with
Moscow residency permit.
So you see key figures
in those positions at the start
and the beginning, not being Russians from Ukraine,
but being Russians from Russia
and Russians from Moscow closely connected
to the government structure
and intelligence structure and so on.
So that is the start and the beginning.
But the way how it exploded the way it did
was also a combination of the economic and ethnocultural
and linguistic factors.
- So for Putin, the war on Donbas
and even in 2022 is a defensive war against
what the Ukrainian government is doing against ethnically
Russian people of Donbas.
Is that fair to say how he describes it?
- What we see, this is certainly the argument, right?
This is certainly the argument and a pretext
because what we see there is
that there would be no,
and there was no independent mobilization in Crimea either,
in Crimea, in Donbas, without Russian presence,
without Russian occupation de facto of the Crimea,
there would've been no, and there was no
before, at least in the previous five
to six years, any mass mobilizations of Russians,
there was none of such mobilizations in Donbas
before Gerkin and other people with military,
with parts of military units showed up there.
So it is an excuse, you've been
to Ukraine, you know that Russian language is not
persecuted in Ukraine.
And if you've not been to Donbas, it would be difficult
or to the Crimea it would be difficult
to find one single Ukrainian school.
Not that they didn't exist at all,
but it would take quite an effort for you to find it
or sometimes even to hear Ukrainian language outside either
of the institutions or the farmer's market.
So that's the reality.
That's the reality that is clear, that is visible.
So imagine under those conditions
and context that someone is persecuting
ethnic Russians or Russian speakers,
to believe in something like that,
one important precondition is
never to step your foot in Ukraine.
- I should mention maybe this is a good moment to mention,
when I traveled to Ukraine, this is
after the start of the war,
You mentioned farmer's market, which is funny.
Basically every single person I talked to,
including the leadership, we spoke in Russian.
For many of them, Russian is the more
comfortable language even.
And the people who spoke Ukrainian are more on
the western side of Ukraine.
And you know, young people that are kind of wanting to show
that in an activist way that they want to fight
for the independence of their country.
So I take your point, I wonder if you wanna comment about
language and maybe about the future of language in Ukraine,
is the future of language going to stabilize on
Ukrainian or is it going to return
to its traditional base of Russian language?
- Very roughly before the start of the war in 2014,
we can talk about parity between Russian and Ukrainian
and also with, as you said,
clearly Ukraine being a dominant language in the west
and Russian being a dominant language on the streets,
certainly in the east of the country.
And then in between of that
to pause a number of these transitional areas
and Ukraine in my experience,
and I visited a lot of countries, not all of them,
and probably, maybe I'll be still surprised,
but in my experience,
this is the only truly bilingual
country that I ever visited.
I lived in Canada for a long period of time.
There is Quebec in the West.
And in Ukraine, you can talk in either Russian
or Ukrainian in any part of the country,
and you would be understood
and you would be responded in a different language
with the expectation that you would understand.
And if you don't understand,
that means you don't come from Ukraine.
That's the reality.
The war and loss of the Crimea
and partial loss of Donbas, of it's major industrial areas
really shifted the balance toward mostly
Ukrainian speaking regions.
And also what you see,
and you clearly pointed to that, starting
with 2014, even a little bit earlier,
the younger generation chooses Ukrainian
as a marker of its identity.
And that started in 2014.
But we have a dramatic shift after 2022.
And on the anecdotal level, I can tell you
that I speak to people who
be in Geneve at the time, this is east
of Crimea at the time of the Russian aggression
and bombardment and so on
and so forth, who had passive knowledge of Ukrainian,
but spoke all their life Russian.
And they would speak Ukrainian to me.
And when I say, okay, why you doing that?
We know each other for decades
and you used Russian?
And he said, "Oh, I don't wanna have anything in common
with people who did that to us."
So there is a big, big push of course
with this current war.
Now the question is whether this change is something
that will stay or not, what is the future?
Linguistic practices are very, very conservative ones.
And we at the Harvard Ukrainian Research Institute have a
project called (speaks foreign language)
digital atlas of Ukraine.
And we were documenting
and mapping different data in time.
And what we noticed a spike in the people self reporting
of use of Ukrainian in 2014
and 2015, at the time of the start of the war, when
the threat was the most clear one,
this is self-reporting.
That doesn't mean that people exactly do what,
but they believe that that's what they're supposed to do
and then return back to where it was
by the year 2016 and 2017.
And so this dynamic can repeat itself,
but given the how long the war is going on,
how big the impact is, how big the stress is,
and that the wave of the future
is probably associated with younger people
who are switching to Ukrainian.
So my bet would be on
Ukrainian language rising in prominence.
- So as we get closer to February of 2022,
there's a few other key moments.
Maybe let's talk about in July, 2021,
Putin publishing an essay titled On The Historical Unity
of Russians and Ukrainians.
Can you describe the ideas expressed in this essay?
- The idea is very conveniently presented
already in the first paragraph,
in the first sentences really of the article
where Putin says that
"For a long time I was saying the Russians
and Ukrainians were one and the same people.
And here is the proof.
This is the historical,"
he develops his historical argumentation apparently
with the help of a lot of people around him.
And he started to talk about Russians
and Ukrainians being one and the same people one year
before the start of the war in 2014.
So in 2013 he was together with Patriarch Kirill
on visit to Kyiv,
and there was a conference specifically organized
for him in the Kyivan Monastery.
And that's where he stated that
the fact that he was with Patriarch Kirill is very important
factor for understanding where the idea is coming from.
This is the idea
that was dominant in the Russian empire of the 19th
and the beginning of the 20th century.
That Russians, Ukrainians,
and Belarusians are really Russian, great Russians,
little Russians and white Russians,
and that they constitute one people.
Yes, there are some dialectical differences.
Yes, Ukrainians sing well, yes, they dance funny.
But overall that doesn't matter.
And that idea actually was
really destroyed, mostly destroyed by the revolution
of 1917 because it wasn't just social revolution.
That's how it is understood
in US, in good part of the world.
It was also national revolution.
It was an empire, it was a revolution
in the Russian Empire.
And to bring this pieces
of empire back within the Soviet Union,
the Bolsheviks had to make concessions.
And one of those concessions was to recognition
of the existence of Ukrainians as a separate nation,
Belarusians as a separate nations, Russians
as separate nations, endowing them
with their own territorial, with borders,
with institutions and so on and so forth.
But there was one institution that was not reformed,
that institution was called the Russian Orthodox Church.
'Cause one of the ways that Bolsheviks dealt with it,
they couldn't eradicate religion completely,
but they arrested the development
of the religion and thinking and theology on the level
as it existed before the revolution of 1917.
So the Russian Orthodox Church of 1917 continued
to be the Russian Orthodox Church in 1991.
And in 2013,
continuing the same imperial mantra of the existence
of one big Russian nation, one unified people.
And when you see the formation
of the ideas about nations,
about foreign policy in the Russian empire
after 1991, they're going back to the
pre-Bolshevik times.
Ukrainians do that as well.
Estonians do that as well.
The difference is that when Ukrainians go back,
they go back to the pre 1917,
the intellectual fathers
and writings of basically liberal nationalism
or sometimes they go to the radical nationalism of Bandera,
which would be not pre-1917, but pre-1945.
When the Russians go
to pre-Bolshevik past looking for the ideas, looking
for inspiration, looking for the narratives,
what they find there is empire,
what they find there are imperial projects.
And that's certainly the story
of the Putin's claim.
That's the story of the argument.
And to conclude the argument
that he lays out there historical argument
comes also almost directly from the narratives
of the late 19th and the beginning of the 20th century.
So it's not only the argument is coming from that era,
but also the argumentation
is coming from that era as well.
- But that those arguments are all
in the flavor of empire.
- It's empire on the one hand.
But also there is imperial understanding of
what Russian nation is that doesn't allow for independence
of its little Russian
and white Russian branches, alleged branches.
Right?
So what what you see with the concept
of the big Russian nation,
that's late 19th beginning 20th century
empire sees the writing on the wall,
that nationalism is on the rise
and it tries to survive by mobilizing
the nationalism of the largest group in the empire,
which happens to be Russian.
Stalin is a big promoter of some form
of Russian nationalism, especially
during the war and after war.
And he started his career
as a very promising Georgian writer writing in Georgian.
So he's not doing that
for some personal affinity
or cultural intellectual roots within
Russian nation or Russian people.
He is doing that for the sake of the success
of his Soviet and communist project.
And he has to get the largest ethnic group on board,
which are Russians.
But Stalin and Putin
have different understanding who Russians are.
Stalin already accepted Ukrainians and Belorussians,
they existed.
Putin goes back to pre-Stalin times.
- So if we step back from
the historical context of this
and maybe the geopolitical purpose of writing such an essay
and forget about the essay altogether.
You know, I have family in Ukraine
and Russia, I know a lot of people in Ukraine
and Russia, forget the war, forget all of this.
There's a kind of, they all kind of sound the same.
Like if I go to France, they sound different
then in Ukraine and Russia.
Like if you lay out this the cultural map
of the world, there's just a different beat and music
and flavor to a people.
I guess what I'm trying to say is there seems
to be a closeness between the cultures of Ukraine or Russia.
Like how do we describe that?
Do we acknowledge that
and how does that add tension
with the national independence?
- First of all, especially when it comes to Eastern Ukraine
or to big cities,
many people in Ukraine spoke Russian, right?
Generally it's the same language, on the top of that
we started our discussion
with talking about the Slavs, right?
So both Ukrainian and Russian language are Slavic languages.
So there is proximity there as well.
On the top of that, there is a history of existence in
the Soviet Union and before that
in one empire for a long period of time.
So you see a lot of,
before the war, a lot of Ukrainian singers
and entertainers performing in Russia and vice versa.
And biography of President Zelenskyy certainly one of the,
fits that particular model
as well, that all talks about similarities.
But this similarities also very often obscure
things that became
so important in the course of this war.
And I already mentioned the book titled
by President Kushma of Ukraine,
Ukraine is not Russia.
So that's the argument.
Despite the fact that you think that we are the same,
we behave differently.
And it turned out that they behave differently.
You have (speaks foreign language) in Moscow
and police violence and that's the end of it.
You have the (speaks foreign language) in Ukraine
and you have police violence
and that's the beginning, that's not the end.
History really matters in the way
why sometimes speak people speak in the same language
with different accents, behave very differently.
Russia and Russian identity was formed around the state
and has difficulty imagining itself outside of the state.
And that state happened to be imperial
for most of Russian history.
Ukrainian project came into existence in
revolt against the state.
Ukraine came into existence out of the parts
of different empires,
which means they left different cultural impact on them.
And for Ukrainians to stay together, a theocratic regime,
so far didn't work.
It's like the colonies of the United States.
You you have to find common language.
You have to talk to each other.
And that became part of the Ukrainian political DNA
and that became a huge factor in the war.
And very few people in Ukraine believed
what Vladimir Putin was saying that Russians
and Ukrainians were one and the same people,
but the majority believed that there're certainly close
culturally and historically nations.
And from that point of view, the bombardment
of the Ukrainian cities became such a shock
to the Ukrainians because deep down
they maybe looked at Syria, they looked at Chechnya
and were explaining that through the fact
that there was basically such a big cultural gap
and difference between Russians
and those countries and those nations.
But my understanding at least, most of them
had difficulty imagining the war of that proportion
and that that sort of ferocity
and that sort of war crimes, the bringing
that sort of war crimes and on that level.
- So it's interesting that you say that in the DNA
of Ukraine versus Russia.
So maybe Russia is more
conducive to authoritarian regimes
and Ukraine is more conducive to defining itself
by rebelling against authoritarian regimes
- By rebellion.
Absolutely.
And that was the story pretty much before 1991.
So what you see since 1991
and what you see today is,
I would say new factor,
certainly in Ukrainian modern history,
'cause Ukrainians traditionally were very successful rebels.
The largest peasant army in the civil War in the Russian
Empire was the (speaks foreign language) army
in southern Ukraine.
And one revolt, Kasakh revolts
and other revolts, one after another.
But Ukrainians had historically difficulty actually
maintaining the sort of freedom that they acquired,
had difficulty associating themself with the state.
And what we see, especially in the last two years,
it's a quite phenomenal development in Ukraine when
Ukrainians associate themselves with the state
where Ukrainians see a state not just as a
foreigner, as historically, it was in Ukrainian history,
not just someone who came to take,
but the state that is continuation of them, that helps
to provide security for them.
That the Ukrainian armed forces, even
before the start of this war had
the highest support and popularity in Ukraine.
The state today functions
unbelievably effectively under attacks and missile attacks,
and again, city government and local government.
And we're witnessing when it comes
to Ukraine, we're witnessing a very important historical
development where Ukrainians found their state
for the first time through most of their history
and try to make a transition from successful rebels
to successful managers and state builders.
- Yeah, I talked to John Mearsheimer recently,
there's a lot of people that believe NATO had a big
contribution to the Russian invasion of Ukraine in 2022.
So what role did NATO play in this full history
from Bucharest in 2008 to today?
- NATO was a big part, certainly
of the Russian justification for the war.
That was the theme that was
up there in the months leading to the aggression.
The truth is that,
and Vladimir Putin went on records saying
that the western leaders were telling him again
and again that there is no chance for Ukraine
to become member of NATO anytime soon.
Russia was very effective back in the year 2008,
in stopping Ukraine
and Georgia on the path of joining NATO.
There was a Bucharest Summit,
at which the US president at that time,
George W Bush was pushing for the membership
and Putin convinced leaders of France
and Germany to block that membership.
And after that membership for Ukraine
and for Georgia, was really removed from the
realistic agenda for NATO.
And that's what the leaders
of the western world in the month leading to the
February, 2022 aggression were trying to convey
to Vladimir Putin.
What he wanted,
there was an ultimatum that really was there to,
not to start negotiations, but really to stop negotiations.
He demanded the withdrawal of NATO to the borders
of the 1997, if I'm not mistaken,
so completely something that neither leaders would accept
nor the country's members of NATO would accept.
But for me, it's very clear that
that was an excuse, that that was a justification.
And what happened later in the year 2022
and 2023 certainly confirms me in that belief,
Finland joined NATO
and Sweden is on the way to join in NATO.
So Finland joined in NATO, increased
border between Russia and NATO, twofold,
and probably more than that.
So if NATO is the real concern,
it would be probably not completely unreasonable to expect
that if not every single soldier,
but at least half of the Russian army fighting in Ukraine
would be moved to protect the new border
with NATO in Finland.
So I have no doubt that no one in Kremlin,
either in the past or today looks favorably
or is excited about
NATO moving or the countries of Eastern Europe joining NATO.
But I have very difficult time imagining that
that was the primary cause of the war.
And what we see also, we talked about Tucker's interview,
he was surprised,
but he believed that Putin was completely
honest when the first 25 minutes of interview,
he was talking about relations between Russia and Ukraine.
He was talking about history
and that was also the main focus of his essay.
Essay was not on NATO and Russia,
his essay was on Russia and Ukraine.
So that is where the real causes are.
The broader context is the fall of empire
and process of disintegration of empire,
not the story of NATO.
- What was, to clarify the reason Putin,
Russia invaded Ukraine in 2022?
- The immediate goal in 2014 when the war started
was to stop the drift of Ukraine toward the West
and outside of the Russian sphere of influence,
the invasion of 2022 perceived the same goals
keeping Ukraine in the Russian sphere of influence.
Once we have the resistance,
quite effective resistance on the part of Ukraine, the
Ramstein and international Coalition in support
of Ukraine, then we see the realization of plan B
where parts of Ukrainian territory are being annexed
and included in the Constitution of the Russian Federation.
So the two scenarios don't exclude each other,
but if scenario number one doesn't work,
then scenario number two goes into play.
- In the gates of Kyiv chapter,
you write about Volodymyr Zelenskyy
in the early days of the war.
What are most important moments to you about this time?
The first hours and days of the invasion.
- The first hours and the first days were the
most difficult psychologically, the rest
of the world really didn't expect Kyiv to last
for more than few days.
Didn't expect Ukraine to last for more than few weeks.
And all the data suggested that that's what would happen.
Ukraine would collapse, be taken over.
Putin called his war a special military operation,
which suggests you also expectations about the scope,
expectations about the time.
So semi-military, semi-police operation.
So every reasonable person in the world believed that
that would would happen.
And it's the heroism of quote unquote unreasonable people
like Zelenskyy, like the commander
of Ukrainian armed forces like Zaluzhnyi,
mayors of the cities, (speaks foreign language)
and others, I'm just naming names that are familiar
to almost all of us now.
But there are thousands of those people, unreasonable people
who decided that it was unreasonable
to attack their country.
And that was the most difficult times and days.
And speaking about Zelenskyy, every
I understand reasonable leader in the West was trying
to convince him to leave Ukraine
and to set a government in exile in Poland or in London.
And it was reasonable to accept his,
one of his predecessors, Mr. Yanukovych fled Kyiv.
A few months before that in Afghanistan,
the president of Afghanistan
fled Afghanistan.
That was a reasonable thing to expect.
And he turned out to be very,
very unreasonable in that sense, that comes
with the guts, his guts and guts people around him
and Ukrainians in general.
- Why do you think he stayed in Kyiv, this former comedian
who played a president on TV,
when Kyiv is being invaded by the second most powerful
military in the world?
- Because I think he believes in things
and one of of those things was that if he
president and he's in the presidential office,
he's there to play his role to the end.
And another thing, my personal, again,
I never met Zelenskyy.
My personal understanding of him is that
he has talent that helped him in his career
before the presidency and then helps now.
He feels the audience
and then channel the attitude of the audience
and amplifies it.
And I think that another reason why he didn't leave Kyiv
was that he felt the audience,
the audience in that particular context were the Ukrainians.
- So he had a sense that the Ukrainians would unify
because he was quite, if you look at the polls
before the war, quite unpopular
and there was still divisions and factions,
and the government is divided.
I mean, there's the east and the west
and all this kind of stuff.
You think he had a sense
that this could unite people?
- The east and the west was not already such an issue
after Crimea and part of Donbas being gone.
So Ukraine was much more united than it was before.
He brought to power his
before that really non-existent party of regions
on his personal popularity.
But the important thing is that he created
a majority in the parliament,
which really reflected the unity that existed
among Ukrainians that didn't, was not there
before, he won with 73% of the population
of those who took part in the elections.
His predecessor Petro Oleksiyovych also carried
90% of the precincts.
And the same happened with Zelenskyy.
So the country unified
after 2014 to a degree it was impossible
to imagine before.
And Zelenskyy felt that, Zelenskyy knew that.
And that's where the talent of politician really matters.
And that that's something that you can see
beyond just data.
And you can feel that.
Apparently Yeltsin had that ability.
- Why did the peace talks fail?
There was a lot of peace talks.
- Well, the main reason is that the conditions that
Russia was trying to impose on Ukraine were basically
unacceptable for Ukraine
because one of the conditions
apart from this strange thing called denazification,
was of course de facto loss of the territory.
And for the future really staying
outside either of NATO
or any western support, which was very clear.
You can buy a couple of weeks, you can buy a couple
of months, but in the conditions like that,
Russia will come back tomorrow
and will take over everything.
And once Ukrainians realized
that they can win on the battlefield,
once the Russians were defeated
and withdrew from Kyiv,
the opportunity emerged to get out
of the negotiations, which was very clear, were leading
if not today, then tomorrow
to the complete destruction of Ukraine.
And then of course, once the territories started
to be liberated, things like butcher
and massacres of the civilian population came to the fore,
which made also quite difficult, if not impossible,
to conduct negotiations from this moral
and emotional point of view.
- What about the claims that, you know,
Boris Johnson, the West, compromised the ability
of these peace talks to be successful, basically kind
of manipulated the talks?
- I asked people who accompanied Boris Johnson
to give that question.
The answer was no.
And I believe this answer, and I'll tell you why,
because it is very difficult for me to imagine
President Zelenskyy to take orders
from anybody in the world, either Boris Johnson
or Joe Biden or anybody else.
And basically doing things that
Zelenskyy believes are not in his interest
or in the interest of his country.
I just can't imagine that anybody in the world
telling Zelenskyy what to do
and Zelenskyy actually following it against
his own wishes and desires, at least if
that is possible, what is in the public sphere
doesn't allow us to suggest that it is.
- That said, Zelenskyy is a smart man
and he knows that the war can only continue
with the west support.
- That is a different supposition to know
that it can continue with the West support.
But if we're talking about withdrawing from the
negotiations, that's not about the continuation
of the war, for that you don't need Western support.
- Well, what I mean is if he started to sense
that the West will support no matter what,
then maybe the space
of decisions you're making is different.
- We can interpret that that way.
But Boris Johnson represented
at that point, Britain, not the United States,
and really what the war showed,
and it was clear already at that time that
what was needed was massive support
from the West as a whole.
And the promise of that support came only
when the West realized that Ukraine can win,
and came only in late April with the Ramstein.
So at least a few weeks later.
So I dunno how much Boris Johnson could promise,
he probably could promise to try to help
and try to convince
and try to work on that
if Zelenskyy acted on that promise.
He certainly was taking a risk.
But the key issue, again, I'm going back where I started
it's principle, an acceptance for Ukraine, the conditions
that were offered and Ukraine was,
the moment they saw the possibility
that they could fight back with Johnson support,
without Johnson support, they took the chance.
- So what are the ways this war can end, do you think?
What are the different possible trajectories,
whether it's peace talks,
what does winning look like for either side?
What is the role of US?
What trajectories do you see that are possible?
- It's a question on one level, very easy
to answer on the other very difficult,
the level on which it is very easy.
It's a broad historical perspective.
If you really believe,
and I believe in that, that this is the war
of the Soviet succession.
That this is the war of the disintegration of empire.
We know how the story ends
and they end with disintegration of empire.
They end with the rise of the new states
and appearance of the new colored spots on the map.
That's the story that started with the American revolution.
So that's long term perspective.
The difficult part is of course what will happen tomorrow.
The difficult part is what they'll be
in two days and or even in two years.
And in very broad terms,
the war can end in one of three scenarios.
The victory of one side, the victory of another side,
and a sort of a stalemate
and compromise, especially when it comes,
when it comes to the territories.
This war is already approaching the
end of the second year.
I follow the news and look analysis.
I don't remember once single piece suggesting
that the next year will bring peace
or will bring peace for sure.
And we are in a situation where
the both sides still believe
that they can achieve something
or improve their position on the battlefield.
Certainly that was the expectations
of Ukrainian side back in the summer
and early fall of 2023.
And from what I understand now,
this is certainly the expectations
of the Russian side today.
This is the largest war in Europe since World War II,
the largest war in the world since Korean War.
And we know that the Korean War ended in this
division of Korea.
But the negotiations were going on for more than two years.
While those negotiations were going on,
both sides were trying to improve their position there.
And until there was a political change, death of Stalin,
rival of Eisenhower in the United States,
and the realization that the chances
of succeeding on the battlefield are huge,
the peace talks didn't come.
So at this point, all three scenarios are possible.
I don't really discount any of them.
It's early to say what will happen.
- So without any political change, let's try to imagine
what are the possibilities that the war ends this year?
Is it possible that it can end with compromise,
basically at the place it started?
- Meaning back to the borders of 2022?
- Yeah.
Back to the borders of '22
with some security guarantees that aren't really guarantees,
but are hopeful guarantees.
- No, it's not just virtual impossibility.
It's impossible without political change in Moscow.
The reason is that back in the fall of 2022,
Vladimir Putin included five of Ukrainian region sublists,
even those that he didn't control
or didn't control fully into the Russian constitution,
which basically in simple language is
that the hands are tied up not only for Putin himself,
but also for his possible successors.
So that's means that no return to the borders
of 2022 without change,
political change in Moscow are possible.
A few days after that decision in Moscow, Zelenskyy
issued a decree saying that no negotiations with Russia.
What that really meant in plain language is
that basically we're not prepared
to negotiate a stable agreement with five obstacles,
not just the next, but also included into
the Russian constitution.
So that's where we are.
So that scenario is again,
everything is possible of course,
but it's highly, highly unlikely.
- So the Russian constitution is a thing that's very,
that makes this all very difficult.
- Yes.
And not only as a negotiation tactic for Putin
or whoever would negotiate on the Russian side,
but also as a legal issue.
- So like the practical aspect of it even is difficult.
- Yes, you really have to change the constitution
before the peace agreement takes hold
or immediately after that.
And with the Minsk agreements, that was one of things that
Russia wanted from Ukraine, change of the Constitution,
and it turned out to be really impossible.
So that's one of the backstories
of the Minsk and collapse of the Minsk agreements.
- Is there something like Minsk agreements
that are possible now to, maybe this is a legal question,
but to override the constitution to sort of
shake everything up.
So see the constitutional amendment
as just a negotiation tactic to come to the table,
to something like Minsk agreement.
- Given how how fast those those amendments
to the constitution were adopted, that suggests
that real executive power
in Russia has enormous power over
the legislative branch.
So it's, again, difficult to imagine,
but technically this is possible again.
Yeah, but possible,
if there is a political change in Moscow,
- I don't understand why assuming political change in Moscow
is not possible this year.
So I'm trying to see if there's a way
to end this war this year, right?
- There is a possibility of armistice, right?
But armistice more along,
like any armistice, along the lines
of the current front lines,
but withdrawal of the Russian troops to the borders
or 2022 at this point, whether it's reasonable
or unreasonable can be achieved only as the result
of the defeat of the Russian army.
Like it happened near Kiev.
Is it possible?
Possible.
Is it likely, especially given what is happening
with the Western support, military support for Ukraine?
Probably not.
- But if Putin, the executive branch has a lot of power,
why can't the United States president,
the Russian president, the Ukrainian president, come
to the table and draw up something like the Minsk agreements
where, and then rapid constitutional changes made,
and you go back to the borders in 2022,
before 2022, like through agreements,
through compromise, impossible for you.
- Certainly not this year.
I look at this year as the time when
at least one side, Russian side, will try to get as much
as it can through military means.
- But that's been happening last year too.
Has been a counteroffensive, there's been attempts-
- That doesn't mean
that New Year somehow is supposed to bring your tactics
that the last year was pretty much
a lot of fight and a lot of suffering.
Very little movement of the frontline.
The biggest change
of the last year was Ukraine victory
on the Black Sea, where they pushed
the Russian Navy into the western part of the pond
and restored the grain corridor
and export from Odessa apparently up to 75% of
what it used to be before the war.
So that's the only major change.
But again the price is enormous in terms of
wealth, in terms of, especially in terms of lives.
- So thinking about what 2024 brings,
Zelenskyy just fired Ukraine's head of the Army,
a man you've mentioned, general Valeri Zaluzhnyi.
What do you make of this development?
- This is a very,
very dangerous moment in the war.
The reason for that is that Zaluzhnyi is someone
who is very popular with the army
and with people in general.
So if you look at that through American prism,
that would be something analogous
to President Truman firing General MacArthur,
given that stakes for US at that time, were very high,
but probably not as high as they're for Ukraine today.
In both cases,
what is at stake is certainly the idea
that the political leadership
and military leadership have to be on the same page.
And the question is whether on the part of Zelenskyy,
this is just the change of the leadership
or this is also the change of his approach to the war.
And then can mean many things.
One can mean him taking more active part in
planning operations.
It can mean also possible change of the tactic in the war,
given that counter offensive didn't work out.
We don't know yet.
I don't know whether the president Zelenskyy
at this point knows exactly what will come next.
But this is the time when the change
of the leadership in the country
and in the army that is at war.
It's one of the most trying,
most dangerous moments.
- So the thing that President Zelenskyy expressed is
that this is gonna be a change of tactics,
making the approach more
technologically advanced, this kind of things.
But as you said, I believe
he is less popular than the chief of the Army, Zaluzhnyi,
80% to 60%, depending on the polls.
Do you think it's possible
that Zelenskyy days are numbered as the president?
That somebody like Zaluzhnyi comes to power?
- What we know is that in this war,
Ukrainian people really united
around their president
and the armed forces were always, even
before the start of the war,
more popular than was the presidential office.
So the change, if happened in that realm
was not so dramatic.
And from what I can see from social media in Ukraine,
there is a lot of unhappiness, a lot of questions.
But there is also realization
and very strong realization that country has to stay united.
And certainly the behavior of Zaluzhnyi himself
is there basically not suggesting any sort
of a pre-Georgian type of scenario.
That gives me some hope, actually a lot of hope.
And in terms of whether Zelenskyy's days are numbered
or not, I don't think they're numbered.
But if Ukraine stays a democracy
and I believe it'll stay, the what comes to my mind
is the story of Churchill,
the story of De Gaulle,
in Poland, the story of Pilsudski,
so once the war is over, really the electorate
in the democratic elections, they wanna change the
political leadership, they wanna move forward.
But Pilsudski came back to power
and De Gaulle came back to power,
and Churchill came back to power.
So, no, whatever happens in the short run
or medium term run, I think that
Zelenskyy days in politics are not numbered.
- So what to you is interesting,
for example, if I get a chance to interview Zelenskyy,
what to you is interesting about the person
that would be good to ask about, to explore about
the state of his mind, his thinking his view of the world
as it stands today?
- Next month were supposed to take place
Ukrainian elections, they're not taking place
because the majority of Ukrainians don't think this is
the right thing to do, to change the president,
to have the elections
to have a political struggle in the middle of the war.
So Zelenskyy refused to call those elections
despite the fact that he is
and continues to be the most popular politician in Ukraine.
So it would be to his benefit.
But that's clearly not
what the Ukrainians want.
But the question of continuing as the president
beyond five years, also one way
or another would raise questions about the legitimacy
and certainly Russia will be playing this card
like there is no tomorrow.
And what I would be interested in asking Zelenskyy about,
whether he sees that his second term,
which comes on those conditions
would suggest different attitudes towards the opposition,
maybe some form of the
coalition government, like it was the case in Britain
with Churchill under different circumstances of course.
Or this is basically, in his opinion, something
that would be destructive
and something that would really be an impediment
for the issue, for the question of unity and war effort.
And I would ask this question, not
to basically suggest that that's the way to go,
but I would be very much interested to hear
what is his thinking about that is.
- Do you think there's a degree during war time
that the power that comes
with being a war president can corrupt the person, sort of
push you away from the democratic mindset
towards an authoritarian one?
- I think that there is a possibility of that, right?
You, in the conditions of
any emergency, war in the case of the Soviet Union,
there was a Chernobyl disaster and so on and so forth.
You make decisions much faster.
You create this vertical and then it's very easy to get
really used to that way, dealing with the issues
in the conditions of emergency, right?
And then they continue emergency (laughs)
or with no emergency, they're continuing the emergency mode.
I think again that that would be a very,
very natural thing for any human being to do,
to make it easier.
Should I do that easier and in more effective way,
or should I do the right way?
That's a challenge.
Sometimes it's difficult to answer this question.
- Lemme stay in power for just a little longer
to do it the efficient way and then time flies away
and all of a sudden you're going for the third term.
And the fourth term.
- And suddenly it's easy to realize
that actually you can't rule in any other way.
You just, whatever skills you had of people
around that can help, is that already gone?
- Exactly.
The people that surround you are not
providing the kind of critical feedback necessary
for a democratic system.
One of the things that Tucker said
after his interview with Putin,
he was just in this hotel just chatting on video,
and he said that he felt like
Putin was not very good at explaining himself,
like a coherent whole narrative
of why the invasion happened.
It's just this big picture.
And he said that's not because he doesn't have one,
but it's been a long time since he's had somebody
around him who he has to explain himself to.
So he's out of practice, which is very interesting.
It's a very interesting point.
And that's what war
and being in power for a prolonged period of time can do.
So on that topic, if you had a chance to talk to Putin,
what kind of questions would you ask him?
What would you like to find out about the
man as he stands today?
- As a historian, I have a lot of questions
and I have questions about when the decision was made
to attack Ukraine and what went into this decision
because we're thinking about that.
We're trying.
So as a historian, I have this big question.
I have question about the Crimea when those decisions
were made.
So that sort of questions, that interest me,
but the rest either I think that I understand
what is going on with him
or I don't expect the answer that can help, for example,
a good question, whether you regret
or not, the start of the war in 2022,
given the enormous, enormous casualties on both sides.
But you can't expect from a politician
an honest answer to this question.
Right?
So there are questions to which I know he can't
answer honestly,
and then there are other questions
to which I think he already
provided all answers that he could.
So what what for me is
of interest are basically questions for a historian
about the timing
and the logic of particular decisions.
- Well, I do wonder how different
what he says publicly is from what he thinks privately.
So a question about when the decision
to invade Ukraine happens is a very good question
to give insight to the difference between
how he thinks about the world privately versus
what he says publicly.
And same about other, you know, about empire, as if you ask
Putin, he will say he has no interest in empire
and he finds the notion silly,
but at the same time,
perhaps privately there's a sense in which he does
seek the reunification of the Russian empire.
- Not in the form of the Russian Empire, not in the form
of the Soviet Union, but certainly in some
form of the Russian control.
That's for me at least, it's quite clear.
Otherwise there would be no
busts to the Russian emperors and Katherine
and Peter and others.
- You wrote in your book titled The Frontline,
Essays on Ukraine's Past and Present,
about the Russian question,
I guess articulated by Solzhenitsyn
first in 1994.
Solzhenitsyn of course is the author of Gulag Archipelago.
He's half Ukrainian.
What is the Russian question?
- Solzhenitsyn clearly identifies himself as a Russian,
and his opposition to the communist regime
was a position of a Russian nationalist.
So his argument was that communism was bad for Russia
and for him, Russian question is about the
Russians, ethnic Russians,
but also he was thinking about Russians
in Putin's terms,
or Putin thinks in Solzhenitsyn's terms about Ukrainians
and Belarusians constituting part of that.
So the Russian question is the biggest tragedy
of the 20th century, the division of the Russians,
the loss of the statehood
and division of the Russians
between different states.
This is for Solzhenitsyn, Russian question.
And his original idea
and plan was presented in the essay
that he published in 1990,
which was called How we Should Restructure Russia,
and restructure Russia meant getting rid of the Baltics,
central Asia and Caucasus and have Russians, Ukrainians
and Belarusians, including those
who live in northern Kazakhstan to create one nation state.
So he was a Russian nationalist,
but he was thinking about Russian nation state as the state
of Russians, Ukrainians and Belarusians.
And once the Soviet Union collapsed,
and his idea was not implemented in the 1990s,
he formulated plan B, taken over by Russia
of Donbas, Crimea and Southern Ukraine, the areas
that now are included in the Russian Constitution.
So in historical terms
and intellectual terms, what is happening today
in the war between Russia
and Ukraine is the vision
on one level or another level that was formulated
by the noble laureate, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn
half Russian, half Ukrainian.
- If there is such a thing,
what would you say is the Ukrainian
question as we stand today?
- The Ukrainian question is very simple.
It's now, it's not anymore acquisition of the nation state,
but actually a sovereign state.
But it's maintenance.
So the Ukrainian question is like dozens
of other questions in the 20th
and 21st century, the rise of the new state.
And that's what is the Ukrainian question,
whether, whether Ukraine will continue to its existence
as a nation, as an independent state
because that existence is being questioned
by stating that Russians and Ukrainians so on,
and the same people which de facto saying Ukraine is Russian
and also trying to to destroy the state.
- Is it possible that if the war in Ukraine continues
for many more years, that the next leader
that follows Zelenskyy would
take Ukraine away from a sort
of democratic western style nation
towards a more authoritarian one, maybe even
with a far right influence, this kind of direction
because of the war, the influence of war?
- Everything is possible
and the longer the war continues,
the more likely scenario like that becomes,
but realization of that scenario
would go against the grain of largest part
of Ukrainian history.
Where Ukraine really emerged
as a pluralistic state on which the elements of democracy
were built in the last 30 years would go against the grain
of the Ukrainian society.
Where as one author formulated in the 1990s,
he wrote a book, Ukrainian Nationalism a Minority Faith,
where the nationalism was a minority faith
and radical nationalism continues
to be, or at least continue to be in 2019, a minority faith
during the last elections.
So possible,
but unlikely given the historical realities of the last
30 plus years.
- I could talk to you for many more hours (laughs)
on Chernobyl alone since you've written a book on
Chernobyl and nuclear disaster.
There's just a million possible conversations here.
But let me just jump around history a little bit.
Back before World War II, my grandmother lived
through Holodomor in World War II, Nazi occupied
Ukraine, Holodomor, what do you learn,
let's say about human nature and about governments
and nations from the fact that Holodomor happened,
and maybe you could say what it is and why it happened.
- Holodomor is a massive famine in Ukraine
between the years 1932 and 1934.
And it happened as the result
of forceful collectivization of the agriculture
and a tamp on the part of Stalin also
really roll Ukraine into the Soviet Union with
basically no potential opposition from Ukraine,
now national communists.
So two things came together in December
of 1932 when in the same decree, Stalin
and Molotov signed a decree on the requisition of the grain,
which lead eventually to the mass starvation
and on the banning of Ukrainian language publications
and education out in other Soviet republics outside
of Ukraine and introducing limitations on
the so-called Ukrainization policies.
So on the use of Ukrainian language in Ukraine itself.
And the numbers are debated.
The numbers that most
of the scholars work today are 4 million.
But again, there are larger numbers as well
that circulate.
And this is, the famine
of '32, '33 was not exclusive Ukrainian phenomenon,
but most of Ukrainians in the Soviet Union died in Ukraine.
And Ukraine was the only place
where the policy on collecting grain were coming together
with the policy of the cleansing
of the political leadership sending people from Moscow
to take over the leadership and attack on Ukrainian culture.
So in terms of what I learn about human nature,
it's more me learning about
the ideologists of the 20th century
because it's not the only famine in the communist lands,
the famine in China, which was in terms of the numbers,
much more devastating than that.
It's in a different category and for a good reason,
but you have holocaust.
What unites these things is the time, this is 20 century,
what unites them are the dominance in the societies
that are doing that, really ideologists
that not just devalued human life,
but considered that actually the way forward is
by destroying large group of populations defined ethnically,
religiously, socially or otherwise,
which tells about the time,
but tells also about humanity because for centuries
before that human life was valued, there were enemies,
but the idea was that human life can put
and you can, at the end of the day, they can be slaves,
you can use them for productive force.
Countries in the 18th century with southern Ukraine,
they will looking for settlers, for people to bring
and live on land.
You move into the 20th century
and there is mass destruction of the population in the name
of ideologies, which basically are
by definition destroy human lives.
And that's what really so shocking and striking
because that's break with not just with issues
of morale, not just with issues of humanity,
with any common sense, what is happening.
And I'm absolutely convinced
that we didn't learn the lesson.
I'm absolutely convinced that we didn't learn the lesson
with turning our page on fascism and communism,
we somehow decided that we're free of that,
that at least in those terms, history came to an end.
That what is ahead is in future, nothing of that sort,
what happened would take place to a degree
that people would get in trouble
for comparing any statements
or events that are happening today with
either the communism of fascism.
And so I feel responsibility of myself
and as a historian in particular for
not doing a better job about telling people
that well, we are who we are
and we have as humans our dark side
and we have to be very careful.
- So there is a human capacity to be captured
by an idea, an ideology that claims
to bring up a better world as the Nazis did,
as Soviet Union did.
And on the path of doing that devaluing human life
that we will bring a better world.
And if millions of people have
to be tortured on the way to that, all right,
but at least we have a better world
and human beings are able to,
if not accept that, look the other way.
- Yes.
So, and in the name of a particular nation
or race, like, like with the Third Reich
or in in the name of the humanity of the future,
so not just devalue, human life destroy human life.
- Is there something fundamental about communism
and centralized planning
that's part of the problem here?
Maybe this also connects to just story of Chernobyl, where
that Chernobyl disaster is not just a story of failure
of a nuclear power plant,
but it's an entire institution
of the scientific and nuclear institution.
But the entirety of the government.
- There is, and there is a number of factors of political
and social character that produced Chernobyl.
And one of them is generally the
atmosphere of secrecy in the Soviet Union.
In the conditions of the Cold War,
Chernobyl reactor was a dual purpose reactor.
It could boil water today
and produce enriched uranium tomorrow, right?
So it was top secret.
And if there were problems with that reactor,
those problems were kept secret even at people who operated.
That's what happened.
That's what happened in Chernobyl.
Another big, big part of the story, which is
specifically Soviet, that's the nature
of the managerial culture
and administrative culture in which people had no right
to make their own decisions
in their place, in their position.
A few years before that, Three Mile Island happened,
which was a big, big nuclear disaster.
But in terms of consequences,
nothing like Chernobyl.
And there in the context of the American legal culture
and managerial culture, people who were
operators who were in managerial positions,
that was their responsibility to take decisions.
President Carter came there,
but he was not calling shots on none of those issues.
What you see with Chernobyl,
and people who saw HBO serious know that very well,
the moment the high official arrives,
everyone actually falls in line,
is the official who calls the shot.
And to move population from the city of Pripyat,
you needed the okay coming from Moscow,
from the very top.
So that is Soviet story
and there is a global story of cutting corners
to meet either deadlines like it was with that test
that they were running at that time
or to meet production quarters.
This is not just socialist thing, you can
replace production quarters with
profit and you get the same story.
So some parts of in that story are generally
reflective of our, today's world in general.
Others are very specific for Soviet Union,
for Soviet experience.
And then the biggest probably Soviet
part of that story is that on the one hand,
the government in Moscow
and Kyiv, they mobilize all resources to deal with that,
but they keep information about what is happening
and the radiation clouds secret
from the rest of the population, something
that completely would be impossible
and was impossible in US, in UK
where other accidents happened.
And then guess what?
A few years later
the Soviet Union collapses very much also thanks
to the mobilization of people over the issue of Chernobyl
and nuclear energy, and people
writing about that subject call it eco-nationalism,
ecological nationalism, which comes at least in part from
withholding information from people.
And in Ukraine, mobilization didn't start over
the issues that led to independence,
didn't start over the issue of language
or didn't start over the issue of national autonomy.
It started under the slogans,
"Tell us the truth about Chernobyl."
We wanna know whether we live in contaminated areas or not.
And that was a very, very strong factor
that crossed the,
not just ethnic religious linguistic lines,
lines between members of the party
or not members of the party
of the top leadership and not, and military and civilian,
because it turned out
that the party car didn't protect you from being affected
by radiation.
So the all national mobilization happens,
the first mass manifestations are about Chernobyl,
not about anything else.
- That's fascinating.
I mean, for people
who might not know, Chernobyl is located in Ukraine.
So it would be, it's a fascinating view
that Chernobyl might be one of the critical sort
of threshold catalysts for the collapse of the Soviet Union.
That's very interesting.
Well, just as a small aside,
I guess this is a good moment to give some love
to the HBO series.
It made me, even though it's British accents
and so on, it made me realize that some
of these stories in Eastern Europe could be told very
effectively through film, through series.
It was quite a, I mean it was so incredibly well done
and it maybe I can ask you historically
speaking, were you impressed?
- I was, I was.
And I think that the miniseries, very truthful
on a number of levels
and very untruthful on some others.
(Lex laughs)
And they got excellent in a very well,
the macro and micro levels.
So the macro level is the issue of the big truth.
And the story there is very much built
around the theme that I just discussed.
Now it's about the cost of lies, right?
And the Soviet Union line to the people.
And that's what the film explores.
So I call it a big truth about Chernobyl.
And they got a lot of
minor things really, really very well.
Like the curtains on the windows, like
how the houses looked from inside and outside.
I didn't see any post-Soviet film
or any western film that would be
so good at captioning those everyday details.
But then there is a huge gray area (laughs)
in between big truth and small truth
is of the recreating the environment.
And that's how you get from one to another.
And then you see the KGB officers coming
and taking someone out of the meeting
and arresting, which was not necessary.
You see the Soviet boss threatening someone
to throw the person from the helicopter.
So you get this Hollywood sort of things despite the fact
that it's HBO series
and they're the best really in terms
as a film in the fourth episode
where they can completely decided just, to hell
with the reality (laughs) and let's make a film.
So they bring Legasov one of the key characters to the
this court meetings that they bring.
The key Soviet party, Boris Shcherbina, he wasn't there.
They created drama there.
So, but so they got the main thing, the big truth right.
And that's why I like this production.
- Sometimes you have to show
what something felt like, you have
to go bigger than it actually was.
I mean, if you, I don't know, if you experience heartbreak
and you want, and you see a film about it,
you want there to be explosions.
- You want to see this in images, visible, right?
So, but the question again,
I just mentioned KGB marching in
and so some party leader giving a speech,
they were not giving that speech, but the sense was there
and it was in the air.
And I, as people of my generation who were there, knew that
and recognized that,
but for new generation, whether they are in Ukraine
and Russia, in US, in Britain, in Zimbabwe, anywhere,
yeah, you have to do
this little and truth and introduce them and,
had a very interesting on air conversation
with the author of the script.
Amazing.
And I asked him the question of, okay,
the film declared really the importance of the truth,
but how do you square that with, yeah,
(both laugh)
with the need in the film to really put it mildly
to go beyond the measures of truth,
whatever understanding of that term is?
- Well, I suppose it is a bit terrifying that some
of the most dramatic moments in history are
probably quite mundane.
The decisions to begin wars, invasions,
they're probably something like a Zoom meeting
on a random Tuesday in today's workplace.
So it's not like there's dramatic music playing.
These are just human decisions and they command armies
and they command destruction.
I personally,
because of that, believe in the power of individuals
to be able to stop wars,
not just start wars, individual leaders.
So lemme just ask about nuclear safety
because there's an interesting point you make.
You wrote in the book, in Atoms and Ashes,
a Global History of Nuclear Disaster.
So technically nuclear energy is extremely safe.
There's a number of people died per energy generated,
it's much safer than coal and oil,
for example, as far as I understand.
But the case you also make is you write quote,
"Many of the political, economic, social
and cultural factors that led to the accidents of the past
are still with us today,
making the nuclear industry vulnerable
to repeating old mistakes in new and unexpected ways,
and any new accidents are certain
to create new anti-nuclear mobilization.
And then you continue with,
this makes the nuclear industry not only risky
to operate, but also impossible to count on
as a long-term solution to an overwhelming problem.
So can you explain that perspective?
It's an interesting one, sort of speaking to the psychology
of when an accident does happen, it has a dramatic effect.
And also speaking to the fact
that accidents can happen
not because of the safety of the nuclear power plant,
but of the underlying structure
of government that oversees it.
- Yes, I wrote book on Chernobyl
and then tried to understand Chernobyl better,
but place in it in the context of other disasters
as a historian and was looking at the political factors
and social factors and cultural factors,
not the physics or engineering part of the story.
And the factors that are still with us
are like it was the case in Chernobyl
the authoritarian regimes, right?
And high centralization of the decision making
and desire to cut corners
and also the issues associated with secrecy.
So that is with us.
If you look at where the future
of the nuclear industry is now at this point,
it's the regimes and parts in the Middle East.
That's a big new frontier.
The countries that are not particularly known
for the history of democratic existence,
where we also have the situation
that we had at Three Mile Island that we had
at Chernobyl.
This is the first generation engineers,
nuclear engineers, right?
So people who are, where the
country doesn't have a lot of experience in generations
after generations working in
that particular industry where it's all new.
That is certainly additional risk.
What we've got now is this current war,
is something that, not that people completely didn't expect,
but didn't happen in the past.
You see the war coming to the nuclear sites,
Chernobyl was taken over by the Russian Army
or National Guard rather on the first day of the invasion.
Then there was Zaporizhzhia,
the largest nuclear power plant in Europe
where the battle was waged on the territory
of the nuclear power plant.
The missiles being fired, buildings catching fire.
And the situation
that brought the Fukushima disaster was there at
Zaporizhzhia more than once, and Fukushima came
because the rectors were shut down
as they are at Zaporizhzhia,
but they still needed electricity to bring water
and to cool them down.
And in Fukushima case, it was the tsunami
that cut off the supply of electricity.
In the case of Zaporizhzhia, there was the war
that was happening in the area around Zaporizhzhia
that did the same effect.
So we have 440 reactors in the world today, plus, minus,
none of them was designed to withstand
the direct missile attack
or to function in the conditions of the warfare.
If operators, they're human,
then they make mistakes like they did at
Three Mile Island or Chernobyl.
But think also if the war is happening around them,
if they're not sure what is happening
with their families, if they don't know whether they will be
next missile, whether we'll hit their room
where they, the control room
or not, that multiplies also.
So we are in a situation where
we are not done yet with
the nuclear accidents, new, each time,
it's not like we don't pay attention or we don't learn.
Smart people work on that.
And after every accident, try to figure the way how not
to step into the same trap.
But next accident would actually
expose a new vulnerability.
You deal with Chernobyl,
and then tsunami comes, you deal with tsunami
and then war comes.
And we really in that sense,
we have sometimes wild imagination,
but sometimes it's difficult to imagine
what can happen next.
So we are not done.
There will be nuclear accidents unfortunately in the future.
And that makes nuclear energy
so problematic when you count on it
to fight climate change.
I'll explain why.
You gave the figures
how many people die from burning coal, from
how many people die from radiation.
And it's a good argument.
Some people would question them
because it's also the issue of not just dying,
but impact of radiation on cancer,
on our health, which is not completely understood yet.
So it's still there, there is a lot of question marks,
but let's assume what you're saying.
That's the figures.
That's how it is, but we as people
we for whatever reason are not afraid of coal,
but we're very much afraid of radiation.
It's invisible.
It's Covid, it's everywhere,
and you can't see it.
And then you start having issues
and then you have problems.
And during the Covid,
the governments closed the borders.
Maybe a good idea, maybe not so good ideas.
Isolation.
So that was the way, governments started to fight
for access to Pfizer, to Moderna,
to Sputnik, to whatever it is, to vaccine.
So now back to the radiation,
what is happening once Chernobyl happens,
that's the highest point in the development
of nuclear industry so far in terms of
how many new reactors were commissioned
or the licenses were issued.
The next reactor after Three Mile Island
in the US go ahead was given, it seems to me 10 years ago
or something like that, the Fukushima happens,
the reaction is in China to that as well.
They're very much concerned.
So there is a saying in the field,
Chernobyl anywhere is Chernobyl everywhere.
After Fukushima, Germany decides to go nuclear free
and gets there at the expense of burning coal.
So that's how we react.
And each major accident, that means global freeze
on the nuclear reactor production
for at least another 10 years.
So that's what I mean that nuclear industry, not just
in terms of technology
and not just in terms of radiation impact on health,
but also politically a very, very unreliable option.
- And to you, you suspect that's an irreparable aspect
of human nature in the human mind
that there's certain things
that just create a kind of panic.
Invisible threats of this kind.
Whether it's a virus or radiation.
There's something about the mind.
If I get a stomach ache in the United States
after Fukushima, I kind of think it's probably radiation,
this kind of irrational type of thinking.
And that's not possible to repair?
- I think we can be trained, right? (laughs)
We can be trained.
- [Lex] Pretty smart, aren't we?
- But generally we're afraid of things that we see,
but even more we're afraid of things that we don't see
and radiation is one of those.
- Let's zoom out on the world.
We talked about the war in Ukraine.
How does the war in Ukraine change the world order?
Lemme just look at everything that's going on.
Zoom out a bit.
China, the Israel/Gaza War, the Middle East, India.
What is interesting to you, important
to think about in the coming years and decades?
- As a historian, and I'm trained that way,
I have a feeling of deja vu.
I see the Cold Wars coming back in many of its features.
And the war started
and we discussed that in 2014,
at least in my interpretation with Russia trying
to really reestablish its control
over the post-Soviet space, and Ukraine
was crucial for that project.
And the more globally Russian vision since 1990s was that
they didn't like the American monopolar world.
They knew and realize that they couldn't go back
to the bipolar world of the Cold War era.
So the vision was multipolar world
in which again, it wasn't just academic exercise,
it was a political exercise in which Russia would be one
of the centers, one of the poles on par with China, on par
with European Union, on par with the United States.
That's very broadly speaking the context
in which the war starts 2014, where we are now,
well we are now in Russia certainly trying
to regain its military strength,
but no one actually believes that Russia is the sort
of a superpower it was imagined before 2022.
We see certainly Russia finding the way
to deal with the sanctions,
but we don't see certainly Russia
as a economic power with any sort of a future.
So it's not an implosion
of the Russian military economic and political power,
but it's significantly actually, it's diminished.
So today, very difficult
to imagine the Russia immersion as another pole
of the multipolar world.
Not impossible, but the war certainly made that
very problematic and much more difficult.
On the other hand, what the war did, it basically
awakened the West, the old West,
United States and Western Europe transatlantic alliance.
And on the top of that,
there are East European countries that are
even much stronger proponents of assistance
for Ukraine than is Germany or the United States of America.
So it is the replay of the Cold War story,
the return of the West, that one of the chapters in my
book, The Russo-Ukrainian War, is called that way.
We also can see the elements of the rebuilding
of the Beijing-Moscow alliance of the 1950s,
which was a very important part of the Cold War.
It was extremely important part of the Korean War
that in many ways launched also the Cold War globally.
So I see a lot of parallels of going back to the time
of the Cold War and the bipolar world that emerges.
It's not anymore the world focused on Washington and Moscow.
It's more like world focused on Washington and Beijing.
And then there are countries in between,
there are countries in between
that join one block or another block that is emergent,
that is not fully formed.
This is, in my opinion, makes the task
of us historians to really go back
to the Cold War and look for through new perspective
on the history of that conflict.
Because there is a lot of things that we can learn.
- So in some ways history does repeat itself here.
So now it's a cold war with China
and the United States.
What's a hopeful trajectory for the 21st century?
For the rest of it?
- The hopeful trajectory is really trying to be as wise
and as lucky as our predecessors during the Cold War were.
(Lex laughs)
Because the dominant discourse
so far about the Cold War was what a horrible thing
that Cold War was.
What did we do wrong?
How did we end up in the Cold War?
And I think especially today,
this is a wrong question to ask.
The right question to ask is how did it happen?
What did we do so right?
That for now more than 70 years, we don't have a world war?
How come that after World War I,
world War II came within 20 years, how come that,
what helped us to keep the world on the brain,
but still away from the global war for such a long period
of time, how to keep the Cold War cold?
That's the biggest lesson that the history
of the Cold War can give us.
And I don't think we ask the question quite often
enough, ask the question that way.
And if you don't ask right questions,
we don't get right answers.
- Yeah, you've written a book,
a great book on the Cuban Missile Crisis,
and we came very close not
to just another World War, but to, you know, a nuclear war
and the destruction of
human civilization as we know it.
So I guess it's a good question to ask,
what did we do so right?
And maybe one of the answers could be that we just got lucky
and the question is how do we keep getting lucky?
- Luck is clearly, clearly one of the factors in the
Cuban missile crisis because what happened there,
and there is one of the lessons is that eventually
the commanders at the top, they believe
that they have all the cards,
they negotiate with each other.
They try to see who blinks first
in the game of nuclear brinkmanship.
The trick is that they don't control
fully people on the ground.
The most dangerous moment,
or one of the most dangerous moment
of the Cuban missile crisis was the
Soviet missile shooting down the American airplane,
killing the pilot, an act of war, right?
So technically we're already in the war,
and the order to shoot the missile was given
with Moscow having no clue what was going on the ground.
Moscow never gave approval for that.
And again, I described
that in book many times about Kennedy bringing back his
wisdom from World War II years.
There there always will be SOB who didn't get the order
or miss things.
And that was happening on the American side as well.
So people who believe
that they're in control really are not in control,
and that can escalate whether they were
very often against, against their issues.
So that is one lesson,
but going back to why we are still here
and why the world
didn't end up in 1962, is that
the leadership, and that's, I come to the issue
that you strongly believing that people,
personalities matter, leaders matter.
They were very different, right?
Age, education, political careers, understanding
what politics are and so on and so forth.
- You mean Kryuchkov-
- Kryuchkov and Kennedy, yes.
But they had one thing in common that in one way they belong
to the same generation, that was generation
of the beginning of it all.
That was the generation of the hydrogen bomb, the bomb
that unlike the atomic bomb,
they knew could destroy the world.
And they were scared, they were scared
of the nuclear weapons,
and they tried to do whatever they could
pushing against the advisors
or were trying to deal with their anxieties.
The first is true for Kennedy.
Then later maybe for Kryuchkov to make sure
that this, that the war between the United States
and the Soviet Union doesn't start
because they knew that that war
would be a nuclear war.
So we have a very, very paradoxical sort of situation.
The crisis occurred because of the nuclear weapons,
because Kryuchkov put them on Cuba,
but the crisis was resolved
and we didn't end in the third World War
because of the nuclear weapons,
because people,
leaders were afraid of them.
And that's where I wanna put emphasis.
It's not that the nuclear weapons created crisis
or solved the crisis, is basically our perception of them.
And we are now in the age
after the Cold War era is the new generation of voters,
is the new generation of politicians.
We don't belong to the generation of beginning at all.
We may be not what beginning is,
but we think that this is-
- It's a different thing.
- That this is something else.
And it's very important.
- It's so fascinating
how that fades into memory that the power
and the respect and fear of the power
of nuclear weapons just fades into memory
and that we may very well make the same mistakes again.
- Yes, we can.
- (laughs) Another leader said that, I believe,
but about a totally different topic.
Well, like you said, I'm also glad that we're here more
as a civilization that we still seem to be going on.
There's several billion of us
and I'm also glad that the two of us are here.
I've read a lot of your books, I've been recommending it.
Please keep writing.
Thank you for talking today.
This was an honor.
- Thank you very much, Lex.
It was a pleasure.
- Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Serhii Plokhy.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you
with some words from Earnest Hemingway.
"Never think that war, no matter how necessary
nor how justified, is not a crime."
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.