There was a five-year waiting list and we got a rotary telephone
but it dramatically changed our lives.
You know, people would come to our house to make calls to their loved ones.
You know, I would, I would have to go all the way to the hospital to get blood test records and it would take two hours to go and they would say
"Sorry, it's not ready.
Come back the next day.
" Two hours to come back, and that became a five-minute thing.
So as a kid, like even this light bulb went in my head
you know, this power of technology to kind of change people's lives.
We had no running water, you know
it was a massive drought, so they would get water in these trucks
maybe eight buckets per household.
So me and my brother, sometimes my mom
we would wait in line, get that and bring it back home.
Many years later, like, we had running water and we had a water heater
and you could get hot water to take a shower.
I mean, like, so, you know
for me, everything was discrete like that.
Uh, and so I've always had this thing
you know, firsthand feeling of, like, how technology can dramatically change
like, your life and, like, the opportunity it brings.
I think if PDOOM is actually high, at some point all of humanity is
like, aligned in making sure that's not the case
right?
And so we'll actually make more progress against it
I think.
So the irony is, so there is a self-modulating aspect there
like, I think if humanity collectively puts their mind to solving a problem
whatever it is, I think we can get there.
So because of that, I think I'm optimistic on the PDOOM scenarios
but that doesn't mean.
..
I think the underlying risk is actually pretty high
but I'm, uh, you know, I have a lot of faith in humanity kind of rising up to the
to meet that moment.
Take me through that experience when there's all these articles saying
"You're the wrong guy to lead Google through this.
Google is lost.
It's done.
It's over.
" The following is a conversation with Sundar Pichai
the CEO of Google and Alphabet, on this
The Lex Fridman Podcast.
Your life story is inspiring to a lot of people.
It's inspiring to me.
You grew up in India, whole family living in a humble two-room apartment
very little, almost no access to technology
and from those humble beginnings, you rose to lead a $2 trillion technology company.
So if you could travel back in time and told that
let's say, 12-year-old Sundar that you're now leading one of the largest companies in human history
what do you think that young kid would say?
I would have probably laughed it off, um
you know, uh, probably too far-fetched to imagine or believe at that time.
You would have to explain the internet first.
For sure.
I mean, computers to me at that time
you know, I was 12 in 1984
so probably, uh, you know, by then I had started reading about them but I hadn't seen one.
What was that place like?
Take me to your childhood.
I grew up in Chennai.
Uh, it's in south of India.
It's a beautiful bustling city, lots of people
lots of energy, you know, simple life
definitely, like fond memories of playing cricket outside the home.
We just used to play on the streets.
All the neighborhood kids would come out and we would play till it got dark and we couldn't play anymore
barefoot.
Um, traffic would come, we would just stop the game
everything would drive through and you would just continue playing
right, just to kind of get the visual in your head.
You know, pre-computers, there was a lot of free time now I
now that I think about it.
Now you have to go and seek that quiet solitude or something.
Newspapers, books is how I gained access to the world's information at the time very well.
Uh, my grandfather was a big influence.
He worked in the post office.
He was so good with language, his English
you know, his handwriting till today is the most beautiful handwriting I've ever seen.
He would write so clearly, he was so articulate
and so he kind of got me introduced into books.
He loved politics, so we, we could talk about anything
and, you know, that was there in my family throughout.
So, uh, lots of books, trashy books
good books, everything from Ayn Rand to books on philosophy to stupid crime novels.
So books was a big part of my life
but that kind of, this whole.
..
It's not surprising I ended up at Google because Google's mission kind of always resonated deeply with me
this access to knowledge, I was hungry for it
but definitely have, you know, fond memories of my childhood.
Access to knowledge was there, so that's the wealth we had.
Uh, you know, every aspect of technology I had to wait for a while
I've obviously spoken before about how long it took for us to get a phone
about five years, but it's not the only thing.
A telephone.
There was a five-year waiting list, uh
and we got a rotary, uh, telephone
but it dramatically changed our lives.
You know, people would come to our house to make calls to their loved ones.
You know, I, I would have to go all the way to the hospital to get blood test records and it would take two hours to go and they would say
"Sorry, it's not ready.
Come back the next day.
" Two hours to come back, and that became a five-minute thing.
So as a kid, like even this light bulb went in my head
you know, this power of technology to kind of change people's lives.
We had no running water, you know
it was a massive drought, so they would get water in these trucks
maybe eight buckets per household.
So me and my brother, sometimes my mom
we would wait in line, get that and bring it back home.
Many years later, like, we had running water and we had a water heater
and you could get hot water to take a shower.
I mean, like, so, you know
for me, everything was discrete like that.
Uh, and so I've always had this thing
you know, firsthand feeling of, like, how technology can dramatically change
like, your life and, like, the opportunity it brings.
So, you know, that was kind of a subliminal takeaway for me throughout growing up.
And, you know, I, I kinda actually observed it and felt it
you know?
So we had to convince my dad for a long time to get a
a VCR.
Do you know what a VCR is?
Yeah?
Yes.
I'm trying to date you now.
Yeah.
You know, because before that you only had
like, kind of one TV channel.
Mm-hmm.
Right?
That's it.
Um, and so, you know, you can watch movies or something like that
but this was by the time I was in 12th grade
we got a VCR, you know?
It was a, uh, like a Panasonic which we had to go to some
like, shop which had kinda smuggled it in
I guess, and that's where we bought a VCR.
But then being able to record, like
a World Cup football game and then.
..
Or, like, get, put, like, videotapes and watch movies.
Like, all that.
So, like, you know, I had these discrete memories growing up.
And so, it always left me with the feeling of like how getting access to technology drives that step change in your life.
I don't think you'll ever be able to equal the first time you get hot water.
To have that convenience of going and- Right.
.
opening a tap and have hot water come out.
Yeah.
It's interesting, we take for granted the progress we've made.
If you look at human history, just those plots that look at GDP across 2
000 years and you see that exponential growth to where most of the progress happened since the Industrial Revolution.
And we just take for granted, we forget how
how far we've gone.
So our ability to understand how great we have it and also how quickly technology can improve is quite poor.
Oh, I mean, it's, it's extraordinary.
You know, I go back to India now
the power of mobile.
..
You know, it's mind-blowing to see the progress through the arc of time.
It's phenomenal.
What advice would you give to young folks listening to this all over the world who look up to you and
uh, find your story inspiring?
Who wanna be maybe the next Sundar Pichai?
Who wanna start, create companies, uh, build something that has a lot of impact in the world?
Look, it's.
..
You have a lot of luck along the way
but you obviously have to make smart choices.
You're thinking about what you wanna do, your brain is telling you something.
But when you do things, I think it's important to kind of get that.
..
Listen to your heart and see whether you actually enjoy doing it
right?
That, that feeling of if you love what you do
it's so much easier and you're going to see the best version of yourself.
And it's easier said than done.
I think it's tough to find things, uh
you love doing, um, but I think kind of listening to your heart a bit more than your mind in terms of figuring out what you wanna do
I think, I think is one of the best things I would
uh, tell people.
The second thing is, I mean, trying to work with people who you feel are.
..
At various points in my life, I worked with people who I felt were better than me
right?
Kind of like, you know, you almost are sitting in a room talking to someone and they're like
"Wow.
" Like, you know, uh, uh.
..
You know, and you want that feeling a few times.
Trying to get yourself in a position where you're working with people who you feel are kind of
like, stretching your abilities is what helps you grow
I think.
Uh, so putting yourself in uncomfortable situations.
And I think often you'll surprise yourself.
So I think being open-minded enough to kind of put yourself in those positions is maybe
uh, maybe another thing I would say.
What lessons can we learn, maybe from an outsider perspective
for me, looking at your story and gotten to know you a bit?
You're humble, you're kind.
Usually, when I think of somebody who has had a journey like yours and climbs to the very top of leadership
they're us- in a cutthroat world, they're usually gonna be a bit of an asshole.
So  what wisdom are we supposed to draw from the fact that
uh, your general approach of, is of balance
of humility, of kindness, listening to everybody?
What's, what's, what's your secret?
I do get angry, I do get frustrated.
I have, I have the same emotions.
All, all of us do, right?
In the context of work and everything.
Uh, but a few things, right?
I, I think, you know, I.
..
Over time, I figured out the best way to get the most out of people.
Uh, you know, you kinda find mission-oriented people who are on the shared journey
who have this inner drive to excellence to do their best.
And, and, you know, you kinda motivate people and
and, and you can, you can achieve a lot that way
right?
And so it, it often tends to work out that way.
But have there been times like, you know
I loo- lose it?
Yeah.
But, you know, not.
..
Maybe less often than others.
Uh, and maybe over the years, uh
less and less so because, you know
I, I find it's not needed to achieve what you need to do.
So losing your shit has not been productive.
Yeah, less often than not.
Okay.
I think people respond to that.
Yeah.
They may do stuff to react to that.
Like, but you, you actually want them to do the right thing.
And, and, and so, you know
maybe there's a bit of, like, sports
you know, you know, I'm a sports fan
in football coaches, uh, in soccer, uh.
..
Not football.
Uh, you know, people, people often talk about
like, man management, right?
Great coaches do, right?
I think there is an element of that in our lives
how do you get the best out of the people you work with?
..
. you know, at times you're working with people who
who are so committed to achieving, if they've done something wrong
they feel it more than you, uh
you do, right?
So you treat them differently than.
..
You know, occasionally there are people who you need to clearly let them know
like, "That wasn't okay," or whatever it is.
But I've often found that not to be the case.
And sometimes the right words at the right time
spoken firmly can reverberate through time.
Also sometimes the unspoken words.
You know, people can sometimes see that
like, you know, you're unhappy without you saying it.
And so sometimes the silence can, uh
deliver that message even more.
Sometimes less is more.
Um, who's the greatest, uh, soccer player of all time
Messi or Ronaldo or Pele or Maradona?
I'm gonna make, uh, you know, in this question- Is this going to be a political answer so no.
..
Oh, no, no, no.
I, I, I will tell a truthful answer- The truth.
.
because, uh, the, the- So it's Messi.
..
truthful answer- Okay.
.
..
no, it is.
You know, it's been interesting because my son is a big Cristiano Ron- Ronaldo fan.
And, uh, so we've had to watch El Clasicos together
you know, wi- with that dynamic in there.
I so admire CR7's.
..
I mean, I've never seen an athlete more committed to that kind of excellence.
And so he's one of the all-time greats
but, you know, for me, Messi is it.
Yeah, when I see Lon- uh, Lionel Messi
you just are in awe that humans are able to achieve that level of greatness and genius and artistry.
When we talk, we'll talk about AI
maybe robotics and this kind of stuff, that level of genius
I'm not sure you can possibly match by AI in a long time.
It's just an example of greatness.
And you have that kind of greatness in other disciplines
but in sport, you get to visually see it
unlike anything else, and just the, the timing
the movement, uh, it's just genius.
I had the chance to see him couple weeks ago.
He played in, uh, San Jose.
Mm-hmm.
So, um, against the Quakes, so I went to see it
see the game.
I was a fan on the.
..
Had good seats, knew where he would play in the second half hopefully
and, uh, even at his age, just watching him when he gets the ball
that movement.
You know, you're right, that special quality
it's tough to describe, but you feel it when you see it
yeah.
He's still got it.
Uh, if we rank all the technological innovations throughout human history
let's go back, uh, maybe the history of human civilizations 12
000 years ago, and you rank them by the.
..
how much of a productivity multiplier they've been.
So, uh, we can go to electricity or the labor mechanization for the Industrial Revolution
or we can go back to the first Agricultural Revolution 12
000 years ago.
In that long list of inventions, do you think AI
when history is written 1,000 years from now
do you think it has a chance to be the number one productivity multiplier?
It's a great question.
Look, many years ago, I think it might have been 2017 or 2018
um, you know, I, I said at that time
like, you know, "AI is the most profound technology humanity will ever work on.
It'll be more profound than fire or electricity.
" So I have to back myself, I.
..
You know, I still think, uh, that's the case.
You know, when you asked this question
um, I was thinking, "Well, do we have a recency bias
" right?
You know, like in sports, it's very tempting to call the current person you're seeing the greatest- Yes.
.
..
player, right?
And, and so is there a recency bias?
And, you know, I do think, uh
from first principles, I would argue AI will be bigger than all of those.
I didn't live through those moments.
You know, two years ago, I had to go through a surgery and then I processed that there was a point in time people didn't have anesthesia when they went through these procedures.
At that moment, I was like, "That has got to be the greatest invention-"  Yeah.
".
humanity has ever, ever done," right?
Yeah.
So, look, we, we don't know what it is to have
uh, uh, lived through those times.
But, you know, and many of what you're talking about were kind of this general things which pretty much affected everything
you know, electricity or internet, et cetera.
But I don't think we've ever dealt with a technology both which is progressing so fast
becoming so capable, it's not clear what the ceiling is.
And the main unique.
..
it's recursively self-improving, right?
It's capable of that.
And so the fact it is going.
..
it's the first technology will kind of dramatically accelerate creation itself
like creating things, building new things, can
can improve and achieve things on its own
right?
I think, like, puts it in a different league
And so.
..
a different league.
And so I think the impact it'll end up having
uh, will far surpass everything we've seen before.
Uh, obviously with that comes a lot of
uh, important things to think and wrestle with
but I definitely think that'll end up being the case.
Especially if you guess the point of where we can achieve superhuman performance on the AI research itself.
So it's a technology that may.
..
this is an open question, but it may be able to achieve a level to where the technology itself can create itself better than it
it could yesterday.
It's like the Move 37 of AlphaResearch or whatever it is
right?
Yeah.
Like, you know, and when, when.
..
yeah, you're right, when, when it can do novel self-directed research.
Obviously, for a long time, we'll, we'll have hopefully always humans in the loop and all that stuff
and these are complex questions to talk about.
But yes, I think the underlying technology.
..
You know, I've said this, like, if you watched.
seeing AlphaGo start from scratch, be clueless
and like become better through the course of a day
you know, like,  you know, kind of like
kind of like, you know, really hits you when you see that happen.
..
. even our, like, the VO3 models
if you sample the models when they were
like, 30% done and 60% done and looked at what they were generating
and you kind of see how it all comes together
it's kind of like, I would say
it's kind of inspiring, a little bit unsettling
right, as a, as a human.
So all of that is true, I think.
Well, the interesting thing of the Industrial Revolution
electricity, like you mentioned, it can go back to the
again, the agriculture, the first Agriculture Revolution.
There is, um, what's called the Neolithic package of the first Agriculture Revolution.
It wasn't just that the nomads settled down and started planting food
but all this other kind of technology was born from that and it's included in this package.
There wasn't one piece of technology.
It's, there's these ripple effects, second and third order effects that happen.
Everything from something silly, like, "silly," profound
like pottery that can store-  .
..
liquids and food, uh, to s- something we kind of take for granted
but social hierarchies, uh, and political hierarchies.
So, like, early government was formed.
'Cause it turns out if humans stop moving and have some surplus food
they start coming up with, uh, they get bored  and they start coming up with interesting systems and then trade emerges
which turns out to be a really profound thing.
And like I said, government.
There, I mean there's just, uh, second and third order effects from that
included in that package is incredible and probably extremely difficult if
if you'll ask one of the people in the nomadic tribes to predict that
it would be impossible.
It's difficult to predict.
But all that said, wha- what do you think are some of the early things we might see in the
quote-unquote, "AI package?
" I mean, most of it probably we don't know today.
But, like, you know, the one thing which we can tangibly start seeing now is
you know, obviously with the coding progress you got a sense of it
it's going to be so easy to imagine
like thoughts in your head, translating that into things that exist.
That'll be part of the package, right?
Like, it's gonna empower almost all of humanity to kind of express themselves.
Maybe in the past you could have expressed with words
but, like, you could kind of build things into existence
right?
You know, maybe not fully today.
We are at the early stages of vibe coding.
You know, I've been amazed at what people have put out online with VO3.
Mm-hmm.
But it takes a bit of work, right?
You have to stitch together a set of prompts.
But all this is gonna get better.
The thing I always think about, this is the worst it'll ever be.
Right?
Like at any  given moment in time.
Yeah, it's interesting you went there as kind of a first thought.
So the exponential increase of access to creativity.
Software, creation, uh, are you creating a program
a piece of content for, to be shared with others?
Games down the line.
All of that, like, just becomes infinitely more possible.
Well, I think the big thing is that
uh, it makes it accessible.
It unlocks the cognitive capabilities of the entire eight billion.
No, I agree.
Look, think about 40 years ago, maybe in the US there were five people who could do what you are doing.
Mm-hmm.
Like go do a interview, you know
and, uh, you know.
But today think about with YouTube and other
other products, et cetera, like how many more people are doing it.
So I think this is what technology does
right?
Like when the internet created blogs, you know
you heard from so many more people.
So I think.
..
But, but with AI, I think that number won't be in the few hundreds of thousands.
It'll be tens of millions of people, maybe even a billion people
like, putting out things into the world in a
a, a deeper way.
And I think it'll change the landscape of creativity
and it makes a lot of people nervous.
Like for example, uh, whatever, Fox
M- MSNBC, CNN are really nervous about this part.
Like, y- you mean this dude in a suit could just do this?
And, and you, and YouTube and, and
and thousands of others, tens of thousands
millions of other creators can do the same kind of thing?
That makes me nervous.
And now y- you get a podcast from NotebookLM that's about five to 10 times better than any podcasts I've ever  done.
Uh- Not true, but yeah.
I'm, I'm, I'm joking at this time
but maybe not, and that changes.
You have to evolve.
Because I, on the podcasting front, I'm a fan of podcasts much more than I am a fan of being a host or whatever.
If there's great podcasts that are both AIs
I'll just stop doing this podcast.
I'll listen to that podcast.
But you have to evolve and you have to change
and that makes people really nervous, I think.
But it's also a really exciting future.
The only thing I may say is I do think
like, in a world in which there are two AI
I think people value and, uh, choose.
..
Just like in chess, you and I would never watch Stockfish 10 or whatever and AlphaGo play against each o- like
it would be boring for us to watch.
But Magnus Carlsen and Gukesh, that game would be much more fascinating to watch.
So it's tough to say.
Like, one way to say is you'll have a lot more content and so you will be listening to AI generated content- Mm-hmm.
.
..
because sometimes it's efficient, et cetera.
But the premium experiences you value might be a version of
like, the human essence wherever it comes through.
Going back to what we talked earlier about watching Messi dribble the ball.
I don't know, one day I'm sure a machine will dribble much better  than Messi
but I don't know whether it would evoke that same emotion in us.
So I think that'll be fascinating to see.
I think the element of podcasting or audiobooks that is about information gathering- Yeah.
.
..
that part might be removed or that might be more efficiently and in a compelling way done by AI
but then it'll be just nice to hear humans struggle with the information .
Contend with the information, try to internalize it
combine it with the complexity of our own emotions and consciousness and all that kind of stuff.
But if you actually want to find out about a piece of hi- history
you go to Gemini.
If you want to see Lex struggle with that history
then you look.
..
Or other humans, you look, you, you look at that.
But, uh, the point is, it's going to change the nature
uh, continue to change the nature of how we discover information
how we consume the information, how we create that information
the same way that YouTube changed everything completely
changed news.
It changed.
..
And that's something our society is struggling with.
Yeah.
YouTube.
..
Look, YouTube enabled.
I mean, you know this better than anyone else
it's enabled so many creators.
There is no doubt in me that, like
we will enable more filmmakers than, than have ever been
right?
You're going to empower a lot more people.
Um, so I think there's an expansionary aspect of this
which is underestimated, I think.
I think it'll unleash human creativity in a way
uh, that hasn't been seen before.
It's tough to internalize.
The only way is if you, if you brought someone from the '50s or '40s and just put them in front of YouTube
you know, I think it would blow their mind away.
Similarly, I think we would get blown away by what's possible in a 10 to 20 year timeframe.
Uh, do you think there's a future
how many years out is it, that
let's say, let's put a mark on it
50% of content, in a comp- good content
50% of good content is generated by VO4
5, 6?
You know, I think depends on what it is for.
Um, like, you know, maybe if you look at movies today with CGI
there are great filmmakers, like used to look at
like, who the directors are and who use it.
There are filmmakers who don't use it at all
you value that.
There are people who use it incredibly.
You know, think about somebody like a James Cameron
like what he would do with these tools in his hands.
But I think there'll be a lot more content created.
Like, just like writers today use Google Docs and not think about the fact that they're using a tool like that
like people will be using the future versions of these things
like it won't be a big deal at all to them.
I've gotten a chance to get to know Darren Aronofsky well.
He's been really  leaning in and trying to figure.
..
It's, it's fun to watch a genius who came up before any of this was even remotely possible
he created Pi, one of my favorite movies
and from there just continued to create a really interesting variety of movies.
And now he's trying to see how can AI be used to create compelling films.
You have people like that, you have people.
..
Uh, I've gotten a chance to know
uh, edgier folks, uh, that are AI first
like Dorr Brothers.
Both Aronofsky and Dorr Brothers create at the edge of the Overton Window of society
you know, they push, whether it's, uh
sexuality or, or violence, it's edgy like artists are
but it's still classy, doesn't cross that line
uh, whatever that line is.
You know, um, Hunter S.
Thompson has this line that the, uh
the only way to find out where the edge
where the line is, is by crossing it
uh, and I think for artists that's true
that's kind of their purpose sometimes, comedians and artists just cross that line.
I wonder if you can comment on the weird place that puts Google
because Google's line is probably different than some of these artists.
What, what's your.
..
How do you think about specifically VO, um
and Flow, about like how to allow artists to get
do crazy shit, but also like the responsibility of like
um, not, for it not to be too crazy?
I mean, it's a great question.
Look, part of.
..
You mentioned Darren, uh, you know, he's a clear visionary
right?
Part of the reason we wor- started working with them early on VO is he's one of those people who's able to kind of see that future
get inspired by it, and kind of showing the way for how creative people can express themselves with it.
Look, I think when it comes to allowing artistic free expression
that is one of the most important values in a society
right?
I think, uh, you know, artists have always been the ones to push
push boundaries, expand the frontiers of thought
uh, and so, look, I think
I think that's going to be an important value we have.
So I think we will provide tools and put it in the hands of artists for them to use and put out their work.
Those APIs, I mean, I almost think of that as infrastructure
just like when you provide electricity to people or something
you want them to use it and like you're not thinking about the use cases on top of it
so- It's a paintbrush.
Yeah.
And, and so I think that's how
obviously there have to be some things, and
you know, society needs to decide at a fundamental level what's okay
what's not.
Uh, we'll be responsible with it, um
but I do think, you know, when it comes to artistic free expression
I think that's one of those values we should work hard to defend.
Uh, I wonder if you can comment on
uh, maybe earlier versions of Gemini were a little bit careful on the kind of things you would be willing to answer.
I just want to comment on, I was really surprised and
uh, pleasantly surprised and en- enjoyed the fact that Gemini 2.
5 Pro is a lot less careful in a good sense.
Don't ask me why, but I've been doing a lot of research on Genghis Khan- .
.
and the, uh, the Aztecs, uh
so there's a lot of violence there in that history
it's a very violent history.
I've also been doing a lot of research on World War I and World War II
and earlier versions of Gemini were very, um
basically this kind of sense, "Are you sure you want to learn about this?
" And now it's actually very factual-.
..
objective, uh, talks about very difficult parts of human history
and does so with nuance and depth.
It's, it's been really nice.
But there's a line there that I guess Google has to kinda walk.
I wonder if it's.
..
And it's also an engineering challenge, how to
how to do that at scale across all the weird queries  that people ask.
What, um.
..
Can you just speak to that challenge?
How do you allow Gemini to say, again
forgive, pardon my French, crazy shit, but not too
not, not too crazy?
I think one of the good insights here has been
as the models are getting more capable, the models are really good at this stuff
right?
Mm-hmm.
And so, I think in some ways
maybe a year ago, the models weren't fully there
so they would also do stupid things more often.
And so, you know, you're trying to handle those edge cases
but then you make a mistake in how you handle those edge cases and it compounds.
But I think with 2.
5, what we particularly found is, once the models cross a certain level of intelligence and sophistication
you know, they are, they are able to reason through these nuanced issues pretty well.
Mm-hmm.
And I think users really want that, right?
Like, you know, uh, you want as much access to the raw model as possible
right?
But I think it's a great area to think about
like, you know, over time, you know
we should allow more and more closer access to it.
Maybe l- may, uh, obviously let people custom prompts if they wanted to
and like, you know, and, you know
experiment with it, et cetera.
Uh, I, I think that's an important direction.
But look, the first principles we wanna think about it is
you know, from a scientific standpoint, like making sure the models.
..
And I'm saying scientific in the sense of
like, how you would approach math or physics or something like that.
Mm-hmm.
From first principles, having the models reason about the world
be nuanced, et cetera, uh, you know
from the ground up is the right way to build these things
right?
Not like some subset of humans kinda hard coding things on top of it.
Uh, so I think it's the direction we've been taking
and I think you'll see us continue to push in that direction.
Yeah, I actually asked.
..
Uh, I gave these notes.
I took extensive notes and I  gave them to Gemini and said
"Can you ask a novel question that's not in these notes?
" And it wrote me.
..
Gemini continues to really surprise me, really surprise me.
It's been really beautiful.
It's an incredible model.
Uh, the, the question its, it
it generated was, "You," meaning Sundar
"told the world Gemini's churning out 480 trillion tokens a month.
Uh, what's the most life-changing five-word sentence hiding in that haystack?
" That's a Gemini question.
But it made me, it gave me a sense.
..
I don't think you can answer that, but it gave me
it may.
..
it woke me up to like, all of these tokens are providing little aha moments for people across the globe.
So that's like learning, that those tokens are.
..
People are curious, they ask a question and they find something out
and it truly could be life changing.
Oh, it is.
I.
..
Look, you know, I had the same feeling about search many
many years ago.
You, you, you know, you, you definitely.
..
You know, these tokens per month has like grown 50 times in the last 12 months
so- Is that accurate, by the way?
The four- Yeah, it is.
Okay.
You know, it is, you know
it is, it is accurate.
I'm glad it got it right.
Um, but you know, that number was 9.
7 trillion tokens per month, 12 months ago
right?
It's gone, gone up to 480.
Uh, you know, it's a 50X increase.
So there's no limit to human cur- curiosity
uh, and I think it's, it's one of those moments.
Uh, maybe, I don't think it is there today
but maybe one day there's a five-word phrase which says what the actual universe is or something like that
and something very meaningful.
But I don't think we are quite there yet.
Do you think the scaling laws are holding strong on
um.
..
There's a lot of ways to describe the scaling laws for AI
but on the pre-training, on the post-training fronts.
So the flip side of that, do you anticipate AI progress will hit a wall?
Is there a wall?
You know, it's a cherished micro kitchen conversation.
Yes.
Once in a while I have it, uh
you know, like when Demis is visiting or
you know, if Demis, Koray, Geoff
Noam, Sergey, a bunch of our people
like.
..
Yeah.
.
you know, we sit and, uh, you know
sh- uh, uh, you know, talk about this
right?
And, um, look, I.
..
We see a lot of headroom ahead, right?
I think, uh, we've been able to optimize and improve on all fronts
right?
Uh, pre-training, post-training, test time compute
tool use, right, over time, making these more agentic.
So, getting these models to be more general world models in that direction
like VO3, uh, you know, the physics understanding is dramatically better than what the VO1 or something like that was.
So you kind of see on all those dimensions
I, I feel, you know, progress is very obvious to see
and I feel like there is significant headroom.
More importantly, you know, I'm fortunate to work with some of the best researchers on the planet
right?
They think, uh, there is more headroom to be had here.
Uh, and so I think we have an exciting trajectory ahead.
It's tougher to say, you know.
..
Each year I sit and say, "Okay
we are gonna throw 10X more compute over the course of next year at it
and, like, will we see progress?
" Sitting here today, I feel like the year ahead will have a lot of progress.
And do you feel any limitations like, uh
that, uh, the bottlenecks, compute limited
uh, data limited, idea limited.
Do you feel any of those limitations?
Or is it full steam ahead on all fronts?
I think it's compute limited in this sense
right?
Like, you know, we can all.
..
Part of the reason you've seen us do Flash
NanoFlash and Pro models.
..
. but not an ultra model.
It's like for each generation we feel like we've been able to get the pro model at like
I don't know, 80, 90% of ultra's capability.
But ultra would be a, a lot more
uh, like slow and a lot more expensive to sell.
But what we've been able to do is to go to the next generation and make the next generation's pro as good as the previous generation's ultra- Yeah.
.
..
but be able to serve it in a way that it's fast and you can use it and so on.
So I do think scaling laws are working
but it's tough to get at any given time the models we all use the most.
This may be like a few months behind the maximum capability we can deliver
right?
Because that won't be the fastest, easiest to use
et cetera.
Also, that's in terms of intelligence, it becomes harder and harder to measure
uh, "performance" in quotes, because, you know
you could argue Gemini Flash is much more impactful than Pro just because of the latency
it's super intelligent already.
I mean, sometimes like latencies, uh, may be more important than intelligence
especially when the intelligence is just a little bit less and Flash not.
..
it's still incredibly smart model.
Yeah.
And so you, you have to now start measuring impact and then it feels like benchmarks are less and less capable of capturing the intelligence of models
the effectiveness of models, the usefulness, the real world usefulness of models.
Uh, another kitchen question.
So lots of folks are talking about, uh
timelines for AGI or ASI, artificial super intelligence.
So AGI, loosely defined, is basically human expert level at a lot of the main fields of pursuit for humans.
And ASI is what AGI becomes presumably quickly by being able to self-improve
so becoming far superior in intelligence across all these disciplines than humans.
When do you think we'll have AGI?
Is 2030 a possibility?
Uh, there's one other term we should throw in there.
I don't know who, who used it first.
Maybe Karpathy did.
AJI.
Have you, have you heard AJI?
The artificial jagged intelligence.
Sometimes feels that way, right?
Both, there are progress and you see what they can do.
And then like you can trivially find they make numeric letters or like
you know, counting R's in strawberry or something which seems to trip up most models or whatever it is
right?
So, uh, so maybe we should throw that term in there.
I, I feel like we are in the AJI phase where like dramatic progress
some things don't work well, but overall
you know, you're seeing, uh, lots of progress.
But if your question is will, will it happen by 2030?
Look, we constantly move the line of what it means to be AGI.
There are moments today, you know, like sitting in a Waymo in a San Francisco street with all the crowds and the people and kind of work its way through.
I see glimpses of it there.
The car is sometimes kind of impatient, trying to work its way
uh, using Astra like in Gemini Live or seeing
uh, you know, asking questions about the world.
What's this skinny building doing in my neighborhood?
It's a streetlight, not a building.
You, you see glimpses.
That's why I use the word AGI because then you see stuff which obviously
you know, we are far from AGI too.
So you have both experiences simultaneously happening to you.
I'll answer your question, but I'll also throw out this.
I almost feel the term doesn't matter.
What I know is by 2030 there'll be such dramatic progress.
We'll be dealing with the consequences of that progress
both the positives, uh, both the positive externalities and the negative externalities that come with it in a big way by 2030.
So that I strongly feel, right?
Whatever we may be arguing about the term or maybe Gemini can answer what that moment is in time in 2030
but I think the progress will be dramatic
right?
So that I believe in.
Will the AI think it has reached AGI by 2030?
I would say we will just fall short of that timeline
right?
So I think it'll take a bit longer.
It's amazing, in the early days of Google DeepMind in 2010
they talked about a 20-year timeframe to achieve
uh, AGI.
So which is, which is kind of fascinating to see.
But, you know, I.
..
For me the whole thing, seeing what Google Brain did in 2012 and when we acquired DeepMind in 2014
uh, right close to where we are sitting in 2012
you know, Jeff Dean showed the image of when the neural networks could recognize
uh, a picture of a cat, right?
And identify it.
You know, this is the early versions of Brain
right?
And so, you know, we all talked about couple decades.
I don't think we'll quite get there by 2030.
So my sense is it's slightly after that.
But I, I would stress it doesn't matter
like what the definition is because you will have mind-blowing progress on many dimensions.
Maybe AI can create videos.
We have to figure out as a society how do we.
..
We need some system by which we all agree that this is AI generated and we have to disclose it in a certain way because how do you distinguish reality otherwise?
Yeah, there's so many interesting things you said.
So first of all, just looking back at this recent
now feels like distant history, uh, with Google Brain.
I mean, that was before TensorFlow, before TensorFlow was made public and open sourced.
So the tooling matters too combined with GitHub ability to share code.
Then you have the ideas of attention transformers and the diffusion now
and then there might be a new idea that seems simple in retrospect but will change everything
and that could be the post-training, the inference time innovations.
And I think ShadCN tweeted that Google is just one great UI from completely winning the AI race.
Meaning like-.
..
UI is a huge part of it.
Like, how that intelligence, uh, uh
I think Logan Cooper project likes to talk about this right now as an LLM
but it become, like, when is it going to become a system where you're sh- talking about shipping systems versus shipping a particular model?
Yeah, it, that matters too.
How the system is, um, manifest itself and how it presents itself to the world.
That really, really matters.
Oh, hugely so.
There are simple UI innovations which have changed the world
right?
And, uh, I absolutely think so.
Um, we will see a lot more progress in the next couple of years as I think AI itself
uh, on a self-improving track for UI itself.
Like, you know, today- Yes.
.
..
we are, like, constraining the models.
The models can't quite express themselves in terms of the UI to
to people.
Um, but that is, uh, like
you know, if you think about it
we've kind of boxed them in that way.
But given these models can code, uh
you know, they should be able to write the best interfaces to express their ideas- Mm-hmm.
.
..
over time, right?
That is incredible idea.
So the APIs are already open.
So you can  you create a really nice agentic system that continuously improves the way you can be talking to an AI.
Yeah.
But it, a lot of that is the interface and then
of course, the incredible multimodal aspect of the interface that Google's been pushing.
These models are natively multimodal.
They can easily take content from any format
put it in any format.
They can write a good user interface.
They probably understand your preferences better than over time.
Like, you know, and so, so all this is
like, the evolution ahead, right?
And so, um, that goes back to where we started the conversation.
I, like, I think there'll be dramatic evolutions in the years ahead.
Maybe one more kitchen question.
Uh, this e- even further ridiculous concept of PDOOM.
So the philosophically minded folks in the AI community think about the probability that AGI and then ASI might destroy all of human civilization.
I would say my PDOOM is about 10%.
Do you ever think about this kind of long-term threat of ASI?
And what would your PDOOM be?
Look, I mean, for sure.
Look, I've, uh, both been, uh
very excited about AI, uh, but I've always felt
uh, this is a technology, you know
we have to actively think about the risks and work very
very hard to harness it in a way that it
it all works out well.
Um, on the PDOOM question, look, it's
uh, you know, won't surprise you to say that's probably another micro kitchen conversation that pops up once in a while
right?
And given how powerful the technology is, maybe stepping back
you know, when you're running a large organization
if you can kinda align the incentives of the organization
you can achieve pretty much anything, right?
Like, you know, if you can get kind of people all marching in towards like a goal
uh, in a very focused way, in a mission-driven way
you can pretty much achieve anything.
But it's very tough to organize all of humanity that way.
But I think if PDOOM is actually high
at some point all of humanity is, like
aligned in making sure that's not the case
right?
And so we'll actually make more progress against it
I think.
So the irony is, so there is a self-modulating aspect there.
Like, I think if humanity collectively puts their mind to solving a problem
whatever it is, I think we can get there.
So because of that, you know, I
I w-, I, I, I think I'm optimistic on the PDOOM scenarios
but that doesn't mean.
..
I think the underlying risk is actually pretty high.
But I'm, uh, you know, I have a lot of faith in humanity kind of rising up to the
to meet that moment.
That's really, really well put.
I mean, as the threat becomes more concrete and real
humans do really come together and get their shit together.
Well, the other thing I think people don't often talk about is probability of doom without AI.
So there's all these other ways that humans can destroy themselves and it's very possible
at least I believe so, that AI will help us become smarter
kinder to each other, uh, more efficient.
Uh, it, it'll help more parts of the world flourish where it would be less resource constrained
which is often the source of military conflict and tensions and so on.
So we a- also have to load into that what's the PDOOM without AI?
With AI, PDOOM with AI and PDOOM without AI  'cause it's very possible that AI will be the thing that saves us
saves human civilizations from all the other threats.
I agree with you.
I think, I think it's insightful.
Uh, look, I felt, like, to make progress on some of the toughest problems would be good to have AI
like, pair helping you, right?
And, and, like, you know, so that resonates with me for sure.
Yeah.
Quick pause.
Bathroom break?
Uh, you know.
Let's do that.
If Notebook LM was the same com- like
what I saw today with Beam, if it was compelling in the same kind of way.
Blew my mind.
It was incredible.
I didn't think it's possible.
I didn't think it's possible before.
One day, my hope is, like, can you imagine
like, the US president and the Chinese president being able to do something like Beam with the LiveMe translation working well?
So they're both sitting and talking, make progress a bit more.
Uh, yeah, just, uh, for people listening
we took a quick bathroom break and now we're talking about the demo I did.
We'll probably post it somewhere somehow, maybe here.
The, I got a chance to experience Beam and it was
uh, i- it's hard to, it's hard to describe it in words how real it felt with just
what is it, six cameras.
It's incredible, it's incredible.
It's, it's one of the toughest products of.
..
You can't quite describe it to people.
Even when we show i- it in slides
it's like you don't know what it is.
You have to kind of experience it.
On the world leaders front, um, politics
geopolitics, there- there's something really special, again with studying World War II and
uh, how much could've been saved if Chamberlain met Stalin in person.
And I sometimes also struggle explaining to people
articulating why I believe meeting in person for world leaders is powerful.
It just seems naive to say that, but there is something there in person and with Beam I- I felt that same thing and then I'm unable to explain.
All I kept doing is what like a child does-  .
..
you look real  you know?
And I mean, I don't know if that makes meetings more productive or so on
but it certainly makes them more, uh.
..
The- the same reason you wanna show up to work versus remote sometimes
that human connection.
I don't know what that is.
It's hard to- it's hard to put into words.
Um, there's some- there's something beautiful about great teams collaborating on a thing that's- that's not captured by the productivity of that team or whatever on paper.
Some of the most beautiful moments you experience in life is at work.
Pursuing a difficult thing together for many months- Oh.
.
..
there's nothing like it.
You're in the trenches and- Yeah.
.
..
yeah, you do form bonds that way, for sure.
And to be able to do that, like
somewhat, uh, remotely in that same personal touch
I don't know, that's a deeply fulfilling thing.
I know a lot of peop- I- I personally hate meetings because a significant percent of meetings when done
uh, poorly are- are- don't- don't serve a clear purpose.
So- but that's a meeting problem, that's not a communication problem.
If you can improve the communication for the meetings that are useful
it's just incredible.
So yeah, I was blown away by the great engineering behind it and then we- we get to see what impact that has that's really interesting
but just incredible engineering.
Really impressive.
Oh, it is, and obviously we'll work hard over the years to make it more and more accessible.
But yeah, even on a personal front outside of work meetings
you know, a grandmother who's far away from her grandchild and being able to
you know, have that kind of an interaction
right?
All that I think will end up being very.
..
I mean, nothing substitutes being in person
but you know, it's not always possible.
You know, you could be a soldier deployed try- trying to talk to your loved one.
So I think, uh, you know, so that's what inspires us.
When you and I hung out last year and took a walk
I remember, I don't think we talked about this but  but I remember
uh, you know, outside of that seeing dozens of articles written by analysts and experts and so on that
um, Sundar Pichai should step down because the perception was that Google was definitively losing the AI race
has lost its magic touch in the, uh
rapidly evolving, uh, technological, uh, landscape.
And now a year later, it's crazy
you show this plot of all the things that were shipped over the past year
it's incredible, and Gemini Pro is winning across many benchmarks and products
uh, as we sit here today.
So take me through that experience when there's all these articles saying
"You're the wrong guy to lead Google through this.
Google is lost, it's done, it's over.
" To today where Google is winning again.
What were some low points during that time?
Look, I, um.
..
I mean, lots to unpack.
Uh, you know, obviously, like, I mean
the- the main bet I made as a CEO was to really
uh, you know, make sure the company was approaching everything in a AI first way
really, you know, setting ourselves up to develop AGI responsibly
right?
And- and- and make sure we're putting out products
uh, which- which embodies that, things that are very
very useful for people.
So look, I- I knew even through moments like that last year
uh, you know, I had a good sense of what we were building internally
right?
So I'd already made, you know, many important decisions
you know, bringing together teams of the caliber of Brain and DeepMind and setting up Google DeepMind.
There were things like we made the decision to invest in TPUs 10 years ago
so we knew we were scaling up and building big models.
Anytime you're in a situation like that, a few aspects.
Uh, I'm good at tuning out noise
right?
Separating signal from noise.
Do you scuba dive?
Like have you- No.
No.
You know, it's amazing like I'm not good at it
but I've done it a few times, but- but sometimes you jump in the ocean
it's so choppy, but you go down one feet under
it's the calmest thing in the entire, uh
universe, right?
So there's a version of that, right?
Like, you know, uh, running Google
you know, you may as well be coaching Barcelona or Real Madrid
right?
Like, you know?
Yeah.
You have a bad season.
So there are aspects to that, but you know
like, look, I- I'm good at tuning out the noise.
I do watch out for signals, you know?
It's important to separate the signal from the noise.
So there are good people sometimes making good points outside so you want to listen to it
you want to take that feedback in.
But, you know, internally, like, you know
you're making a set of consequential decisions, right?
As leaders, you're making a lot of decisions
many of them are like inconsequential.
..
. like it feels like, but over time you learn that.
Most of the decisions you're making on a day-to-day basis doesn't matter.
Like, you have to make them and you're making them just to keep things moving.
But you have to make a few consequential decisions
right?
And, and, uh, we had set up the right teams
right leaders, we had world-class researchers, we
uh, were training Gemini.
Internally there are factors which were, for example
outside people may not have appreciated.
I mean, T-TPUs are amazing, but we had to ramp up TPUs too.
That took time, right?
And, and, uh, to scale actually having enough TPUs to get the compute needed.
But I could see internally the trajectory we were on
and, and, be, you know, I was so excited internally about the possibility.
..
To me, this moment felt like one of the biggest opportunities ahead for us as a company.
Mm-hmm.
That the opportunity space ahead, or the next decade
next 20 years has been given what has happened in the past.
Um, and I thought we were set up
like, better than most companies in the world to go
uh, realize that vision.
I mean, you had to make some consequential
bold decisions.
Like, you mentioned the merger of DeepMind and Brain.
Uh, maybe it's my perspective just knowing humans
I'm sure there's a lot of egos involved
it's very difficult to merge teams and I'm sure there were some hard decisions to be made.
Can you take me through your process of how you think through that?
Do you go to pull the trigger and make that decision?
Maybe what were some painful points?
How do you navigate those turbulent waters?
Look, we were fortunate to have two world-class teams.
Uh, but you're right, like, it's like somebody coming and telling to you
"Take Stanford and MIT-" Right.
".
..
and then put them together and create a great department.
" Right?
And, and easier said than done.
Um, but we were fortunate, you know
phenomenal teams, both had their strengths, you know
but they were run very differently, right?
Like, uh, Brain was kind of a lot of diverse projects
bottoms up, and out of it came a lot of important research breakthroughs.
DeepMind at the time had a strong vision of how you wanna build AGI and so they were pursuing their direction.
But I think through those moments, luckily tapping into
um, you know, Geoff had expressed a desire to be more
to go back to more of a scientific- Mm-hmm.
.
..
individual contributor routes.
You know, he felt like management was taking up too much of his time
uh, and, and, and Demis naturally
I think, uh, you know, uh
was running DeepMind and w- was a natural choice there.
But I think it was.
..
You're right, you know, it took us a while to bring the teams together
credit to Demis, Geoff, Koray, all the great people there.
They worked super hard to combine the best of both worlds when you set up that team.
A few sleepless nights here and there as we put that thing together.
We were patient in how we did it so that it works well for the long term
right?
And, and some of that in that moment
I think, yes, with things moving fast
uh, I think you definitely, uh, felt the pressure
but I think we pulled off that, uh
transition well, and, you know, I think
I think, uh, you know, they've obviously
uh, doing incredible work and there's a lot more incredible things I heard coming from them.
Like we talked about, you have a very calm
even-tempered, respectful demeanor.
During that time, whether it's the merger or just dealing with the noise
uh, did, w- were there times where frustration boiled over?
Like, did you, uh, have to go a bit more intense on everybody than you usually would?
Probably, y- you know, probably, right.
I think, I think in the sense that
you know, there was a moment where we were all driving hard
but when you're in the trenches working with passion
you're gonna have days, right, you disagree
you argue, but, like, all that
I mean, just part of the course of working intensely
right?
And, uh, you know, at the end of the day
all of us are doing what we are doing because- uh
the impact it can have, we are motivated by it.
It's like, uh, you know, for many of us
this has been a long-term, uh, journey.
And so it's been super exciting, the positive moments far outweigh the
kind of, stressful moments.
Just early this year, I had a chance to celebrate back to back over two days
like, uh, you know, Nobel Prize for Geoff Hinton
and the next day a Nobel Prize for
uh, Demis and John Jumper.
You know, you work with people like that
all that is super inspiring.
Is there something, like, with you where you had to
like, put your foot down, maybe with Les
uh, versus more, or, like, "I'm the CEO and we're ma- we're doing this"?
To my earlier point about consequential decisions you make
there are decisions you make, people can disagree pretty vehemently and.
..
But at some point, like, you know
you make a clear decision and you, you just ask people to commit
right?
Like, you know, you can disagree, but it's time to disagree and commit so- Yeah.
.
..
that we can get moving.
And whether it's put- putting the foot down or
you know, like, you know, it's a natural part of what all of us have to do
and, you know, I think you can do that calmly and  be very firm in the direction you're making the decision.
And I think if you're clear, actually people over time respect that
right?
Like, you know, if you can make decisions with clarity
I find it very effective in meetings where you're making such decisions to hear everyone out.
I think it's important when you can to hear everyone out.
Sometimes what you're hearing actually influences how you think about and you're wrestling with it and making a decision.
Sometimes you have a clear conviction and you state so
"Look, I, uh, I, you know
this is how I feel and, you know
this is my conviction," and you kind of place the bet and you move on.
Are there big decisions like that?
I'm kind of intuitively assume the merger was the big one.
I think that was a very important decision
uh, you know, for, for the company to
to meet the moment.
I think we had to make sure we were
uh, we were doing that and doing that well.
I think that was a consequential decision.
There were many other things.
We set up a AI infrastructure team, like
to really go meet the moment, to scale up the compute we needed to
and really brought teams from disparate parts of the company
kind of created it to, to move forward.
Um, you know, bringing people, like
getting people to kind of work together physically
both in London with DeepMind and what we call Gradient Canopy
which is where the Mountain View Google DeepMind teams are.
But one of my favorite moments is I routinely walk
uh, like multiple times per week to the Gradient Canopy building where our top researchers are working on the models.
Sergey is often there amongst them, right?
Like, you know, just, you know
loo- looking at, uh, you know, getting an update on the models
seeing ?
s.
So all that, I think that cultural part of getting the teams together back with that energy I think ended up playing a big role too.
What about the decision to recently add AI mode?
So Google Search is the, uh, as they say
the front page of the internet.
It's like a legendary minimalist thing with 10 blue links
like, that's w- when people think internet
they think that page.
And now you're starting to mess with that.
So the AI mode, which is a separate tab
and then integrating AI in the results, I'm sure there were some battles in meetings on that one.
Look, uh, it, it, you know
in some ways when mobile came, you know
people wanted answers to more questions so we're kind of constantly evolving it.
But you're right, this moment, you know
that evolution, because the underlying technology is becoming much more capable
you know, you can have AI give a lot of context
you know.
But one of our important design goals though is when you come to Google Search
you're going to get a lot of context
but you're going to go and find a lot of things out on the web.
So that will be true in AI mode
in AI overviews, and so on.
But I think to our earlier conversation, we are still giving you access to links
but think of the AI as a layer which is giving you context
summary, maybe in AI mode you can have a dialogue with it back and forth- Mm-hmm.
.
..
on your journey, right?
And, but through it all, you're kind of learning what's out there in the world.
So those core principles don't change, but I think AI mode allows us to push the f- we have our best models there
right?
Uh, models which are using search as a deep tool really for every query you're asking
kind of fanning out, doing multiple searches
like, kind of assembling that knowledge in a way so you can go and consume what you want to
right?
And, and, and that's how we think about it.
I got a chance to listen to a bunch of
uh, Elizabeth "Liz" Reid- Yeah.
.
..
describe this, two things stood out to me that she mentioned.
One thing is what you were talking about is the query fan-out
which I didn't even think about before, uh
is the, the powerful aspect of integrating a bunch of stuff on the web for you in one place.
So yes, it provides that context so that you can decide which page to then go on to.
The other really, really big thing speaks to the earlier in terms of productivity multiplier that we were talking about that she mentioned was
um, language.
So one of the things you don't quite understand is it
through AI mode, you make, for non-English speakers
you make sort of, let's say, English language websites accessible by
in the reasoning process as you try to figure out what you're looking for.
Of course, once you show up to a page
you can use a basic translate.
Yeah.
But that process of figuring it out, if you empathize with a large part of the world that doesn't speak English
their, like, web, uh, is much smaller in that original language.
And so it unlocks, again, unlocks that huge cognitive capacity there that we don't.
..
You know, you take for granted here with all the bloggers and the journalists writing about AI mode
you forget that this now unlocks, um
'c- c- 'cause Gemini is really good at translation.
Oh, it is.
I mean, uh, the multimodality, the translation
uh, its ability to reason, we are dramatically improving tool use.
Uh, like as, as of putting that power in the flow of search
I, I think.
..
Look, I'm, I'm super excited with the AI overviews we've
we've seen the product has gotten much better.
We, you know, we measure it using all kinds of user metrics.
It's obviously driven strong growth of the product.
Uh, and, you know, we've been testing AI mode
you know, it's now in the hands of millions of people and the early metrics are very encouraging.
So, look, I, I, I'm excited about this next chap- chapter of Search.
For people who are not thinking through or are aware of this
so there's the 10 blue links with the AI overview on top that provides a nice summarization.
You can expand it.
And you have sources and links- Links.
.
..
now- Yep.
.
..
embedded.
Yeah.
I believe, at least Liz said so
I actually didn't notice it, but there's ads in the AI overview also.
I don't think there's ads in AI mode.
..
. uh, when ads in AI mode.
So no.
When, when do you think.
..
I mean, it's.
Okay, we should say that in the '90s
I remember the animated GIFs, banner GIFs that take you to some shady websites that have nothing to do with anything.
AdSense revolutionized advertisement.
It's one of the greatest inventions, um
in, in, in recent history because it allows us for free to have access to all these kinds of services.
So ads fuel a lot of really powerful services.
And in, at its best, it's showing you relevant ads
but also very importantly, in a way that's not super annoying.
Mm-hmm.
Right?
In a classy way.
So, uh, when do you think it's possible to add ads into AI mode
and what does that look like from a classy
non-annoying perspective?
Two things.
Early part of AI mode, uh, we'll obviously focus more on the organic experience to make sure we are getting it right.
I think the fundamental value of ads are it enables access to deploy the services to billions of people.
Second is ads are.
..
The reason we've always taken ads seriously is we view ads as commercial information
but it's still information, and so we bring the same quality metrics to it.
I think with AI mode, to our earlier conversation about.
..
I think AI itself will help us over time figure out
you know, the best way to do it.
I, I think given we are giving context around everything
we.
..
I think it'll give us more opportunities to also explain
"Okay, here's some commercial information," like today as a podcaster you do it at certain spots and you probably figure out what's best in your podcast.
Um, I, I think so there are aspects of that
but I think, you know, I think the underlying need of people value commercial information
businesses are trying to connect to users, all that doesn't change in a AI moment.
But look, we will rethink it.
You've seen us in YouTube now do a mixture of subscription and ads.
Like obviously, you know, we, we are now introducing subscription offerings
uh, across everything.
And so as part of that we can optimi-.
..
The optimization point will end up being a different place as well.
Do you see a trajectory in the possible future where AI mode completely replaces the 10 blue links plus AI overview?
Our current plan is AI mode is going to be there as a separate tab for people who really want to experience that
but it's not yet at the level where our main search page is.
But as features work, we'll keep migrating it to the main page
and so you can view it as a continuum.
AI mode will offer you the bleeding edge experience
but it'll.
..
Things that work will keep overflowing to AI overviews in the main
main experience.
And the idea that AI mode will still take you to the web
to the human-created web.
Yes, that's going to be a core design principle for us.
So really users decide, right?
They drive this.
Yeah.
It's just exciting, a little bit scary that it might change the internet
because you.
..
Google has been dominating with a very specific look and idea of what it means to have the internet and to
as you move to AI mode, I mean
I, it's just a different experience.
Um, I think Liz was talking about
I think you've mentioned that you ask more questions
you ask longer questions.
Dramatically different types of questions.
Yeah.
Like it actually fuels curiosity.
Like I think it's.
..
For me, I've been asking just a much larger number of questions of this black box machine
let's say.
Yeah.
Whatever it is.
And, and with AI overview, it's interesting
like I.
..
'cause I still value the human.
I still ultimately want to end up on the human-created web
but I.
..
like you said, the context really helps.
It helps us deliver higher quality referrals, right?
You know, where people are like.
..
They, they have much higher likelihood of finding what they're looking for.
They're exploring, they're curious, their intent is getting satisfied more.
So all.
..
That's what all our metrics show.
It makes the humans that create the web nervous.
The journalists are getting ner-.
..
They've already been nervous, like we mentioned.
CNN is nervous because of podcasts.
Um, it makes people nervous.
Look, I, I, I think news and journalism will play an important role
you know, in the future.
Uh, we are pretty committed to it
right?
And, uh, so I think making sure that ecosystem.
..
In fact, I think we'll be able to differentiate ourselves as a company over time because of our commitment there.
So it's, it's, it's something I think
you know, I definitely value a lot and
and as we are designing, we'll continue prioritizing approaches.
I'm sure for the people who want, they can have a fine-tuned AI model that's clickbait hit pieces
uh, that will replace current journalism.
Uh, that's a shot at journalism.
Forgive me.
Uh, but I, I find that if you're looking for really strong criticism of things
that Gemini is very good at providing that.
Oh, absolutely.
It's better than anything the.
..
For now, I mean, people are concerned that there will be bias that's introduced
that as the A- AI systems become more and more powerful
there's incentive from sponsors, uh, to roll in and try to control the output of the AI models.
Uh, but for now, the objective criticism that's provided is way better than journalism.
Of course, the argument is the journalists are still valuable
but then, uh, I don't know, the crowdsourced journalism that we get on the open internet is also very
very powerful.
I feel like they're all super important things.
I think it's good that you get a lot of crowdsourced information coming in.
..
. but I feel like there is real value for high-quality j- journalism
right?
And, and I think these are all complementary.
I think, like, I view it as I find myself constantly seeking out also
like, trying to find objective reporting on
on things too, uh, and, and sometimes you get more context from the crowdfunded sources you read online
but I think both end up playing a super important role.
So there's, uh, you've spoken a little about
about this.
Dennis talked about this, sort of the
the slice of the web that will increasingly become about providing information for agents
so what we can think about is, like
two layers of the web.
One is for humans, one is for agents.
Do you see the AI agents, do you
do you see the one that's for AI agents growing over time?
Do you see there still being long-term, five
ten years' value for the human-created, human-created-for-the-purpose-of-human-consumption web
or will it all be agents in the end?
Today, like, not everyone does, but
you know, you, you go to a sh- you go to a big retail store
you love walking the aisle, you love shopping
uh, or grocery store, picking out food
et cetera.
But you're also online shopping and they're delivering
right?
So both are complementary, and, like, that's true for restaurants
et cetera.
So I do feel like over time, websites will also get better for humans.
They will be better designed.
Uh, AI might actually design them better for humans.
So I, I expect the web to get a lot richer and more interesting and
uh, better to use.
At the same time, I think there'll be an agentic web which is also making a lot of progress
and you have to solve the business value and the incentives to make that work well
right?
Like for people to participate in it.
But I think both will co-exist, and obviously the agents may not need the sa- I mean
not may not, they won't need the same design and
uh, UI paradigms which humans need to interact with.
Uh, but I think both will, both will be there.
I have to ask you about Chrome.
Uh, I have to say for me personally
Google Chrome was probably.
..
I don't know.
I, I, I'd like to see where I would rank it
but in this temptation, and this is not recency bias
although it might be a little bit, but I think it's up there
top three, maybe the number one piece of software for me of all time.
This is incredible.
It's really incredible.
The browser is our window to the web
and Chrome really continued for many years, but even initially to push the innovation on that front when it was stale
and it continues to challenge, it continues to make it more
uh, performant, so efficient, and just innovate constantly.
Uh, and the, the, the Chromium aspect of it.
Anyway,  uh, you were one of the pioneers of Chrome
pushing for it when it was an insane idea.
Probably one of the ideas that was criticized and doubted and so on.
So can you tell me, um, the story of what it took to push for Chrome?
What was your vision?
Look, it was a, such a dynamic t- time
uh, you know, around 2004, 2005 with Ajax
the web suddenly becoming dynamic in a matter of few months.
Flickr, Gmail, Google Maps, all kind of came into existence
right?
Like the fact that you have an interactive dynamic web
the web was evolving from simple, uh
text pages, simple HTML to rich dynamic applications.
But at the same time, you could see the browser was never meant for that world
right?
Like JavaScript execution was super slow.
Uh, you know, the browser was far away from being an operating system for that rich modern web which is coming into
uh, coming into place.
So that's the opportunity we saw, like
uh, you know, it's an amazing early team.
I still remember the day we got a shell on WebKit running and how fast it was.
Uh, you know, we had the clear vision for building a browser
like we wanted to bring core OS principles into the browser
right?
Like, so we built a secure browser sandbox.
Each tab was its own, but n- these things are common now
but at the time, like, it was pretty unique.
Uh, we found an amazing team in Aarhus
Denmark, uh, with the leader who built the J- V8
the JavaScript VM- Mm-hmm.
.
..
which at the time was 25 times faster than
uh, e- e- any other JavaScript VM out there.
And by the way, you're right, we open sourced it all and
you know, and put it in Chromium too
but we really thought the web could work much better
um, uh, you know, much faster and you could be much safer browsing the web.
And the name Chrome came was because we literally felt people were like
the, the, the chrome of the browser was getting clunkier.
We wanted to minimize it.
And so that was the origins of the project.
Definitely obviously a highly biased person here talking about Chrome.
Uh, but, eh, you know, it's the most fun I've had
uh, building a product from the ground up and
you know, it, it was an extraordinary team.
Uh, I had, uh, my co-founders in the project
like, perfect, so definitely fond memories.
So for people who don't know, Sundar
I mean, it is probably fair to say that y- you're the reason we have Chrome.
Yes, I know there's a lot of incredible engineers
but pushing forward inside a company that probably was opposing it.
..
. c- 'cause it's a crazy idea.
Because, um, as everybody probably knows, it's incredibly difficult to build a browser.
Yeah, look, I, uh, Eric, who was the CEO at the time
I think i- i- it was less that he was opposed to it
he kind of first time knew w- what a crazy thing it is to go build a browser.
And so he definitely was like, this is
you know, the, uh, there was a crazy aspect to actually wanting to go build a browser.
But, um, he was very supportive.
Uh, you know, everyone, uh, all the founders where.
..
I think once we started, you know
building something and we could use it and see how much better
from then on, like, you know, you're
you're really tinkering with the product and making it better.
It came to life pretty fast.
What, uh, wisdom do you draw from that?
From, um, pushing through on a crazy idea in the early days that ends up being revolutionary?
W- what, for future crazy ideas like it?
I mean, this, this is something Larry and Sergey have articulated clearly
I really interna- internalized this early on, which is
you know, their whole feeling around working on moonshots
like, as a way, when you work on something very ambitious
first of all, it attracts the best people
right?
So that's an advantage you get.
Number two, because it's so ambitious, you don't have others working on something crazy
so you pretty much have the path to yourselves
right?
It's like Waymo and self-driving.
Number three, it is, even if you end up quite not accomplishing what you set out to do and you end up doing 60%
80% of it, it'll end up being a terrific success.
So, so, you know, that's the advice I would give people
right?
I think like, you know, it's just aiming for big ideas has all these advantages and
and it's risky, but it also has all these advantages which people
I don't think, fully internalize.
I mean, you mentioned one of the craziest
biggest moonshots, which is Waymo.
Uh, it's one when I first saw
over a decade ago, a Waymo vehicle
a Google self-driving car vehicle.
I, it was, it was, for me
it was an a-ha moment for robotics.
It made me fall in love with robotics even more than before
it gave me a glimpse into the future.
So it's incredible.
I'm truly grateful for that project, for what it symbolizes.
But it's also a crazy moonshot.
'Cause for, for a long time,  Waymo's been just
uh, like you mentioned with scuba diving
just not listening to anybody, just calmly improving the system better and better
more testing, just expanding, uh, the operational domain more and more.
First of all, congrats on, uh, 10 million paid robotaxi rides.
Uh, what lessons do you take from Waymo about
like, the, the perseverance, the persistence on that project?
Well, c- really proud of the progress
uh, we have had with Waymo.
One of the things I think we were very committed to
you know, the final 20% can look like.
..
I mean, uh, we always say, right
the first 80% is easy, the final 20% takes 80% of the time.
I think we definitely, we're, we're working through that phase with Waymo
but I was aware of that, so.
But, you know, we knew we were at that stage.
We knew we were.
..
the technology gap between.
while there were many people, many other self-driving companies
we knew the technology gap was there.
In fact, we- uh, right at the moment when others were doubting Waymo is when
uh, I made the decision to invest more in Waymo
right?
Because.
..
so, uh, so in some ways it's
it's counterintuitive, uh, but I think.
..
Look, we've always been a deep technology company and like
uh, you know, Waymo is a version of kinda building a AI robot that works well.
And so we get attracted to problems like that
the caliber of the teams there, uh
you know, uh, phenomenal teams.
And so, I know you follow the space super closely
uh, you know, I'm talking to someone who knows the space well
but it was very obvious it's gonna get there
and, you know, there's still more work to do.
But we, you know, it's a good example where we always prioritized being ambitious and safety at the same time
right?
Mm-hmm.
And, and, and equally committed to both and
and pushed hard and, you know, c- couldn't be more thrilled with
uh, how it's working, uh, how much people love
love the experience.
And it, this year has definitely, we have scaled up a lot
and we'll continue scaling up in '26.
That said, uh, the competition is heating up.
You've been, uh, friendly with Elon, uh
even though technically he's a competitor, but you've been friendly with a lot of tech CEOs in that way
just showing respect towards them and so on.
What, what do you think about the robotaxi efforts that Tesla is doing?
Do you see it as competition?
What do you think?
Do you like the competition?
We are one of the earliest and biggest backers of SpaceX
uh,  as Google, uh, right?
So, uh, you know, uh, thrilled with
uh, what SpaceX is doing and fortunate to be
uh, investors as a company there, right?
And, and look, we don't compete with Tesla directly
we are not making cars, et cetera
right?
We are building L4, 5 autonomy.
We are building a Waymo driver, which is general purpose and can be used in many settings.
They're obviously working on making Tesla self-driving too.
I'm just assumed it's a de facto that Elon would succeed in whatever he does.
So, like, you know, I
I, you know, that, that, that is
uh, not something I question.
So, but I think we are so far from.
..
these spaces are such vast spaces.
Like, I, I think, think about transportation
the opportunity space, the Waymo driver is a general-purpose technology we can apply in many situations.
So you have a vast green space, um-In all future scenarios
I see Tesla doing well and, you know
Waymo doing well.
Like we mentioned with the Neolithic package, I think it's very possible that in the
quote-unquote, "AI package," when the history is written
autonomous vehicles, self-driving cars is, like, the big thing that changes everything.
Imagine over a period of, uh, a decade or two
just a complete transition from manually driven to autonomous.
In ways we went- we might not predict
it might change the way we move about the world completely
so that, you know, the possibility of that
and then the second and third order effects
as you're seeing now with Tesla, very possibly you would see some
um.
..
Internally with Alphabet, maybe Waymo, maybe some of the Gemini robotics stuff
it might lead you into the other domains of robotics 'cause we should remember that Waymo's a robot.
Mm-hmm.
It just happens to be on four wheels.
So you, you said that the next big thing
we can also throw that in the AI package
the big aha moment might be in the space of robotics.
What do you think th- that would look like?
Demis and the Google DeepMind team is very focused on Gemini robotics
right?
So we are- Yeah.
.
definitely building the underlying models well, so we have a lot of investments there
and I think we are also pretty cutting edge in our
uh, research there.
So we are definitely driving that direction.
We obviously are thinking about applications in robotics.
We'll, we'll kind of work .
..
We are partnering with a few companies today
but it's an area I would say stay tuned.
We are, you know, we are yet to fully articulate our plans outside
but it's an area we are definitely committed to driving a
a lot of progress, but I think AI ends up driving that massive progress in robotics.
The field has been held back, uh
uh, for, for a while.
I mean, the hardware has made extraordinary
uh, progress.
Uh, the software had been the challenge
but, you know, with AI now and
uh, and, and the, and the generalized models we are building
uh, you know, we are building these models
getting them to work in the real world in a safe way
in a generalized way is the frontier we're pushing pretty hard on.
Well, it's really nice to see the d- the models and the different teams integrated to where all of them are pushing towards one world model that's being built.
So from all these different angles, multimodal.
..
You're ultimately trying to get Gemini.
S- s- the same thing that would make AI mode really effective in answering your questions
which requires a kind of world model, is the same kind of thing that would help a robot be useful in the physical world
so everything's aligned.
That, that is what makes this moment so unique because running a company for the first time
you can do one investment in a very deep horizontal way.
On top of it you can, like
drive multiple businesses forward, right?
And, you know, and that's, that's effectively what we are doing in Google and Alphabet
right?
Yeah, it's all coming together like it was planned ahead of time
but it's not, of course.
It's all distributed.
I mean, if, uh, Gmail and Sheets and all these other incredible services
I can sing Gmail praises for years.
I mean, just, just revolutionized email, but the moment you start to integrate AI Gemini into Gmail.
..
I mean, that's the other thing.
Speaking of productivity multiplier, people complain about email
but that changed everything.
Email, like, the invention of email changed everything
and it's been ripe.
..
There's been a few folks trying to revolutionize email
some of them on top of Gmail, but that's
like, ripe for innovation, not just spam filtering
but  you, uh, you.
..
They demoed a really nice demo of- Personalized responses
right?
.
..
personalized responses, and it.
At first I was like.
..
At first I felt really bad about that
but then I realized that there's nothing wrong to feel bad about because when you.
..
Uh, the example you gave is when a friend asks
you know, you went to whatever hiking location
uh, "Would you.
..
Have any advice?
" And they just search just through all your information to give them good advice and then you put the cherry on top
maybe some love or whatever, camaraderie, but it.
..
The informational aspect, the knowledge transfer it does for you.
I think there'll be important moments, like it should be imp- Like today
if you write a card in your own handwriting and send it to someone
that's a special thing.
Similarly, there'll be a time, I mean
to, to your friends, maybe your friend wrote and said he's not doing well or something
and those are moments you want to save your times for writing something
reaching out, but, you know, like saying
"Give me all the details of the trip you took
" uh, you know, to me makes a lot of sense for
uh, a AI assistant to help you
right?
And, uh, uh, so I think both are important
but I think.
..
Uh, uh, I think I'm excited about that direction.
Yeah, I think ultimately it gives more time for us humans to do the things we humans find meaningful
and, uh, I think it scares a lot of people because we're gonna have to ask ourselves the hard question of like
what do we find meaningful?
And I'm sure there's answers, and it's the old question of the meaning
meaning of existence is you, you have to try to figure that out.
That might be ultimately, uh, parenting or being creative in some domains of art or writing
and it, it challenges to, to, to.
..
Like, you know, it's a good question of to ask yourself
like, "In my life, what is the thing that brings me most joy and fulfillment?
" And if I'm able to actually focus more time on that
that's really powerful.
I think that's the, uh, you know
that's the holy grail, if you get this right.
I think it allows more people, uh
to find that.
I have to ask you, on the programming front
uh, AI is getting really good at programming.
Gemini, both the agentic and just the LLM has been incredible
so a lot of programmers are really worried that their jobs.
..
They will lose their jobs.
Uh, how worried should they be, and how should they adjust so they can be thriving in this new world where more and more code is written by AI?
I think a few things.
Looking at Google, um, you know, we've given various stats around like
you know, 30% of, uh, code now uses
like, AI-generated suggestions or whatever it is.
But the most important metric, and we carefully measure this
like, how much has our engineering velocity increased as a company due to AI
right?
And it's, like, tough to measure and we kind of rigorously try to measure it.
And our estimates are at, that number is now at 10%
right?
Like, now across the company we've accomplished a 10% engineering velocity increase using AI but we plan to hire engineers
more engineers next year, right?
So you, uh, because the opportunity space of what we can do is expanding too
right?
Mm-hmm.
And so I think hopefully, you know
for, uh, at least in the near to mid-term
for many engineers, it frees up more and more of the
uh, you know, even in engineering and coding
there are aspects which are so much fun.
You're designing, you're architecting, you're solving a problem.
There's a lot of grunt work, you know
which all goes hand-in-hand.
But it hopefully takes a lot of that away
makes it even more fun to code, frees you up more time to create
problem solve, brainstorm with your fellow colleagues and so on
right?
So that's, that's the opportunity there.
And second, I think, like, you know
it'll attract.
..
uh, it'll put the creative power in more people's hands
which means people create more.
That means there'll be more engineers doing more things.
So it's tough to fully predict, but
you know, I think in general in this moment
it feels like, you know, you know
people, uh, adopt these tools and be better programmers.
Like, there are more people playing chess now than ever before
right?
So, uh, you know, it feels positive that way to me
at least speaking from within a Google context
uh, is how I would, you know
talk to them about it.
I still, I just know anecdotally, a lot of great programmers are generating a lot of code.
Yeah.
So their productivity, they're not always using all the code just.
..
you know, it's, there's still a lot of editing.
But like even for me, I'm still programming as a side thing
I think I'm like 5X more productive.
I don't.
..
I think that's, uh.
even for a large code base that's touching a lot of users like Google's does
I'm imagining like very soon that productivity should be going up even more.
Oh, the big unlock will be as we make the agented capabilities much more robust
right?
Mm-hmm.
I think that's what unlocks that next big wave.
I think the 10% is, like, a massive number.
Like, you know, if tomorrow like I showed up and said like
"You can improve like a large organization's productivity by 10%.
" When you have tens of thousands of engineers
that's a phenomenal number.
Uh, and, you know, that's different than what others cite as statistics saying like
you know, like, "This percentage of code is now written by AI.
" I'm talking more about like overall.
..
Actual productivity.
.
..
uh, actual productivity, right?
Engineering productivity, which is two different things
and, uh, which is the more important
uh, metric.
And, but I think it'll get better
right?
And like, you know, uh, I think there's no engineer who tomorrow if you magically became 2X more productive
you're just gonna create more things, you're gonna create more value-added things.
And so I think they, you'll, you'll find more satisfaction in your job
right?
So.
And there's a lot of aspects.
I mean, the actual Google code base might just improve because it'll become more standardized
more, um, easier for people to move about the code base because AI will help with that.
And therefore, that will also allow the AI to understand the entire code base better
which makes the engineering aspect.
And so I've been using Cursor a lot- Yeah.
.
..
uh, as, as a way to program with Gemini and other models.
It's like, it.
..
one of its powerful things is it's aware of the entire code base
and that allows you to ask questions of it
it allows the agents to move about that code base in a really powerful way.
I mean, that's a huge unlock.
Think about, like, you know, migrations
refactoring old code bases.
Refactoring, yeah.
Yeah.
I mean, th- think about like, you know
once we can do all this in a much better
more robust way than where we are today.
I think in the end everything will be written in JavaScript and run
run in Chrome.
.
I think  it's all going to that
uh, direction.
I mean, just for fun, Google has legendary coding
coding interviews, uh, like rigorous interviews for the engineers.
How.
..
can you comment on how that has changed in the era of AI?
It's just such a weird.
..
uh, you know, the whiteboard interview
uh, I assume is now allowed to have some prompts.
Such a, a, a good question.
Look, I do think, you know, we're making sure
you know, we'll, we'll introduce at least one round of in-person interviews for people-  Yeah.
.
..
just to make sure the fundamentals are there.
I think they'll end up being important.
But it's an equally important skill.
Look, if you can use these tools to generate better code
uh, like, you know, I think
I think that's an asset.
And so, uh, you know, I think
uh.
..
so overall I think it's a, it's a massive positive.
Vibe coding engineer.
Uh, do you recommend, uh, pe- people
uh, students interested in programming still get an education
uh, in computer science, a college education?
What do you think?
I do.
If you have a passion for computer science
I would.
You know, computer science is obviously a lot more than programming alone.
So I would.
I still don't think I would change what you pursue
um-I think AI will horizontally allow impact every field.
It's pretty tough to predict in what ways.
So any education in which you're learning good first principles thinking
I think is good education.
You've revolutionized web browsing.
You've re- revolutionized a lot of things over the years.
Um, Android changed the game.
It's an incredible, uh, operating system.
We could talk for hours about Android.
What does the future of Android look like?
Is it, is it possible it becomes more and more AI-centric
uh, especially now that you throw into the mix Android XR with
uh, being able to do augmented reality and
um, mixed reality and virtual reality in the physical world?
You know, the best innovations in computing have come when your
uh, through a paradigm IO change, right?
Like, you know, when, when.
..
with GWE and then with the graphic user interface and then with multi-touch in the context of mobile voice later on.
Similarly, I feel like, uh, you know
AR is that next paradigm.
I think it was held back both the system integration challenges of making good AR is very
very hard.
The second thing is you need AI to actually kind of.
..
otherwise the IO is too complicated.
For you to have a natural seamless IO to that
uh, uh, paradigm, AI ends up being super important.
And so this is why Project Astra ends up being super critical for that Android
uh, XR world.
Uh, but it is.
I think when you use glasses and, you know
always been amazed like at the, at the how useful these things are going to be.
So I.
..
look, I think it's a real opportunity for Android.
I think XR is one way it will kind of really come to life.
But I think there's an opportunity to rethink the mobile OS too
right?
I think we've been kind of living in this paradigm of
like, apps and shortcuts, all that won't go away.
But again, like if you're trying to get stuff done at an operating system level
you know, it needs to be more agentic so that you can kind of describe what you want to do or
like, it proactively understands what you're trying to do
learns from how you're doing things over and over again and kind of is adapting to you.
All that is kind of, like, the unlock we need to go and do.
Uh, with a basic efficient, minimalist, uh
UI, I've gotten a chance to try the glasses and they're incredible.
It's the little stuff.
It's hard to put into words, but no latency.
It just works.
Even that little map demo where you look down and you look up and there's a very smooth transition between the two
and useful.
..
very small amount of useful information is shown to you.
Enough not to distract from the world outside
but enough to provide a bit of context when you need it.
And some of that be-.
..
in order to bring that into reality, you have to solve a lot of the OS problems to make sure it works when you're integrating the AI into the whole thing.
So every- everything you do launches an agent that answers some basic question for you.
It's a good moonshot.
You know, I lo- like that.
Yeah.
It's crazy.
No, but, but, you know, I think
uh, we are, you know.
..
but it's much closer to reality than, uh
other moonshots.
You know, we expect to have glasses in the hands of developers later this year and
and i- i- you know, in consumer science next year.
So it's an exciting time.
Yeah.
Well ex- extremely well executed.
Beam.
..
a- all the stuff, you know, 'cause I.
sometimes you don't know, like somebody commented on a
uh, a top comment on one of the demos of Beam.
Uh, they said, uh, "This will either be killed off in five weeks or revolutionize all meetings in five years.
" And th- there's very much.
..
Google tries so many things and sometimes sadly kills off very promising projects be- because there's so many other things to focus on.
I use, I use so many Google products.
Google Voice I still use.
I'm so glad that's not being killed off.
That's still alive.
Thank you, f- whoever is defending that
'cause it's, it's awesome.
And i- it's great they keep innovating.
I- I just want to list off just as a big thank you.
So Search, obviously Google revolutionized.
Chrome and all of these could be multi-hour conversations.
Gmail, I've been singing Gmail praises forever.
Maps, incredible technological innovation on revolutionizing mapping.
Android, like we talked about.
YouTube, like we talked about.
AdSense, uh, Google  Translate for the academic mind of Google Scholar is incredible when the.
..
with the b- and also the scanning of the books.
So making all the world's knowledge, um
accessible even when that knowledge is a kind of niche thing
which Google Scholar is.
Uh, and then obviously with DeepMind, uh
with AlphaZero, AlphaFold, AlphaEvolve.
I could talk forever about AlphaEvolve.
That's mind-blowing all of that  released.
And as part of that, uh, set of things you've released in this year when
uh, those brilliant articles were written about Google is done.
Uh, and, uh, like we talked about pioneering self-driving cars and quantum computing
which could be another thing that is low key as scuba diving its way to changing the world forever.
Uh, so another potheads/microkitchen question,  if you build AGI
what kind of question would you ask it?
Wh- what would you, what would you want to talk about?
Definitively, Google has created AGI that can basically answer any question.
What topic are you going to?
What.
..
where, where's the, where's the.
where are you going?
It's a great question.
Um, maybe it's proactive by then and shou- should tell me a few things I should know.
But I think if I were to ask it-I think it'll help us understand ourselves much better
um, in a way that'll surprise us
I think.
Um, and so maybe that's.
..
You already see people do it with the products.
And so.
..
But, you know, in the AGI context
I think that'll be pretty powerful.
On a personal level or, or general human nature?
On a personal level, like you talking to AGI.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
I think, I think, you know, uh
there is some chance it'll, it'll kinda understand you in a
in a very deep way, uh, I think
uh, you know, in a profound way
that's a possibility.
Uh, I, I think there's also the obvious thing of
like, maybe it helps us understand the universe better
um, you, you know, in a way that expands the frontiers of our understanding of the world.
Uh, that is something super exciting.
But, look, I, I really don't know.
I think, you know, I haven't, I haven't had access to something that powerful yet
but I think those are all possibilities.
I think that on the personal level, asking questions about yourself could.
..
a sequence of questions like that about, "What makes me happy?
" I think we'd be very surprised to learn the.
..
those kind of the, um.
a sequence of questions and answers we might explore some profound truths in the way that sometimes art reveals to us
great books reveal to us, great conversations with loved ones reveal
uh, things that are obvious in retrospect
but are nice when they're said.
Uh, but for me, number one question is about how many alien civilizations are there?
.
100%.
Are they- That's gonna be your first question?
.
Number one, how many living and dead alien civilizations?
Um, maybe a bunch of follow-ups, like
how close are they?
Are they dangerous?
Um, if, if there's no alien civilizations
why?
Uh, or if there's n- no advanced alien civilizations
but bacteria, like life everywhere, why?
What is the barrier preventing it from getting to that?
Uh, is it because that there's, uh.
..
that when you get sufficiently intelligent, you end up
uh, destroying ourselves because you need competition in order to develop an advanced civilization?
And when you have competition, it's going to lead to military conflict
and conflict eventually kills everybody.
I don't know.
I'm gonna have that kind of discussion.
Get a, get an answer to the Fermi paradox.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And, like, have a real discussion about it.
I'm not sure if it's a, um.
..
I'm realizing now with your answer, it's a more productive
um, answer 'cause I'm not sure what I'm gonna do with that information
but maybe it speaks to the general human curiosity that Liz talked about
that we're all just really curious.
And making the world's information accessible allows our curiosity to be satiated s- some.
With AI even more, we can be more and more curious and learn more about the world
about ourselves.
And in so doing, I always wonder if.
..
I don't know if you can comment on
like, is it possible to measure the.
..
not the GDP productivity increase, like we talked about
but maybe the.
..
whatever that increases, the, the breadth and depth of human knowledge that Google has unlocked with Google Search
and now with AI Mode, with Gemini
it's a difficult thing to measure.
Many years ago, there was a.
..
I think it was a MIT study, they just estimated the impact of Google Search
and they basically said it's the equivalent to.
..
on a per person basis, it's few thousands of dollars per year per person
right?
Uh, like it's value that got created per year
And, and.
..
but it's, yeah, it's tough to capture these things
right?
Like, you kind of take it, take it for granted as these things come
uh, and, and the frontier keeps moving
but, uh, you know, how do you measure the value of something like AlphaFold over time
right?
And, and, and, and so on.
So it's- And also the increase in quality of life when you learn more.
I have to say, like, with, uh
some of the programming I do done by AI
for some reason I'm more excited to program.
Yeah.
Uh, and so the same with knowledge
with discovering things about the world, uh
it makes you more excited to be alive
it makes you more curious to.
..
And it keeps.
The more curious you are, the more exciting it is to live and experience the world.
And it's very hard to.
..
I don't know if that makes you more productive.
It probably.
..
not nearly as much as it makes you happy to be alive.
And that's a hard thing to measure the quality of life increase that some of these things do.
As AI continues to get better and better at everything that humans do
what do you think is the biggest thing that makes us humans special?
Look, I, I, I think it's tough to.
..
I mean, the essence of humanity, there's something about
uh, you know, the consciousness we have
what makes us uniquely human, maybe the lines will blur over time
uh, and, and it's tough to articulate
but, uh, I hope.
..
hopefully, you know, we live in a world where if you make resources more plentiful and make the world le- uh
lesser of a zero-sum game over time, right?
And, and.
..
which it's not, but, you know, in a resource constrained environment
people perceive it to be, right?
And, and, um, and so I hope the
the values of what makes us uniquely human
empathy, kindness, all that surfaces more is the aspirational hope I have.
Yeah, it multiplies the compassion, but also the curiosity.
Just the, the banter, the debates we'll have about the meaning of it all.
And I, I a- also think in the scientific domains
all the incredible work that DeepMind is doing
I think we'll still continue to, to play
to explore scientific questions, uh, mathematical questions
physics questions, even as AIs.
..
. gets better and better at helping us solve some of the questions.
Sometimes, the question itself is a really difficult thing.
Uh, both the right new questions to ask and the answers to them and
and, and the self-discovery process which it'll drive
I think.
You know, our early work with both CoScientists and AlphaEvolve just is just super exciting to see.
What gives you hope about the future of human civilization?
Look, I've always.
..
I'm, I'm, I'm an optimist and, you know
I, I, I look at, um.
..
Now, if you were to say you take the journey of human civilization
uh, it's been, you know, we've relentlessly ma- made the world better
right, in many ways.
At any given moment in time, there are big issues to work through.
It may look, but, you know, I always ask myself the question
"Would you have been born now or any other time in the past?
" I most often, not most often, almost always would rather be born now
right?
You know?
And so that's the extraordinary thing that human civilization has accomplished
right?
And, like, you know, and we've
we've kind of constantly made the world a better place.
And so something tells me as humanity we always rise collectively to drive that
uh, frontier forward.
So I expect it to be no different in the future.
I agree with you totally.
I'm truly grateful to be alive in this moment
and I'm also really excited for the future.
And the work, uh, you and the incredible teams here are doing is one of the big reasons I'm excited for the future.
So thank you.
Thank you for all the cool products you've built
and please don't kill Google Voice.
Uh, the- Thank you, Sundar.
We won't, yeah.
Thank you for talking today.
This was incredible.
Thank you.
Real pleasure.
Appreciate it.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Sundar Pichai.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description or at lexfridman.
com/sponsors.
Shortly before this conversation, I got a chance to get a couple of demos that frankly blew my mind.
The engineering was really impressive.
The first demo was Google Beam, and the second demo was the XR glasses.
And some of it was caught on video.
So I thought I would include here some of those
uh, video clips.
Hey, Lex.
Hi there.
My name's Andrew.
I lead the Google Beam team, and we're gonna be excited to show you a demo.
We're gonna show you, I think, a glimpse of something new.
So that's the idea, a way to connect
a way to feel present from anywhere with anybody you care about.
Here's Google Beam.
This is a development platform that we've built.
So there's a prototype here of Google Beam.
There's one right down the hallway.
I'm gonna go down and turn that on in a second.
We're gonna experience it together.
We'll be back in the same room.
Wonderful.
Whoa.
Okay.
Hey, Lex.
Here we are.
All right.
Okay.
This is real already.
Wow.
This is real.
Good to see you.
This is Google Beam.
Uh-huh.
We're trying to make it feel like you and I could be anywhere in the world
but when these magic windows open, we're back together.
I see you exactly the same way you see me.
It's almost like we're sitting at the table sharing a table together.
I could- Yeah.
.
you know, learn from you, talk to you
share a meal with you, get to know you.
So you can feel the depth of this.
Uh, or just use your hand.
Yeah, great for me too.
Wow.
So for people who probably can't even imagine what this looks like
there's a, there's a 3D version.
It looks real.
You look real.
Yeah.
It looks, to me, it looks real to you.
It looks like you're coming out of the screen.
And we, we quickly believe, um, once we're in Beam that we're just together.
Yeah.
Yep.
Like, you settle into it.
You're naturally attuned to seeing the world like this
and you just get used to seeing people this way but literally from anywhere in the world with these magic screens.
This is incredible.
It's a neat technology.
Wow.
So I saw demos of this but they're
they don't come close to the experience of this.
Right.
Yeah, I think one of the top YouTube comments on one of the demos I saw was like
"Why would I want a high definition?
Like, I'm trying to turn off the camera.
" Yeah.
But this actually is, this feels like the camera's been turned off and we're just in the same room together.
This is really compelling.
That's right.
I, I know it's kind of late in the day too
so I brought you a snack just in case you're a little bit hungry.
But, um.
..
So what, uh, can you push it farther and it just becomes
ah- Yeah.
Let's, let's try to float it between rooms
you know?
It kind of fades it from my room into your world.
And then, and then you see my hand
the depth of my hand.
Yeah, of course.
Yeah.
Wow.
Of course, yeah.
It feels like you've.
..
Um, try this.
Try giving me a high five, and there's almost a sensation of human touch.
Yeah.
You can almost feel- Yes.
.
..
because you're so attuned to, you know
that should be a high five, it feeling like you could connect with somebody that way.
Yeah.
So it's kind of a magical experience.
Oh, this is really nice.
How much does it cost?
Yeah, you.
..
Would, would you.
Got a lot of companies testing it.
We just announced that we're gonna be bringing it to offices soon as a set of products.
We've got some companies helping us build these screens.
Um, but eventually I think this will be in almost every screen.
There's nothing, I'm not wearing anything.
Well, I'm wearing a suit and tie- I don't think so.
.
to clarify.
Yeah.
I am wearing clothes.
This is not CGI.
But outside of that, cool, and the audio's really good.
And you can see me in this same three-dimensional way.
Yeah.
Okay.
The audio's spatialized, so if I'm talking from here
of course it sounds like I'm talking from here.
You know, if I move to the other side of the room- Wow.
.
..
I'm here.
Uh, so these little subtle cues, these really matter to bring people together.
All the non-verbals, all the emotion, the things that are lost today
here it is.
We put it back into this system.
You pulled this off.
And it feels like you're.
..
Holy shit.
They pulled it off.
And integrated- Yeah.
.
into this, I saw the translation also.
Right?
This is the- Yeah, we've got a bunch of things.
Let, let me show you a couple kind of cool things.
Let's do a little bit of work together.
Maybe we could, um, critique one- Yeah.
.
of your latest, uh.
..
Um, so, uh, you know
it's you and I work together, so of course we're in the same room
but with this superpower I can bring other teams- Look at that.
.
in here with me.
Um, and it's, it's nice.
It, you know, it's like we could sit together
we could watch something, we could work.
Um, we've shared meals as a team together in this system.
But once you do the presence aspect of this- Wow.
.
you wanna bring some other superpowers to it.
And so you can do, review code together.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
I've got some, uh, slides I'm working on.
You know, maybe you could help me with this.
Keep your eyes on me for a second.
I'll slide back into the center.
I didn't really move, but the system just kind of puts us in the right spot and knows where we need to be.
Oh, so you just turn to your laptop
the system moves you, and then it does the overlay automatically?
It kind of morphs the room to put things- Yeah.
.
in the spot that they need to, to be in.
Everything has a place in the room.
Everything has a sense of presence or spatial consistency
and that kind of makes it feel like we're together with us and other things.
I, I should also say, you're not just three-dimensional.
It feels like you're leaning, like, out of the screen.
You f- you- I am?
You're like coming out of the screen.
Right.
You're not just in that world three-dimensional.
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
Holy crap.
All right.
So- Move back to center?
Okay, okay, yeah, yeah.
Let, let me tell you how this works.
You probably already have the, the premise of it
but there's two things.
Yeah.
Two really hard things that we put together.
One is a AI video model.
So there's a set of cameras, you asked kind of about those earlier.
There's six color cameras, just like webcams that we have today- Mm-hmm.
.
taking video streams and feeding them into our AI model and turning that into a 3D video of you and I.
Mm-hmm.
It's effectively a light field, so it's kind of an interactive 3D video that you can see from any perspective.
That's transmitted over to the second thing, and that's a light field display
and it's happening bidirectionally.
I see you and you see me both in our light field displays.
These are effectively flat televisions or flat displays
but they have this sense of dimensionality, depth
size is correct.
You can see shadows and lighting are correct.
Mm-hmm.
And everything's correct from your vantage point.
So if you move around ever so slightly and I hold still
you see a different perspective here.
You see kind of things that were occluded become revealed.
You see shadows that, you know, moving the way they should move.
All of that's computed and generated using our AI video model for you.
It's based on your eye position.
Where does the right scene need to be placed in this light field display for you just to feel present?
It's real time, no latency.
I'm not seeing late- you weren't freezing up at all.
No, no, I hope not.
I think it's-  It's you and I together
real time.
That's what you need for real communication, and at a
at a quality level that I think is- This is awesome.
.
..
realistic.
Is it possible to do three people?
Like, is that gonna move that way also?
Yeah.
Let me, let me kind of show you.
So if, if she enters the room with us- Mm-hmm.
.
..
you can see her, you can see me
and if we add more people, you eventually lose the sense of presence.
You kind of shrink people down, you lose a sense of scale.
So think of it as the window fits a certain number of people.
Mm-hmm.
If you want to fit a big group of people
you want, you know, the board room or the big room
you need like a much wider window.
Um, if you want to see, you know
just grandma and the kids, you can do smaller windows.
So everybody has a seat at the table
everybody has a sense of where they belong
and there's kind of this sense of presence that's obeyed.
If you have too many people, you kind of go back to like 2D metaphors that we're used to
people in tiles placed anywhere.
For the image I'm seeing, did you have to get scanned?
I, I mean, I see you without being scanned.
So it's just so much easier if you don't have to wear anything
you don't have to pre-scan.
Yeah.
You just do it the way it's supposed to happen without anybody having to learn anything or put anything on.
I thought you had to solve the, the scanning problem
but here you don't.
It's just cameras.
No, that's right.
It's just vision.
That's right.
It, it's video.
Yeah, we're not trying to kind of make an approximation of you
because everything you do every day matters, you know?
I cut myself shaving-  .
..
I put on a pin.
Um, all the little kind of, you know
aspects of you, those just happen.
Um, we don't have the time to scan or kind of capture those or dress avatars.
We, we kind of appear as we appear.
And so all that's transmitted truthfully as it's happening.
Chris, still, how you doing?
Nice to meet you.
So, um, as Max mentioned, we've got AI glasses here.
We start with, um, a foundation of great glasses
something stylish, lightweight, wearable.
Then we say, "How can we build great technology and experiences on top of that?
" Um, one of the core tenets of the Android XR platform
this idea of a multimodal conversational device, see what you see
hear what you hear.
So you've got a camera, you've got speakers
multiple microphones for speaker isolation.
Um, I'll give you a chance to try these yourself.
Yeah.
Sorry.
All right.
We'll put it up there.
Whoa.
Yeah.
So the first thing you see- Yeah.
.
is a super, uh, simple, straightforward home screen.
Yes.
So you probably see the time, the weather
calendar appointments there.
This is designed to be sort of your one-stop shop for quick glanceable information throughout the day.
Mm-hmm.
We want it to be something that's, um
easy to, you know, get what you need and then go back to what you're doing.
So you can imagine, you know, turning on the display
getting that quick glance, and then, um
continuing on your way.
You can be fully conversational at this point.
You can, um, ask questions, for example
about the paintings.
You can interrupt, you can ask follow-up questions.
And as I mentioned before, if you want to at any time pause
you just tap there on the right.
Gemini, how much does this painting cost?
The painting is called The Bridge of Les Filippes
1875 by Armand Guillaumin.
It appears to be a print, and it would be impossible to know its cost without finding the seller.
Okay, so this is fake.
I understand.
Why do humans pay so much money for paintings?
People pay a lot for paintings because of their artistic merit
the artist's fame, sense of rarity, and for the appreciation you can learn.
So, uh, a few more things that we want to show you just for
uh, sake of time.
Could you go ahead and long press on the side again to
to sleep Gemini there?
Um, there you go.
Um, did you catch Google I/O last week by any chance?
Yes.
So you might have seen on stage the
uh, Google Maps experience very briefly.
Mm-hmm.
I wanted to give you a chance to get a sense of what that feels like today.
You can imagine you're walking down the street.
If you look up like you're walking straight ahead
you get quick turn-by-turn directions.
So you have a sense of-  Well done.
.
what the next turn is like- Nice.
..
without taking your phone in your pocket.
Oh, that's so intuitive.
Sometimes you need that quick sense of which way- Yeah.
.
is the right way.
Sometimes.
Yeah.
So you, let's say you're coming out of the subway- Every time.
.
getting out of a cab, you can just glance down at your feet.
We have it set up to translate from Russian to English.
Mm-hmm.
I think I get to wear the glasses.
And you speak to me if you don't mind.
I can speak Russian.
Uh, .
I'm doing well.
How are you doing?
Tempted to swear, tempted to say inappropriate things.
.
Uh, I see it transcribed in real time
and so obviously, you know, based on the
uh, different languages and sequence of subjects and verbs
there's a slight delay sometimes, but it's really just like subtitles for the real world.
Cool.
Thank you for this.
All right, back to me.
Hopefully watching videos of me having my mind blown like the apes in 2001: A Space Odyssey playing with a monolith was
uh, somewhat interesting.
Uh, like I said, I was very impressed.
And now I thought if it's okay, I could make a few additional comments about the episode and just in general.
In this conversation with Sundar Pichai, I discussed the concept of the Neolithic package
which is the set of innovations that came along with the first agricultural revolution about 12
000 years ago, which included the formation of social hierarchies
the early primitive forms of government, labor specialization
domestication of plants and animals, early forms of trade
large-scale cooperations of humans like that required to build
yes, the pyramids and temples like Gbekli Tepe.
I think this may be the right way to actually talk about the inventions that changed human history.
Not just as a single invention, but as a kind of network of innovations and transformations that came along with it.
And the productivity multiplier framework that I mentioned in the episode
I think is a nice way to try to concretize the impact of each of these inventions under consideration.
And, uh, we have to remember that each node in the network of the sort of fast follow-on inventions is in itself a productivity multiplier.
Some are additive, some are multiplicative.
So in some sense, the size of the network in the package is the thing that matters when you're trying to rank the impact of
uh, inventions on human history.
The easy picks for the period of biggest transformation
at least in sort of, uh, modern day discourse
is the Industrial Revolution, or even, uh
in the 20th century, the computer or the internet.
I think it's because it's easiest to intuit for modern day humans the impact
the exponential impact, uh, of those technologies.
But recently, and I suppose this changes week to week
but, uh, I have been doing a lot of reading on ancient human history
so recently my pick for the number one invention would have to be the first agricultural revolution
the Neolithic package that led to the formation of human civilizations.
That's what enabled the scaling of the collective intelligence machine of humanity
and for us to become the early bootloader for the next 10
000 years of technological progress, which, yes
includes AI and the tech that builds on top of AI.
And of course, it could be argued that the word invention doesn't properly apply to the agricultural revolution.
I think actually, uh, Yuval Noah Harari argues that it wasn't the humans who were the inventors
but, uh, a handful of plant species
namely wheat, rice, and potatoes.
This is strictly a fair perspective, but I'm having fun
like I said, with this discussion.
Here, I just think of the entire Earth as a system that continuously transforms
and I'm using the term invention in that context
asking the question of when was the biggest leap on the log scale plot of
uh, human progress?
Will AI, AGI, ASI eventually take the number one spot on this ranking?
I think it has a very good chance to do so
due, again, to the size of the network of inventions that will come along with it.
I think we discussed in this podcast, uh
the kind of things that would be included in the so-called AI package
but I think there's, uh, a lot more possibilities
including, uh, discussed in previous podcasts, in many previous podcasts
including with Dariam Aday, uh, talking on the biological innovation side
the science progress side.
In this podcast, I think we talk about something that I'm particularly excited about in the near term
which is unlocking the cognitive capacity of the entire landscape of brains that is the human species.
Making it more accessible through education and through machine translation
making information knowledge and the rapid learning and innovation process accessible to more humans
to the entire eight billion, if you will.
So I do think language or machine translation applied to all the different methods that we use on the internet to discover knowledge is
uh, a big unlock.
But there are a lot of other stuff in the so-called AI package
like discussed with Dario, curing all major human diseases.
He really focuses on that in the Machines of Love and Grace essay.
I think there will be huge leaps in productivity for human programmers and semi-autonomous human programmers
so humans in the loop, but most of the programming is done by AI agents
and then moving that towards a superhuman AI researcher that's doing the research that develops and programs the AI system in itself.
I think there will be huge transformative effects from autonomous vehicles.
These are the things that we maybe don't immediately understand or we understand from an economics perspective
but there will be a point when AI systems are able to interpret
understand, interact with the human world to a sufficient degree to where many of the manually controlled human in the loop systems we rely on become fully autonomous.
And I think mobility is such a big part of human civilization that.
..
There will be effects on that, that are not just economic
but are social, cultural, and so on.
And there's a lot more things I could talk about for a long time.
So obviously, the integration, u- utilization of AI in the creation of art
film, music.
I think the digitalization and, um, automating basic functions of government and then integrating AI into that process
thereby decreasing corruption and cost and increasing transparency and
uh, efficiency.
I think we as humans, individual humans will continue to transition further and further into cyborgs.
So the- there's already a AI in the loop of the human condition
and that will become increasingly so as the AI becomes
uh, more powerful.
The thing I'm obviously really excited about is major breakthroughs in science
and not just in the medical front, but
uh, in physics, fundamental physics, which would then lead to energy breakthroughs
increasing the chance that we become, we actually become a Kardashev type I civilization
and then enabling us in so doing to do interstellar exploration of space and colonization of space.
I think there- also, in the near term
much like with the, uh, Industrial Revolution that led to rapid specialization of skills and expertise
there might be a great sort of de-specialization.
So as the AI, AI system become superhuman experts at particular fields
there might be greater and greater value to being the integrator of AIs
for humans to be sort of generalists.
Uh, and so the great value of the human mind will come from the generalists
not the specialists.
That's a real possibility that that changes the way we are about the world
that we wanna know a little bit of a lot of things and move about the world in that way.
That could have, when passing a certain threshold
a complete shift in who we are as a collective intelligence
as a, as a human species.
Also, as an aside, when thought thinking about the invention that was the greatest in human history
again, for a bit of fun, we have to remember that all of them build on top of each other.
And so we need to look at the delta
the step change on the, I would say
impossibly to perfectly measured plot of exponential human progress.
Really, we can go back to the entire history of life on Earth
and, uh, previous podcast guest, Nick Lane
does a great job of this in his book
Life Ascending, listing these 10 major inventions throughout the evolution of life on Earth
like DNA, photosynthesis, complex cells, sex
movement, sight, all those kinds of things.
I forget the full list that's on there
but I think that's so far from the human experience that my intuition about
let's say, productivity multipliers of those particular invention completely
uh, breaks down, and, uh, a different framework is needed to understand the impact of these inventions of evolution.
The origin of life on Earth or even the Big Bang itself
of course, is the OG invention that set the stage for all the rest of it
and there are probably many more turtles under that which are yet to be discovered.
So anyway, we live in interesting times
fellow humans.
I do believe the set of positive trajectories for humanity outnumber the set of negative trajectories
but not by much.
So, uh, let's not mess this up.
And now, let me leave you with some words from French philosopher Jean de la Bruyre
"Out of difficulties grow miracles.
" Thank you for listening, and hope to see you next time.