well, i'm glad you're still here.
i'm also glad i'm still here.
yes.
i mean, those of us who know you and who have followed you,
uh, looked at our phones one morning in august, i think,
and it was pablo dv disappears in france,
arrested.
um, and then, you know, no one heard from you for several days.
it was it was kind of
it was actually kind of a pivot point in the way i understand europe,
speaking for myself.
so, if you don't mind, i don't think you've done any interviews since then.
what like what happened that day?
you just like the events of the day.
let's start there.
august last year.
august last year, i arrived to paris
and i'm greeted in the airport by a few what were you doing here?
i just
for touristic
po purposes
like i was just hanging
around for
a couple of days and i was supposed to go to finland
after
and
i wasn't supposed to stay.
there was no business meeting of any kind and i was greeted by policemen.
they asked me certain questions asked me to follow them.
were you confused like why are policemen meeting me at the airport?
definitely.
at first i thought there may be some additional
security checks because of the olympics of the parolympics.
something's going on.
julia, my girlfriend, she was worried.
she was asking me is is it all right?
i said it's all right.
it's france.
it's fine.
of course.
and and then they read me a list of charges like i know 16 charges
all kinds of crimes.
i was very confused at first because like i have nothing to do with crime.
i've never been convicted.
i have, you know,
we are a company that is trying to comply with the with the best standards.
and and so at at at that moment, i realized that
it's not something i did, it's something other people did using the app i created,
telegram, which is used by a billion people.
so probably some people do you know all of them or unfortunately, not.
okay.
unfortunately.
um i try my best to meet more but
so yeah and then i was put into a car and
with a small motorcade with police cars with sirens and
which is funny because in pre in the previous countries that i visited
i also was accompanied by motorcades because i was visiting the heads of states there.
and here in france there was certain consistency.
so i was greeted in the same way so to say.
were you like texting?
i couldn't because they took my phone and i wasn't they immediately took your phone?
yeah.
i wasn't allowed to contact anyone except for my assistant
who i
asked to find me some lawyers
and reach out to certain friends that i have and try to understand what was going
on.
and then i spent four days in police custody.
a building in south of paris that
that is i think run by the police customs the customs police officers or department whatever
and there i had
to answer a lot of questions
but you spent 4 days with no contact no phone
yes in what kind of accommodations
was a seven seven square meter room or 70 ft room.
uh, no windows, concrete block.
um, a bed this narrow.
uh, no linen, no pillow, a mattress this thin, like yoga mat this thin.
uh, maybe 1 cm, 1/2 in, and that's it.
and constantly, uh, blinking light, which was a bit annoying.
locked door.
there's yeah, the the door was very securely
locked, i must so you're in a you're in a cell?
yes, it was a solitary cell, so to say.
there were no other people there.
so they put you in solitary confinement.
you could say that.
yes.
well, sounds like that's what it is.
well, it wasn't a prison or or or jail.
it wasn't.
well, if there's a locked door, no pillow, but legally speaking, it wasn't.
yeah.
legally speaking, so legally speaking,
why were you being held against your will by the french government?
did you ever in the first four days were did they make it clear to you?
so i understood that they were worried about the alleged
um
lack of response
from telegram towards
the judicial requests coming from france
which turned out to be not true because we've never received a single
legally binding legal request coming from france.
so i was even more confused and
i i asked the the french policeman, why haven't you been
following the european law and
serving your legal request in the way prescribed by this law, right?
it's defined by the digital services act and it's it's it's there.
it's you can google the process.
you you can read the privacy policy of telegram.
it's easily accessible on the website.
so why didn't you do it?
and they didn't answer
but thanks god they started to do it and and then they started to receive responses
helping them to identify criminal suspects
meaning we would disclose ip address and phone number
of
people
who were suspects in criminal investigations
when we received court orders
signed by a judge right and this was something that we had in place
since a year ago before that so it's it's not something that the french
have forced us to do.
it's something that we already had in place.
we had a company in belgium processing these requests.
other countries have successfully been using this process.
but somehow the french have ignored it completely.
and this is why you know i was very surprised why haven't you been doing this?
why?
but this is the process.
and and to be clear, i mean i think this is like standard for social media
companies.
a company
whether it's facebook
or x
or
snapchat
or any of them get a court order
from a
country
in which
they have users
and the court order says
you know we have reasonably
this person's a criminal can we have the ip address
i think they all comply
with that
correct
yes
well it's the dsa law
if you don't comply with it
you can be
fined you can be banned
well it's a question whether you want to continue
providing your service in the european union but it's only
concerns it only concerns
the identification data meaning ip address and in some
cases phone number of the suspect.
it has nothing to do with for example
private messages of a person or other kinds of activity
which is much more protected
much more private even if we wanted to we wouldn't be able to disclose this information
but it's not required by the law.
yes.
but what you're describing is
like the state of play across europe anyway for all the companies.
exactly.
okay.
so, but
because this is like a normal thing that's already take it's a process that everyone recognizes
and it's been ongoing.
you must be very confused
as to why you're being held in this jail that they're not calling a jail.
were you confus like were you worried?
it was very hard to i stepped off an airplane
and a bunch of cops showed up,
took
my phone
away
and threw me in the back of a car and
took me to a
cell
even
if they pretended
it was not a jail but wouldn't let me out and lock the door
for 4 days without
being able to contact my family.
i'd be concerned.
were were you concerned?
that was very surprising.
i was shocked.
i was you're very diplomatic.
you know, at first i thought there was some mis mistake.
they they got the wrong guy.
like i thought like they list they read the list of charges.
they have nothing to do with these crimes like organized crimes, selling drugs, all those things.
like what do i have to do with that?
then i realized it's it's serious because they're not letting me out.
they keep
keep
me there
in this in this okay, but just for perspective, so you've got a billion users.
it's a multi-billion dollar company.
you started the company.
you own the company.
it's a huge company.
it's one of the biggest social media companies in the world.
um and so there's a process.
so if they think the telegram is doing something wrong,
they send letters to your general counsel
or
maybe get your phone number, which i'm sure they could pretty easily
get.
french intelligence, i'm sure, has everybody's phone number, and just call you and tell you.
i've never heard of a ceo of a multi-billion dollar company
getting arrested at the airport for
on
grounds like this.
well, you're very right.
it never happened before.
it's like completely it's unprecedented.
outrageous.
it's unprecedented, right?
never.
so, it's something that i think was very unnecessary
because on top of what you just described, i'm also a french citizen.
so, in how did you wind up because you're not from france originally?
yeah, i'm not from france originally,
but i have certain ties to france and and i was awarded
so to say this
citizenship for
using a specific process
which took several years, but
i didn't cut any corners
like i had to pass the french exam
test like if i had to do certain things that you'd normally do
when you're because you wanted to be a french citizen.
i wanted i like i love the country.
it's a great country.
it's a great culture.
of course, these events
are alarming
and that's why i think it makes sense to speak about them.
um, and and
the most interesting part of it is that every french citizen has
his or her personal home address
in the passport.
so, the authorities
of france
know very well how to reach out to this person
like it's
he's
there or
she's there.
and on top of that, the consulate of france
is located in the same building as the tilgrim office
in dubai.
so the same building.
the same building.
like you remember i've been to the building.
it's not a huge building by the way.
no, not really.
and it it's just two floors below.
so two floors from the french consulate.
we're two floors from the french consulate.
and i was a frequent visitor to the consulate.
and whenever any
french agency authority or like representative of of france of the government wanted to see me,
they had no issue whatsoever
arranging such meetings and these meetings took place.
i was happy just to go two floors
below the my office
and have a conversation or invite them to to our office.
so it's very very strange what happened because it could have been resolved by
different means if you think well
obviously they went way out of their way to humiliate you
to issue they announced that they arrested you.
i mean you were not obviously
scanning google for news stories about yourself cuz you didn't you couldn't.
they couldn't.
but the rest of us were and they announced we've arrested
paul durov and
arm sales or drug sales or kitty porn or i mean who knows like horrible
it's like what?
um so they were trying to terrify you and humiliate you.
obviously this is something that was also very unusual.
so what my lawyers told me here in france that normally
the prosecutor's
office
is not that public.
they're not issuing press statements every day and they're not commenting on their investigations
which was not the case with me where they were very active.
they were trying to have you read the
have you gone back
so you were of course you were locked
up and
you couldn't
read the coverage
but have you gone back and read it
for the those four days when you were being held?
well, i when i was in police custody, i heard from one of the policemen.
he told me every newspaper in the world is covering this and is mentioning you.
and i said, "what's going on?" he said, "well, a lot of people are supportive."
but i asked him, "what do newspapers write about this case?" and he told me, "everything
but truth."
and i freaked out at that moment, like everything but truth.
seriously.
and when i went when went
um
this four days ended
and i was can i just ask like what what was your family doing?
and you've got children and parents and like what were
to be honest this is the hardest part because i'm pretty
stress resilient so i can take care of myself
but being there locked there thinking about what's going on with my mom.
you know she's she's very ill.
she's very elderly.
she was very worried as i learned after
what's going on with with my kids and and
this is something that gets to you and
and you couldn't contact them.
no, there's no way because you don't have access to
any device
or you you can't even read anything.
what did they think was going on?
they were very surprised and very confused and very worried.
everybody wants to feel secure at home.
it's your castle.
there's nothing like going to sleep with a complete sense of safety.
that's why you sleep soundly.
that's why we cannot speak highly enough of simply safe.
most security systems take action only after someone breaks into your house.
that's a little late.
simply safe's new active guard outdoor protection feature helps stop breakins before they occur.
and that gives you peace of mind,
and it means you won't have to sleep with a baseball bat or loaded handgun
on your bedside, though you might want to.
anyway, here's how it works.
if something suspicious happens outside your property, cameras and live monitoring agents will detect it.
they'll speak to the intruder, turn on spotlights, and can call the police if necessary.
it's no surprise that cnet named simplysafe the best home security system of 2025.
over 4 million americans trust it because it's preemptive.
monitoring plans start around $1 per day.
there are no hidden fees.
60-day money back guarantee.
visit
simplysafe.com/tucker
to get 50%
off a new system
with a professional
monitoring
plan and your first month free.
that's simply [music] sim.com/tucker.
there's no safe like simply.
so, the people trying to wreck our civilization want you to be passive.
they want you weak so they can control you.
weakness is their goal.
no thanks.
our friends at beam,
a proud american
company,
understand that our country can only be great if its people are strong.
and that's why they've created a new creatine
product to help listeners like you stay mentally
sharp
and physically
fit.
people like to mock creatine.
cn doesn't like creatine at all, but people buy it cuz it works.
beams creatine can help you improve your strength, your brain health, your longevity.
it's completely free of sugar and synthetic garbage that's in almost everything else that you eat.
of course, you don't hear about it too much because again, a population that is strong,
clear-minded, and physically capable is a threat to tyrants.
that's why they want you playing video games.
to celebrate
american strength, actual american strength, beam is offering up to 30%
off their bestselling creatine for the next 48 hours.
go to shopbeam.com/tucker.
use the code tucker at checkout.
that's shopbeambeam.com/tucker.
use the code tucker for up to 30% off.
it's built on core values, integrity, results, no bs.
beam, we strongly recommend it.
just for perspective, those who don't know your story, i won't tell the whole story.
it's an amazing story.
we
did an
interview
with
you
maybe
a year
and a half
ago
in
which
you
told
your
story.
you're russian as people can probably hear in your voice
and sound like you're pretty happy in russia, successful in russia.
you had to leave russia for political reasons.
the government was trying to use your company for its own purposes.
you didn't want to be used.
you left your own country
um and moved well moved around and but wound up in dubai and france.
were you ever arrested by putin?
no.
okay.
just to put a finer point on this, i mean i'm not, you know, defending putin.
but you were arrested by the french government in the free west.
did that did you ever kind of see the irony there?
that was the most unexpected
place to get arrested in for me because before in this trip i visited
several countries.
some of these countries are considered in the west to be autocratic or authoritarian.
but i had
and and and tilgrim is very very popular in these countries i visited
before coming to paris.
and i had zero issues whatsoever despite the fact that tilgrim does zero
censorship in terms of political speech
and tilgrim provides 100%
privacy and and confidentiality
to its users in all these places.
so you do not extract personal information from your users unlike our company.
yes.
we never do that.
okay.
but other companies i mean facebook is
i mean meta is very rich because they extract that personal data.
right.
that's a business model.
yes.
that's true.
but i'm not attacking them.
sorry i am attacking them.
but but that's what they do.
and you don't do that.
yes.
we don't have to do that.
we
came up with ways to monetize telegram without having to abuse people's personal data this way.
so, telegram became profitable last year and very profitable more than half a billion
dollars in profit
without having to rely on methods like this
when you have to extract personal data and then
use it for
targeting ads for example.
we have very successful sub subscription paid subscription service on telegram.
we have, you know, we monetize in in ways that are consistent with our values
that are voluntary.
i mean, your users have to sign up for the things yes.
that make you money, not just stealing their data from them.
exactly.
and and the service is free and we just crossed 1 billion monthly user
threshold or milestone.
congratulations.
thank you.
so,
it's it's growing very
fast and we're
very happy with what we
we're very
proud with what we do
because if you look at any
mobile
messaging app
right now and we're number two
after you can guess which other app
we're the second most popular messaging app in the world.
but most of the features that you use
on a modern messaging app
first appeared
first were created by telegram and then they were borrowed.
we
came up with a list of like
such features
and those are not
like
small
things.
those are basic things that you know in every modern messaging app like the way
you
respond to messages,
the way you share links, the way you share documents,
the the text formatting,
many many many things like dozens of those
first appeared on telegram and then three to eight years after they've been copied by
our rivals.
one of which is larger than telegram and others are smaller.
but still we are proud.
i'm not gonna guess how green one.
yes.
but we are proud that we're we've been able to shape
what the industry is like today and and define how billions of people communicate.
but it's just i'm just going back to like this story which is
by the way i love your
slavic deadpan approach to this.
um it's like it's crazy.
i mean, if mark zuckerberg or elon got grabbed,
you know, at the
private part of de gaul airport, you'd be like, "stop like what?
the world is ending."
but they grabbed you and people like, "oh, he's got a russian last name.
it's fine.
i'm sure there's a good reason."
well,
i hope it had nothing to do with my
ethnicity because that of course it did.
are you joking?
that would be very alarming because you got run out of russia, by the way.
i just want to say that again.
you got run out.
you'd probably still be living there if you hadn't had to leave.
so, it's clearly you didn't participate in whatever they're mad about in russia.
you're gone.
yeah.
but it still can make you an easier target.
i'm aware of that because people don't know my story, right?
people not everybody watched our last interview and not everybody had where was the out?
so, i was well, i know you and
obviously i like you so
and i like what you're doing.
i like your commitment to privacy and to the user and i think the users
privacy
should play a role in your
in your thinking about a business and that's what my view and you agree
most companies
don't agree
so i'm on your side
but where were all the civil libertarians
jumping to your defense like how can you just grab someone at the airport
because
well cuz who knows why can you just do that
put him in jail for 4 days
take his
phone
like where were your defenders?
well, to be fair, some people did
some speak up and and and and
defended me and i actually there were
more than 10 million or more than i think a very big number of people
who signed a petition to free me.
yes.
so, it was was a a very very large movement.
i was i'm thinking more like the united nations,
you know, human rights watchd dogs like where are they?
if this happened in north korea, which it, you know, i don't know, it hasn't.
so, but if it happened there, we'd be like, "oh my gosh, it's stalinism,
but it happens in france." and you're like, "i'm sure there's a good reason."
that's you know that's what makes this situation so complicated because
we have to look at the instances
such as this one regardless of
which jurisdiction
i was born in which jurisdiction is conducting this investigation it should be completely
unbiased right so it's it's it's very concerning.
and did they ask you questions about russia during your four days of entertainment?
i think so, but it wasn't the focus of their questioning.
the the the the most questions were about the
um way telegram operates as if it's some kind of mystery.
you know, we we're a big company.
we are audited by a big four auditing firm.
we work with the with the biggest financial institutions.
so we're we're a big company and we spend millions of dollars
every quarter on legal compliance.
so we pay to law firms
to receive the best advice
in in order to make sure we don't violate
laws
anywhere
and we are we operate in almost 200 countries.
so it was very very surprising for me to
get detained in paris and learn that telegram did something wrong or didn't process
some
requests.
and then when i learned more about it,
i realized that we did actually nothing wrong because
the law is very clear
in in describing the process that should be followed
in order for this request to be processed and it wasn't followed.
and that's something that french prosecutors could have found out in about six minutes.
obviously, that's the irony of it.
it was like you could google telegram police contact, telegram
eu
corporation, whatever, and it would be instantly visible online for anybody who has access to google.
for some reason, it wasn't used by, right?
and you have to think that there's like a reason.
before i ask about that, how was the food in french prison, by the way?
um there was i think they made some exception in relation to food for me.
so it was fine.
i was fine.
it was pretty good.
i you know i don't eat meat.
i don't eat fast food.
so i was good with
enough fish and i could do my 200
push-ups in the morning like 200
squats
and then i repeated it because i didn't have access to a gym.
so i i kept my routine there.
did you join a gang?
no, i was alone there.
you were alone?
anybody push in your cell?
um, it's just the whole thing's incredible.
so, where does it stand now?
you know, we're in i should say we're in france right now.
you're still in france.
i'm still in france.
um, many many months later, eight almost eight months.
eight months later, you're still in france.
um, why are you still here?
so there is this
limitation on my travel traveling ability so to say which is called judicial control.
judicial control is when you can't leave the country
freely
because there is still investigation going on and you one of the suspects or the suspect.
i was
still
being allowed to go to dubai and i
returned last week from dubai
and i will be going to dubai
later this week but it's it's a very very restricted
controlled
process still
and what's the idea there since you own a multi-billion
dollar company with a billion
users
that's really f
like where where
would you go on planet
earth if you were going to run away?
well, that's exactly like my the source of my misunderstanding and my confusion here.
so where i'm not running anywhere and you know i've been to dubai came back.
so it's very hard for me to understand
my role in being here because
i'm required to answer some questions in relation to telegram every like
fifth month or fourth month.
so the other like 3 or 4 months i am just
having to be here for reasons that are very hard for me to understand.
what's their argument?
i mean i'm just confused.
so no one's actually despite the headlines
that
flooded the world in august when you were arrested,
detained, whatever they're calling it, put in a cell.
um you were not involved in kitty porn,
drug sales,
organized crime, arm, i can't even remember.
but like the worst crimes in the world,
no one is actually claiming you were involved in those crimes.
correct.
okay.
they're saying that you had
of your billion users,
there were a few who may have been doing bad things and you're saying,
i tried, but i i didn't know that.
it's not my fault.
right.
correct.
it'd be like saying to donald trump, there are 350 million people in america.
you know, onethird the number of users you have and
some of them are using kitty porn or selling drugs or, you know, organized driving.
we're putting you in jail for it.
i mean, that's like it's insane.
so, why are you still here?
like, what is the claim against you?
i'm still trying to find out to be to be honest.
i'm i'm still confused.
so, at first they said,
"oh, you failed to respond to our legal requests and that's why you're complicit."
but first of all, we
it's not true that we didn't respond to legally binding legal requests.
and secondly,
it's a very u extensive interpretation of complicity even for the french
you know legal and judicial system.
what i'm what i hear from my lawyers is that it's quite unprecedented.
they had a couple of really small niche apps that are like 10,000 smaller than telegram
and were targeted specifically at criminals.
they were nothing like they didn't even have these companies that they didn't even have bank
accounts.
they they it was a a different profile.
they were not audited by big four organization.
but it's these companies have been persecuted in france before and their
founders
i understand were accused of
running a platform
that
is created for the purpose to facilitate
crime.
it's pretty much obvious that tilgrim is not such a company, right?
so it's it's has a billion users.
every eighth person on the planet is a user
of telegram like a regular one and and it's it's incomprehensible
to assume that all these people like people are criminals and and and
you know everybody knows the story of telegram
very well it's not something that
was built for
criminals
however
this reasoning as far as i understand is being
used also in our case
they say that all right so you
created this app and this app was used by other people.
they were criminals and you didn't do enough
to prevent them
from doing what they were doing.
which again is is
contrary to what we see on other platforms like you have instances
where problematic content exists despite the best efforts
of
social media platforms moderation teams and so on and so forth.
it's almost impossible to avoid that.
but the claim itself just conceptually doesn't make sense.
i mean, if someone commits armed robbery in burgundy or tulus or nice,
can president mcronone be arrested for that because it's his country, he runs the country
and he didn't do enough to stop the armed robbery in tulus?
like, how can that stand?
why isn't he in jail?
like, that that's nuts.
well, the logic also eludes me, so to say.
back with the the russian understatement.
no, i it's so look, here's the inescapable conclusion.
i think as from a bystanders perspective
that they do this in public rather than just calling you.
so we have a problem we work it out or call your lawyers.
they arrest you in public.
they slander you.
they try and tie you to the worst crimes
man commits
and then they put you in jail.
um and so they're trying to sweat you to intimidate you
um to wear you down in order to get
into the back door of telegram so they can spy on
people.
probably really for political reasons.
that's the what they're really worried about is a revolt in their own country.
every government's really worried mostly about its own population revoling against this bad governance.
like that's their real fear
and they hate
telegram because it offers users privacy and that's a threat to them
and so they force you as the owner of the company to give them the keys.
that's what it looks like.
well, to be clear, nobody approached me with the demand to give the so-called keys.
such keys don't exist technically, but if
if
somebody approaches me and says we need the keys,
you'll be among the first to to
learn about it.
but that hasn't happened.
well, actually the us government pushed you.
i remember the fbi was trying to yeah.
yeah.
because this is something governments want, not just of you, but of all social media companies.
you know what's interesting?
in the us, you have a process
that allows the government to actually force any engineer
in any tech company
to implement a backdoor
and not tell anyone about it with using this process called the gag order.
and
there there are certain legal procedures, not tell his own employer about it
and not yes, exactly.
if you tell your own boss, you can end up in jail.
like gag order this actually.
yeah, this is something that it's on wikipedia in france.
i in the soviet union or in the us?
in the us.
okay.
i am not criticizing.
so your employees have a legal obligation to act as fifth column spies,
saboturs
against you, your employees.
well, that's the one of the reasons we didn't discuss last time why
i didn't move to the us with my team.
and you got mugged in san francisco on your one trip there.
exactly.
but but i i did this extensive legal analysis
like i asked my lawyers, the us lawyers, what is this thing called the gag order?
and they explained it to me and how it works and how it could potentially
be
applied.
so we decided maybe not the best place for a privacy oriented platform.
but here in france, we really don't know
because there there are a lot of conspiracy theories about it.
and at first i thought
i i
also started
to be concerned
like
what is this about?
but then when the french
police and the french judges started to
send their requests in accordance to the european law to telegram
and receive the identification data, meaning the ip address of criminal suspects,
they seem to become very happy.
they expressed their joy in the press.
they said, "oh, tilgrim is now cooperating."
all of a sudden, as if it was something new.
can i ask you to pause when when they said that?
i remember that very well.
yeah.
that sounded to me like they were trying to discredit
you
and were sending the message cuz they were not specific.
they just said they're cooperating.
and that made it sound to the rest of the world like, "oh, they broke pavle.
they hung him by his ankles and burned him with galwis
until he finally gave up and
turned over the the back end to them and now they're spying on all telegram users.
you're cooperating like you would in east germany in 1975. that's that's what it sounded like.
yeah.
that's why it's so important to clarify this because this perception
is not only bad for telegram, it's even worse for for the image of france
because if you if you think about it, it's france is still
a land where
laws and legal procedures should be
adhered to
and even in this case if you want
additional access
to certain data, personal data, it has to be done in accordance with laws.
and then every company for example us we never disclosed private messaging data
to any third party including governments
and if it's in some country they would say you have to do it
we would discontinue providing services in that country then doing it.
isn't that why you left russia in the first place?
yes.
so you've been through this.
you left your own country because you refused to give up the privacy of the user.
yeah.
but here it's catch it's catching up because last month
the senate here in france passed a law basically banning
encryption.
this law was
forcing all messaging app providers to implement the backd dooror for the french law enforcement
to to fight crime.
the problem here was fight crime.
well they exactly because the problem here was there is no such thing as an exclusive
backdoor.
if you implement the back door,
technically other
actors
are able to
exploit it
and it could be foreign agents, it could be hackers, it could be anyone.
so that law would have put millions of people or tens of millions of of french
citizens in danger.
the their private messages would would have been exposed.
the criminals however would would have instantly switched to niche
smaller apps
not mainstream apps
and if the government was tried to
would try to ban this apps they would switch to vpns
they would they would even become more efficient in hiding their traces.
so the criminals would experience zero problems if that law is passed.
is the law-abiding
citizens
who would be affected and that's why it's so problematic and nobody was talking about it.
and asked my french friends like, "have you heard about this law?" like they no,
they were completely unaware.
and luckily the national assembly here in france shot that bill down.
so it didn't pass this time.
but if you look at the u new project by the eu by the european commission
published in early april,
they again
want to do exactly that to backdoor encryption
but now on the eu level
and and that raises many serious questions because
no country in the world
banned encryption so far even the the places that you would consider authoritarian places
for reasons that i just described.
this it's just a huge threat for the entire population
to for all users for all users to
legally force companies to implement backd doorors.
so i think it's very important that people talk about these things first of all that
france is not
an a a country where freedoms are disrespected
right for for example if people assume that france can now take ceos of
tech companies
um hostage in in such a way that you that you describe
and then extract certain personal data from them using
illegal and unlawful
processes.
that would be a big big blow for the image of france.
but i don't think we're there because we haven't chip away at this concept of
the rules-based
order.
the rules-based order, which everyone in nato is always lecturing everybody else about the rules-based order.
there's nothing rules-based about what they did to you.
i'm sorry.
i mean, that's just that's might makes right.
that's we have guns and you don't.
it's our airport, not yours.
you're going to jail.
i just don't see the legal justification for doing this to anybody.
it was excessive in my view, but it was also a sign that
um
again in my view this investigation was not based on
thorough analysis of what telegram represents
and and
what the goals of the company are.
and again they has been no attempt and they had
didn't even try
to
solve this in a more
traditional conventional way
before starting a legal way actually a legal and diplomatic way.
what did they do with your phone?
well, they just kept my phone.
i hope they they
scrutinize it because there they have a lot of proof
that actually telegram
is a completely
legitimate and compliant organization and we have spent
huge funds on
content moderation and legal compliance all over the world since like 10 years ago.
so they're welcome to have my phone.
who sells your bonds?
um yeah.
so, telgram issued bonds a few years ago.
we were happy to have the assistance of jp morgan, the the world's biggest bank, right?
and world's biggest bank.
so, i just i only asked
i knew that and i just wanted you to say it because
just to underscore the point.
this is you're not like some,
you know, bellow russian college student doing this out of your room or something.
this like this like a worldwide huge company.
it's just absolutely crazy.
and it doesn't have as deep penetration in the united states
as it does in the rest of the world.
so, i just i just want people to know this is not some sketchy deal.
this is like i can't just can't believe they did that.
where are you now in the process?
so, the process is not going too fast, but this is the tradition here in france.
so, i'm not now, i'm just visiting for a couple days.
you think i'll get out of here?
so the i haven't been granted a fast track in my case.
um and and you know i' i've just seen my investigative judges.
they have this role of investigative judges here in france.
so my current status is i'm not on trial.
it's an investigation
intended to find out whether there'll be enough evidence to put this on trial.
so, i'm not even on trial yet.
there's but you're basically imprisoned in france.
but i well, i'm not imprisoned, but can you can you leave whenever you want?
i can't leave france freely.
that's true.
uh, so what how is that not imprisoned?
um, well, i mean that i mean there are great restaurants.
i'm not you know what i mean?
it's not a commissary
with
guys with face tattoos, but you if you can't leave, then aren't you by definition imprisoned?
you could say so.
i just don't want to create this image
of a real prison
in in the minds
of our viewers.
this is i don't know if anyone can see the cell we're in.
it's pretty nice room service and everything.
i mean, no, it's france.
it's it's like very first world in some ways, but not in its attitudes.
i'm i'm learning.
um, so how long will that continue?
and and you've got
children,
you know, and a life and a business and friends and family and
they're not in france as far as i know.
though.
yes, they're all in dubai and i have
kids in dubai that i am unable to
not just see i'm unable to
legally take care of them by signing certain documents i have to sign and
i've
you know it's it's
been
very stressful also for my mom for my mom
who is gravely ill and i can't see her.
um i also have this company to run.
we have a billion users.
it's it's it's it's
important
and i am doing it remotely now but it's not as efficient.
so if you if you think about it, france is less than 1%
of the telegram user base.
it's it's some something like half of 1%.
and the other 99 and a half% are coming from elsewhere, right?
india, indonesia, you name it.
and it's kind of counterintuitive for me
that the entire organization is impacted because we have this ongoing investigation here in france.
particularly given the fact that
it's going
in a pace
that only requires me to be here once like in in in several months.
um so i do think that the current restriction is
um very strange and very unnecessary and i hope it will be lifted later this year.
and if it's not
your identity is constantly under attack and just the last year americans lost over 16 billion
to scammers online.
anyone can fall victim to this.
your social security
number,
your bank account,
your credit profile
can be exposed
and you won't even know it.
and the second they are exposed,
thieves can take out loans in your name, open credit cards, wreck your life financially.
identity guard can save you.
identity guard monitors
everything from your credit card to your bank accounts to your social security number,
looking for early signs of fraud before
damage is done.
if something weird happens, you get an instant alert.
if someone does steal your identity, identity guard's expert team works directly with banks,
credit card companies, and lenders to shut it down quickly.
end the scam.
having your identity stolen is a nightmare.
someone in this country becomes a victim of identity the theft every six seconds.
identityguard protects you.
30-day free trial and exclusive discount at identityguard.com/tucker.
protect yourself before it's too late.
identity.com/tucker.
you're probably pretty sick in nike.
it's hard to blame you for feeling that way.
any company that worships colin kaepernick,
any company that shills for the lunacy of the left social agenda
is clearly not on your side.
in fact, they're your enemy.
you need an alternative.
xxxy athletics is the far better choice.
it's the only athletic brand committed to fighting fighting for free speech, women's sports,
and the truth.
honesty, the truth.
they're not going to lie to you.
for example, did you know that 80% of americans oppose letting men play in women's sports?
that's not a radical view.
it's a moderate, sensible view rooted in biology.
but woke corporations like nike make you feel like a lunatic
for saying obvious things like men are men and women are women.
that is tyranny.
how can you fight back?
by abandoning the companies promoting it and by embracing companies like xxxy athletics.
it's an american company.
it's not opposed to the united states or to telling the truth.
head to the truthfits.com
to learn a lot more and use the code tucker25
for 25% off.
well, let's see.
because first of all, this investigation can't last forever.
they it can probably last for another several
months or a year and then it will have to either go
on trial or
be concluded.
you could be criminally charged for this.
everything is possible.
like you can't rule out.
guess if they'd arrest you at the airport, they'd do anything, right?
that's what bothered me when i was in police custody for these four days.
like first thing, something like this should have never happened because
i assumed there were certain
thorough procedures
to verify a lot of
u alleged facts before taking a decision such as this.
like you can't start something like this based on a in a media article that
telegram
allegedly is non-ooperative
or that telegram
supposedly has worse
content moderation
than other platforms.
both these facts turned out to be completely false.
you have to be really thorough
and examine things before making this decision because this the decisions such as this
are not only harmful
for for my relatives or for my company of my for me personally.
decisions such as this i think impact france as a whole
and as i'm a french i'm a french citizen so i worry about that as well.
i really think that out of all social media platforms, telegram was probably the most friendly
potential partner for france.
and every time
anyone
from from the french government,
the french authorities reached out to me,
i did my best to help.
i helped.
so this for me looked almost like friendly fire like where they're they're
trying to attack their own ally
in a way and i was so surprised that this would happen
because
the collateral damage
not just for me and my company but for the image of france
is quite significant and i
talked to many of my friends the ceo of big tech companies
and they were very concerned and asked me can i still come to france?
is it like is it still safe to be in france?
people were worried and and the ceos of the smaller companies
that don't have a billion users are even more worried.
they say
look
they did this to you and you
you're very well known and the company of your profile is
you know
should be treated in in certainly in in certain different way.
so, and i'm running a small startup.
a friend of of mine would say, "i'm scared to come."
and you know, this trend continues.
so, i heard,
but there's the sad thing is like nobody's afraid to go to usbekistsan actually.
i'm not endorsing usbekistan.
i've never been there, but i
never met anyone who's like, "i'm too afraid to go to usbekistsan."
yeah, i was there last summer.
it was great.
i didn't even know that.
but that's the point.
i mean
right these countries that you grew up thinking are
primitive or don't have functioning legal systems or
you know whose
laws are really just a function of the whim of the monarch
or whatever
they turn out to be kind of fine with
what you do or what i do or what any
normal
person
who believes in human rights does but it's like
france
or great britain
like didn't you get citizenship here thinking
this
was a safe haven
as someone who was in
some sense kind of a refugee
from his own country
a refugee
do you have principle
like i don't want to share this with the government
i'm
leaving?
didn't you
choose this country for citizenship
because you thought that it was a place that was committed to human rights?
well, the slogan of france is liberty equality, right?
so, equality.
so, it's it's something that i strongly believe in and it's certainly something that
france
stands for in my
in my opinion and for pretty much everybody who was born in the soviet union
like i was
western europe
is considered to be this place where freedoms and human rights are respected
and and
that's why it was such a shock for me back there in the police custody.
interestingly,
the interpreter that we had during this four days in police custody
also immigrated from the soviet union.
she was translating english to french and back.
and after being present there for 2 days,
she
said during a break with all the policemen and
you know, clerks and everybody present there and she said, "i left the soviet
union hoping i would be in a country with freedoms."
and and it seems now that the soviet union has caught up with me.
and
i've
what so i was very surprised to hear her say that
because for me france is not there yet.
france is still the country that respects human rights and freedoms.
however, i understood i later understood why she was so sensitive to this because she actually
experienced
what life is like
in an environment
where you don't have freedom of speech and you you don't have a free market economy.
and that's why every perceived change for in in this direction where freedoms are less respected
um is is taking very is making them very very concerned people from the soviet union.
and i myself
i remember my life i was a small kid in the soviet
union but i remember
having only three tv channels and all these three tv channels show the same tv program
with the about the communist party
and i remember having two kinds of ice cream in the shops
across the city and across the country and no more.
and then when i was brought to italy as a five-year-old
kid
and i could see, okay, actually i could have 100 tv channels
and some of them even show
disney cartoons and japanese
anime.
that's great.
i can go to a shop downstairs and they have 200 different kinds of ice cream.
that's much better that i experienced in the soviet union.
and i thought maybe these things
afterwards i realized that this
systems
called the free market economy and and respect to freedom of speech and basic human rights
they're actually very good concepts because they make your life abundant.
but the problem is i remember this this life in the absence of of these things.
other people from the soviet union probably from cuba from other countries like that experience that.
people who were born and grew up here, for example, in france,
have not necessarily had this experience.
they take freedoms for granted.
they think it's
things are going going to be fine because we're a free country and what can possibly
go
wrong?
unfortunately, the history knows many examples when free societies gradually degraded into societies without freedoms.
and one good example was last month with this anti- encryption law.
i told you before about because people were completely ignorant here in france.
the public was completely ignorant.
so no encryption means no privacy.
yes.
correct.
it means everybody's vulnerable like everybody's messages can leak can can can it's mindboggling.
and of course every time something like this is proposed very
um logically sounding justifications are used to protect the children.
to protect the children, to fight crime, to
you know neither of which they bother doing
by the way they don't care about children
and they don't stop crime
or in the soviet union they would say like in mao is china
and other places they would say oh our geopolitical
rival is trying to stir chaos in our country so we have to limit
this it's qatar doing it it's russia
it's qatar
so yeah i don't know
but but but
it's always some troskyite wreckers.
it's some unseen force from a foreign land trying to wreck our project.
so, we need to oppress you to keep you safe.
yes.
but it's not easy because now in the european union, you have all these laws
that basically say you have to remove anything.
it's actually part of the digital services act.
you have to remove anything one of the european countries
demands you remove for the entire of the diet of the european union.
so if you have for example romania or estonia or any of other of this
very highly respected countries
demanding that you remove like most of telegram channels for whatever reason
you have to remove them then you can appeal
well it will take you probably several years
but you have to remove them within like i very short time frame
otherwise you'll be facing
fines, bans, and so on.
how is it not the warsaw pact?
i mean, how is that not soviet?
if you criticize the people in charge, we shut you down.
that's what they're saying.
interesting you would say that.
it was in 2009, 2008. actually, i made my first dream trip to
latvia on a train from st.
petersburg and something was wrong with my visa.
so i had to get off in the border town in latia.
but i had this long discussion with a border police officer.
well, i seem to like border policemen.
so border police officer in latia and i started to discuss his life in latia
after latia was accepted in the eu.
and he told me this interesting thing.
and he said, "you know, we hated being in the soviet union,
but now that we are in the eu, we realize
we
are in a
very similar organization." of course, we're in the soviet union again.
unelected foreigners are still making the key decisions and you don't get to talk.
so, it's very funny you would compare this two systems.
of course, they're very different.
but still, but fundamentally,
if you're not allowed to criticize the people in charge,
you live in a tyranny.
i mean, what what's the other definition of it?
i have to be able to say to the person making the decisions,
i don't like that decision, and here's why.
and i have to be able to say it in public.
and i've always felt the problem that you have
as the person who owns and runs telegram
is that you make it easy for people to come together online.
you have the channels
and that is
i don't know if you thought this through and you
you're an engineer when you when you built
it
but that is potentially a massive threat to governments
because it's not simply communicating one-on-one there
you know people can create their own well
channels
just like a tv channel and reach a lot of like-minded
people and they could potentially organize
organize
that's true but one thing that makes telegram different we don't promote these channels so
everything that you have on telegram
is something that you have to deliberately search for and subscribe for.
yes.
so unlike some other apps that
constantly
recommend you content and content sources, we don't do that.
you open telegram, it's just an empty list of chats.
if you don't have any friend there and if you
are not subscribed to any channel, you have to deliberately
find one.
so i think we're completely neutral platform.
we allow everybody to express their voice within the
the rules of the you know common sense
and and then everybody can
decide
which point of view makes more sense to them
and
see if if for example the government is right or their position is right.
right.
well that's called freedom.
that's called freedom.
unfortunately, it's something that surprisingly
um faces a lot of backlash.
may i ask you a question about encryption?
so, the advances in computing power, well, they're calling it quantum computing, right?
so, they're just so exponential
that it's hard even to understand for the non-engineer
brain like mine, but they're they're profound.
the speed at which processes are now occurring.
does that eliminate what is the techn what is the technological state of play?
does that eliminate encryption?
encryption will have to change.
correct.
the encryption has to change and there has been made progress in
encryption which is like quantum secure.
so it's a constant evolution.
so the the the tools to decrypt
become stronger and then the tools to encrypt become stronger.
that makes sense.
are you confident that
encryption
that secure encryption will still exist
as a technological matter
with the rise of the super fast quantum computing?
it's very hard to be confident in anything because
first of all we have to rely on the computing power of our devices
to decrypt things.
of course there are very sophisticated algorithms in place that
make it so that you don't have to have the same
level of computing power on your device
as in a data center
to say you don't have to bring a data center with you.
yeah.
exactly.
so it it's it's not exactly like that.
build a nuclear power plant, buy 100 acres.
you don't have to but you know it continues.
so the the
particular state actors have almost infinite
computing power at their disposal and they have certain technologies
at their disposal that they may not be
telling everybody about.
so they might not be telling people about it.
so it's very possible that what you're saying will become reality or is already reality.
who knows?
so
um
that
kind of is
one of the
and
i don't
you know i know you
have
well you're legally bound here in france so you're under some kind of
state control.
so and i know your life is complicated because of it.
so i don't want to
push you to say things or to get you in trouble but
um it does feel like a a determined government can spy on anybody it wants to.
that's the way it feels to me.
do you think that's true?
well, i think the biggest risk for personal privacy is
um
the ability of any state actor to penetrate
the device of the person, the mobile device for example, because there are so-called zero day
vulnerabilities on ios or android
phones for example, that the governments
sometimes know about and the secret agencies know about and they can exploit them.
but everybody else doesn't know and they can't defend from them themselves from them.
so if you became a target of a government,
it's really likely that they would install this
trojan so-called trojan called pegasus on your device.
and i was one of these people
eight years ago
that had a pegasus installed on their phones according to the leaked reports.
been there.
um,
is there any way,
and i think a lot of people are there without
knowing it,
and i i'm
know that.
is there any way to know if your phone has been compromised?
if
what
you're
looking at and typing
is being read by somebody else, is there any way to know for certain?
for certain, probably no.
but there are ways to check that and see if known vulnerabilities have been
um
exploited on your phone
and and i know there are some organizations that can help you with that.
i'll where's your phone?
did you didn't leave it out?
i don't use a phone.
i haven't used the phone for from for a year almost.
i find oh, france took it.
oh, france took it.
but even before it took it, i wasn't using my phone.
i didn't have a sim card in the phone.
i just use it to test telegram the app because we have constant product updates.
i have to test it like at least twice a week.
but i don't i i'm not a user of a phone.
so i just want to say again, you're an engineer, too.
i mean, you're not like a marketing guy.
you're like a build the app guy.
so you understand the technology.
yes.
because you built it.
so you're coming from a a highly informed perspective when you make technology choices.
is that fair?
you could say so.
yeah.
one of the most informed probably in the world.
and you don't have a phone.
what is that like?
why don't you have a phone?
well, i don't use phone regularly, right?
i probably own a phone, but i don't use phone.
i don't carry a phone with me because i find it extremely distracting.
i find it also
um potentially
um
um harming my privacy.
mhm.
and
i i i
also
just i i don't think it's a necessary device for me to have when
i want to focus on something.
i would rather use my laptop or my ipad
and and put together some notes or or or some u interact with my team, right?
so i wouldn't want to just open my phone and disappear there consuming short form content.
and that's why i don't use a phone.
i i'm i
trying to extract this from you for one simple reason which is i think that
when you come across someone who knows an immense amount about technology really understands the technology
it's interesting to know his perspective on technology
like with everything you know
you don't use a phone
so i just think you know people can draw their own conclusions
from that right
so what do you you saw ross albertch got the guy who was pardoned.
yes.
yeah.
silk road.
mhm.
so, he ran silk road and i'm hardly an expert on this.
i was very pleased when he got pardoned.
um, but it seemed like no one accused him of selling drugs, by the way.
you know, you would never know that from
the new york times, but he was not like dealing
drugs on playgrounds
or anything like that.
he had a site
um that made commerce possible outside the control of government
and there apparently were bad people doing bad things on it.
also
a lot of good people doing
good things on it but it was none of it was controlled
by the government
and he got life in prison for that.
that's my takeaway.
and
so maybe there will all
my
sort of conclusion from this is
as long as people like you create technology
that makes it harder for government to control people, you will be a target
of government action.
you think that's it?
well, first of all, i wouldn't necessarily compare
teleg with silk and i'm not and i didn't mean to.
but i but the but the idea
that
the idea that
they need to
control everything that is happening online
and if they can't they're going to punish you.
that does seem like a real fact.
i think everybody's trying to reach their goals and be more efficient in what they do.
for example, you ask
any minister of interior,
any head of police, and they'll tell you, "oh, encryption is a big problem."
if it weren't for encryption, we would solve all crime.
they they don't see it two steps or three steps ahead.
yes.
and it's not necessarily like some huge conspiracy where
like evil governments wants to want to take more and more control.
although that may be the case.
i'm not knowledgeable on that subject.
it's it seems to me more like everybody is trying to
solve
the problems that they see
using the tools that they have at their disposal
even if
it negatively impacts
other areas, you know, of our lives.
you're a very generous man, i must say.
last question, and thank you for doing this.
um how long are you going to be in france?
and once you leave france, will you be coming back to france?
i don't know yet when these restrictions will be lifted.
i hope later this year we'll be able to travel to
my home country which is dubai
freely.
i
um i will probably come back to france because it's it's a great place
to spend time in.
of course.
i had a lot of i have spent a lot of time in france now
eight eight months.
um so
um kind of a full immersion program.
how's your french?
it's it's actually good.
i was very good when i passed my french exam to receive the passport.
it got 97 points out of 100. but i didn't practice my french much.
most of my friends are americans.
but even here in paris and and and and and my french friends speak perfect english.
so i didn't got a chance to practice.
u but now you've had that chance?
no, because i speak english with me.
it's it's it changed.
like before 15 years ago, 20 years ago,
it was difficult not to speak french in france.
now for better or worse, you can get by using english.
i'm trying to use my french,
but
i don't sound
as
in
i sound even less intelligent
in in french
than in english.
so, people switch back to english with me.
but you don't anticipate like having to stay for the next 20 years or anything here.
i i would be very surprised if that happened because you see, i'm traveling to dubai.
i'm coming back.
it's it's just obvious that i'm not a somebody who would try to escape forever.
and
um
and it's that this investigation has to be concluded in why one way or the other.
of course, then if it goes to trial, if that happens, it can take another
several years.
but then again, it would be completely
um crazy.
i would say if i would have to move to france and live here permanently
for the whole duration of this process.
um, i would i would say that the most likely
i i expect that that i would be able to travel again later this year.
well, we're certainly rooting for you, pablo.
thank you very much.
thank you so much.
[music] so, it turns out that youtube is suppressing this show.
on one level, that's not surprising.
that's what they do.
but on another level, it's shocking.
with everything that's going on in the world right now,
all the change
taking
place in our economy
and our politics,
with the wars we're on the cusp of fighting right now,
google has decided you should have less information
rather than more.
and that is totally wrong.
it's immoral.
what can you do about it?
well, we could whine about it.
that's a waste of time.
we're not in charge of google.
or we could find a way around it.
a way that you could actually get information that is true, not intentionally deceptive.
the way to do that on youtube, we think, is to subscribe to our channel.
subscribe, hit the little bell icon to be notified when we upload and share this video.
that way, you'll have a much higher chance of hearing actual news and information.
so, we hope that you'll do