The following is a conversation with Terence Tao
widely considered to be one of the greatest mathematicians in history
often referred to as the Mozart of Math.
He won the Fields Medal and a Breakthrough Prize in Mathematics and has contributed groundbreaking work to a truly astonishing range of fields in mathematics and physics.
This was a huge honor for me, for many reasons
including the humility and kindness that Terry showed to me throughout all our interactions.
It means the world.
This is the Lex Fridman Podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description or at lexfridman.
com/sponsors.
And now, dear friends, here's Terence Tao.
What was the first really difficult research-level math problem that you encountered?
One that gave you pause maybe?
Well, I mean, in your undergraduate, um
education, you learn about the really hard impossible problems
like the Riemann hypothesis, between primes conjecture.
You can make problems arbitrarily difficult, and that's not really a problem.
In fact there's even problems that we know to be unsolvable.
What's really interesting are, are the problems just on the
on the boundary between what we can do relatively easily and what are hopeless
um, but what, uh, problems where
like, existing techniques can do, like, 90% of the job and then y- you just need that remaining 10%.
Um, I think as a PhD student
the Kakeya problem certainly caught my eye, and it just got solved actually.
It's a problem I've worked on a lot in my early research.
Historically, it came from a little puzzle by the Japanese
uh, mathematician Shoji Kakeya, uh, in like 1918 or so.
Um, so, the puzzle is that you
you have, um, a needle, um
in c- on the plane, um, or- or think of like a
like driving on- on- on- on- on a road
something, and you want to- to execute a U-turn
you want to turn the needle around, um
but you want to do it in as little space as possible
uh, so you want to use as little area
uh, in order to turn it around.
So, um, but the needle is infinitely maneuverable.
So you can imagine just spinning it around its
um, as a unit needle, you can spin it around its center
um, and I think, um, that gives you a disc of- of area
I think, pi over 4.
Um, or you can do a three-point U-turn
which is what they, we teach people in- in the driving schools to do
uh, and that actually takes area pi over 8
uh, so it's- it's a little bit more efficient than
um, a rotation.
And so for a while people thought that was the most efficient
uh, way to turn things around, but Bazikovic
uh, showed that in fact, uh, you could actually
uh, turn the needle around using as little area as you wanted.
Mm.
So.
001, there was some really fancy multi, um
uh, um, back and forth U-turn thing that you could- you could do
that- that you could turn a needle around.
And in so doing, it would pass through every intermediate direction.
Is this in the two-dimensional plane?
This is in the two-dimensional plane, yeah.
So we understand everything in two dimensions.
So the next question is, what happens in three dimensions?
So suppose like the Hubble Space Telescope, this tube in space
and you want to observe every single star in the universe
so you want to rotate the telescope to reach every single direction.
And here's the unrealistic part, suppose that space is at a premium
which it totally is not.
Yeah.
Uh, you want to occupy as little volume as possible in order to rotate your- your needle around
in order to see every single star in the sky.
Um, how small a volume do you need to do that?
And so you can modify Bazikovic's construction, and so if your telescope has zero thickness
then you can use as little volume as you need.
That's a- a simple modification of the two-dimensional construction.
But the question is that if your telescope is not zero thickness
but- but just very, very thin, some thickness delta
what is the minimum volume needed to be able to see every single direction as a function of delta?
So as delta gets smaller, as the needle gets- gets thinner
the volume should go down but- but how fast does it go down?
Um, and the conjecture was that it goes down very
very slowly, um, like logarithmically, um
uh, roughly speaking, and that was proved after a lot of work.
So this seems like a puzzle, why is it interesting?
So it turns out to be surprisingly connected to a lot of problems in partial differential equations
in number theory, in geometry, combinatorics.
For example, in- in wave propagation if you splash some- some water around
um, you create water waves an- they- they travel in various directions.
Um, but waves exhibit both w- both particle and wave type behavior.
So you can have what's called a wave packet
which is like a- a very localized wave that is localized in space and moving a certain direction in time.
And so if you plot it in both space and time
it occupies a region which looks like a tube.
And so what can happen is that you can have a wave which initially is- is very dispersed but it all come- it all focuses at a single point later in time.
Like, you can imagine dropping a- a pebble into a pond and ripples spread out
but then if you time reverse that- that
um, that scenario, and the equations of wave motion are time reversible
you can imagine ripples that are converging, um
to a single point and then a- a big splash occurs
um, maybe even a singularity.
Um, and so it's possible to do that
uh, and geometrically what's going on is that there's also light rays
um, so like if- if- if this wave represents light for example
um, you can imagine this wave as a superposition of photons
um, all traveling at the speed of light
they- they all travel on these light rays and they're all focusing at this one point.
So you can have a very dispersed wave focus into a very concentrated wave at one point in- in space and time but then it defocuses again and it's- it separates.
But potentially if the conjecture had a negative solution
so what I mean is that there's- there's a- a very efficient way to pack
um, tubes pointing in different directions into a very
very narrow region of- of- of, uh
very narrow volume.
Then you would also be able to create waves that start out
some- there'll be some arrangement of waves that start out very
very dispersed but they would concentrate not just at a single point but
um, um, there'll be a- a large
um, uh, there'll be a lot of concentrations in space and time
and, uh, um, and you could create what's called a blowup
where these waves, their amplitude becomes so great that the laws of physics that they're governed by are no longer wave equations but something more complicated and nonlinear.
Um-And so in mathematical physics, we care a lot about whether certain equations in- in- in wave equations are stable or not
uh, whether they can create, um, these singularities.
There's a famous, uh, unsolved problem called the Navier-Stokes regularity problem.
So the Navier-Stokes equations, the equations that govern the fluid flow of- of incompressible fluids
like water, the question asked, if you start with a smooth velocity field of water
can it ever concentrate so much that, like
the velocity become infinite at some point?
Uh, that's called a singularity.
We don't see that, um, in real life.
You know, if you splash around water on- on the bathtub
it won't explode on you, um, or- or have pa- have water leaving at the speed of light or anything
but potentially it is possible.
Um, and in fact, in recent years
the- the consensus has- has drifted towards the
uh, the- the belief that, uh, that in fact for certain very special con- initial con- uh
configurations of- of, say, water, that singularities can form.
But people have not yet been able to
uh, to actually establish this.
The Clay Foundation has these seven Millennium Prize problems
has a million dollar prize for solving one of these problems.
Uh, this is one of them.
Of these seven, only one of them has been solved
uh, uh, the Poincaré conjecture by Perelman.
So the Kakeya conjecture is not directly, directly related to the Navier-Stokes problem
but understanding it would help us understand some aspects of things like wave concentration
which would indirectly probably help us, uh
understand the Navier-Stokes problem better.
Can you speak to the Navier-Stokes, so the existence and smoothness
like you said, Millennial Prize problem?
Right.
You've made a lot of progress on this one.
In 2016, you published a paper, Finite Time Blow-Up For an Averaged Three-Dimensional Navier-Stokes Equation.
Right.
So- so we're trying to figure out if this thing usually doesn't blow up- Right.
.
..
but can we say for sure it never blows up?
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah, that is literally the- the- the million dollar question.
So, uh, this is what distinguishes mathematicians from pretty much everybody else.
Like, if- if- if something ho- holds 99.
99% of the time, um, that's good enough for most
you know, uh, for- for- for- for most things.
But mathematicians are one of the few people who really care about whether every
like, 100%, really 100% of all, um
situations are covered by- by, um.
..
Yeah.
So most fluids, most of the time
um, say water do- does not blow up
but could you design a s- very special initial state that does this?
And maybe we should say that this is a- this is a set of equations that govern in the field of fluid dynamics- Yes.
.
uh, trying to understand how a fluid behaves and it's actually turns out to be a really compli- you know
fluid is- Yeah.
.
..
extremely complicated thing to try to model.
Yeah.
So it has practical importance.
So this Clay Prize problem concerns what's called the incompressible Navier-Stokes
which governs things like water.
There's something called the compressible Navier-Stokes, which governs things like air.
And that's particularly important for weather prediction.
Weather prediction, it does a lot of computational fluid dynamics
a lot of it is actually just trying to solve the Navier-Stokes equations as- as best they can.
Um, also gathering a lot of data so that they can get- they can ini- initialize the equation.
There's a lot of moving parts.
So it's very important problem practically.
Why is it difficult to prove general things about the set of equations
like it not- not blowing up?
Short answer is Maxwell's demon.
.
Uh, so Maxwell's demon is a concept in thermodynamics.
Like, if you have a box with two gases in
uh, oxygen and nitrogen, uh, and maybe you start with all the oxygen on one side and nitrogen on the other side
but there's no barrier between them, right?
Then they will mix, um, and they should stay mixed
right?
There's- there's- there's no reason why they should unmix.
But in principle, because of all the collisions between them
there could be some sort of weird conspiracy that- that
um, like maybe there's a microscopic demon called Maxwell's demon that will
um.
..
Every time a oxygen and nitrogen atom collide
they will bounce off in such a way that the oxygen sort of drifts onto one side and then nitrogen goes to the other
and, uh, you could have an extremely improbable configuration emerge
uh, which we never see.
Um, and- and wh- which statistically it's extremely unlikely
but mathematically it's possible that this can happen and we can't rule it out.
Um, and this is a s- situation that shows up a lot in mathematics.
Um, a basic ex- example is the digits of pi
3.
14159 and so forth.
The digits look like they have no pattern
and we believe they have no pat-.
..
On the long term, you should see as many ones and twos and threes as fours and fives and sixes.
Uh, there- there should be no preference in the digits of pi to favor
let's say, seven over eight.
Um, but maybe there's some demon in the digits of pi that- that
like, every time you compute more and more digits
it sort of biases one digit to another.
Um, and this is a conspiracy that should not happen.
There's no reason it- it should happen, but
um, there's- there's- there's no way to prove it
uh, with our current technology.
Okay, so getting back to Navier-Stokes.
Uh, fluid has a certain amount of energy
and because the fluid's in motion, the energy gets transported around.
And, uh, water is also viscous.
So if the energy is spread out over many different locations
the natural viscosity of the fluid will just damp out the energy and it will- it will- it will go to zero.
Um, and this is what happens, um
in, um, uh, when we actually experiment with water.
Like, it- you splash around, there's- there's some turbulence and- and waves and so forth
but eventually it- it settles down and- and- and the- the lower the amplitude
the- the smaller the velocity, the- the more calm it gets.
Um, but potentially, there is some sort of demon that keeps pushing the
uh, the energy of the fluid into a smaller and smaller scale.
And it'll move faster and faster.
And at faster speeds, the effect of viscosity is relatively less.
And so it could happen that- that it- it creates a s- some sort of
um, um, what's called a self-similar blob scenario
where, you know, um, the energy of the fluid sta- starts off at some
um, large scale, and then it all sort of
um, transfers its energy into a smaller
um, region of- of- of the fluid
which then, at a much faster rate
um, moves in- into, um, an even s- smaller
uh, region and so forth.
Um, and- and each time it does this
uh, it takes maybe half as- as- as long as- as- as the previous one.
And then s- yeah, you could- you could- you could actually
uh, converge to- to all the energy
um, concentrating in one point in a f- a finite amount of time.
Um, and that- that- that's, uh, that scenario is called a finite time blow-up.
Um, so in practice, this doesn't happen.
Um, so water is what's called turbulent.
Um, so it is true that, um
if you have a big eddy of water
it will tend to break up into smaller eddies
but it won't transfer all the s- the energy from one big eddy into one small eddy.
It will transfer it into maybe three or four.
And then those might split up into maybe three or four small eddies of their own.
And so the energy gets dispersed till the point where the viscosity can
can then k- keep everything under control.
Um, but if it can somehow, um
concentrate, um, all the energy, keep it all together
um, and do it fast enough that
that the viscous effects, uh, don't have enough time to calm everything down
then this blowup can occur.
So there are papers who had claimed that
"Oh, you just need to take into account conservation of energy and
and just carefully use the viscosity and you can keep everything under control for not just the Navier-Stokes
but for many, many types of equations like this.
" And so like in the past, there had been many attempts to try to obtain what's called global regularity for Navier-Stokes
which is the opposite of final time blowup
that velocity stays smooth, and it all failed.
There was always some sign error or some subtle mistake and
and it, it couldn't be salvaged.
Um, so what I was interested in doing was trying to explain why we were not able to disprove
um, final time blowup.
I couldn't do it for the actual equations of fluids
which were too complicated.
But if I could average the equations of motion of Navier-Stokes
so physically if, if, um, if I could turn off certain types of
of ways in which water interacts and, and only keep the ones that I want.
Um, so in particular, um, if
um, if it's a fluid and it could transfer its energy from a large eddy into this small eddy or this other small eddy
I would turn off the energy channel that would transfer energy to this
this one, and, and direct it only into
um, this smaller eddy while still preserving the law of conservation of energy.
So you're trying to make it blow up?
Yeah.
Yeah, so I, I, I basically engineer
um, a blowup by changing the laws of physics
which is one thing that mathematicians are allowed to do.
We can change the equation.
How does that help you get closer to the proof of something?
Right.
So it provides what's called an ob- obstruction in mathematics.
Um, so, so what I did was that
uh, basically if I turned off the
um, certain parts of the equation so that.
..
Which usually when you turn off certain interactions make it less nonlinear
it makes it more regular and less likely to blow up.
But I found that by turning off a very well designed set of
of, of, of, of, of interactions
I could force all the energy to blow up
uh, in finite time.
So what that means is that if you wanted to prove
um, global regularity for Navier-Stokes, um, for the actual equation
you had, uh, you must use some feature of the true equation
which, which my artificial equation, um, does not satisfy.
So it, it rules out certain, um
certain approaches.
So, um, it's.
..
The thing about math is, is, is it's not just about finding
uh, you know, taking a technique that is gonna work and applying it
but you, you need to not take the techniques that don't work.
Um, and for the problems that are really hard
often there are dozens of ways that m- y- you might think might apply to solve the problem
but, uh, it's only after a lot of experience that you realize there's no way that these methods are going to work.
So having these counterexamples for nearby problems, um
kind of rules out, um, uh.
..
It, it saves you a lot of time because you
you, you're not wasting, um, energy on
on things that you now know cannot possibly ever work.
How deeply connected is it to that specific problem of fluid dynamics
or is this a more general intuition you built up about mathematics?
Right.
Yeah, so the key phenomenon that, uh
was, uh, my, my technique exploits is what's called supercriticality.
So in partial differential equations, often these equations are like a tug of war between different forces.
So in Navier-Stokes there's the dissipation, um
force coming from viscosity, it, and it's very well understood.
It's linear, it calms things down.
If, if viscosity was all there was
then, then nothing bad would ever happen.
Um, but there's also transport, um, that
that energy from, in one location of space can get transported because the fluid's in motion to
to other locations.
Um, and that's a nonlinear effect, and that causes all the
all the problems.
Um, so there are these two competing terms in the Navier-Stokes equation
uh, the dissipation term and the transport term.
If the dissipation term dominates, if it's
if it's large, then basically you get regularity.
And if, um, if the transport term dominates
then, uh, then we don't know what's going on.
It's a very nonlinear situation.
It's unpredictable.
It's turbulent.
So sometimes these forces are in balance at small scales
but not in balance at large scales or
or vice versa.
Um, so Navier-Stokes is what's called supercritical.
So at, at smaller and smaller scales the transport terms are much stronger than the viscosity terms.
So the viscosity terms are the things that calm things down
um, and so this is, um, um
this is why the problem is hard.
In two dimensions, so the Soviet mathematician
uh, Ledochinskaya, she in the '60s showed that in two dimensions
there was no blowup.
And in two dimensions, the, the Navier-Stokes equations is what's called critical.
The effect of transport and the effect of viscosity are about the same strength even at very
very small scales.
And we have a lot of technology to handle critical and also subcritical equations and prove
um, regularity.
But for supercritical equations, it was not clear what was going on.
And I did a lot of work and then there's been a lot of follow-up showing that for many other types of supercritical equations you can create all kinds of blowup examples.
Once the nonlinear effects dominate the linear effects at small scales
you can have all kinds of bad things happen.
So this is sort of one of the main insights of this
this line of work is that supercriticality versus criticality and subcriticality
this, this makes a big difference.
I mean, the, that's a key qualitative feature that distinguishes some equations from being sort of nice and predictable and
and, you know, like, like planetary motion.
And I mean, there, there's certain equations that
that you can predict for millions of years and
uh, or, or thousands at least.
Again, it's not really a problem.
But, but there's a reason why we can't predict the weather past two weeks into the future because it's a supercritical equation.
Lots of really strange things are going on at
at very fine scales.
So whenever there is some huge source of nonlinearity- Yeah.
.
..
that can create a huge problem for predicting what's gonna happen?
Yeah.
And if the nonlinearity is somehow more and more featured and interesting at
at small scales.
Um, I mean there's- there's many equations that are nonlinear
but, um, in ma- in- in many equations you can approximate things by the bulk.
Um, so for example, planetary motion, you know
if you wanted to u- understand the orbit of the moon or Mars or something
you don't really need the microstructure of, uh
like the seismology of the moon or- or like exactly how the mass is distributed
um, you just.
..
basically, you- you can almost approximate these planets by point masses.
Uh, and you.
..
it's just the aggregate behavior is important.
Um, but if you want to model a fluid
um, like- like the weather, you can't just say
"In Los Angeles, the temperature is this
the wind speed is this.
" For supercritical equations, the finest scale information is- is really important.
If we can just linger on the Navier-Stokes
uh, equations a little bit.
So you suggested.
..
maybe you can describe it, that one of the ways to
uh, solve it, or to negatively resolve it
would be to.
..
sort of to construct a liquid, a kind of liquid computer- Right.
.
..
and then show that the halting problem from computation theory has
uh, consequences for fluid dynamics, so, uh- Right.
.
show it in that way.
Can you describe this- this idea?
Right.
Yeah, so this came out of- of this work of constructing th- this- this av- this average equation that- that blew up.
Um, so one, um.
..
as- as part of how I had to- to do this.
so there's sort of this naive way to do it
you j- you- you just keep tr- pushing
um, um.
..
every time you- you get energy at one scale
you- you push it immediately to the next scale as- as fast as possible.
This is sort of the naive way to- to- to- to force blow up
um, which is like in five and higher dimensions this works.
Um, but in three dimensions there was this funny phenomenon that I discovered
that if you- if you keep.
..
if- if you change the laws of physics
you just always keep trying to push, um
the energy into smaller and smaller scales, um
what happens is that the energy s- starts getting spread out into multi- ma- many scales at once
um, so that you have- you have energy at one scale
you're pushing it i- into the next scale
and then, um, as soon as it enters that scale
you also push it to the next scale
but there's still some energy left over from the previous scale
um, you're trying to do everything at once
um, and this spreads out the energy too much
um, and then it turns out that- that
um, it makes it vulnerable for viscosity to come in and actually just damp out everything.
So, um, so it turns out this- this direct approach doesn't- doesn't actually work.
There was a separate paper by some other authors that actually showed this
um, in three dimensions.
Um, so what I needed was to program a delay
um, so kind of like airlocks, uh
so, um, I- I needed an equation which would start with a- a fluid doing something at one scale
it would push as energy into the next scale
but it would s- stay there until all the energy from the- from the larger scale got transferred
and only after you pushed all the energy in
then you sort of opened the next gate
uh, and- and then you- you push that in as well.
So, um, by doing that it kind of.
..
the energy inches forward scale by scale in such a way that it's always
um, localized at one scale at a time
um, and then it can resist the effects of viscosity because it's- it's not dispersed.
Um, so in order to make that happen
um, yeah, I had to construct a rather complicated non-linearity
um, and it was basically like, um
you know, like.
..
it was constructed like an e- electronic circuit
so I- I actually thank my wife for this because she was trained as a electrical engineer
um, and, um, you know, she- she talked about
um, uh.
..
you know, she had to design circuits and so forth
and, you know, if you- if you want a circuit that does a certain thing
like maybe have a light that- that flashes on and then turns off and then on and then off
you can build it from s- from more primitive components
you know, capacitors and resistors and so forth
and you have to board a diagram, and you
um.
..
and these diagrams, you can- you can sort of follow with your eyeballs and say
"Oh yeah, the- the- the current will- will board up here and then it will stop and then it will do that.
" So I knew how to build the analog of basic electronic components
you know, like resistors and capacitors and so forth
and- and I would- I would stack them together
um, in su- in such a way that- that I would create something that would open one gate and then there'd be a clock that would.
..
and then once the clock hits a certain threshold
it would close it.
Uh, become a Rube Goldberg type machine
but described mathematically, and this ended up working.
So what I realized is that if you could pull the same thing off for the actual equations
so if the equations of water support a computation
so, um.
..
like if you can imagine kind of a steampunk
but it's really water punk, uh, type of thing where
um, you know.
..
so modern computers are electronic, you know
they- they- they're powered by- by electrons p- passing through very tiny wires and interacting with oth- other electrons and- and so forth
but instead of electrons, you- you can imagine these pulses of- of water moving at a certain velocity
and maybe it's.
..
they're two different configurations corresponding to a bit being up or down.
Probably that if you had two of these moving bodies of water collide
uh, they would come out with some new configuration which is.
..
which would be something like an AND gate or OR gate
you know, that.
..
uh, it- it.
the- the output would depend in a very predictable way on- on the inputs.
And, like, you could chain these together and maybe create a Turing machine
and- and then you could.
..
you have computers, uh, which are made completely out of water
um, and if you have computers, then maybe you can do robotics
uh, you know, so.
..
you know, hydraulics and so forth.
Um, and so you could create some machine which is basically a- a fluid analog of what's called a Von Neumann machine.
Uh, so Von Neumann proposed if you want to colonize Mars
the sheer cost of transporting people and machines to Mars is just ridiculous
but if you could transport one machine to Mars and this machine had the ability to mine the planet
create some more materials, smelt them, and build more copies of the same machine
um, then you could colonize a whole planet
um, over time.
Um, so, uh, if you could build a fluid machine which
uh.
..
yeah, so it's- it's- it's a- it's a robo- it's a fluid robot
okay, and what it would do.
..
its- its purpose in life, it's programmed so that it would create a smaller version of itself in some sort of cold state
it- it wouldn't start just yet.
Once it's ready, the big robot configured with water would transfer a- all its energy into the s- the smaller configuration and then power down
okay, and then, like- like.
..
it cleaned itself up, and then what's left is this newest state which would then turn on and do the same thing
but smaller and faster.
..
. and then the equation has a certain scaling symmetry.
O- once you do that, it can just keep iterating.
So this, in principle, would create a blow up
uh, for the actual Navier-Stokes, and this is what I managed to accomplish for this average Navier-Stokes.
So it provided this sort of roadmap to solve the problem.
Now, this is, uh, a, a pipe dream because
uh, there are so many things that are missing for this to actually be a reality.
Um, so, um, I, I, I can't create these ba- basic logic gates.
Um, I, I don't, I don't have these
these special configurations of water.
Um, I mean, there's candidates.
There's things called vortex rings that might possibly work
but, um, um, but also, you know
analog computing is really nasty, um, com- compared to digital computing.
I mean, 'cause there's always errors.
Um, you'll, you have to, you have to do a lot of error correction along the way.
I don't know how to completely power down the big machine so that it doesn't interfere with the
the running of the smaller machine.
But everything in principle can happen.
Like, it doesn't contradict any of the laws of physics.
Um, so it's sort of evidence that this thing is possible.
Um, there are other groups who are now pursuing ways to make Navier-Stokes blow up which are nowhere near as ridiculously complicated as this.
Um, um, they, they actually are
are pursuing much closer to the, the direct self-similar model
which can, uh, it, it doesn't quite work as is
but there could be some simpler scheme than what I just described to make this work.
There is a real leap of genius here to go from Navier-Stokes to this Turing machine.
So it goes from what, the self-similar blob scenario that you're trying to get the smaller and smaller blob- Mm-hmm.
.
..
to now having a liquid Turing machine get smaller- Right.
.
..
and smaller and smaller, and somehow seeing how that could be used to say something about a blow up.
I mean, that's a big leap.
So there's precedent.
I mean, um, so the, the thing about mathematics is that it's
it's really good at, um, spotting connections between what you think of
what you might think of as completely different
um, problems.
Um, but if, if the mathematical form is the same
you, you, you can, you can draw a connection.
Um, so, um, there was a lot of work previously on what are called c- cellular automata.
Mm-hmm.
Um, the most famous of which is Conway's Game of Life.
There's this infinite discrete grid, and any given time
the grid is either occupied by a cell or it's empty.
And there's a very simple rule that, uh
that tells you how these cells evolve.
So s- sometimes cells live, and sometimes they
they die.
Um, and there's a, um, you know
um, when I was a, a student
uh, it was a very popular screen saver to actually just have these
these animations l- like going, and, and they look very chaotic.
In, in fact they look a little bit like turbulent flow sometimes.
But at some point people discovered more and more interesting structures within this game of life.
Um, so for example they discovered this thing called a glider.
So a glider is a very tiny configuration of like four or five cells
which evolves, and it just moves at a certain direction.
And that's like this, this vortex rings
this analog.
Um, yeah, so this is an a- analogy
the game of life is kind of like a discrete equation and
and, um, the fluid, Navier-Stokes is a continuous equation
but mathematically they have some similar features.
Um, and, um, so over time people discovered more and more interesting things that you could build within the game of life.
The game of life is a very simple system
it only has like three or four rules
um, to, to do with it.
But, but you can design all kinds of interesting configurations inside it.
Um, there's something ca- called a glider gun that does nothing else but spit out gliders one at a t- one
one at a time.
Um, and then after a lot of effort people managed to create
um, AND gates and OR gates for gliders.
Like there's this massive ridiculous structure which if you
if a, if a, if you have a stream of gliders
um, coming in here, and a stream of gliders coming in here
then you may produce extreme gliders coming out if m- s- may- maybe if both of
of the, um, streams, um, have gliders
then there'll be an- an ou- output stream.
But if only one of them does, then nothing comes out.
Mm-hmm.
So they could build something like that.
And once you could build an, um
these basic gates, then just from software engineering you can build almost anything.
Um, uh, you can build a Turing machine.
I mean, the, it's, it's like an enormous steampunk type thing
it's, they look ridiculous, but then people also generated self-replicating objects in the game of life
a massive machine, a Bonomo machine, which over a lo- huge period of time and
and it always looked like glider guns inside doing these very steampunk calculations.
It would create another version of itself which could replicate- That's so incredible.
A lot of this was like community crowdsourced by
uh, like amateur mathematicians actually.
Um, so I knew about that, that
that work, and so th- that is part of what inspired me to propose the same thing for Navier-Stokes.
Um, that really just, a much, as I said
analog is much worse than digital.
Like, uh, it's gonna be, um
you can't just directly take the constructions in the game of life and plunk them in
but again, it just, it shows it's possible.
You know, there's a kind of emergence that happens with these cellular automata local rules.
Mm-hmm.
Maybe it's similar to fluids, I don't know
but local rules operating at scale can create these incredibly complex dynamic structures.
Do you think any of that is amenable to mathematical analysis?
Do we have the tools to say something profound about that?
The thing is you can get this emergent very complicated structures
but only with very carefully prepared initial conditions
yeah.
So, so these, these, these glider guns
and, and gates, and, and software machines
if you just plunk down randomly some cells and you run the game of life
you will not see any of these.
Um, and th- that's the analogous situation with Navier-Stokes again
you know, that, that with, with typical initial conditions you will n- you will not have any of this weird computation going on.
Um, but basically through engineering, you know
by, by, by s- specially designing things in a very special way you can make clever constructions.
I wonder if it's possible to prove the sort of the negative of like basically prove that only through engineering can you ever create- Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
.
something interesting.
This, this is a recurring challenge in mathematics that
um-.
..
I call it the dichotomy between structure and randomness
that most objects that you can generate in mathematics are random.
Uh, they look like rad.
..
Like, the digits of pi, well, we believe is a good example.
Um, but there's a very small number of things that have patterns.
Um, but, um, now, you can prove something has a pattern by just constructing
you know.
Like if, if something has a simple pattern and you have a proof that it
it does something like repeat itself every so often
you can do that.
But, um.
..
And you c- you can prove that, that.
For example, you can, you can prove that most sequences of
of digits have no pattern.
Um, so like if, if you just pick digits randomly
there's something called the law of large numbers that tells you that you're going to get as many ones as
as twos, uh, in the long run.
Um, but, um, we have a lot fewer tools to
to, to.
..
If I give you a specific pattern like the digits of pi
how can I show that this doesn't have some weird pattern to it?
Some other work that I spend a lot of time on is to prove what are called structure theorems or inverse theorems that give tests for when something is
is very structured.
So some functions are what's called additive, like if you have a function that maps the natural numbers to the natural numbers
so maybe, um, you know, two maps to four
three maps to six and so forth.
Um, some functions are what's, what's called additive
which means that if you add.
..
if you add two inputs together, the output gets
gets added as well.
Uh, for example, uh, multiplying by a constant.
If you multiply a number by 10, um
if you, i- i- if you multiply A plus B by 10
that's the same as multiplying A by 10 and B by 10 and then adding them together
so some, um, functions are additive.
Some functions are kind of additive but not completely additive.
Um, so for example, if I take a number N
I multiply by the square root of two and I take the integer part of that
so 10 by the square root of two is like 14 point something
so 10 will map to 14.
Um, 20 will map to 28.
Um, so in that case, a- additivity is true then
so 10 plus 10 is 20 and 14 plus 14 is 28
but because of this rounding, uh, sometimes there's round off errors and
and sometimes when you, um, add A plus B
this function doesn't quite give you the sum of
of the two individual outputs, but the sum plus minus one.
Um, so it's almost additive, but not quite additive.
Um, so there's a lot of useful results in mathematics
and I've worked a lot on developing things like this
to the effect that if, if a function exhibits some structure like this
then, um, it's basically th- there's a reason for why it's true and the reason is because there's
there's some other nearby function which is actually
um, compl- completely structured, which is explaining this sort of partial pattern that you have.
Um, and so if you have these sort of inverse theorems
it, um, it creates this sort of dichotomy that
that either the objects that you study are either have no structure at all or they are somehow related to something that is structured.
Um, and in either way, in either
um, uh, in either case, you can make progress.
Um, a good example of this is that there's this old theorem in mathematics called Szemerédi's theorem
uh, proven in the 1970s.
It concerns trying to find a certain type of pattern in a set of numbers and the
the pattern is arithmetic progression, things like 3
5, and 7, or, or, or 10
15, and 20.
And Szemerédi, Endre Szemerédi proved that, um
any set of, of numbers that's sufficiently big
um, what's called, what's called positive density
has, um, arithmetic progressions in it of
of any length you wish.
Um, so for example, um, the odd numbers have a set of density one half
um, and they contain arithmetic progressions of any length.
Um, so in that case, it's obvious because the
the od- the odd numbers are really, really structured.
I can just take, uh, uh, 11
13, 15, 17.
I can just.
..
I can, I can easily find arithmetic progressions in
in, in that set.
Um, but, um, Szemerédi's theorem also applies to random sets.
If, if I take the set of all numbers and I flip a coin
um, and I, uh, for each number
and I only keep th- the numbers which
for which I got a heads, okay
so I just flip coins.
I just randomly take out half the numbers
I keep one half, so that's a set that has no
no patterns at all, but just from random fluctuations
you will still get a lot of, um
um, of arithmetic pro- progressions in that set.
Can you prove that there's arithmetic progressions of arbitrary length within a random- Yes.
Um, have you heard of the infinite monkey theorem?
Usually methodicians give boring names to theorems, but occasionally- Yeah.
.
..
they, they give colorful names.
Yes.
The popular version of the infinite monkey theorem is that if you have an infinite number of monkeys in a room with each a typewriter
they type out, uh, text randomly.
Almost surely one of them is going to generate the entire screw of Hamlet or any other finite string of text.
Uh, it will just take some time
uh, quite a lot of time actually.
But if you have an infinite number, then it happens.
Um, so, um, basically the theorem says that if you take an infinite string of
of digits or whatever, um, eventually any finite pattern you wish will emerge.
Uh, it may take a long time
but it will eventually happen.
Um, in particular, arithmetic progressions of any length will eventually happen.
Okay, but you need, uh, but you need an extremely long random sequence for this to happen.
I suppose that's intuitive, it's just infinity.
Yeah, infinity absorbs a lot of sins.
Yeah.
How are we humans supposed to deal with infinity?
Well, you can think of infinity as
as, as an abstraction of, um, a finite number for which you
you do not have a bound full.
Um, that, uh, you know, I mean
so nothing in real life is truly infinite.
Um, but, you know, you can
um, you know, you can ask these old questions like
what if I had as much money as I wanted
you know, or what if I could go as fast as I wanted?
And a way in which mathematicians formalize that is mathematics has found a formulism to idealize instead of something being extremely large or extremely small
to actually be exactly infinite or zero.
Um, and often the, the mathematics becomes a
a lot cleaner when you do that.
I mean, in physics we, we joke about
uh, assuming spherical cows.
Um, you know, like, real world problems have got all kinds of real world effects
but you can idealize, send some things to infinity
send some things to zero.
Um, and, um, and the mathematics becomes a lot simpler to work with there.
I wonder how often using infinity, uh
forces us to deviate from, um, the physics of reality.
Yeah.
So there's, there's a lot of pitfalls.
Um, so, you know, we, we spend a lot of time in undergraduate math classes teaching analysis
um, and analysis.
It's often about how to take limits and
and, and whether you.
..
You know, so for example, A plus B is always B plus A-Um
so when, when you have a finite number of terms and you add them
you can swap them and there's, there's no problem.
But when you have an infinite number of terms
there are these sort of show games you can play where you can have a series which converges to one value but you rearrange it and it suddenly converges to another value.
And so you can make mistakes.
You have to know what you're doing when you allow infinity.
Um, you have to introduce these epsilons and deltas and
and, and there's, there's a certain type of way of reasoning that helps you avoid mistakes.
Um, in more recent years, um, people have started taking results that are true in
in infinite limits and try what's cal- and what's called finitizing them
um, so you know that something is true eventually but
um, you don't know when, now give me a rate.
Okay, so such that if I don't have an infinite number of monkeys but
but a large finite number of monkeys, how long do you have to wait for Hamlet to come out?
Um, and, uh, that's a more qua- quantitative question.
Um, and this is something that you can
you can, um, attack by purely finite methods and you can use your finite intuition.
Um, and i- in this case it turns out to be exponential in the length of the text that you're
you're trying to generate.
Um, so if.
..
um, and so this is why you never see the monkeys create Hamlet.
You can maybe see them create a four-letter word
but nothing that big.
And so I personally find once you finitize an infinite statement it's
it does become much more intuitive a- and it's no longer so
so weird.
Um.
..
So even if you're working with infinity it's good to finitize so that you can have some intuition?
Yeah.
The downside is that the finitized proofs are just much
much messier.
Yeah.
And, and, uh, yeah, so the
so the infinite ones are found first usually
like decades earlier, uh, and then later on people finitized them.
So since we mentioned a lot of the math and a lot of physics- Mm-hmm.
.
..
uh, what to you is the difference between mathematics and physics as disciplines
as ways of understanding, of seeing the world?
Maybe we can throw in engineering in there
you mentioned your wife is an engineer, give a new perspective on circuits.
Right.
So there's a different way of looking at the world given that you've done mathematical physics
so you, you've, you've worn all the hats.
Right.
So I think science in general is an interaction between three things.
Um, there's the real world, um, there's what we observe of the real world
our observations, and then our mental models as to h- how we think the world w- works.
Um, so, um, we can't directly access reality
okay?
Uh, all we have are the, uh
observations which are incomplete and they, they have errors
um, and, um, there are many
many cases where we would, um, uh
we want to know, for example, what is the weather like tomorrow and we don't yet ha- have the observation and we'd like to make a prediction.
Um, and then we have these simplified models
sometimes making unrealistic assumptions, you know, spherical cow type things.
Those are the mathematical models.
Mm-hmm.
Mathematics is concerned with the models.
Science collects the observations and it proposes the models that might explain these observations.
What mathematics does i- uh, we, we stay within the model and we ask what are the consequences of that model
what observations, what, what predictions will the model make of the
of future observations.
Uh, or past observations, does, does it fit observed data?
Um, so there, there's definitely a symbiosis.
Um, it's math.
..
I guess mathematics is, is unusual among other disciplines is that we start from hypotheses
like the axioms of a model, and ask what conclusions come out from that model.
Um, in almost any other discipline, uh
you start with conclusions, you know, I want to do this
I want to build a bridge, you know
I want, I want to, to make money
I want to do this, okay?
And then you, you, you find the paths to get there.
Um, a lot.
..
there's, uh, there's a lot less sort of speculation about
you know, suppose I did this, what would happen?
Um, you know, planning and, and modeling.
Um, uh, speculative fiction maybe is, is one other place
uh, but, uh, that's about it actually.
Most of things we do in life is conclusions driven
including physics and sci- you know, I mean
they want to know, you know, where is this asteroid gonna go
you know, or what, what, what is the weather gonna be tomorrow?
Um, but, um, mathematics also has this other direction of
of going from the, uh, the axioms.
What do you think, there is this tension in physics between theory and experiment.
Mm-hmm.
What do you think is a more powerful way of discovering truly novel ideas about reality?
Well, you need both, top-down and bottom-up.
Um, yeah, it's just a, it's a really interaction between all these thing
AI.
So over time the observations and the theory and the modeling should g- both g- get closer to reality.
But initially, and it is, I mean
uh, this is, um, this is always the case out there
they're always far apart to begin with.
Um, but you need one to figure out
uh, where, where to push the other
you know?
So, um, if your model is predicting anomalies
um, that are not picked up by experiment
that tells experimenters where to look, you know
um, to, to, to, to find more data to refine the models.
Um, you know, so it, it goes
it goes back and forth.
Um, within mathematics itself, there's, there's also a theory and experimental component.
It's just that until very recently, theory has dominated almost completely.
Like 99% of mathematics is theoretical mathematics, and there's a very tiny amount of experimental mathematics.
Um, I mean, people do do it
you know, like if they want to study prime numbers or whatever
they can just generate large datasets and with a com- so once we had computers
um, we began to do it a little bit.
Um, although even before.
..
well, like Gauss for example, he discovered
he conjectured the most basic theorem in, in number theory
it's called the prime number theorem, which predicts how many primes that are up to a million
up to a trillion.
It's not an obvious question, and basically what he did was that he computed
uh, I mean, mostly, uh, um
by himself, but also hired human computers
um, people who, whose professional job it was to do arithmetic
um, to compute the first 100,000 primes of something and made tables and made a prediction.
Um, that was an early example of experimental mathematics.
Um, but until very recently it was not
um, yeah, I mean, theoretical mathematics was just much more successful.
I mean, because doing complicated mathematical computations is
uh, was just not, not feasible, uh
until very recently.
Uh, and even nowadays, you know, even though- though we have powerful computers
only some mathematical things can be, um
explored numerically.
There's something called the Commodore explosion.
If you want to- to study, for example
Zeamer–Modyi's theorem, you want to study all possible subsets of the numbers one to 1
000, there's only 1,000 numbers.
How bad could it be?
It turns out the number of different subsets of- of one to 1
000 is two to the power of 1
000, which is way bigger than- than- than any computer can currently can- can enu- in fact
any computer ever will ever get, uh
enumerate.
Um, so if you have to be
um.
..
There are certain math problems that very quickly become just intractable to attack by direct brute force computation.
Uh, chess is another, um, uh
famous example.
Uh, it's the number of chess positions
uh, we can't get a c- computer to fully explore
but now we have AI, um, um
we have tools to explore this space not with 100% guarantees of s-success
but with experiment, you know?
So like, um, we can empirically solve chess now
right?
For example, uh, we have, we have a
uh, very, very good AIs that they can.
..
you know, they don't explore every single position in- in the game tree
but they have found some very good approximation.
Um, and people are using actually these chess engines
uh, to make.
..
uh, to do experimental chess.
Um, that, uh, they're- they're revisiting old chess theories about
oh, you know, when you.
..
this type of opening, you know, th- this is a good- this is a good type of move
this is not, and they can use these chess engines to actually
uh, refine, uh, and in some cases overturn
um, um, conventional wisdom about chess.
And I- I do hope that, uh
that mathematics will- will have a larger experimental component in the future
perhaps powered by AI.
We'll, of course, ta- talk about that
but in the case of chess, and there's a similar thing in mathematics
the.
..
I don't believe it's providing a kind of formal explanation of the different positions.
No.
It's just saying which position is better or not
and then you can intuit as a human being
and then from that, we humans can construct- Yes.
.
a theory of the matter.
Right.
You've mentioned the Plato's cave allegory.
Mm-hmm.
So in case people don't know, it's where people are observing shadows of reality
not reality itself, and they believe what they're observing to be reality.
Is that, in some sense, what mathematicians and maybe all humans are doing
is, um, looking at shadows of reality?
Do.
..
is it possible for us to truly access reality?
Well, there are these three ontological things.
There's actual reality, there's our observations, and our- our models.
Um, and- and technically, they are distinct
and I think they will always be distinct
um- Right.
.
..
but they can get closer, um, over time.
Um, you know, so, um.
..
and the process of getting closer often means that you're.
you have to discard your initial intuitions, um
so, um, a- astronomy r- provides great examples
you know, like, you know, like
your.
..
an initial model of the world is that it's flat because it's.
it looks flat, you know, and- and
um, and that it's.
..
and it's big, you know, and the rest of the universe
the skies is not.
..
you know, like, the sun, for example
looks really tiny, um, and so you- you start off with a model which is actually really far from reality
um, but it fits kind of the observations that you have
um, you know?
So, you know, so things look good for.
..
you know, but if it.
over time, as you make more and more observations
bringing it closer to- to- to reality, um
the model gets dragged along with it, you know?
And so over time, we had to realize that the Earth was round
that it spins, it goes around the solar system
the solar system goes around the galaxy, and so on and so forth
and the.
..
it goes by the universe and it's expanding.
Um, the expansions are self-expanding, accelerating, and in fact very recently
in- in this year or so, there's a.
..
even the assertion of the universe itself is
uh.
..
there's evidence now that it's- it's non-constant.
And, uh, the explanation behind why that is
is- It's catching up.
Um-  It's catching up.
I mean, it's still, you know, the dark matter
dark energy- Yes.
Mm-hmm.
.
this- this kind of thing.
Yes.
We have a- we have a model that sort of explains.
..
that fits the data really well.
It just has a few parameters that, um
uh, you have to specify.
Um, but so, you know, people say
"Oh, that's fudge factors," you know
with- with enough fudge factors, you can- you can explain anything.
Um, yeah, but, uh, the mathematical point of the model is that
um, you want to have fewer parameters in your model than data points in your observational set.
So if you have a model with 10 parameters that explains 10 out- 10 observations
that is a completely useless model.
It's what's called overfitted.
But, like, if you have a model with- with
you know, two parameters and it explains a- a trillion observations
which is basically.
..
uh.
so, uh.
..
yeah, the- the- the dark matter model I think has like 14 parameters and it explains petabytes of data
um, that- that- that- that- the astronomers have.
Um, you can think of a- of a theory
uh, like one way to think about
um, a- a physical mathematical theory.
..
a- a theory is- it's- it's a compression of- of the universe
um, and, uh, uh, data compression.
So, you know, you have these petabytes of observations
you like to compress it to a model which you can describe in five pages and specify a certain number of parameters
and if it can fit to reasonable accuracy
you know, a- almost all of your- of your observations
that.
..
I mean, the more compression that you make
the better your theory.
In fact, one of the great surprises of our universe and of everything in it is that it's compressible at all.
That's the- Yeah.
.
..
unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics.
Yeah.
Einstein had a quote like that.
The- the most incomprehensible thing about the universe is that it is comprehensible.
Right.
And not just comprehensibly.
You can do an equation like E equals MC squared.
There is actually a.
..
some mathematical possible explanation for that.
Um, so there's this phenomenon in mathematics called universality.
So many complex systems at the macroscale are coming out of lots of tiny interactions at- at the macroscale
and normally because of the common form of explosion
you would think that, uh, the macroscale equations must be like infinitely
exponentially more complicated than- than the, uh
the microscale ones, and they are if you want to solve them completely exactly.
Like if you want to model, um
all the atoms in a box of- of air
uh, that's like Avogadro's number is humongous
right?
There's a huge number of particles.
If you actually had to track each one
it would be ridiculous.
But certain laws emerge at the microscopic scale that almost don't depend on what's going on at the macroscale or only depend on a very small number of parameters.
So if you want to model a gas
um, of, you know-.
..
quintillion particles in, in a box.
You just need to know its temperature and pressure and volume and a few parameters
like five or six, and it models almost everything you
you need to know about these 10 to the 23 or whatever particles.
Um, so we, we have, um
we, we don't understand universality anywhere near as we would like mathematically
but there are much simpler toy models where we do
um, have a good understanding of why universi- universality occurs.
Um, uh, most basic one is, is the central limit theorem.
That explains why the bell curve shows up everywhere in nature
that so many things are distributed by, uh
what's called a Gaussian distribution, uh, famous bell curve.
Uh, there's now even a meme with this curve.
And even the meme applies broadly.
Yeah.
There's a universality to the meme.
Yes, you can call meta, uh-  .
..
if you like.
But there are many, many processes.
For example, you c- you can take lots and lots of independent
um, random variables and average them together
um, uh, in, in various ways.
You basically.
..
you take a simple average or more complicated average
and we can prove in various cases that
that these, these bell curves, these Gaussians emerge
and it is a satisfying, satisfying explanation.
Um, sometimes they don't.
Um, so, so if you have many different inputs and they're all correlated in some s- systemic way
then y- you can get something very far from a bell curve to show up.
Uh, and this is also important to know when such a system fails.
So universality is not a 100% reliable thing to rely on at that
um, um.
..
there the global financial crisis was a, a famous example of this.
Uh, people thought that, uh, um
mortgage de- defaults, um, um, had this sort of
um, Gaussian-type behavior that, that if you
if you ask.
..
if a population of, of, of, uh
you know, 100,000 Americans with mortgages
ask what, what proportion of them will default on their mortgages
um, if everything was decorrelated, it would be a nice bell curve and
and like you can, you can, you can manage risk of options and derivatives and so forth and
um, and it is a very beautiful theory.
Um, but if there are systemic shocks in the economy  uh
that can push everybody to default at the same time
uh, that's very non-Gaussian behavior.
Um, and, uh, this wasn't fully accounted for  in
uh, 2008.
Um, now I think there's some more awareness that this is a.
..
systemic risk is actually a, a much bigger issue.
And, uh, just because the model is pretty
uh, and nice, uh, it may not match reality.
And so, so the mathematics of working out what models do is really important
um, but, um, also the, the
the science of validating when the models, uh
fit reality and when they don't.
Um, I mean, that.
..
you need both.
Um, and, but mathematics can help because it c- it can
it c- uh, for example, these central limit theorems
it, it tells you that, that if you have certain axioms like
like, like, uh, non-correlation, that if all the inputs were not correlated to each other
um, then you have this kind of behavior that things are fine.
It, it tells you where to look for weaknesses in the model.
So b- if you have a mathematical understanding of central limit theorem and someone proposes to use these Gaussian copulas or whatever to mo- to model
um, default risk, um, if you're mathematically
um, trained, you would say, "Okay
but what are the systemic correlation between all your inputs?
" And so then the.
..
then you can ask the economists, you know
how, how, how much of a risk is that?
Um, and then you can, you can
you can go look for that.
So there's always this, this, uh, this synergy between science and
and mathematics.
A little bit on the topic of universality.
..
Mm-hmm.
You're known and celebrated for working across an incredible breadth of mathematics
reminiscent of Hilbert a century ago.
In fact, the great Fields Medal-winning mathematician
Tim Gowers, has said that you are the closest thing we get to Hilbert.
Ah.
He's a colleague of yours.
Oh, yeah.
Good friend.
But anyway, so y- you are known for this ability to go both deep and broad in mathematics
so you're the perfect person to ask, do you think there are threads that connect all the disparate area- areas of mathematics?
Is there a kind of deep underlying structure
uh, to all of mathematics?
There's certainly a lot of connecting threads, um
and a lot of the progress of mathematics has.
..
can be represented by taking.
by stories of two fields of mathematics that were previously not connected and finding connections.
Um, an ancient example is, um, geometry and number theory.
You know, so, so in the times of the ancient Greeks
these were considered different subjects.
Um, I mean, mathematicians worked on both.
You know, you could, uh, work both on
on geometry most famously, but also on numbers.
Um, but they were not really considered related.
Um, I mean, a little bit, like
you know, you, you could say that
that the.
..
this length was five times this length because you could take five copies of this length and so forth.
But it wasn't until Descartes who really realized that.
..
uh, who developed what we now call analytic geometry
that you can, you can parametrize the plane
a geometric object, by, um, by two real numbers
right?
Every point can be.
..
uh, and so geometric problems can be turned into
into problems about numbers.
Um, and the, the.
..
today this feels almost trivial, like the.
there's like.
..
there's, there's, there's no content to this.
Like, of course, uh, you.
..
you know, um, a plane is X
X and Y, you know, of course
that's what we teach and it's internalized.
Um, but it was an important development that these
these two fields are, are.
..
were unified.
Um, and I suppose this has just gone on throughout mathematics over and over again
that algebra and geometry were separated and now we have this root algebraic geometry that connects them and
and over and over again.
And that's certainly the type of mathematics that I enjoy the most.
So I think there's sort of different styles to being a mathematician.
I think hedgehogs and foxes.
A fox knows many things a little bit
but a, a hedgehog knows one thing very
very well.
Um, and in mathematics there's definitely both hedgehogs and foxes
um, and then there's people who are kind of.
..
uh, who can play both roles.
Um, and I think i- ideal collaboration between mathematicians in- involves very d- you need some diversity
y- like, um, a f- a fox working with many h- hedgehogs or
or vice versa.
So yeah, but, but I identify mostly a- as a fox
uh, certainly.
I, I, I like, uh, arbitrage somehow
you know, like, like, um, learning how one field works
learning the tricks of that world and then going into another field which.
..
. people don't think of it as related
but I can, I can adapt the tricks.
So see the connections between- Yeah.
.
the fields.
Yeah.
So there are other mathematicians who are far deeper than I am
like who, they're, who have, they're really hedgehogs
you know.
They, they've, they, they know everything about one field and they're much faster and
and more effective in that field, but I can
I can give them these extra tools.
I mean, you've said that you can be both a hedgehog and a
and the fox, depending on the context- Yeah.
.
..
depending on the collaboration.
So what.
..
Can you, if it's at all possible
speak to the difference between those two ways of thinking about a problem?
Say you're encountering a new problem, you know
searching for the connections versus, like, a very singular focus.
I'm much more comfortable with, with the
uh, the, uh, the fox paradigm.
Yeah, so, um, yeah, I, I like looking for analogies
narratives.
Um, I, I spend a lot of time
if, if there's a result, I see it in one field and I like the result
it's a cool result, but I don't like the proof.
Like-  .
..
it uses types of mathematics that I'm not super familiar with.
Um- Yes.
.
..
I often try to reprove it myself using the tools that I favor.
Um, often my proof is worse, um
but, um, by the exercise of doing so
um, I can say, "Oh, now I can see what the other proof was trying to do.
" Um, and from that, I can get some understanding of
of the tools that are used in, in that field.
So it's very exploratory, very doing crazy things in crazy fields and like
yeah, reinventing the wheel a lot.
Yeah, whereas, so the hedgehog style is
uh, I think much more scholarly, you know
you, you are very knowledge based, you
you, you, you stay up to speed on like all the developments in this field
you, you know all the history, um
you have a very good understanding of, of exactly the strengths and weaknesses of
of each particular, uh, technique.
Um, yeah, uh, I think you
you'd rely a lot more on sort of calculation than sort of trying to find narratives.
Um, so yeah, I mean, I can do that too
but, uh, there are other people who are extremely good at that.
Let's step back and, uh, uh, maybe look at the
the, a bit of a romanticized version of mathematics.
Mm-hmm.
So, uh, I think you've said that early on in your life
uh, math was more like a puzzle-solving activity- Mm-hmm.
.
when you were, uh, young.
When did you first encounter a problem or proof where you realized math can have a kind of elegance and beauty to it?
That's a good question.
Um, when I came to graduate school
uh, in Princeton, um, so John Conway was there at the time
he, he passed away a few years ago
but, uh, I remember one of the very first research talks I
I went to was a talk by Conway on what he called extreme proof.
So Conway just had this, this amazing way of
of thinking about all kinds of things in a
in a way that you wouldn't normally think of.
So, um, he thought of proofs themselves as occupying some sort of space
you know, so, so, um, if you wanted to prove something
let- let's say that there's infinitely many primes
okay?
There are always different proofs, but you could
you could rank them in different axes, like some proofs are elegant
some proofs are long, some proofs are
are, um, are elementary and so forth.
Um, and so there's this cloud.
..
So the space of all proofs itself has some sort of shape.
Um, and so he, he was interested in
in extreme points of the shape, like out of all
all these proofs, which one is the shortest at the ex- at the expense of everyth- everything else or
or the most elementary or, or whatever.
Um, and so he gave some examples of well-known theorems
and then he would give what he thought was
was the extreme proof, um, in these different aspects.
Um, um, I just found that really eye-opening
um, that, that, um, you know
it's not just getting a proof what was
uh, was interesting, but, but once you have that proof
you know, trying to, to, uh
to optimize it in various ways, um
that, that proof, um, uh, proofing itself had some craftsmanship to it.
Um, it certainly informed my writing style
um, that, you know, like when you do your
your math assignments in undergraduate, your homework and so forth
you, you're sort of encouraged to just write down any proof that works
okay?
And hand it in and get a, as long as it gets a tick mark
you, you move on.
Um, but if you want your, your results to actually be influential and be read by people
um, it can't just be correct.
It should also, um, be a pleasure to read
you know, um, motivated, um, be adaptable to
to generalize to other, um, things.
Um, it's the same in, in many other disciplines
like, like coding.
There's, there's a lot of analogies between math and coding.
I like analogies, if you haven't noticed.
Um, but, um- Yeah.
.
..
like you can code something, a spaghetti code that works for a certain task and it's quick and
and dirty and it works, but there's lots of good principles for
for, um, writing code well so that other people can use it
build upon it and so on, and has fewer bugs and whatever.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and there's similar things with math- mathematics
so.
Yeah, the.
..
First of all, there's so many beautiful things there and Conway is one of the great minds
uh, in mathematics ever and computer science.
Uh, just even considering the space of proofs- Yeah.
.
..
and saying, "Okay, what does this space look like?
And what are the extremes?
" Uh, like you mentioned, coding as an analogy is interesting because there's also this activity called
uh, Code Golf- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
.
..
which I also find beautiful and fun, uh
where people use different programming languages to try to write the shortest possible program that accomplishes a particular task.
Yeah.
And I believe there's even competitions on this.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And, uh, it's also a nice way to stress test not just the.
..
sort of the programs, or in this case the proofs
but also the different languages, maybe that's a different notation or whatever to use to
to accomplish a different task.
Yeah.
Yeah, you learn a lot.
I mean, it, it may seem like a frivolous exercise
but it, it can generate all these insights which
if you didn't have this artificial, um-.
..
objective, uh, to, to, to pursue
you, you might not see.
What to you is the most beautiful or elegant equation in mathematics?
I mean, one of the things that people often look to in
in beauty is the simplicity.
So if you look at E equals MC squared.
Mm-hmm.
So when, when a few concepts come together
that's why the Euler identity- Hmm.
.
..
is often considered, uh, the most beautiful equation in mathematics.
Mm-hmm.
Do you, do you find beauty in that one
in the Euler identity?
Yeah.
Well, as I said, I mean, what I find most appealing is
is connections between different things that y- that
um.
..
So the, if you, uh, E to the Phi I equals minus one.
Um, so yeah, people are like, "Oh
this uses all the fundamental constants.
" Okay.
That- that- that's.
..
I mean that's cute.
Um, but, but-  .
..
to me- Yeah.
.
so the exponential function was introduced by Euler to measure exponential growth
you know, so comp- compound interest or decay
or anything which is continuously growing, continuously decreasing.
Growth and decay or dilation or contraction is modeled by the exponential function.
Um, whereas Pi, uh, comes around from circles and rotation
right?
If you want to rotate a needle, for example
180 degrees, uh, you need to rotate it by Pi radians.
And I, complex numbers, represents this function on an imaginary axis
so a 90-degree rotation, so a change in direction.
So the exponential function represents growth and decay in the direction that you already are.
Um, when you stick an I in the exponential
it, it, it.
..
Now it's, it's instead of motion in the same direction as your current position
it's motion as right angles to your current position
so rotation.
Um, and then so E to the
E to the Pi equals minus one tells you that if you rotate for time Pi
you end up at the other direction.
So it unifies geometry through dilation and exponential growth
you know, dynamics through this act of
of complexification, rotation by, by, by I.
So it, it connects together all these towards mathematics
you know.
Yeah.
That that was geometerically complex, and complex
and, um, the complex numbers, they're all considered almost.
..
Yeah, they were all next door neighbors in mathematics
because of this iden- identity.
Do, do you think the thing you mentioned is cute
the, the, the collisional notations from these disparate fields
um, is just a frivolous side effect?
Or do you think there is legitimate, like
value in- Um- .
..
notation, although our old friends come together  in the night.
Right.
Well, it's, it's, it's confirmation that you have the right concepts.
Um, so when you first study anything
um, you, you have to measure things and give them names.
Um, and initially, sometimes your.
..
Because your, your model is getting too far off from reality
you give the wrong things the best names
and you only find out later what's, what's really important.
Physicists can do this sometimes.
I mean, but it turns out okay.
So actually, physics, so E equals MC squared.
Okay.
So, uh, one of the, the big things was the E
right?
So when, when Aristotle first came up with his laws of
of motion and then, and then, um
Galileo and Newton and so forth, you know
they saw the things they could, they could measure.
They could measure mass and acceleration and force and so forth.
And so Newtonian mechanics, for example, you know
F equals MA was the famous, uh
Newton's second law of motion.
So those were the, the primary objects
so they gave them the central billing in the theory.
It was only later after people started analyzing these equations
that there always seemed to be these quantities that were conserved.
Um, so, um, in particular momentum and energy.
Um, uh, and it's not obvious that things happen in energy.
Like, it's not something you can directly measure the same way you can measure mass and
and, and velocity and so forth.
But over time, people realized that this was actually a really fundamental concept.
Hamilton eventually, in the 19th century, reformulated Newton's laws of physics into what is called Hamiltonian mechanics
where the energy, which is now called the Hamiltonian
was the dominant object.
Once you know how to measure the Hamiltonian of any system
you can describe completely the, the dynamics
like what, what happens to, to all
to all the states.
Like it's.
..
Um, it, it really was a central actor
which was not obvious initially.
Um, and this, uh, helped actually
uh.
..
This change of perspective really helped when quantum mechanics came along
uh, because i- um.
..
The early physicists who studied quantum mechanics, they had a lot of trouble trying to adapt their New- Newtonian thinking because you know everything was a particle and so forth
to, to, to quantum mechanics, you know
because now everything, because it was a wave
it just looked really, really weird.
Um, like you ask, "What is the quantum version of F equals MA?
" And it's really, really hard to, to give an answer to that.
Um, but it turns out that the Hamiltonian
which was so, um, secretly behind the scenes in classical mechanics
also is the key, uh, object in
um, um, in quantum mechanics, that this.
..
There's also an object called a Hamiltonian.
It's a di- different type of object.
It's what's called an operator rather than, than a function
but, um, and, um.
..
But again, once you specify it, you specify the entire dynamics.
So there's something called Schoenibers equation that tells you exactly how quantum systems evolve once you have a Hamiltonian.
So side by side, they look completely different objects
you know.
Like, so one involves particles, one involves waves and so forth.
But with this centrality, you could start actually transferring a lot of intuition and facts from classical mechanics to quantum mechanics.
So for example, in, in classical mechanics
there's this thing called Noether's theorem.
Every time there's a symmetry in a physical system
there is a conservation law.
So the laws of physics are translation invariant.
Like, if I move 10 steps to the left
I experience the same laws of physics as if I was here
and that corresponds to conservation of moment- momentum.
Um, if I turn around by ni- by some angle
again I experience the same laws of physics.
Uh, this corresponds to the conservation of angular momentum.
If I wait for 10 minutes, um
I still have the same laws, laws of physics
um, so there's time translation variance.
This corresponds to the law of conservation of energy.
Um, so there's this fundamental connection between symmetry and conservation
um, and that's also true in quantum mechanics even though the equations are completely different.
But because they're both coming from the Hamiltonian
the Hamiltonian controls everything, um, every time the Hamiltonian has symmetry
the equations will, will have a conservation law.
Um, so it's, it's, it's, it's.
..
Once you have the right language, it actually makes things
um, uh, a lot, a lot cleaner.
One of the problems why we can't unify quantum mechanics and general relativity yet
we haven't figured out what the fundamental objects are.
Like, for example, we have to give up the notion of space and time being these almost Euclidean type spaces
and it has to be s- um.
..
. you know, and, you know, w- we kind of know that at very tiny scales
uh, um, there's gonna be quantum fluctuations as a space- space-time foam
um, and trying to- to use Cartesian coordinates X
Y, Z is gonna be.
..
It's- it's just, it's- it's a non-starter.
But we don't know how to, what to replace it with.
Um, we don't actually have the mathematical re- um
uh, concepts, you know, the analog of the Hamiltonian that sort of organized everything.
Does your gut say that there is a theory of everything
so this is po- even possible to unify
to find this language that unifies general relativity and quantum mechanics?
I believe so.
I mean, the history of physics has been that of unification
much like mathematics, um, over the years.
You know, electricity and magnetism were, were separate theories and then Maxwell unified them.
You know, Newton unified the- the motions of the heavens with the motions on
of objects on the Earth and so forth.
So it should happen.
Uh, it's just that the, um, uh.
..
again, to go back to this model of the
of the observations and- and- and theory, part of our problem is that physics is a victim of its own success.
That, uh, two big theories of- of- of physics
general relativity and quantum mechanics are so- are so good now.
It's that together they cover 99.
9% of sort of all the observations we can make.
Um, and you have to, like, either go to extremely insane particle accelerations or- or the early universe or- or- or things that are really hard to measure
um, in order to get any deviation from either of these two theories
to the point where you can actually figure out how to- how to c- combine them together.
Um, but I have faith that we.
..
you know, we've- we've- we've been doing this for centuries and we've made progress before.
There- there's no reason why we should stop.
Do you think it will be a mathematician that develops a theory of everything?
What often happens is that when the physicists need
uh, um, some theory of math- math- mathematics
there's often some precursor that the mathematicians, um
worked out earlier.
So when Einstein started realizing that space was curved
he went to some mathematician and asked, you know
"Is there, is there some theory of curved space that the mathematicians already came up with that could be useful?
" And he said, "Oh, yeah.
There's a.
..
I think, uh, Riemann came up with something.
" Um, and so yeah, Riemann had developed Riemannian geometry
um, which is precisely, um, you know
a- a- a- a theory of spaces that are curved in- in various general ways
which turned out to be almost exactly what was needed
um, for Einstein's theory.
This is going back to- to Wigner's unreasonable effectiveness on mathematics.
I think the theories that work well to explain the universe tend to also involve the same mathematical objects that work well to solve mathematical problems.
Mm-hmm.
Ultimately, they're just sort of both ways of organizing data
um, in- in- in- in useful ways.
It just feels like you might need to go to some weird land that's very hard to- to intuit.
Like.
..
Yeah, yeah.
.
you know, you have like string theory.
Yeah.
That- that's, that was, that was a leading candidate for many decades.
It's- I think it's slowly falling out of fashion because it's- it's not matching experiment
uh.
..
So one of the big challenges, of course
like you said, is experiment is very tough- Yes.
.
..
because of the how effective- Yeah.
.
..
both theories are.
But the other is like just, you know
you're talking about you're not just deviating from space-time
you're going into like some crazy number of dimensions.
Yeah.
You're doing all kinds of weird stuff that to us.
..
We've gone so far from this flat Earth that we started on- Yes.
.
like you mentioned.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That now we're just.
..
It's- it's very hard to use our limited ape descendants of
uh, uh, cognition to intuit what that reality really is like.
This is why analogies are so important, you know?
I mean, so yeah, when.
..
The round Earth is not intuitive because we're- we're stuck on it.
Um, but, you know, but y- y- y- you know
but round objects in general, we have pretty good intuition
a little bit, uh, and we have intuition about light works and so forth.
And like it's- it's actually a good exercise to actually work out how eclipses and phases of- of the sun and the moon and so forth can be really easily explained by- by- by- by round Earth and round moon
you know, um, and models.
Um, and- and you can just take
you know, a basketball and a golf ball and- and- and- and a light source and actually do these things yourself.
Um, so the intuition is there, um
but yeah, you have to transfer it.
That is a big leap intellectually for us to go from flat to round Earth-  .
..
because, you know, our life is mostly lived in flat land.
Yeah.
To load that information in.
..
We're all like take it for granted.
We take so many things for granted because science has established a lot of evidence- Mm-hmm.
.
for this kind of thing.
But, you know, we're on a r- ro- round rock - Yeah.
.
..
flying through space.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And it's a big leap and you have to take a chain of those leaps the more and more and more we progress.
Right.
Yeah.
So modern science is maybe again a victim of its own success
is that, you know, in order to be more accurate
it has to- to move further and further away from your initial intuition.
And so, um, for someone who hasn't gone through the whole process of science education
it looks more and more sus- suspicious- Yeah.
.
..
because of that.
So, you know, we- we- we need
we need more grounding.
I mean, I- I think, um.
..
I mean, you know, there are- there are scientists who do excellent outreach
um, but there's- there's- there's- there's- there's lots of science things that you can do at home.
I- I.
..
there's lots of YouTube videos.
I did a YouTube video recently with Grant Sandeson
we talked about this earlier, that, uh
you know, how- how the ancient Greeks were able to measure things like the distance of the moon
distance of the Earth, and, you know
using techniques that you c- you could also replicate yourself.
Um, it doesn't all have to be like fancy space telescopes and- and very intimidating mathematics.
Yeah.
That's, uh.
..
I highly recommend that.
I believe you give a lecture and you also did an incredible video with Grant.
It's a beautiful experience to try to put yourself in the mind of a person from that time- Mm-hmm.
.
..
shrouded in mystery.
Right.
You know, you're like on this planet.
You don't know the shape of it, the size of it.
You see some stars, you see some
you see some things and you try to like localize yourself in this world- Yeah
yeah.
.
..
and try to make some kind of general statements about distance to places.
Change of perspective is really important.
They say travel broadens the mind, right?
This is intellectual travel, you know.
Put yourself in the mind of- of the ancient Greeks or- or some other-.
..
person from some other time period, make hypotheses
spherical cows, whatever- Mm-hmm.
.
..
you know, speculate.
Um, and you know, this is- this is what mathematicians do
and some art- you know, sort of artists do
actually.
It's just incredible that given the extreme constraints
you can still say very powerful things.
That's why it's inspiring.
Looking back in history, how much can be figured out- Right.
.
..
when you don't have much to figure out stuff with.
Right, well if you propose axioms, then the mathematics lets you
you know, follow those axioms to- to their conclusions
and sometimes you can get quite a long way from
you know, initial hypotheses.
If we're gonna stay in the land of the weird
you mentioned general relativity.
You've, uh,  you've contributed, uh
to the mathematical understanding of Einstein's field equations.
Can you explain this work, and, uh
from a sort of mathematical standpoint, uh
wh- what aspects of general relativity are intriguing to you
challenging to you?
I have worked on some equations.
There's something called the- the wave maps equation
or the sigma field model, which is not quite the equation of spacetime gravity itself
but of certain fields that might exist on top of spacetime.
Um, so Einstein's equations of relativity just describes space and time itself
um, but then there's other fields that live on top of that.
Uh, there's the e- electromagnetic field, there's things called Yang-Mills fields
and there's this whole hierarchy of different equations
of which Einstein's is considered one of the most non-linear and difficult
but relatively low on the hierarchy was this thing called the wave maps equation.
So it's a wave which, at any given point
uh, is fixed to be like on a sphere.
Um, so, uh, like think of a bunch of arrows in space and time
and- and- and yeah, so it's pointing in- in different directions
um, but they propagate like waves.
If- if- if you wiggle an arrow, it will- it will propagate and- and make all the arrows move kind of like
uh, sheaves of wheat in a wheat field.
And I was interested in the global regularity problem again for this ques- like
is it possible for- for all the energy here to- to collect at a point?
So the equation I considered was actually what's called a critical equation
where it's actually the behavior at all scales is roughly the same
um, and I was able barely to show that- um
that you couldn't actually force a scenario where all the energy concentrated at one point
that the energy w- I had to dismiss a little bit
and the moment it disappeared a little- a little bit
it would- it would- it would stay regular.
Yeah, this was back in 2000.
That was part of why I got interested in Navier-Stokes afterwards
actually.
Yeah, so I developed some techniques to
um, solve that problem.
So part of it is- it- it was
um, this problem is really non-linear, uh
because of the curvature of the sphere, um
there's- there was a certain non-linear effect, which was a non-perturbative effect.
It was, when you sort of looked at it normally
it- it looked larger than the linear effects of the wave eq- equation
um, and so it was hard to- to keep things under control
even when the energy was small.
But I developed what's called a gauge transformation.
So the equation is kind of like an evolution of- of- of sheaves of wheat
and- and they're all bending back and forth
and so there's a lot of motion, um
but like if you imagine like stabilizing the flow by attaching little cameras at different points in space
which are trying to move in a way that captures most of the motion
and under the sort of stabilized flow, the flow becomes a lot more linear.
I discovered a way to transform the- the equation to reduce the amount of non-linear effects
um, and then I was able to- to- to- to solve the equation.
I found this transformation while visiting my aunt in Australia
and I was trying to understand the dynamics of all these fields
and I- I couldn't do it with pen and paper
um, and I hadn't non-officialated computers to- to do any computer simulations.
So I ended up closing my eyes, being on- on the floor
and just imagining myself to actually be this vector field
and rolling around to try to- to see how to change coordinates in such a way that somehow things in all directions would behave in a reasonably linear fashion.
And, uh, yeah, my aunt walked in on- on me while I was doing that
and she was asking what did I- why am I doing- doing this.
Um- It's complicated is the answer.
Yeah, yeah.
And, you know, she went, "Okay
fine.
You know, you're a young man.
I don't ask questions.
" I- I- I have to ask about the
you know, um, how do you approach solving difficult problems?
What.
..
If it's possible to go inside your mind when you're thinking
are you visualizing in your mind the mathematical objects
symbols maybe?
What are you visualizing in your mind usually when you're thinking?
Um, a lot of pen and paper.
One thing you pick up as a mathematician is sort of
uh, I call it cheating strategically.
Um, so, uh, the- the beauty of mathematics is that- is that you get to change the ru- change the problem
change the rules as you wish, uh
because you don't get to do this for any other field.
Like, you know, if- if you're an engineer and someone says
"Build a bridge over this- this river," you can't say
"I want to build this- a bridge over here instead
" or, "I want to build it out of paper in- instead of steel.
" Um, but a mathematician, you can- you can do whatever you want.
Um, it's- it's like trying to solve a computer game where you can.
..
there's unlimited cheat codes available, uh, and so
you know, you- you can- you can set this.
..
uh, so I.
there's a dimension that's too large, I'll set it to one.
I'll solve the one-dimensional problem first.
Or there's a main term and an error term
I'm gonna make a spherical cow assumption, I- I'll assume the error term is zero.
And so the way you should solve these problems is- is not in sort of this Iron Man mode where you make things maximally difficult
um, but actually, uh, the way you should- you should approach
um, uh, any reasonable math problem is that you.
..
if- if there- if there are 10 things that are making your life difficult
find a version of the problem that turns off nine of the difficulties
but only keeps one of them, um
and solve that.
Um, and then that just figures.
..
so you- you- you install nine cheats.
Okay, if you install 10 cheats, then- then the game is trivial
but you install nine cheats, you solve one problem
that- that- that- that- that teaches you how to deal with that particular difficulty.
And then you turn that one off, and you turn someone else- something else on
and then you solve that one.
And after you- you know how to solve the 10 problems- 10 difficulties separately
then you have to start merging them a- a few at a time.
Um, I- I.
..
as a kid, I watched a lot of these Hong Kong action movies.
Um, you know, it's s- it's part of my culture.
Um, and, uh, one thing is that every time it's a fight scene
you know, so maybe the- the hero gets swarmed by 100.
..
. bad guy, goons, whatever.
But it would always be choreographed so that he'd only be
only fighting one person at a time, and then he would defeat that person and move on.
And, and because of that, he could
he could defeat all of them.
Right?
But whereas if they had fought a bit more intelligently and just swarmed the guy all at once
uh, it would make for much, uh
much worse choreo- um, cinema, but, uh
but they would win.
Are you usually, uh, pen and paper?
Are you working, uh, with computer latex?
I'm mostly pen and paper actually.
So in, in my office I have four giant blackboards.
Um, and sometimes I just have to write everything I know about the problem on the four blackboards and then sit on my couch and just sort of see the whole thing.
Is it all symbols like notation or is there some drawings?
Oh, there's a lot of drawing and a lot of bespoke doodles that
that only make sense to me.
Um, I mean, and, and that's the beauty of blackboard is you can erase and it's
it's, it's very organic thing.
Um, I'm beginning to use more and more computers.
Um, partly because AI makes it much easier to do simple coding things that
you know, if I wanted to plot a function before
which is moderately complicated as some iteration or something
you know, I'd had to, to remember how to set up a Python program and
and, and, and, and how does a full loop work and
and debug it and it would've taken two hours and so forth.
And, and now I can do it in 10
15 minutes as, as much.
Um, yeah, I'm, I'm using more and more
uh, computers to do simple ex- uh
explorations.
Let's talk about AI a l- a little bit if we could.
So, um, maybe a good entry point is just talking about computer assisted proofs in general.
Can you describe the lean formal proof programming language and how it can help as a proof assistant and maybe how you started using it and how
uh, it has helped you?
So, um, Lean is a computer language
um, much like sort of standard languages like Python and C and so forth
except that in most languages the focus is on producing executable code.
Lines of code do things, you know
they, they flip bits or, or they make a robot move or
or they, they deliver you text on the internet or something.
Um, so Lean is a language that can also do that.
Uh, it can also be run as a standard
uh, traditional language, but it can also produce certificates.
So a software language like, like Python might do a computation and give you the answer as seven.
Okay.
Does the sum of three plus four is equal to seven.
But, uh, Lean can produce not just the answer
but, but a proof that, uh, how it got the
the answer of seven as three plus four
a-a-and all the steps involved in, in
in, in, um.
..
so it, so it creates these more complicated objects
not just statements, but statements with proofs attached to them.
Um, and, um, every line of code is just a way of pre- piecing together previous statements to
to create new ones.
So the idea is not new.
These things are ca- are called proof assistants.
And so they provide languages for which you c- you can create quite complicated
um, intricate mathematical proofs and, um, they produce these certificates that
that give a 100%, um, guarantee that your arguments are correct if you trust the compiler of Lean.
But they made the compiler really small and you can.
..
there are several different compilers available for the same
like Can you give people some intuition about the
the difference between writing on pen and paper versus using Lean programming language?
How hard is it to formalize- Right.
.
..
a statement?
So Lean, a lot of mathematicians were involved in the design of Lean.
So it's, it's designed so that, um
individual lines of code resemble individual lines of mathematical argument.
Like you might want to introduce a variable
you might want to proof by contradiction, you
you're, um.
..
There are various standard things that you can do and
and it's, it's written so that ideally it should be like a one-to-one correspondence.
In practice, it isn't because Lean is like explaining a proof to an extremely pedantic colleague who will-  .
..
will point out, "Okay, did you really mean this?
Like what, what happens if this is zero?
Okay.
Um, did you.
..
how do you justify this?
" Um, so Lean has a lot of automation in it
um, to try to, to, uh
to be less annoying.
Um, so for example, um, every mathematical object has to come with a type.
Like if I, if I, I talk about X
is X a real number or, um
a, a, a natural number or, or a function or something?
Um, if, if you write things informally
um, it's often in terms of context.
You say, you know, um, "Clearly X is equal to.
..
uh, let X be the sum of Y and Z
and Y and Z were already real numbers.
So X should also be a real number.
" Um, so Lean can do a lot of that.
Um, but every so often it, it says
"Wait a minute.
Can you tell me more about what this object is
uh, what type of object it is?
" You see?
You have to think more, um, at a philosophical level about not just sort of computations that you're doing
but sort of what each object actually, um
is in some sense.
Is it using something like LMS to do
uh, the type inference or like you mentioned with the real number?
It's, it's using much more traditional, what's called good old fashioned AI.
You can represent all these things as trees and there's always algorithm to ma- match one tree to another tree.
So it's actually doable to figure out if something is a
a real number or- Yeah.
.
..
a natural number?
Yeah.
Every object sort of comes with a history of where it came from and you can
you can kind of trace- Oh, I see.
Okay.
Um, yeah.
So it's, it's, it's designed for reliability.
So, uh, modern AIs are not used in.
..
it's a disjoint technology.
People are beginning to use AIs on top of Lean.
So when a mathematician tries to program, um
a proof in, in Lean, um, often there's a step
"Okay, now I want to use, um
the fundamental theorem calculus to say, okay
to do the next step.
" So the Lean developers have built this
this massive project called MathLib, a collection of tens of thousands of useful facts about mathematical objects.
And somewhere in there is the fundamental theorem calculus
but you need to find it.
So a lot of the bottleneck now is actually Lemma search.
You know, there's a tool that, that
you know, is in there somewhere and you need to find it.
Um, and so you can.
..
there are various search engines specialized for MathLib that you can do.
Um, but there's now these large language models that you can say
"Look, um, I need the fundamental calculus at this point
" and it's like, okay, uh, um
for example, when I code I have GitHub Copilot installed as a plug-in to my IDE and it scans my text and it sees what I need.
It says, you know.
..
I might even type, "Okay, now I need to use the fundamental theorem calculus.
" Okay.
And then it, it might suggest, "Okay
try this," and like maybe 25% of the time it works exactly.
And then another-.
..
10, 50% of the time it doesn't quite work but
it- it's close enough that I can say
"Oh yeah, if I just change it here and here
it will, it will work.
" And then like half the time it gives me complete rubbish.
Um, so but people are beginning to use AIs a little bit on top.
Um, uh, mostly on the level of fancy auto-complete.
Um, that, uh, you can type half or one line of a proof and it will find
it will tell you- Yeah.
But what a fancy, especially Fancy with a sort of capital letter effort has
uh, uh, removed some of the friction- Yeah.
.
..
a mathematician might feel when they move from pen and paper to formalizing.
Yes, yeah.
So right now I estimate that the effort
time and effort taken to formalize a proof is about 10 times the amount taken to
to write it out.
Yeah, so it's doable but, uh, you don't.
..
It's, it's annoying.
But doesn't it like kill the whole vibe of being a mathematician- Yeah.
Just- So I mean- .
..
having a pedantic co-worker?
Right, yeah.
If, if that was the only aspect of it
okay.
But, um, okay, there, there are some
there, there are some cases where it's actually more pleasant to do things formally.
So th- there was, there was a theorem I formalized and there was a certain constant 12
um, that, that came up, uh
at, um, in, in the final statement and so this 12 had to be carried all through the proof
um, and like everything had to checked.
They'd, it goes, uh, all the
there are all these other numbers that had to be consistent with this final number 12.
And then, so we wrote a paper between this theorem with this number 12 and then a few weeks later
someone said, "Oh, we can actually improve this 12 to an 11 by reworking s- some of these steps.
" And when this happens with pen and paper
um, like every time you change a parameter
you have to check line by line that every single line of your proof still works
and there can be subtle things that you didn't quite realize.
Some properties on number 12 that you didn't even realize that you were taking advantage of.
So a proof can break down at a subtle place.
Um, so we had formalized the proof with this constant 12 and then when this
this new paper came out, uh, we said
"Okay.
Let's.
..
" Uh, so that took like three weeks to formalize
uh, and, and like 20 people to formalize this
this, this original proof.
So, oh, but n- now let's, let's
um, uh, uh, let's update the 12 to 11 and what you can do with Lean is that you just
in your headline theorem, you, you change your 12 to an 11
you run the compiler, and like of the thousands of lines of code you have
90% of them still work and there's a couple that are lined in red.
Now I can't justify these, these steps but it immediately isolates which steps you need to change.
But you can skip over everything which, which works just fine.
Um, and if you program things correctly
um, with good programming practices, most of your lines will not be red
um, and there'll just be a few places where you.
..
I mean, if, if you don't hard code your constants but you sort of
uh- Mm-hmm.
.
..
um, um, y- you use smart tactics and so forth
yeah, y- you can localize, um, the things you need to change to
to a, a very small, um, period of time.
So it's like within a day or two
we had updated our proof to have.
..
'Cause this is a very quick process, you know.
Um, you make a change, there are 10 things now that don't work.
For each one, you make a change
another five more things that don't work but
but the process converges much more smoothly than with pen and paper.
So that's for writing.
Are you able to read it?
Like if somebody else sends a proof, are you able to like.
..
How, what's, what's the, uh, versus paper and- Yeah.
So the proofs are longer but each individual piece is easier to read.
So, um, if you take a math paper and you jump to page 27 and you look at paragraph six and y- you have a line of text of math
I often can't read it immediately because it
it assumes various definitions which I have to
to go back and, and maybe on ten pages earlier this was defined and there's the
um, the proof is scattered all over the place and you basically are forced to read fairly sequentially.
Um, it's, it's not like say a novel where like
you know, in a theory you could
you know, open up a novel halfway through and start reading.
There's a lot of context.
But with Lean, if you put your cursor on a line of code
every single object there, you can hover over it and it would
it would say what it is, where it came from
wh- whether something's justified.
You can trace things back much easier than sort of flipping through a math paper.
So one thing that Lean really enables is actually collaborating on proofs at a really atomic scale that you really couldn't do in the past.
So traditionally with pen and paper, um
when you want to collaborate with another mathematician
um, either you do it at a blackboard where you
um, you can really interact, but if you're doing it sort of by email or something
um, basically, yeah, you have to segment it.
Say I'm gonna, I'm gonna finish section three
you do section four but, uh, you can't really sort of work on the same thing
uh, collaboratively at the same time.
But with Lean, you can be trying to formalize some portion of the proof and say
"Oh, I got stuck at line 67 here
I need to prove this thing but it
it doesn't quite work.
Here's the, like the three lines of code I'm having trouble with.
" Um, but because all the context is there
someone else can say, "Oh, okay, I recognize what you need to do.
You need to, to do, to apply this trick or this tool
" and you can do extremely atomic level conversations.
So because of Lean, I can collaborate
you know, with dozens of people across the world
most of whom I don't.
..
have never met in person, um, and I'm.
may not know actually even whether they're.
..
um, how reliable they are in, in
in their, um, um, in, in the proof they give me.
But Lean gives me a certificate of, of trust
um, so I can do, I can do trustless mathematics.
So there's so many interesting questions.
There's.
..
So, so one, you're, you're known for being a great collaborator.
So what is the right way to approach solving a difficult problem in mathematics when you're collaborating?
Are you doing a divide and conquer type of thing or are you brain s-.
..
Are you focusing on a particular part and you're brainstorming?
There's always a brainstorming process first, yeah.
So math research projects sort of by their nature
when you start, you don't really know how to do the problem.
Um, it's not like an engineering project where some other theory has been established for decades and it's
it's implementation is the main difficulty.
You have to figure out even what is the right path.
Uh, so, so this is what I said about
about cheating first, you know.
Um, it's like, um.
..
To go back to the bridge building analogy
you know, so first assume you have infinite budget and
and like unlimited amounts of, of, of workforce and so forth.
Now can you, can you build this bridge?
Okay, okay.
Now have infinite budget but only finite workforce
right?
Now can you do that and so forth?
Um, so, uh, I mean, of course
you know, no engineer can actually do this 'cause they have fixed requirements.
Yes, there's these sort of jam sessions always at the beginning where you try all kinds of crazy things and you
you make all these assumptions that are unrealistic but you plan to fix later
um, and you try to see if there's even some-.
..
skeleton of an approach that might work.
Um, and then hopefully that breaks up the problem into smaller sub-problems
which you don't know how to do but then you f- uh
you focus on, on the sub-ones.
Uh, and sometimes different collaborators are better at
at working on, on certain things.
Um, so one of my theorems I'm known for is a theorem with Ben Green we sampled
the Green-Tao Theorem.
Um, it's a statement that the primes contain arithmetic progressions of any length.
So it, it was a modification of this theorem with Szemerédi.
And the way we collaborated was that Ben had already proven a similar result for progressions of length three.
Um, he showed that sets like the primes contain lots and lots of progressions of length three
um, even, and even, um, subsets of the primes.
So the subsets do.
Um, but his techniques only worked for
um, for the three progressions.
They didn't work for longer progressions.
Um, but I had these techniques coming from ergodic theory
which is something that I had been playing with and
and, uh, and I knew better than Ben at the time.
Um, and so, um, if I could justify certain randomness properties of se- some set relating of the primes
right?
There's, there's a certain technical condition which if I could have it
if, if Ben could supply me this
this fact, I could give, I could conclude the theorem.
But I.
..
what I asked was a really difficult question in number theory
which, um, he said, "No, there's no way we can prove this.
" "Can you.
..
" So he said, "Can you prove your part of the theorem using a weaker hypothesis that I have a chance to prove it?
" And he proposed something which he could prove
but it was too weak for me.
Yeah.
Uh, I- I can't use this.
Um, so there's this, there was this conversation going back and forth.
Um, so, so different cheats too.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I wanted to cheat more and he wants to cheat less.
Yeah.
Uh, but eventually we found a, a
a, a, a, a property which A
he could prove, uh, and B, I could use.
Um, and then we, we could prove our theorem and.
..
Um, yeah, so there's, there's a
there are all kinds of dynamics, you know.
I mean, it's, it's, it's every
every, um, collaboration has its, has its- Mm-hmm.
.
has some story.
It's.
..
no two are the same.
And then on, on the flip side of that
like you mentioned, with Lean programming- Mm-hmm.
.
..
now that's a- almost like a different story because you can do.
you can create I think you've mentioned a kind of a blueprint- Mm-hmm.
Right.
.
..
for a problem.
And then you can really do a divide-and-conquer- Yeah.
.
..
with Lean, where you're working on separate parts- Right.
.
..
and, uh, using the computer system proof checker essentially- Yeah.
.
..
to make sure that everything is correct along the way.
Yeah.
So it makes everything compatible and, uh
yeah.
A- and trustable.
Um, yeah, so currently, uh, only a few mathematical projects can be cut up in this way.
At the current state-of-the-art most of the Lean activity is on formalizing proofs that have already been proven by humans.
Mm-hmm.
A math paper basically is a boop- a blueprint in a sense.
It, it is taking a, a difficult statement
like big theorem, and breaking up into maybe a- a hundred little lemmas.
Um, but often not all written with enough detail that each one can be sort of directly formalized.
A blueprint is like a really pedantically written version of a paper where every step is explained as
uh, as much detail as, as, as possible and tr- trying to make each step kind of self-contained
um, and, or depending on only a very specific number of
of previous statements that have been proven, so that each node of this blueprint graph that gets generated can be tackled independently of
of the others.
And you don't even need to know how the whole thing works.
Um, so it's like a modern supply chain
you know?
Mm-hmm.
Like if you want to create an iPhone or s- or some other complicated object
um, no one person can, can build a
um, s- single object but you get a specialist to
to just.
..
if they're given some widgets from some other company
they can combine them together to form a slightly bigger widget.
I think that's a really exciting possibility because you can have.
..
if you can find problems that could be- Right.
.
..
uh, broken down this way then you could have
you know, thousands of contributors, right?
Yes, yes, yes, yeah.
And this will be completely distributed- So I told you before about the split between theoretical and experimental mathematics
and right now most mathematics is theoretical and only a tiny bit is experimental.
I think the platform that Lean and, and other software tools
uh.
..
so, um, you know, GitHub and things like that
um, allow, uh, they will allow ex- experimental mathematics to be.
..
to scale up, um, to a much greater degree than we can do now.
So right now if you want to, um
um, do any mathematical exploration, uh, of some mathematical p- pattern or something
you need some code to write out the pattern and.
..
I mean, sometimes there are some computer algebra packages that could help but often it's just one mathematician coding lots and lots of Python or whatever.
And because coding is such an error-prone activity
it's not practical to allow other people to collaborate with you on writing the modules for your code because if one of the modules has a bug in it
the whole thing's- is un- unreliable.
Um, so it's.
..
these are, uh.
so you get these bespoke, uh, spaghetti code written by non-.
..
not professional programmers but by mathematicians, you know
and they're clunky and, and, and slow and
um.
..
and so because of that it's, it's
it's hard to, to really mass produce experimental results.
Um, but, um, yeah, but I think with Lean
I mean, so I'm already starting some projects where we are not just experimenting with data but experimenting with proofs.
So I have this project called the Equational Theories Project.
Basically, we generated about 22 million little problems in abstract algebra.
Maybe I should back up and tell you what
what the project is.
Okay, so abstract algebra studies operations like multiplication and addition and their abstract properties.
Okay?
So multiplication for example is commutative.
X times Y is always Y times X
at least for numbers.
Um, and, uh, it's also associative.
X times Y times Z is the same as X times Y times Z.
Um, so, um, these operations obey some laws that
you know, uh, that, that don't obey others.
For example, X times X is not always equal to X
so that law is- is not always true.
So given any, any operation, it obeys some laws and not others.
Um, and so we generated about 4
000 of these possible laws o- of algebra that certain operations satisfy
and our question is which laws imply which other ones?
Um, so for example does commutativity imply associativity?
And the answer is no because it turns out you can describe an operation which obeys the commutative law but doesn't obey the associative law.
So by producing an example you can, you can show that commutativity does not imply associativity.
But some other laws do imply other laws by substitution and so forth
uh, and you can write down some
some algebraic proof.
So we look at all the pairs between these 4
000 laws, and there's like 22- 22 million of these pairs.
And for each pair we ask, "Does this law imply this la- um
law?
If so, give a, give, uh
give a proof.
If not, give a counter-example.
" Mm-hmm.
Um, so 22 million problems, each one of which you could give to a
like an, an undergraduate algebra student and they had a decent chance of solving the problem.
Although there are a few, of these 22 million
there are like 100 or so that are really quite hard
okay?
But a lot are easy.
And the project was just to, to work out
to determine the entire graph, like, like which ones imply which other ones.
That's an incredible project, by the way.
Such a good idea, such a good test of the very thing we've been talking about on a scale that's remarkable.
Yeah, so it would not have been feasible
you know, I mean the state of the art in the literature was like
you know, 15 equations and sort of how they entire.
..
Uh, that's sort of at the limit of what a human pen and paper can do.
So yeah, so you need to scale that up
so you need a crowd source, but you also need to trust all the
um.
..
Now I, uh, yeah, I mean
uh, no one person can check 22 million of these proofs.
Mm-hmm.
Right?
You, you need it to be computerized
and so it only became possible with, with Lean.
Um, we were hoping to use a lot of AI as well
um, so that the project is almost complete.
Um, so of these 22 million, all but two have been settled.
Um- Wow.
And, uh, well actually, and of those two
uh, we have a pen and paper proof of the two
uh, and we, we're formalizing it.
In fact, I was, uh, this morning I was working on it
finishing it.
Um, so we're almost done on this.
Um, it's, it's- That's incredible.
It's, yeah, uh, uh, fantastic.
How many people were you able to get?
Uh.
..
About 50.
Uh, which in mathematics is, is considered a huge number.
It's a huge number.
Yeah.
That's crazy.
So we're gonna have a paper with 50 authors
uh, and a, a big appendix of who contributed what.
Here's an interesting question, now to maybe speak even more generally about it.
When you have this pool of people, is there a way to
uh, organize the contributions by level of expertise of the people
of the contributors?
Now, okay, uh, I'm asking a lot of pothead questions here
but I, I'm imagining a bunch of humans
and maybe in the future some AIs- Yeah.
Can there be like an Elo rating type of situation where.
..
Like a gamification of this?
The beauty of, of these Lean projects is
is that automatically you get all this data
you know.
So like, like everything's being uploaded to this GitHub
and GitHub tracks who contributed what.
Um, so you could generate statistics from
at, at any, at any later point in time.
You could say, "Oh, this person contributed this many
this many lines of code," or whatever.
I mean, these are very crude metrics.
Um, I would, I would definitely not want this to become like
you know, part of your tenure review or something.
Uh, um, but um, I mean
uh, I think already in, in, in enterprise computing
right, people do use some of these metrics as part of
of the assessment of, of, uh, performance of a
of an employee.
Um, again, this is a direction which is a bit scary for academics to go down.
We, we, we don't like metrics so much.
And yet academics use metrics.
They just use old ones.
Number of papers.
Yeah, uh, yeah.
Uh, it's true, it's true that, uh
I mean, um- It feels like this is a metric
while flawed, is, is going in the
more in the right direction, right?
Yeah.
It's an interesting.
..
At, at least it's a very interesting metric.
Yeah, I think it's interesting to study.
I mean, I think you can, you can do studies of
of whether these are better predictors.
Um, there's this problem called Goodhart's law.
If a statistic is actually used to incentivize performance
it becomes gamed, um, and then it is no longer a useful measure.
Oh, humans, always ga-  Yeah, yeah
no- A- always gaming the systems.
No, I mean, it's, it's, it's rational.
So what we've done for this pr- project is
is self-report.
So, um, there are actually standard categories
um, from the sciences of what types of contributions people give.
So there's, there's, uh, concept and validation and resources and
and, and, and, and coding and so forth.
Um, so we, we, we.
..
There's a standard list of 12 or so categories
um, and we just ask each contributor to.
..
There's a big matrix of all the, of all the authors and all the categories
just to tick the boxes where they think that they contributed.
Um, and just to give a rough idea
you know, like, oh, so you did some coding and
and, uh, and you provided some compute but you didn't do any of the pen and paper verification or whatever.
And I think that, that works out.
Traditionally, mathematicians just order a- alphabetically by surname.
So we don't have this tradition as in the sciences of
you know, lead author and second author and so forth
like, which we're proud of.
You know, we make all the authors equal status
but it doesn't quite scale to this size.
So a decade ago, I was involved in these thi- things called Polymath projects.
It was a crowdsourcing mathematics, but without the Lean component.
So it was limited by you needed a human moderator to actually check that all the contributions coming in were actually valid
um, and this was a huge bottleneck actually.
Um, but still we had projects that were
you know, 10 authors or so.
But we had decided at the time, um
not to try to decide who did what
um, but to have a single pseudonym.
Um, so we created this fictional character called DHJ Polymath in the spirit of Bob Akee.
Bob Akee is this, uh, the pseudonym for
uh, a famous, uh, group of mathematicians in the 20th century.
But, um, and so the paper was auth- authored under pseudonym
so none of us got the author credit.
Um, this actually turned out to be not so great for a couple reasons.
Uh, so, so one is that if you actually wanted to be considered for tenure or whatever
you could not use this paper in your
uh, uh, as your submitted, as your
one of your publications because it wasn't.
..
you didn't have the formal author credit.
Um, um, but the other thing that we've recognized much later is that when people referred to these projects
they naturally refer to the most famous person who was involved in the project.
"Oh, so this was Tim Gow's polymath project
" or, "This was Terence Tao's polymath project
" and not mention the, the other 19 or whatever people that were involved.
Ah, yeah.
So we're trying something different this time round where we have everyone's an author
um, but we will have an a- an appendix with this matrix and we'll see how that works.
I mean, uh, so both pr- projects are incredible
just the fact that you're involved in such huge collaborations.
But I think I saw a talk from Kevin Buzzard about
uh, the Lean programming languages a few years ago and he was saying that
uh, this might be the future of mathematics.
And so it's also exciting that you're embracing
uh, one of the greatest mathematicians i- i- in the world embracing this
uh.
..
. what seems like the paving of the future of mathematics.
Um, so I have to ask you here about the integration of AI into this whole process of Deep Mind's AlphaProof was trained using reinforcement learning on both failed and successful formal lean proofs- Mm-hmm.
.
..
of IMO problems.
Yes, yes, yes.
So this is sort of high-level high school.
Oh, very high level, yes.
Very high level high school of mathematics problems.
What do you think about this system and maybe what is the gap between this system that is able to prove the high school level problems- Right.
.
..
uh, versus graduate level, uh, problems?
Yeah, th- the difficulty in- increases exponentially with the- the number of steps involved in the proof.
It's a combinatorial explosion, right?
So the thing with large language models is
is that they make mistakes and.
..
So if a proof has got 20 steps and your large language model has a 10% failure rate
um, at each step, um, of g- of going in the wrong direction
like, uh, it's- it's- it's extremely unlikely to actually
uh, reach the end.
Actually, uh, just to take a small tangent here
is, how hard is the problem of mapping from natural language to the formal program?
Oh, yeah.
It's extremely hard, actually.
Um, natural language, you know, it's very fault tolerant.
Um, like you can make a few minor grammatical errors and a speaker in a second language can get some idea of what you're saying.
Um, yeah, but, but formal language
yeah, you know, if- if you get one little thing wrong
um, I think that the whole thing is- is- is nonsense.
Got it.
Um, even formal to formal is- is- is very hard.
There, there are different incompatible, um, uh
proof assistant languages.
Uh, there's Lean but also Coq and Isabelle and- and so forth.
And I keep.
..
Even converting from a formal language to an informal language
um, is, uh, is an unsolved
basically unsolvable problem.
That is fascinating.
Okay, so, uh, but once you have an informal language
they're using, um, their RL-trained model, so some- something akin to AlphaZero that they use in Go- Yes.
.
..
to then try to come up with proofs.
They also have a model, I believe it's a separate model for geometric problems.
Yes.
So what impresses you about this system and
um, what do you think is the gap?
Yeah.
We talked earlier about things that are amazing over time become kind of normalized.
Um, so, yeah, now somehow it's
oh, of course geometry is a solvable problem.
Right.
That's true.
I mean, it's still beautiful, the- the work they're doing.
Yeah, yeah, no, uh, it- it's- it's a great work because it shows what's possible.
I mean, um, it's, it.
..
Um, the approach doesn't scale currently.
Yeah.
Three days of Google's server as server time to solve one
uh, high school math problem there.
This- this is not a scalable, uh
prospect, um, especially with the exponential increase in
um.
..
as- as the complexity, um, increases.
We should mention that they got a silver medal performance.
The equivalent of.
I mean, yeah- Equivalent of a silver medal performance.
.
..
I mean, they.
So first of all, they took way more time than was
uh- Mm-hmm.
.
..
alloted.
Um, and they had this assistance with- where the humans started helped by- by formalizing.
Um, but, uh, also they- they gave them those full marks for the solution which I guess is formally verified
so I guess that's- that's- that's fair.
Um, yeah.
Um, there- there are efforts.
..
There was.
There will be a proposal at some point to actually have an- an AI Math Olympiad where at the same time as the human contestants get the- the actual olympiad
um, problems, AIs will also be given the same problems
the same time period, um, and the outputs will have to be graded by the same judges.
Um, um, and.
..
Which means it will have to be written in natural language rather than formal language.
Oh, I hope that happens.
Yeah.
I hope that this IMO it happens.
I hope, I hope next one.
It's.
..
It won't happen this IMO.
The performance is not good enough in- in the time period and- and
uh, um.
..
But there are smaller competitions, uh.
There are competitions where the- the answer is a- is a number rather than a- a long form proof.
Um, and that's- that's.
..
Um, AI is actually a lot better at
um, problems where there's a specific numerical answer
um, because it's- it's- it's easy to- to- to- uh
to reinforce, do reinforcement learning on it.
Yeah, you got the right answer, you got the wrong answer.
Uh, it's- it's- it's a very clear signal.
But a long form proof either has to be formal and then you.
..
Uh, the Lean can give it thumbs up/thumbs down
or it's informal, um, but then you need a human to grade it- Mm-hmm.
.
to tell.
..
Uh, and if you're trying to do billions of- of reinforcement learning
um, you know, um, um, runs
you're not.
..
you can't hire enough humans to, uh
to grade those.
Um, I mean, it's already hard enough for- for the large language models to do reinforcement learning on- on just the- the regular text that- that people get.
But now if you actually hire people not just to give thumbs up/thumbs down but actually check the- the output mathematically
yeah, uh, that's too expensive.
So if we, uh, just explore this possible future
what- what- what is the thing that humans do that's most special in
um, in mathematics so.
..
That you could see AI, uh, not cracking for a while?
So i- inventing new theories?
So coming up with new conjectures versus, uh
proving the conjectures?
Right.
Building new abstractions?
New representations?
Maybe, uh, in AI Terrence style with
uh, seeing new connections between disparate fields?
It's a good question.
Um, I- I think the nature of what mathematicians do over time has changed a lot.
Um, you know, um, so 1
000 years ago, mathematicians had to compute the date of Easter
uh, and there was really complicated, uh
calculations, you know, but it's all automated
been automated for centuries.
Uh, we don't need that anymore.
You know, they used to navigate, to do spherical navigation
spherical trigonometry, to navigate how to get from-from
um, the old world to the new or something
uh, very complicated calculations, again, been automated.
Um, you know, even a lot of undergraduate mathematics
even before AI, um, like Wolfram|Alpha for example
uh, is- is not a language model but it can solve a lot of undergraduate level math tasks.
So on the computational side, verifying routine things like having a- a problem and
um, and say, "Here's a problem in partial differential equations.
Could you solve it using any of the 20 standard techniques?
" Um, and- Mm-hmm.
.
they are.
..
Yes, I've tried all 20 and here are the 100 different permutations and- and here's my results.
Um, and th- that type of thing I think will work very well.
Um, type of scaling to once you solve one-.
..
problem to, to a- make the AI attack a hundred adjacent problems.
Um, the things that humans do still
uh, is also where the AI really struggles right now
um, is knowing when it's made a wrong turn
um, that it can say, "Oh, I'm gonna solve this problem.
I'm gonna split up this one into, um
into these two cases.
I'm gonna try this technique.
" And, um, sometimes if you're lucky and it- it's a simple problem
it's the right technique and you solve the problem and sometimes it will
it will get.
..
it will have a prob- it would, it would propose an approach which is just complete nonsense.
Um, and but, like, it looks like a proof.
Um, so this is one annoying thing about LLM-generated mathematics.
S- so, um- Yeah.
.
..
we, we've, we've had human-generated mathematics that's very low quality
um, uh, like, you know, su- submissions maybe who don't have the formal training and so forth.
But if a human proof is bad, you can tell it's bad pretty quickly.
Mm-hmm.
It makes really basic mistakes.
But the AI-generated proofs, they can look superficially flawless- Yeah.
.
uh, and it's partly because that's what the reinforcement learning has actually trained them to do
uh, to, to make things.
..
to, to produce text that looks like c- um
uh, what is correct, which for many applications is good enough.
Um, uh, so the errors are often really subtle and then when you spot them
they- they're really stupid.
Um, like, you know, they.
..
like, no human would have actually made that mistake.
Yeah, it's actually really frustrating in the programming context because I
I program a lot and- Mm-hmm.
Yeah, when a human makes.
..
when a low-quality code, there's something called code smell
right?
Mm-hmm.
Yes.
Yeah.
You can tell.
You can tell immediately like, "Okay, there's signs.
" Right.
Yeah, yeah.
But with, with AI-generated code- Odorous.
.
..
and then you're right- Yeah.
.
..
eventually you find an obvious dumb thing that just looks- Yeah.
.
..
like good code.
Yeah.
So, um- It's very tricky to.
..
and frustrating for some reason to- Yeah.
So- .
..
have to work.
Yeah, so the sense of smell.
Yes, yes.
This, this is, this is one thing that humans have
um, and it, it, there's a metaphor called mathematical smell that- Yeah.
.
..
uh, there's.
we.
..
it's not clear how to get the AIs to duplicate that.
Eventually, um, I mean so the, the
the way, um, AlphaZero and so forth that make progress on Go and
and chess and so forth is, is in some sense they have developed a sense of smell for Go and chess positions- Mm-hmm.
.
..
that, that this position is good for white
this good for black.
Um, they can't enunciate why, um, but just having that
that sense of smell lets them strategize.
So if AIs gain that ability to sort of assess the viability of certain proof strategies
so, so you can say, "I'm going to try to
to break up this problem into two small sub-tasks" and they can say
"Oh, this looks good.
The, the two tasks look like they're simpler tasks than
than your main task and they still got a good chance of being true
um, so this is good to try
" or, "No, you've, you've, you made the problem worse because each of the two sub-problems is actually harder than your original problem
" which is actually what normally happens if you try a random
uh, thing to try.
Normally you actually.
..
it's very easy to transform a problem into an even harder problem.
Mm-hmm.
Very rarely do you problem.
..
transform to a simpler problem.
Um, yeah, so if they can pick up a sense of smell
then they could maybe start competing with, uh
uh, human-level mathematicians.
So, so this is a hard question
but not competing but collaborating.
Yeah.
If.
..
okay, hypothetical.
If I gave you an oracle that was able to do some aspect of what you do and you could just collaborate with it- Yeah
yeah, yeah.
.
..
what would that oracle.
what would you like that oracle to be able to do?
Would you like it to, uh, maybe be a verifier
like check- Mm-hmm.
.
..
do the code sme- like your.
yes, uh, Professor Tsao, this is the correct.
..
this is a good.
this is a p- promising fruitful direction- Yeah
yeah, yeah.
Or, or would you like it to
uh, generate possible proofs and then you see which one is the right one- Mm-hmm.
Um, or would you like it to maybe generate different representation
different.
..
totally different ways of seeing this problem?
Yeah.
I think all of the above.
Um, a l- a lot of it is we don't know how to use these tools because it
it's a paradigm that i- is not.
..
um, yeah, we have not had in the past assistants that are competent enough to understand complex instructions- Mm-hmm.
.
..
um, that can work at massive scale but are also unreliable.
Uh, like it's, it's an interesting
uh, a b- bit unreliable in subtle ways whilst we.
..
whilst providing s- sufficiently good output.
Um, it's a interesting combination.
Um, you know, I mean, you have r- you have
like, graduate students who you work with who are kind of like this but n- not as scaled.
Um, you know, and, and, and with previous software tools that
um, can work at scale but, but very narrow.
Um, so we have to figure out how to
how to use, um.
..
I mean, um, so Tim Kao, actually you mentioned
he actually f- foresaw like in, in 2000 he was envisioning what mathematics would look like in
in actually two and a half decades.
That's funny.
And, yeah, he, he wrote in his.
..
in, in his article, uh, like a
a, a hypothetical conversation between a mathematical assistant of the future
um, and himself, you know, trying to solve a problem and they would have
have a conversation that sometimes the human would
would propose an idea and the AI would
would evaluate it and sometimes the AI would propose an idea
um, and, uh, and sometimes a competition was required and the AI would just go and say
"Okay, I've, I've checked the, the 100 cases needed here.
" Or, um, uh, "The first, uh
uh.
..
you, you said this is true for all and I've checked up to 100
um, and it looks good so far.
" Or, "Hang on, there's a problem at N equals 46.
" And so just a freeform conversation where you don't know in advance where things are going to go but just based on
on I think ideas are good proposed on both sides
calculations are good proposed on both sides.
I've had conversations with AI where I say
"Okay, let's.
..
we're going to collaborate to, to solve this math problem
" and it's a problem that I already k- know the solution to
so I, I try to prompt it
"Okay, so here's the problem.
I, I suggest using this tool.
" And then it'll find this, this lovely argument using a completely different tool e- which eventually goes
you know, into the weeds and say
"No, no, no, try using this.
" Okay, and it might start using this and then it'll go back to the
the tool that it wanted to, to
to do before.
Um, and, like, you have to keep railroading it
um, onto the path you want and I
I could eventually force it-.
..
to get the proof I wanted.
Um, but it was like herding cats
um, like and the amount of personal effort I had to take to
not just to prompt it, but also check its output
because it, like a lot of what it looked like it was going to work
and I know there's a problem on line 17.
And I, basically arguing with it
um, like it was more exhausting than doing it unassisted.
So like it.
..
But that's the current state of the art.
I wonder if there's, there's a phase shift that happens to where it no longer feels like herding cats and m- maybe it'll surprise us how quickly that comes
you know?
I, I, I believe so.
Um, so in formalization, like I mentioned before
that it takes ten times longer to formalize a proof than to write it by hand.
With these modern AI tools, it's, uh
and also just better tooling, it's, um
the Lean, um, um, developers are doing a great job adding more and more features and making it user-friendly.
Uh, it's going from nine to eight to seven
okay, no big deal.
But one day it will drop below one
um, and that's a phase shift because suddenly
um, it makes sense when you write a paper
to, to write it in Lean first
uh, or through a conversation with AI who's generating Lean
um, on the fly with you.
And it becomes natural for journals to accept
uh, maybe they'll offer expedite refereeing, you know
like if, if a paper has already been formalized in
in, in Lean, um, they'll just ask the referee to comment on
on the significance of the results and how it connects to literature
and not worry so much about the correctness
um, because it, that's been certified.
Um, papers are getting longer and longer in mathematics and it gets harder and harder to get good ref- refereeing for
um, the, the really long ones, unless they're really important.
Uh, it, it is actually an issue which.
..
And the formalization is coming at just the right time
for this to be- And easier and easier it gets because of the tooling and all the other factors- Right.
.
then you're going to see much more like Mathlib will grow- Right.
..
potentially exponentially.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's, uh, it's a, it's a virtuous
uh, cycle, okay.
I mean, one phase shift of this type that happened in the past was the adoption of LaTeX.
Mm-hmm.
So, so LaTeX is, is typesetting language that all mathematicians use now.
So in the past people used all kinds of word processors and typewriters and
and whatever.
But at some point, LaTeX became easier to use than all other competitors.
And like people would switch, you know
within a few years, like it was just a dramatic
um, phase shift.
It's a wild out there question, but what
what year, how far away are we from a
uh, AI system being a collaborator on a proof that wins the Fields Medal?
Or that level?
Okay.
Um, well it depends on the level of collaboration
I mean- No, like it deserves to be- Right.
.
to get the Fields Medal, like so half and half .
Okay.
Already, like I c- I can imagine a Fields Medal winning paper having some AI assistance in writing it
you know, uh, just you know, like the autocomplete alone is already.
..
I, I, I use it, like it speeds up my
my own writing.
Um, um, like you know, you
you could have a theorem and you have a proof and the proof has three cases and I
I, I write down the proof of the first case and the autocomplete just suggests
"Oh, now here's how the proof of the second case could work
" and like it was exactly correct, and that was great.
Saved me like five, ten minutes of
uh, of typing.
But in that case the AI system doesn't get the Fields Medal?
No.
Uh.
..
are we talking 20 years, 50 years
100 years?
What do you think?
Okay.
Uh, so I, I gave a prediction in print
it was about 2026 which is now next year.
Um, there will be math collaborations, you know
with AI.
So not Fields Medal winning but, but like actual research level math papers- Like published ideas that are- Yeah.
.
..
in part generated by AI.
Um, maybe not the ideas but at least some of the computations
um, um, the verifications, yeah.
I mean, there, there are- Has that already happened?
It's already happened, yeah.
There, there are, there are problems that were solved
uh, by a complicated process con- conversing with
with AI to propose things and then the human goes and tries it and it
and the contract doesn't work, um, but the
it might pose a different idea, um
it, it's hard to disentangle exactly.
Um, there are certainly math results which could only have been accomplished because there was a math
method, human mathematician and an AI involved.
Um, but it's hard to sort of disentangle credit.
Um, I mean these tools, they, they do not
uh, replicate all the skills needed to do mathematics.
But they can replicate sort of some non-trivial percentage of them
you know, 30, 40%.
So they can fill in gaps, um
you know, so uh, coding is, is
is a good example, you know, so I
I, um, um, it's annoying for me to code in Python and I'm not
I'm not a native, um, I'm not a professional programmer.
Um, but um, the- with AI the fr- the friction cost of doing it is much reduced.
Uh, so it fills in that gap for me.
Um, AI is getting quite good at literature review.
Um, I mean there's still a problem with
um, hallucinating, you know, references that don't exist.
Um, but this I think is a solvable problem.
If you train in the right way and so forth
you can, you can.
..
And um, and verify, um, using the internet.
Um, you should in a few years get to the point where you have a lemma that you need and say
"Has anyone proven this lemma before?
" And it will do basically a fancy web search AI system to say
"Yeah, yeah, there are these six papers where something similar has happened.
" And I mean it will.
..
You can ask it right now and it will give you six papers of which maybe one is legitimate and relevant
one exists but is not relevant, and four are hallucinated.
Um, it has a non-zero success rate right now
but there's so much garbage, so much.
..
The signal to noise ratio is so poor that it's
it's, um.
..
It's most helpful when you already somewhat know the literature
um, and you just need to be prompted to be reminded of a paper that was already subconsciously in your memory.
Versus helping you discover new you were not even aware of what is the correct citation.
Yeah, that's.
..
Yeah, that it can sometimes do but
but when it does it's, it's buried in a list of options which the other- That are bad.
Yeah.
I mean being able to automatically generate a related work section
that is correct- Yeah.
That's actually a beautiful thing, that might be another phase shift because it assigns credit correctly.
Yeah, yeah.
It does, it breaks you out of the silos of- Yeah
yeah, yeah, no- .
..
thought, you know?
Yeah, no but it, it, there's a big hump to overcome right now.
I mean, it's, it's like self-driving cars
you know?
Right.
It, it, the safety margin, it has to be really high- Yeah.
.
for it to be, um, uh, to be feasible.
So yeah, so there's a last mile problem
um, with a lot of AI applications
um, that, uh, you know, they can develop tools that work 20%
80% of the time, but it's still not good enough
um, and in fact even worse than good in some ways.
I mean, another way of asking the field's mental question is what year do you think you'll wake up and be like real surprised?
You read the headline, the news or something happened that AI did
like, you know, real breakthrough, something.
It doesn't, you know, like field's metal or even hypothesis
it could be like really just this AlphaZero moment would go
that kind of thing.
Right, right.
Um, yeah this, uh, this decade I can
I can see it like making a conjecture between two unrelated
two, two things that people thought was unrelated.
Oh, interesting.
Generating a conjecture, that's a beautiful conjecture.
Yeah.
And, and actually has a real chance of being correct and
and meaningful, and, um- Because that's actually kind of doable
I suppose, but where the data is
it's yeah.
Yeah.
Well, it's- No, that would be truly amazing.
Um, the current models struggle a lot.
I mean, so, um, a version of this is
um, I mean the, the physicists have a dream of getting the AIs to discover new
new laws of physics.
Um, uh, you know, they, the dream is you just feed it all this data
okay?
Uh, uh, and, and this is a
here, here is a new patent that we didn't see before.
But it actually even struggle, the current state of the art even struggles to discover old laws of physics
um, from the data.
I mean, uh, or if it does
uh, there's a big concern of contamination that
that it did only because like somewhere in its training data it already somehow knew
um, you know, Boyle's Law or whatever law you
you're trying to, to reconstruct.
Um, part of it's that we don't have the right type of training data for this
um, you know, so for laws of physics like we
we don't have like a million different universes with a million different laws of nature.
Um, and, um, like a lot of what we're missing in math is actually the negative space of.
..
so we have published things of things that people have been able to prove
um, and conjectures that ended up being verified
um, or maybe counter examples produced.
But, um, we don't have data on
on things that were proposed and they're kind of a good thing to try
but then people quickly realized that it was the wrong conjecture and then they
they said, "Oh, but we, we should actually change
um, our claim to modify it in
in this way to actually make it more plausible.
" Um, there's this, there's a trial and error process which is a real integral part of human mathematical discovery
which we don't record because it's, it's embarrassing.
Uh, we make mistakes and, and we only like to publish our
our wins.
Um, and, uh, the AI has no access to this data to tr- train on.
Um, I sometimes joke that basically, you know
AI has to go through, um, um
grad school and actually, you know, go to grad courses
do the assignments, go to office hours
make mistakes, um, get advice on how to correct the mistakes
and learn from that.
Let me, uh, ask you, if I may
about, uh, Grigori Perelman.
Mm-hmm.
You mentioned that you try to be careful in your work and not let a problem completely consume you.
Just, you really fall in love with the problem and it really cannot rest until you solve it.
But you also hasted to add that sometimes this approach actually can be very successful.
Mm-hmm.
An example you gave is Grigori Perelman who proved the Poincaré conjecture and did so by working alone for seven years with basically little contact with the outside world.
Can you explain this one Millennium Prize problem that has been solved
Poincaré conjecture, and maybe speak to the journey that Grigori Perelman's been on?
All right.
So it's, it's a question about curved spaces.
Earth is a good example.
So let's do, let's think of it as a 2D surface.
In just being round, you know, there could maybe
happy a torus with a hole in it or it can have many holes
and there are, there are many different topologies a priori that
that surface could have, even if you assume that it's
it's bounded and, and, uh, and
and smooth and so forth.
So we, we have figured out how to classify surfaces.
As a first approximation, uh, everything's determined by something called the genus
how many holes it has.
So the sphere has ze- genus zero, a donut has genus one
and so forth.
And one way you can tell these surfaces apart
probably the sphere has, which is called simply connected.
If you take any closed loop on the sphere
like a big closed loop rope, you can contract it to a point and while staying on the surface.
And the sphere has this property, but a torus doesn't.
And if you own a torus and you take a rope that goes around
say the, the outer diameter of the torus- Mm-hmm.
.
..
there's no way, it, it can't get through the hole.
There's no way to, to contract it to a point.
So it turns out that the, the sp- sphere is the only surface with this property of contractibility.
I mean up to like continuous deformations of the sphere.
So, um, there's things that are what are called topologically
um, equivalent to the sphere.
So Poincaré asked the same question in higher dimensions.
Um, so this, it becomes hard to visualize
uh, because, um, surface you can think of as embedded in three dimensions
but a, a curved three space, we don't have good intuition of 4D space to
to, to live in.
And then there are also 3D spaces that can't even fit into four dimensions.
You need five or six or s- or higher.
But anyway, uh, mathematically you can still pose this question
that if you have a bounded three dimensional space now
which is also has this simply connected property that every loop can be contracted
can you turn it into a three dimensional version of a sphere?
And so this is the Poincaré conjecture.
Weirdly in higher dimensions, four and five it actually was easier.
So the, uh, it was solved first in higher dimensions.
There's somehow more room to do the deformation.
It, it's easier to, to, to move things around to
to, to be a sphere.
But three was really hard.
So people tried many approaches.
There's sort of combinatorial approaches where you chop up the
the, the surface into little triangles or
or tetrahedra and you, you just try to argue based on how the faces interact each other.
Um-.
..
there were, um, algebraic approaches.
Uh, there's, there's various algebraic objects, uh
like this called the fundamental group that you can attach to these homology and co-homology and
and, and all these very fancy tools.
Um, they also didn't quite work.
Um, but Richard Hamilton proposed a, um
partial differential equations approach.
So you take, um, you take.
..
So the problem is that you.
so you have this object which is so secretly a sphere
but it's given to you in a, in a really
um, in a weird way.
So it's like, like, think of a ball that's been kind of crumpled up and twisted
and it's not obvious that it's a ball.
Um, but, um, like if you
if you have some sort of surface which is
which is a deformed sphere, you could
um, uh, you could.
..
For example, think of it as a surface of a balloon
you could try to inflate it.
You, you blow it up, um, and naturally as you fill it with air
um, the, the wrinkles will sort of smooth out and it will turn into
um, um, a nice round sphere.
Um, yeah, unless of course it was a torus or something in which case it would get stuck at some point
like, if you inflate a torus, it
it would.
..
there, there'd be a point in the middle when the inner ring shrinks to zero
you get a, you get a singularity and you can't blow up any further.
Uh, you can't flow any further.
So he created this flow, which is now called Ricci flow
which is a way of taking a, an arbitrary surface or
or space and smoothing it out to make it rounder and rounder- Mm-hmm.
.
to make it look like a sphere.
And he wanted to show that, that either
uh, this process would give you a sphere or it would create a singularity.
Um, actually very much like how PDEs either have.
..
they have global regularity or finitely blow up.
Like, it, it basically.
..
it's almost exactly, exactly the same thing.
It's all connected.
Um, and so.
..
and, and he showed that for two dimensions
two-dimensional surfaces, um, if you started something like no singularities ever formed
um, you, you never ran into trouble and you could flow and
and it will give you a sphere.
Mm-hmm.
And it.
..
so he, he got a new proof of the two-dimensional result.
Well, by the way, that's a beautiful explanation of Ricci flow and its application in this context.
How difficult is the mathematics here, like
for the 2D case?
Is it- Yeah, these are quite sophisticated equations on par with the Einstein equations of
but slightly simpler, but, um, um.
..
Yeah, but, but they were considered hard nonlinear equations to solve.
Um, and there's lots of special tricks in 2D that
that, that helped.
But in 3D the problem was that, uh
th- this equation was actually super critical.
So this has the same promise as Navier-Stokes.
As you blow up, um, maybe s- the curvature could get concentrated in
in finer and smaller and smaller regions, and it
um, it looked more and more nonlinear and things just looked worse and worse.
And there could be all kinds of singularities that
that showed up.
Um, some singularities, um, like if you.
..
uh, there's these things called neck pinches where
where the, uh, the surface sort of creates a.
..
behaves like a, like a, like a
a barbell and it, it, it pinches at a point.
Some s- some singularities are simple enough that you can still see what to do next
you just make a snip and then you can turn one surface into two and you evolve them separately.
But there was, there was a con- the prospect that there's some really nasty
like, knotted singularities showed up that you
you couldn't see how to, um, resolve in any way
uh, that you couldn't do any surgery to.
Mm-hmm.
Um, so you need to classify all the singularities
like, what are all the possible ways that things can go wrong?
Um, so what Perelman did was.
..
first of all, he, he made the problem.
he turned the problem from a super critical problem to a critical problem.
Um, I said before about how, um
the admission of the o- of energy, the Hamiltonian
like, really clarified, um, Newtonian mechanics.
Um, uh, so he introduced, uh
something which is now called Perelman's reduced volume and Perelman's entropy
um.
..
he introduced new quantities, kind of like energy
that looked the same at every single scale and turned the problem into a cr- critical one where the nonlinearities actually suddenly looked a lot less scary than they did before.
Um, and then he had to solve.
..
he still had to analyze the singularities of this critical problem.
Uh, and that itself was a problem similar to this wave path thing I worked on
actually .
Um, so on the, on the level of difficulty of that.
..
so he managed to classify all the singularities of this problem and show how to apply surgery to each of these
and through that was able to, to resolve the Poincaré conjecture.
So, um, quite.
..
uh, like, a lot of really ambitious steps
um, and like, like nothing that a large language model today
for example, could.
..
I mean, um, at best, uh
I could imagine a, a model proposing this idea as one of hundreds of different things to try.
Um, but the other 99 would be complete dead ends
but you'd only find out after months of
of work.
He must have had some sense that this was the right track to pursue because like
you know, like, it takes years to get from
from A to B.
So you've done, like you said, actually
you see, even strictly mathematically, but more broadly in terms of the process
you've done s- similarly difficult things.
What, what can you infer from the process he was going through because he was doing it alone?
What are some low points in a process like that when you start to
like.
..
you've mentioned hardship, like, uh, AI doesn't know when it's failing.
Yeah.
What, what happens to you, you're sitting in your office
when you realize the thing you did for the last few days
maybe weeks- Yeah.
.
..
is a failure?
Well, for me, I switch to different problems .
Uh, so, uh, as I said
I'm, I'm, I'm a fox, I'm not a hedgehog.
But you legitimately.
..
that is a break that you can take is
is to step away and look at it from a problem.
Yeah, yeah.
You can modify the problem too.
Um, I mean, um, you can add some cheat.
..
uh, if, if there's a specific thing that's blocking you
uh, th- this, um.
..
some bad case keeps showing up that, that
that.
..
for which your tool doesn't work, you can just assume by fiat this
this bad case doesn't occur.
So you, you do some magical thinking
um, for the.
..
uh, but, but strategically, okay?
For the point.
..
to see if the rest of the argument goes through.
Um, if there's multiple problems, uh, with
with, with your approach, then maybe you just give up
okay?
But if this is the only problem
uh, you know, and everything else checks out
you know, then it's still worth fighting.
Um, so yeah, yeah, you have to do some
some sort of forward reconnaissance sometimes to-  .
..
uh, you know- And that is sometimes productive to assume like
"Okay, we'll figure it out-" Oh, yeah
yeah, yeah.
".
..
eventually.
" Um, sometimes actually it's, it's even productive to make mistakes.
So, um, one of the.
..
I mean, um.
there was a project which actually, uh
we won some prizes for  actually, with
uh, with four other people.
Um, we were working on this PDE problem
a- again, actually this blow up regularity type problem
um, and it, it was considered very hard.
Um-.
..
Jean Bourgain, um, uh, who was a
another field specialist who worked on, on a special case of this
but he could not solve the general case.
Um, and we worked on this problem for two months and we found
we thought we solved it.
We, we had this, this cute argument that if everything fit and
and we were excited.
Uh, we were planning a celebration.
We, um, said we'll get together and have champagne or something.
Um, and we started writing it up
um, and one of, one of us
not me actually but another co-author said, "Oh
um, in this, in this lemma here
we s- um, we have to estimate these 13 terms that sh- that show up in this expansion.
" And we estimated 12 of them, but in our notes I can't find the
the estimation of the 13th.
"Can you, can someone supply that?
" And I said, "Sure, I'll look at this.
" And, and actually it's, oh yeah
we didn't cover, we completely omitted this term.
And this term turned out to be worse than the other 12 terms put together.
Um, in fact, we could not estimate this term.
Um, and we tried for a few more months
uh, and all different permutations and there was always this one thing
one term that we could not control.
Um, and so like, um, this was very frustrating.
Um, but because we had already invested months and months of effort into this already
um, we stuck at this.
We, we tried increasingly desperate things and
and crazy things.
Um, and after two years, we found an approach which is actually somewhat different by quite a bit from our initial
um, strategy, which did actually, didn't generate these problematic terms and
and, and actually solved the problem.
So we, we solved the pr- problem after two years.
But if we hadn't had that initial full storm of nearly solving the problem
we would have given up by month two or something
and, and worked on an easier problem.
Um, yeah, if we had known it would take two years
not sure we would've started the project.
You know, sometimes actually having the incorrect.
..
you know, it's, it's like Columbus traveling to the New Y- New World.
He had an in- incorrect version of, uh
measurement of the, uh, size of the earth
um, and he thought he was going to find a n- new trade route to India.
Uh, or at least that was how he s- sold it in his prospectus.
I mean, it c- it could be that he actually secretly knew
but.
..
Just on the psychological element, do you have
like, emotional or, like, self-doubt that just overwhelms you
moments like that?
You know, 'cause it, th- this stuff
it feels like math, it's so engrossing that
like, it can break you.
When you, like, invest so much of yourself in the problem and then it turns out wrong
you could start to.
..
similar way chess has broken some people.
Yeah.
Um, I, I think different mathematicians have different levels of emotional investment in what they do.
I mean, I think for some people it's just a job.
You know, you, you have a problem and if it doesn't work out
you, you work on, you work on the next one.
Um, yeah, so the fact that you can always move on to another problem
um, it reduces the emotional connection.
I mean, there are cases, you know
so there are certain problems that are mathematical diseases where
where, where just latch onto that one problem and they spend years and years thinking about nothing but that one problem
and, and, um, you know, maybe their
their career suffers and so forth, and they say
"Oh, but I've got this big win.
This will, you know, once I, once I finish this
this problem, I will, that will, that will make up for all the years of
of, of, of lost opportunity.
" And th- that's, that's.
..
I mean, occasionally, occasionally it works
but I, I, um, I really don't recommend it for people without the
the right fortitude.
Yeah, so I, I've never been super invested in any one problem.
Um, one thing that helps is that we don't need to call our problems in advance.
Uh, um, well, uh, when we do grant proposals
uh, we sort of say, "We will
we will study this set of problems.
" But even though we don't promise, "Definitely by five years I will supply a proof of all these things
" you know.
We, um, you promise to make some progress or discover some interesting phenomena
uh, and maybe you don't solve the problem but you find some related problem that you
you can say something new about.
Uh, and that's, that's a much more feasible task.
But I'm sure for you there's problems like this.
You have, you have, um, made so much progress towards the hardest problems in the history of mathematics.
So is there, is there a problem that just haunts you
it sits there in the dark corners, you know
twin prime conjecture, Riemann hypothesis, Goldbach conjecture?
Twin prime, that sounds.
..
Well, again, so I mean, the problems like the Riemann hypothesis
those are so far out of reach.
Uh, I, I- Oh, you think so?
Yeah.
There, there's no even viable strategy.
Like, even if I activate all my
all the cheats that I know of-  .
..
um, in this problem, like it, there's just still no way to get from A to B.
Yeah.
Um, like it's, it's, um, I think it needs a breakthrough in another area of mathematics to happen first
and for someone to recognize that, that that would be a useful thing to transport into this problem.
So we, we should maybe s- step back for a little bit and just talk about prime numbers.
Okay.
So they're often referred to as the atoms of mathematics.
Can you just speak to the structure that these
uh, atoms provide?
So the natural numbers have two basic operations attached to them
addition and m- multiplication.
Um, so if you want to generate the natural numbers
you can do one of two things.
You can just start with one and add one to itself over and over again
and that generates you the natural numbers.
So additively they're very easy to generate, one
two, three, four, five.
Or you can take the prime num-.
..
if you want to generate multiplicatively, you can take all the prime numbers
two, three, five, seven, and multiply them all together.
Um, and together they, they, they get you all the
the, the natural numbers except maybe for one.
So there are these two separate ways of thinking about the natural numbers
from a additive point of view and a mul- multiplicative point of view.
Um, and separately they're not so bad.
Um, so like any question about the natural numbers that only involves addition is relatively easy to solve
and any question that only involves multiplication is relatively easy to solve.
Um, but what has been frustrating is that you combine the two together
um, and suddenly you get an extremely rich.
..
I mean, we know that there are statements in number theory that are actually as
uh, undecidable.
There are certain polynomials in some number of variables
you know, is there a solution in the natural numbers?
And the answer depends on, on an undecidable statement
um, like, like whether, um, the axioms of
of mathematics are consistent or not.
Um, but, um, yeah, but even the s- the simplest problems that combine something multiplicative
such as the primes, with something additive
such as shifting by two, uh, separately we understand both of them well
but if you ask, when you shift a prime by two
do you, can you get a, how often can you get another prime?
We, it's been-.
..
amazingly hard to relate the two.
And we should say that the twin prime conjecture is just that.
It posits that there are infinitely many pairs of prime numbers that differ by two.
Yes.
Now, the interesting thing is that you have been very successful at pushing forward the field in answering these complicated questions
uh, of this variety, like you mentioned
the green tile theorem.
It proves that prime numbers contain arithmetic progressions of any length.
Right.
Which is mind-blowing that you can prove something like that.
Yeah, so what we've realized because of th- this
this type of research is that this.
..
different patterns have different levels of, uh
indestructibility.
Um, so, so what makes the twin prime problem hard is that if you take all the primes in the world
you know, 3, 5, 7, 11
and so forth, there are some twins in there
11 and 13 is a twin prime, pair of twin primes and so forth
but you could easily, if you wanted to
um, redact the primes to get rid of
to get rid of the, um, these twins.
Like, uh, the twins, they show up and there are infinitely many of them
but they're actually reasonably sparse.
Um, not the.
..
there's not.
I mean, initially there's quite a few
but once you go out to the millions
trillions, they become rarer and rarer.
And you could actually just.
..
you know, li- if, if someone was given access to the database of primes
they'd just edit out a few, a few primes here and there.
They could make the twin prime conjecture false by just removing
like, 0.
01% of the primes or something.
Hmm.
Um, just well, well chosen to, to
um, to do this.
And so you could present a censored database of the primes which passes all of the statistical tests of the primes
you know, that it, it obeys things like the prime number theorem and
and other facts about the primes, but doesn't contain any twin primes anymore.
Um, and this is a real obstacle for the twin prime conjecture.
It, it means that any proof strategy to actually find twin primes in the actual primes must fail when applied to these slightly
uh, edited primes.
And so it, it must be some very
um, subtle, delicate feature of the primes that you can't just get from
like, like, aggregate cis- s- s- statistical analysis.
Okay, so that's out.
Yeah.
On the other hand, arithmetic progressions has turned out to be much more robust.
Um, like you can take the primes and you can eliminate 99% of the primes actually
you know, and you can take, take any 99% that you want
and, uh, it turns out.
..
and this is another thing we've proved is that you still get arithmetic progressions.
Um, arithmetic progressions are much.
..
you know, they're like cockroaches.
Of arbitrary length though.
Yes.
That's crazy.
Yeah.
I mean, so, so, uh, for people who don't know
arithmetic progressions is a sequence of numbers that differ by some fixed amount.
Yeah.
But it's, again, like.
..
it's, it's infinite monkey type phenomenon.
For any fixed length of your set, you don't get arbitrary length progressions.
You only get quite short progressions.
But you're saying twin prime is not an infinite monkey phenomena?
Hmm?
No- I mean, it's a very subtle monk-.
..
it's still an infinite monkey phenomena, isn't it?
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
If, if the primes were really genuinely random
if the primes were generated by monkeys, um
then yes, in fact the infinite monkey theorem would- Oh
but you're saying that twin prime is.
..
it doesn't.
you can't use the same tools, like
the.
..
it doesn't appear random almost.
Well, we don't know.
Uh, yeah, we, we, we believe the primes behave like a random set.
And so the reason why we care about the twin prime conjecture is
is it's a test case for whether we can genuinely confidently say with
with 0% chance of error that the primes behave like a random set.
Okay, random.
..
yeah, random versions of the primes we know contain twins.
Um, at least wi- wi- with 100% probability
uh, or probably turning to 100% as you go out further and further.
Um, yeah, so the primes, we believe that they're random.
Um, the reason why arithmetic progressions are indestructible is that regardless of whether your set looks random or looks s- um
structured, like periodic, in both cases, um
arithmetic progressions appear, but for different reasons.
Um, and this is basically all, all the ways in which the thing.
..
uh, there are many proofs of, of these sort of arithmetic progression theorems and they're all proven by some sort of dichotomy where your set is either structured or random and in both cases you can say something and then you put the two together.
Um, but in twin primes, if, if the primes are random then you're happy
you win.
But if your primes are structured, they could be structured in
in a specific way that eliminates the twin
the twins.
Uh, and we can't rule out that one conspiracy.
And yet you're able to make a, as I understand
progress on the k-tuple version.
Right, yeah.
So, um, the one funny thing about conspiracies is that any one conspiracy theory is really hard to disprove.
Uh-huh.
Yeah.
Uh, that, you know, if, if you believe the world is run by lizards
you say here's some evidence that, that it
it's not run by lizards.
Well, that, that evidence was planted by the lizards.
Yeah.
Like, um, you might have encountered
uh, uh, this kind of phenomena.
Yeah.
So, so- Yes.
.
..
like, like, um, a pure.
like there's, there's almost no way to
to, um, definitively rule out a conspiracy.
And the same is true in mathematics, that a conspiracy that is to-.
..
solely devo- devoted to eliminating twin primes, you know
like it would.
..
you'd have to also infiltrate other areas of mathematics to do so.
But, but, like, it could be made consistent
at least as far as we know.
But there's a weird phenomena that you can make one con- um
uh, one conspiracy rule out other conspiracies.
So, you know- Hmm.
.
..
if the world is run by lizards they can't also be run by aliens.
Right, right.
So one unreasonable thing is, is, is
is hard to disprove, but, but more than one
there are, there are tools.
Um, so yeah, so for example we
we know there's infinitely many primes that are
um, uh, no two which are.
..
so they're the only pairs of primes which differ by at most
uh, um, 246 actually is, is
is the current record.
Oh, so there's like a bound- Yes.
.
..
on the.
Right.
So, like, there's twin primes, there's this thing called cousin primes that differ by
by four, um, there's this thing called sexy primes that differ by six.
Uh, what are sexy primes?
Primes that differ by six.
Okay.
The name is much less ex- it's constantly much less exciting than the name suggests.
Got it.
So you can make a conspiracy rule out one of these
but, like, once you have like 50 of them
it turns out that you can't rule out all of them at once.
It just.
..
it requires too much energy somehow in this conspiracy space.
How do you do the bound part?
How do you, how do you develop a bound for the difference between the primes that- Okay
so, um- .
..
that there's an infinite number of?
So it's ultimately based on, uh, what's called the Pitchfork Principle.
Um, so the pigeonhole principle, uh, it's a statement that if you have a number of pigeons and they all have to go into
into pigeonholes, and you have more pigeons than pigeonholes
then one of the pigeonholes has to have at least two pigeons in.
So there has to be two pigeons that are
that are close together.
So for instance, if you have, uh
100 numbers and they all range from one to 1
000, um, two of them have to be at
at most 10 apart.
Mm-hmm.
'Cause y- y- you can divide up the numbers from one to 100 into 100 pigeonholes.
Let's, let's say we have 100, we have 101 numbers.
101 numbers, then two of them have to be
uh, distance less than 10 apart, because two of them have to belong to the same pigeonhole.
So it, it's a basic, um, basic feature of
uh, a basic principle in mathematics.
Um, so it doesn't quite work with the primes regularly
'cause the primes get sparser and sparser as you go out
that, that fewer and fewer numbers are prime.
But it turns out that there's a way to assign weights to the pr- to
to numbers.
Like, um, so there are numbers that are kind of
uh, almost prime, uh, but they're not.
..
they, they don't have no factors at all other than themselves and one
but they have very few factors.
Um, and it turns out that we understand almost primes a lot better than we understand primes.
Um, and so, uh, for example
uh, it was known for a long time that there were twin almost primes
uh, that this has been worked out.
So almost primes are things we, we kind of understand.
So you can actually restrict the attention to a s- a suitable set of almost primes
and, uh, whereas the primes are very sparse overall
uh, relative to the almost primes, they actually are
are much less sparse.
They may, um.
..
You can set up a se- a set of almost primes where the primes are densely like
say, 1%.
Um, and that gives you a shot at proving by applying some sort of pigeonhole principle that
that there's pairs of primes that are distinct only 100
100 apart.
But in order to prove the twin prime conjecture
you need to get the density of primes in something almost always up to
up to a threshold of 50%.
Um, once you get up to 50%
you will get twin primes.
But, uh, unfortunately, there are barriers.
Um, w- we know that, that no matter what kind of good set of almost primes you pick
the density of primes can never get above 50%.
It's called the parity barrier.
Um, and I would love to find.
..
Yeah, so one of my long-term dreams is to find a way to breach that barrier
because it would open up not only the t- twin prime conjecture
but the Goldbach conjecture and many other problems in number theory are currently blocked
because our current techniques would require impro- going beyond this theoretical
um, parity barrier.
It's, it's like, it's like pulling fast at the speed of light.
Yeah.
So we should say twin prime conjecture, one of the biggest problems in the history of mathematics.
Goldbach conjecture also.
Uh, they feel like next door neighbors.
Uh, has there been days when you felt you saw the path?
Oh, yeah.
Um, um.
..
Yeah.
Uh, sometimes you try something and it
it works super well.
Um, you, you again.
..
Again, the sense of mathematical smell, uh
we talked about earlier.
Uh, you learn from experience when things are going too well.
Yeah.
Because there are certain difficulties that you sort of have to encounter.
Um, um, think the way a, a c- colleague might put it is that
um, you know, like, if, if you
uh, on the streets of New York and you're put in a blindfold and you're put in a car and
and, um, after some hours, um
you.
..
the blindfold's off and, and you're in Beijing.
Um, you know, I mean, that was too easy somehow.
Yeah.
Like, like there was no ocean being crossed.
Even if you don't know exactly what Howard.
..
what, what was done, uh, you're suspecting that
that something w- wasn't right.
But is that still in the back of your head to.
..
Do you return to these, to the prime.
Do you return to the prime numbers every once in a while to see?
Yeah, when I have nothing better to do
which is less and less now, 10 times
which is I get busy with so many things these days.
But yeah, when I have free time and I'm not.
..
and I'm too frustrated to, to work on my sort of real research projects
and I also don't want to do my administrative support
I don't want to do some errand for my family
um-  .
..
I can play with these, these things
uh, for fun.
Uh, and usually you get nowhere.
Yeah, yeah, so you have to learn to just say
"Okay, fine.
I.
..
Once again, uh, nothing happened.
I wi- I will move on.
" Um, yeah, very occasionally one of these problems I actually solved.
Uh, uh, well, sometimes as you say
uh, you think you solved it and then you're euphoric for
uh, maybe 15 minutes and then you think
"I should check this 'cause this is too easy
too good to be true.
" And it usually is.
What's your gut say about when these problems would be
uh, solved?
Um.
..
Twin prime and Goldbach prime?
Twin prime, I think we will keep getting- Ten years?
.
..
keep getting more partial results.
Um, uh, it does need at least one.
..
Uh, this parity barrier is, is the biggest remaining obstacle.
Um, there are simpler versions of the conjecture where we are getting really close.
Um, so I think we will.
..
In 10 years, we will have many more much closer results.
We may not have the whole thing.
Um, yeah, so twin primes is somewhat close.
Yeah.
Riemann hypothesis, uh, I have no clue.
I mean, it o- it has to happen by accident I think
uh- So th- the Riemann hypothesis is a kind of more general conjecture about the distribution of prime numbers
right?
Right.
Yeah.
It's, it's, it's states that are sort of viewed multiplicative
like for, for questions only involving multiplication
no addition, the primes really do behave
uh, as randomly as, as you could hope.
So there's a phenomenon in probability called square root cancellation that
um.
..
You know, like if, if you want to poll
say, America, uh, about s- on some issue
um, and you, you ask one or two voters
and you may have sampled a bad sample
and then you get, you get a
a really imprecise, um, measurement of the
of the full average.
But if you sample more and more people
the accuracy gets, gets better and better and it.
..
The accuracy improves like the square root of the number of
of people you, uh, you sample.
So yeah, if you sample, um, 1
000 people, you can get like a two
3% margin of error.
So in the same sense, if you measure the primes in a certain multiplicative sense
there's a certain type of statistic you, you can measure and it's
it's called the Riemann zeta function, and it fluctuates up and down.
But, uh, in some sense, um
as you keep averaging more and more, if you sample more and more
the fluctuations should go down as if they were random.
And there's a very precise way to quantify that
and the Riemann hypothesis is a very elegant way that captures this.
But, um, as with many other ways in mathematics
we have very few tools to show that something really genuinely behaves r- like
really random.
And this is actually not, not just a little bit random
but it's, it's asking that it behaves as random as an actually random set
this, this, this square root cancellation.
..
. and we know actually because of things related to parity problem
actually, that- that most of us usual techniques cannot hope to settle this question.
Um, the proof has to come out of left field.
Um, yeah, but, uh, what that is
you know, no one has any serious proposal.
Um, yeah, and- and there's- there's various ways to sort of
as I said, you- you can modify the primes a little bit
and you can destroy the Riemann- Riemann hypothesis.
Um, so, like, it has to be very delicate.
You can't apply something that has huge margins of error.
It has to just barely work, um
and like, um, there's like all these pits- pitfalls that you have to
like, dodge very adeptly to- The prime numbers is just fascinating.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
What- what to you is, um, most mysterious about the prime numbers?
That's a- that's a good question.
It's also, like, conjecturally we have a good model of them.
I mean, like, as I said, I mean
they have certain patterns.
Like the primes are usually odd, for instance.
But apart from this of obvious patterns, they behave very randomly
and just assuming that they behave.
..
So there's something called the Cramer random model of the primes that- that- that after a certain point
primes just behave like a random set.
Um, and there's various slight modifications to this model
but this has been a very good model.
It matches the numerics.
It tells us what to predict.
Like, I can tell you with complete certainty the Turing complete conjecture is true.
Uh, the random model gives overwhelming odds that it's true.
I just can't prove it.
Most of our mathematics is optimized for solving things with patterns in them
um, and the primes have this anti-pattern
um, as do almost everything really, but we can't prove that.
Yeah, I guess it's not mysterious how the primes be ran- kind of random because there's no reason for them to be
um, uh, to have any kind of secret pattern.
But what is mysterious is what is the mechanism that really forces the randomness to happen
uh, and this is just absent.
Another incredibly surprisingly difficult problem is the Collatz conjecture.
Oh, yes.
Simple to state- Mm-hmm.
.
..
beautiful to visualize- Yes.
.
..
in its simplicity, and yet extremely, uh
difficult to solve, and yet you have been able to make progress.
Uh, uh, Paul Rudyar said about the Collatz conjecture
"That mathematics may not be ready for such problems.
" Mm-hmm.
Others have stated that it is an extraordinarily difficult problem completely out of reach
this is in 2010, out of reach of present day mathematics and yet- Yeah.
.
..
you have made some progress.
Why is it so difficult to make?
Can you actually even explain what it is
is it easy to- Oh, yeah, yeah
yeah.
So it's a- it's a- it's a problem that you can explain
um, you know, it- it, um
it helps with some, um, visual aids
but yeah, so you take any natural number like say 13
and you apply the following procedure to it.
So if it's even, you divide it by two
and if it's odd, you multiply it by three and add one.
So even numbers get smaller, odd numbers get bigger.
So 13, uh, would become 40, because 13 times three is 39
add one, you get 40.
So it's a simple process.
For odd numbers and even numbers, they're both very easy operations
and then you put them together, it's still reasonably simple.
Um, but then you ask what happens when you iterate it.
You- you take the output that you just got and feed it back in.
So 13 becomes 40, 40 is now even
divide by two is 20, 20 is still even
divide by two, 10, five, and then five times three plus one is 16
and then eight, four, two, one.
So, uh, and then from one it goes one
four, two, one, four, two, one.
It cycles forever.
So the sequence I just described, um
you know, 13, 40, 20, 10 so forth
these are also called hailstone sequences because there's an oversimplified model of- of hailstone formation
you know, which is not actually quite correct but it's still somehow taught to high school students as a first approximation
is that, um, like a- a little nugget of ice gets- gets
uh, an ice crystal, forms in- in a cloud
and it goes up and down because of the wind
uh, and- and sometimes when it's cold
it acquires a bit- a bit more mass
and maybe it melts a little bit, and this process of going up and down creates this sort of partially melted ice
which eventually creates this hailstone, and eventually it falls down to the earth.
So the conjecture is that no matter how high you start up
like you take a number which is in the millions or billions
you co- you have this process that- that goes up if you're odd and- and down if you're even
it eventually goes down to- to- to earth all the time.
No matter where you start with this very simple algorithm
you end up at one.
Right.
And you might climb for a while- Right.
Yeah, so it's- .
..
and come down.
Yeah, if you plotted, um, these sequences
they look like Brownian motion.
Um, they look like the stock market
you know, they just go up and down in a- in a seemingly random pattern.
And in fact usually that's what happens, th- that- that if you plug in a random number
you can actually prove at least initially that it would look like
um, a random walk.
Um, and it's actually a random walk with
uh, a downward drift.
Um, it's like if you're always gambling on- on
uh, roulette at a- at the casino with odds slightly weighted against you
so sometimes you- you win, sometimes you lose
but over, in the long run, you lose a bit more than you win
um, and so normally your wallet will hit- will go to zero
um, if you just keep playing over and over again.
So statistically it makes sense that it would do it.
Yes.
Yeah.
So- so the result that I- I proved roughly speaking asserts that- that statistically
like 99% of all inputs would- would drift down to
maybe not all the way to one, but to be much
much smaller than what you started.
So i- it's- it's like if I told you that if you go to a- a casino
most of the time you will end up
if you keep playing for long enough, you end up with a smaller amount in your wallet than when you started.
Uh, that's kind of like the res- what- the result that I proved.
So why is that result, like, can you continue down that thread to prove the full conjecture?
Well, the- the problem is that, um
my- I- I used arguments from probability theory
um, and there's always this exceptional event.
So, you know, so in probability we have these- this law of large numbers
um, which tells you things like if you play a casino with a
um, a game at a casino with a losing
um, expectation, over time you are guaranteed
or almost surely with proba- probability as close to 100% as you wish
you're guaranteed to lose money.
But there's always this exceptional outlier.
Like, it is mathematically possible that even in- when the game is- is the odds are not in your favor
you could just keep winning slightly more often than you lose.
..
. very much like how in Navier-Stokes there could be
you know, um, most of the time
um, your waves can disperse.
There could be just one outlier choice of initial conditions that would lead you to blow up.
And there could be one outlier choice of
um, um, a special number that you stick in that shoots off to infinity while all other numbers crash to Earth
uh, c- crash to one.
Yeah.
Um, in fact, um, there's some mathematicians there
um, who've, uh, Alex Kontorovich, for instance
who've proposed that, um, that actually, um
these collapse, uh, iterations are like this similar automata.
Um, that yeah, yeah, if you look at what happened on
on, in binary, they do actually look a little bit like
like these Game of Life type patterns here.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and in an a- analogy to how The Game of Life can create these
these massive, like, self-replicating objects and so forth
possibly you could create some sort of heavier than air flying machine.
You know, um, a number which is
uh, actually encoding this machine which is
uh, just, whose job it is to encode
is to create a, a, a version of itself which is
which is larger.
Heavier than air machine encoded in a number- Yeah.
.
..
that flies forever.
Yeah.
So Conway, in fact, worked on-  .
..
worked on this problem as well.
Oh, wow.
So Conway, um, so similar.
..
In fact, uh, uh, that was one of our inspirations for the Nav- Navier-Stokes project.
Uh, Conway studied generalizations of the collapse problem where instead of multiplying by three and adding one or dividing by two
you, you have more complicated branch rules.
But, but instead of having two cases
maybe you have 17 cases and then you go up and down.
And he showed that once your iteration gets complicated enough
you can actually encode Turing machines and you can actually make these problems undecidable and
and do things like this.
In fact, he invented a programming language for
uh, these kind of fractional linear transformations.
He called it FACTRAT as a play on
on Fortran, uh, and he showed that
that you could, um, you, you can program as
uh, Turing complete.
You could, you could, you could, uh
um, you could make a program that if
if your number you insert in was encoded as a prime
it would sink to zero, it would go down
otherwise it would go up, uh, and things like that.
Um, so the general class of problems is
is really, uh, as complicated as all the mathematics.
Some of the mystery of the cellular automata that we talked about
uh, s- s- having a fra- mathematical framework to say anything about cellular automata
maybe the same kind of framework is required- Yeah.
Yeah.
.
for the Collatz conjecture?
Yeah.
If you want to do it, not statistically
but you really want 100% all inputs to
to, to fall to Earth.
Yeah.
So what might be feasible is, is
yeah, assisting 99%, you know, going to go to one- Yeah.
.
..
but like everything, yeah, uh, that looks hard.
What would you say is out of these within reach famous problems is the hardest problem we have today?
Is it Riemann hypothesis?
Riemann is up there.
Um, P equals NP is, is a good one because
like, uh, that's a m- that's, that's a meta-problem.
Like, if you solve that in the
um, in the positive sense that you can find a P equals NP algorithm
then potentially this solves a lot of other problems as well.
And we should mention some of the conjectures we've been talking about
you know, a lot of stuff is built on top of them now.
Yeah.
There's ripple effects.
P equals NP has more ripple effects than basically any other- Right.
If the Riemann hypothesis is disproven, um
that'd be a big mental shock to number theorists.
Uh, but it would have follow-on effects for
um, cryptography.
Mm-hmm.
Um, because a lot of cryptography uses number theory
um, uses number theory constructions involving primes and so forth.
And, um, it relies very much on the intuition that number theorists have built over many
many years of what operations involving primes behave randomly and which ones don't.
Um, and in particular, our encryption, um
methods are designed to turn text with information on it into text which is indistinguishable from
um, fr- from random noise, so, um
and hence, b- we believe to be almost impossible to crack
um, at least, b- uh, mathematically.
Um, but, uh, if something as core to our beliefs as the Riemann hypothesis is
is wrong, it means that there are
there are actual patterns of the primes that we're not aware of.
And if there's one, there's probably gonna be more.
Um, and suddenly a lot of our crypto systems are in doubt.
Uh- Yeah.
But then how do you then say stuff about the
the primes ?
Yeah.
Uh- Like you're going towards the, uh
Collatz c- conjecture again.
Um, because if I, I, I.
..
Do you want it to be random, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
You want it to be randomly.
And so more broadly, I'm just looking for more tools
more ways to show that, that- Yeah.
.
..
that things are random.
How do you prove a conspiracy doesn't happen?
Right.
Is there any chance to you that P equals NP?
Is there some, can you imagine a possible universe?
It is possible.
I mean, there's, there's various, uh
scenarios.
I mean, there, there, there's one where it is technically possible but in fact it's never actually implementable.
The evidence is sort of slightly pushing in favor of no
that P, probably P is not equal to NP.
I mean, it seems like it's one of those cases seem
or similar to Riemann hypothesis that I think the evidence is le- leaning pretty heavily on the no.
Certainly more on the no than on the
on the yes.
The funny thing about P equals NP is that we have also a lot more obstructions than we do for almost any other problem.
Um, so while there's evidence, uh, we also have a lot of results ruling out many
many types of approaches to the problem.
Uh, this is the one thing that the computer scientists have actually been very good at
is actually saying that, that certain approaches cannot work
no-go theorems.
It could be undecidable.
We don't, yeah, we don't know.
There's a funny story I read that when you won the Fields Medal
somebody from the internet wrote you  and asked
uh, you know, "What are you gonna do now that you've won this prestigious award?
" And, and then you just quickly, very humbly said that
you know, "This shiny medal is not gonna solve any of the problems I'm currently working on
so I'm just.
..
"  Okay.
"I'm gonna keep, I'm gonna keep working on them.
" It's just, first of all, it's funny to me that you would answer an email in that context.
And second of all, it, um, it just shows your humility.
But anyway, uh, maybe you could speak to the Fields Medal
but it's another way for me to ask
uh, w-.
..
about, uh, Grigori Perelman.
What do you think about him famously declining the Fields Medal and the Millennium Prize
which came with a $1 million of prize money?
He stated that, "I'm not interested in money or fame.
The prize is completely irrelevant for me.
If the proof is correct, then no other recognition is needed.
" Yeah.
No, he's, he's somewhat of an outlier
um, even among mathematicians who tend to
uh, to have, uh, somewhat idealistic views.
Um, I've never met him.
Uh, I think I'd be interested to meet him one day
but I, I never had the chance.
I, I know people who met him.
He's always had strong views about certain things.
Um, you know, I mean, it's
it's not like he was completely isolated from the
the math community.
I mean, he would, he would give talks and- Mm-hmm.
.
..
and write papers and so forth.
Um, but at some point he just decided not to engage with the rest of the community.
He was, he was disillusioned or something.
Um, I don't know.
Um, and he decided to, to, uh
uh, to peace out, uh, and
you know, collect mushrooms in St Petersburg or something.
Right.
And, and that's, that's fine, you know.
You can, you can do that.
Um, I mean, that's another sort of flip side to.
..
I mean, we are not s-.
A lot of the problems that we solve
you know, they.
..
Some of them do have practical application and that's
that's great.
But, uh, like, if you stop thinking about a problem
you, you know.
..
So he's, he hasn't published since in
in this field but that's fine 'cause many
many other people have done so as well.
Um, yeah, so I guess one thing I didn't realize initially with the Fields Medal is that it
it sort of makes you part of the establishment.
Mm-hmm.
Um, you know?
So, you know, most mathematicians, you know
there's, uh, they're just career mathematicians, you know.
You just focus on publishing your next paper
maybe getting one st- step.
..
promote one, one rank, you know, and
and starting a few p- projects, maybe ha- taking some students or something.
Yeah, but then suddenly people want your opinion on things and
uh, you have to think a little b- about
uh, you know, things that you might just sort of foolishly say because you know no one's gonna listen to you .
Uh, it's just, it's more important now.
Is it constraining to you?
Are you able to still have fun and be a rebel and try crazy stuff and- Well
uh- .
..
play with ideas?
I have a lot less free time than I- Yeah.
.
..
had previously.
Um, I mean, mostly by choice.
I mean, I, I, I could.
..
Obviously I have the option to sort of
uh, decline, uh.
..
So I decline a- a lot of things.
I, I, I could, I could decline even more.
Um, or I could acquire a reputation for being so unreliable that people don't even ask anymore.
Uh, but this is, this- I love
I love the different algorithms you use.
This is great.
Uh, uh, this.
..
It's, it's, it's always an option.
Um, but, you know, um, there are things that are
you know, like.
..
I, I mean, sort of.
I mean, I, I, I don't spend as much time as I do as a postdoc
you know, just, just working on one problem at a time or
um, fooling around.
I still do that a little bit.
But I, yeah.
As you advance in your career, it's somewhat.
..
The more soft skills.
So math somehow front loads all the technical skills to the early stage of your career.
So, um, yeah, so it's, uh.
..
As a postdoc, it's publish or perish.
You, you, you're insent- you're, you're incentivized to basically focus on
on proving very technical theorems just to prove yourself
um, as well as prove the theorems.
Um, but then as, as you get more senior you have to start
you know, mentoring and, and, and
and giving interviews, uh, and, uh
and trying to shape, um, direction in the field both research-wise and
and, you know, uh, sometimes you have to
uh, uh, you know, do s- very s- administrative things.
And it's kind of a, uh, the right social contract because you
you need to, to work in the trenches to see what can help mathematicians.
The other side of the establishment, sort of the
the really positive thing is that, um
you get to be a light that's an inspiration to a lot of young mathematicians or young people that are just interested in mathematics.
And it's like- Yeah, yeah.
It's just how the human mind works.
This is where I would probably, uh
say that I like the Fields Medal, th- that it does inspire a lot of pe- young people somehow.
I don't.
..
This is just how human brains work.
Yeah.
At the same time I also want to give sort of respect to somebody like Grigori Perelman who is critical of awards.
In his mind those are his principles, and any human that's able for their principles to
like, do the thing that most humans would not be able to do
it's beautiful to see.
Right.
Some recognition is, is necessary and important
uh, but yeah, it's, it's also important to not let these things take over your life- Yeah.
.
..
um, and like only be concerned about
uh, getting the next big award or whatever.
Um, I mean, uh, if it.
..
Yeah, so ag- again you see these people try to only solve like really big math problems and
and not work on, on, on things that are less
uh, sexy if you wish- Mm-hmm.
.
..
but, but, but actually, uh, still interesting and
and ins- instructive.
As you say, like, the way the human mind works it's
um.
..
We understand things better when they're attached to humans
um, and also, uh, if they're attached to a small number of humans.
Like s- I.
..
The, this, this, this.
The way our humans, um, mind is
is wired we can comprehend the relationships between
you know, 10 or 20 people.
Uh, but once they get beyond that
like, 100 people, I.
..
there's, there's a, there's a limit.
I think there's a name for it.
Um, beyond which, uh, it just becomes the other.
Yeah.
Um, and, uh, so we have.
..
You have to simplify the whole mass of
you know, 99.
9% of humanity becomes the other.
Um, and, uh, and often  these models are
are, are incorrect and this causes all kinds of problems.
But, um, so yeah.
So to humanize a subject, you know
if you identify a small number of people and say
"Oh, these are representative people of a subject.
" You know, these are role models, uh
for example.
Um, that has some role, um, but it can also be
um, uh.
..
Yeah, too much of it can be harmful because it's.
I, I'll be the first to say that my own career traff- path is not that of a typical mathematician.
Um, I did a very accelerated, uh
education.
I skipped a lot of classes.
Um, I think I always had very fortunate mentoring
uh, opportunities.
Um, and I think I was at the right place at the right time.
Just because someone does- doesn't have my, um
trajectory, you know, it doesn't mean that they
they can't be good mathematicians.
I mean, they could be math, good mathematicians in
in a very different style, uh, and we need people w- with a different style.
Um, and, you know, even if.
..
Uh, and sometimes too much focus is given on the
on the person who d- does the last step to complete
um-.
..
a, a project in mathematics or elsewhere that's
that's really taken, you know, centuries or decades of lots and lots of building on lots of previous work.
Um, but that's a s- a story that's difficult to tell
um, if you're not an expert because
you know, it- it's easier to just say one person did this one thing
you know, it makes for a much simpler history.
I think on the whole it, um
is a hugely positive thing to, to talk about Steve Jobs- Mm-hmm.
.
..
as a representative of Apple when I personally know and
of course, everybody knows the incredible design
the incredible engineering teams-  .
..
just the individual humans on those teams, they're not a team
they're individual humans on a team and there's a lot of brilliance there
but it's just a nice shorthand like a ver- like pie.
Yeah.
Steve Jobs- Yeah, yeah.
.
..
pie.
As a, as a starting point, you see
you know- Yeah.
.
..
as a fir- as a first approximation, that's- Yes.
.
..
that's how you put it.
And then read some biographies and then look into much deeper first approximation.
Yeah.
That's right.
Uh, so you menti- you were at Princeton to
um- Mm-hmm.
Andrew Wiles at that time- Oh, yeah.
.
..
who was a professor there.
Mm-hmm.
It's a funny moment how history is just all interconnected.
And at that time he announced that he proved the Fermat's Last Theorem.
Oh, yeah.
What did you think, maybe looking back now with more context about that moment in
uh, math history?
Yeah, so I was a graduate student at the time.
I mean, I, I vaguely remember, you know
there was press attention and, uh, um
we all had the same, um, uh
we all had pigeonholes in the same mailroom
you know, so we all checked our mail and
and like suddenly Andrew Wiles' mailbox exploded to be overflowing
uh-  That's a good, that's a good metric.
Yeah, um, you know, so yeah
we all, we all talked about it at
at tea and so forth.
I mean, uh, we, we didn't understand
most of us still didn't understand the proof.
Um, we understood sort of high level details
um, like there's an ongoing project to formalize it in Lean that Kevin Buzzard is heading.
Yeah, can, can we take that small tangent?
Is it, is it.
..
how difficult is that?
'Cause as, as I understand the Fermat's Last
the, the proof for, uh, Fermat's Last Theorem has like super complicated objects- Yeah.
Yeah, the- .
..
it's really difficult to formalize, no?
Yeah, I guess, yeah, you're right
the, the objects that they use, um
you can define them, uh, so they've been defined in Lean
okay, so it's, so just defining what they are- Mm-hmm.
.
can be done.
Uh, that's really not trivial but it's been done
uh, but there's a lot of really basic facts about
um, these objects that have taken decades to prove and that they're
they're in all these different math papers.
And so lot- lots of these have to be formalized as well.
Um, Kevin's, uh, K- Kevin Buzzard's goal actually
he has fi- a five-year grant to formalize Fermat's Last Theorem
and his aim is that he doesn't think he will be able to get all the way down to the basic axioms what he wants to formalize it to the point where the only things that he needs to rely on is black boxes or things that were known by 1980 to
um, to number theorists at the time.
Um, and then some other person or some other work would have to be done to
to, to get from there.
Uh, so it's, it's a different area of mathematics than
um, the type of mathematics I'm used to.
Um, um, in analysis, which is kind of my area
um, the objects we study are kind of much closer to the ground.
We study, I study things like prime numbers and
and, and functions and, and things that are within the scope of a high school
um, uh, math education to at least
uh, define.
Um, yeah, but then there's this very advanced algebraic side of number theory where people have been building structures upon structures for quite a while
um, and it's, it's a very sturdy structure.
There's a, there's, it's, it's, it's been
it's been very, um, the, the
the at the base at least it's extremely well developed with textbooks and so forth.
But, um, um, it does get to the point where
um, if you're, if you haven't taken these years of study and you wanna ask about what
what is going on at, um, like level six of th- of this tower
I, you have to spend quite a bit of time before they can even get to the point where you can see
you see something you recognize.
What, uh, inspires you about his journey that was similar
as we talked about seven years mostly s- working in secret?
Yeah, uh, it's a, that is a
a romantic, uh, yeah, so it kind of fits with the sort of the
the romantic image that I think people have of mathematicians to the extent they think of them at all as these kind of eccentric
uh, you know, wizards or something, um.
So yeah, that certainly kind of, uh
uh, accentuated that perspective, you know, I mean
it's, it is a great achievement.
Yeah, his style of solving problems is so different from my own
um, but wh- which is great.
I mean, we- we need people like that.
Can you speak to it?
Like what, uh- Um- .
..
in, in terms of like the, you like the collaborative.
I like moving on from a problem if it's giving too much difficulty.
Got it.
Um, got it.
But you need the people who have the tenacity and the
the fearlessness, um, and I, I
I've collaborated with, with people like that where
where I want to give up, uh
'cause the, the first approach that we tried didn't work and the second one didn't approach.
They're convinced and they have third, fourth and the fifth approach works
um, and I'd have to eat my words
"Okay, I didn't think this was gonna work
but, uh, yes, you were right all along.
" And w- we should say for people who don't know
not only are you known for the brilliance of your work but the incredible productivity
just the number of papers which are all very high quality.
So there's something to be said about being able to jump from topic to topic.
Yeah, it works for me.
Yeah, I mean, but there are also people who are very productive and they
they focus very deeply on, yeah.
I think everyone has to find their own workflow.
Um, like one thing which is a shame in mathematics is that we have.
..
mathematics there's sort of a one size fits all approach to teaching
teaching mathematics, um, and, you know
so we have a certain curriculum and so forth.
I mean, you know, maybe like if you do math competitions or something you get a slightly different experience.
But, um, I think many people, um
they don't find their, their native math language
uh, until very late, uh, or usually too late so they
they stop doing mathematics and they have a bad experience with a teacher who's trying to teach them one way to do mathematics and they
they don't like it.
Um, my theory is that, um, humans don't come.
..
e- evolution has not given us a math center of our brain directly.
We have a vision center and a language center and some other centers
um, which have ev- evolution has honed but we
it doesn't, we don't have an innate sense of mathematics.
Um-.
..
but our other centers are sophisticated enough that different people
uh, uh, we, uh, we, we can repurpose other areas of our brain to do mathematics.
So, some people have figured out how to use the visual center to do mathematics
and so they think, think very visually when they do mathematics.
Some people have repurposed their, their language center and they think very symbolically.
Um, you know, um, some people like if- if they are very competitive and if they like gaming
there's a type, there's a part of your brain that's very good at
at, at, uh, uh, at solving puzzles and games and
and, and that can be repurposed.
But, um, like when I talk to other mathematicians
you know, they don't quite think.
..
I can tell that they're using some, uh
different styles of, of thinking than I am.
I mean, not, not disjoint, but they
they may prefer visual.
I, I'm, I- I don't actually prefer visual so much.
I need also visual aids myself.
Um, you know, mathematics provides a common language where we can still talk to each other even if we are thinking in
in different ways.
But you could tell there's a different set of subsystems being used in the thinking process.
Yeah, like, like they take different paths.
They're very quick at things that I struggle with and vice versa
um, and yet they still get to the same goal.
Yeah.
Um- That's beautiful.
.
..
and, yeah, but I mean the way we educate.
Un- unless you have like a personalized tutor or something
I mean, education sort of just by natural skill has to be mass produced.
You know, you have to teach to 30 kids
you know, they have 30 different styles.
You can't, you can't teach 30 different ways.
On that topic, what advice would you give to students
uh, young students, who are struggling at
with math, uh, but they're interested in it and would like to get better?
Is there something in this- Yeah.
Uh- .
..
in this complicated educational context, what, what would you advise?
Yeah, it's a tricky problem.
One nice thing is that there are now lots of sources for mathematical enrichment outside the classroom.
Mm-hmm.
Um, so in, in, in my day there already there were math competitions.
Um, and you know, there were also like popular math books in the library.
Mm-hmm.
But now you have, you know, YouTube
uh, there, there are forums just devoted to solving
you know, math puzzles and, um, and math shows up in other places.
You know, like, um, for example
there, there are hobbyists who play poker
uh, for fun.
Uh, and, um, they, they, you know
they're for very specific reasons are, are interested in very specific probability questions.
Yes.
Um, and, and they, they actually.
..
There's a community of amateur probabilists in, in
in poker, um, in chess, in baseball.
I mean, there's, there's, there's, uh
yeah.
Um, there's math all over the place
um, and I'm, I'm hoping actually with the
with these new sort of tools for LEAN and so forth that actually we can incorporate the broader public into math research projects.
Um, like this is almost, is, uh
is- doesn't happen at all currently.
So in the sciences there is some scope for citizen science
like astronomers, uh, they can.
..
There are amateurs who have discovered comets, and there's biologists
there are people who, who identify butterflies and so forth.
Um, and in math, in, um.
..
There are a small number of activities where
um, amateur mathematicians can like discover new primes and so forth.
But, but previously because we have to verify every single contribution
um, like most mathematical research projects, it would not help to have input from the general public.
In fact it would probably, it would just be
be time-consuming because just error checking and everything.
Um, but you know, one thing about these formalization projects is that they are bringing together more.
..
bringing in more people.
So I'm sure there are high school students who have already contributed to some of these
these formalizing projects, who contribute to MathLib.
Um, you know, you don't need to be a PhD holder to just work on this one atomic thing.
There's something about the formalization here that also
uh, uh, at the very first step opens it up to the programming community too.
Yes.
The people who are already comfortable- Yes.
.
..
with programming.
It seems like programming is somehow maybe just a feeling
but it feels more accessible to folks than math.
Yeah.
Math is seen as this like extreme, especially modern mathematics
seen as this extremely difficult to enter area and programming is not.
So that could be just an entry point.
You can execute code and you can get results.
You know, you can print out how the world pretty quickly.
Yeah.
Um, you know, like if, uh
if programming was taught as an almost entirely theoretical subject
where you're just taught the computer science, the theory of functions and
and, and, and routines and so forth
and outside of some, some very specialized homework assignments
you and I could program like on the weekend for fun.
Yeah.
Or yeah, that would be as, considered as hard as math.
Mm-hmm.
Um, so as I said, there are communities of non-mathematicians where they're deploying math for some very specific purpose
you know, like optimizing their poker game and
and for them then math becomes fun for them.
Uh, what advice would you give in general to young people how to pick a career?
How to find themselves?
Like what would they be good at?
Yeah, that's a- that's a tough, tough
tough question.
Yeah, so, um, there's a lot less certainty now in the world.
You know, I mean, there was this period after the war where
uh, at least in the West, you know
if you came from a good demographic you
uh, you know, like you, there was a very stable path to a- to a good career.
You go to- to college, you get an education
you pick one profession and- and you stick to it.
It's becoming much more a thing of the past.
So I think you just have to be adaptable and flexible.
I think people have to get skills that are transferrable.
You know, like, like learning one specific programming language or one specific subject
mathematics or something, it's- it's- it's.
..
That itself is not a super transferrable skill
but sort of knowing how to, um
reason with, with abstract concepts or how to problem solve when things go wrong.
These are things which I think we will still need even as our tools get- get better and we know- you'll- you'll be working with AIs more and so forth.
But actually you're an interesting case study.
I mean, you're like a- one of the great living mathematicians
right?
And then you had a way of doing things and then all of a sudden you start learning.
..
First of all, you kept learning new fields.
Yeah.
But you learned LEAN.
That's not- that's a non-trivial thing to learn.
Like that's a- Yeah.
That's a.
..
For- for a lot of people, that's an extremely uncomfortable leap to take
right?
Yeah.
A lot of mathematicians.
First of all, I- I've always been interested in new ways to do mathematics.
I- I- I feel like a lot of the ways we do things right now are inefficient.
Um, like I- I- I spend, uh
me and my colleagues, we spend a lot of time doing very routine computations or doing things that other mathematicians would instantly know how to do
and we don't know how to do them
uh, and why can't we search and get a quick response and so forth.
So, that's why I've always been, uh
interested in exploring new workflows.
About four or five years ago, I was on a committee where we had to ask for ideas for interesting workshops to run at a math institute
and at the time, Peter Shortser had just
uh, formalized one of his- his, um
new theorems, and there were some other developments in computer-assisted proof that looked quite interesting and I said
"Oh, we should- we should, uh, um
we should run a workshop on this.
This would be a good idea.
" Um, and then I- I was a bit too enthusiastic about this idea
so I- I got volun- voluntold to actually run it
um, so I did with a bunch of other people
Kevin Buzzard and Jordan Ellenberg and- and, uh
a bunch of other people.
Um, and it was- it was, uh
a- a- a nice success.
We brought together a bunch of mathematicians and computer scientists and other people and- and we got up to speed on state of the art
um, and there was really interesting, um
developments that- that most mathematicians didn't know was going on.
Um, there were lots of nice proofs of concept.
You know, just little hints of- of what was going to happen.
This is just before ChatGPT, but there was
even then, there was one talk about language models and the potential
uh, capability of- of those in the future.
So, that got me excited about the subject
so I started giving talks, um, about this is something we should- more of us should start looking at
um, now that I- I'd arranged to run this conference
and then ChatGPT came out, and like suddenly
AI was everywhere.
And so, uh, I got interviewed a lot
um, about- about this topic, um, and in particular
um, the interaction between AI and- and formal proof assistants
and I said, "Yeah, they should be combined.
This- this is- this is, um, there's perfect synergy to happen here.
" And at some point I realized that I have to actually do
not just talk the talk, but walk the walk
you know?
Mm-hmm.
Like, you know, I don't work in machine learning
I- and I don't work in proof formalization and there's a limit to how much I can just rely on authority and say
"Oh, I- I- I'm a world-known mathematician.
Just trust me, you know, when I say that this is going to change mathematics and I'm not doing it any- when I don't do any of it myself.
" So, I felt like I had to actually
uh- uh, justify it.
You know, there's.
..
A lot of what I get into, actually
um, I don't quite see in advance as to how much time I'm gonna spend on it
and it's only after I'm sort of waist-deep in- in- in- in a project that I- I realize.
By that point, I'm committed.
Well, that's deeply admirable that you're willing to go into the fray
be in some small way a beginner, right?
Mm-hmm.
Or have some of the sort of challenges that a beginner would
right?
So new- Yeah.
.
..
new concepts, new ways of thinking.
Also, you know, sucking at a thing that others.
..
I think in that talk, you know
you could be a Fields Me- Medal-winning mathematician and an undergrad and know something better than you.
Yeah, um, I think mathematics inherently.
..
I mean, mathematics is so huge these days that nobody knows all of modern mathematics
um, and inevitably we make mistakes and
um, you know, uh, you can't cover up your mistakes with just sort of bravado and- and
uh- Yeah.
.
..
I mean, because people will ask for your proofs
and if you don't have the proofs, you don't have the proofs
um.
..
Gotta love that.
Yeah.
So it does keep us honest.
I mean, not- not.
..
I mean, you can still.
I- it's not a perfect panacea, but I think
uh, we do have more of a culture of admitting error than.
..
Because we're forced to all the time.
Big ridiculous question, I'm sorry for it once again.
Who is the greatest mathematician of all time?
Maybe one who's no longer with us.
Uh, who are the candidates?
Euler, Gauss, Newton, Ramanujan, Hilbert?
Uh, so first of all, it's- it's as mentioned before
like there's- there's some time dependence.
On the day.
Yeah, uh, like- like if- if you- if you plot cumulatively over time
for example, Euclid, like- like sort of like- Yeah.
.
..
is- is- is one of the contenders.
Um, and then maybe some unnamed, a- a- anonymous mathematicians before that.
Um, you know, the, whoever came up with the concept of odd numbers
you know?
You know, um- Do mathematicians today still feel the impact of Hilbert
just- Oh, yeah.
.
..
directly of what, everything that's happened in the 20th century?
Yeah, yeah.
Hilbert spaces.
We have lots of things that are named after him
uh, of course.
Just the arrangement of mathematics and just the introduction of c- certain concepts.
I mean, 23 problems have been extremely influential.
There's some strange power to the declaring which problems- Yeah.
.
..
are hard to solve.
Yeah.
The statement of the open problems.
Yeah, I- I mean, you know, there's this bystander effect in- in everywhere
right?
Like if- if no one says, "You should do X
" everyone just sort of mills around waiting for somebody else to- to
uh, to do something and- and like nothing gets done.
Um, so, and- and like- like it's.
..
The one- one thing that actually, uh
you have to teach undergraduates in mathematics is that you should always try something.
So, um, you see a lot of paralysis
um, in an undergraduate trying a math problem.
If they recognize that there's a certain technique that- that can be applied
they will try it.
But there are problems for which they see none of their standard techniques obviously applies and the common reaction is then just paralysis.
"I don't know what to do.
" Uh, or, um, what was it?
I think there's a quote from The Simpsons
"I've tried nothing and I'm all out of ideas.
"  Um, so, you know, like the next step then is to try anything
like no matter how stupid, um, and in fact
how, almost the stupider the better.
Um, which, you know, and one
a technique which is almost guaranteed to fail
but the way it fails is going to be instructive.
Um, like it fails because you're- you're not at all taking into account this hypothesis.
Oh, this hypothesis must be useful.
That's a clue.
I think you also suggested somewhere this- this fascinating approach which  really stuck with me.
I started using it and it really works.
I think you said it's called structured procrastination?
No, yes, yeah.
It's when you really don't want to do a thing then you imagine a thing you don't want to do more.
..
Yes, yes.
.
..
that's worse than that and then in that way you procrastinate by not doing the thing that's worse.
Yeah, yeah.
It's a nice, it's a nice hack.
It actually works.
Yeah, yeah.
Um, I mean, with anything that I
you know, I mean like if, um.
..
Psychology is really important.
Like, you- you- you talk to athletes like marathon runners and so forth and
uh, and they talk about what's the most important thing
is it their training regimen or their diet?
And so so much of it is actually psychology.
Um, you know, just- just tricking yourself to- to think in the form that's feasible
um, so that you can- you're motivated to do it.
Is there something our human mind will never be able to comprehend?
Well, a sort of.
..
Like as a mathematician, I mean, you know
like I g- by induction, I- I- it's a sufficiently.
..
There must be some sufficiently large number that you can't- .
.
..
not understand.
Uh, that was the first thing that came to mind.
So that, but even broadly, is there.
..
Are we lim- is there something about our mind that's- we're going to be limited
even with the help of mathematics?
Well, okay.
I mean, it's like how much augmentation are you willing.
..
Like if- like, for example, if I didn't even have pen and paper
um, like if I had no technology whatsoever
okay, so I'm not allowed blackboard, pen and paper- Right.
You're already much more limited than you would be.
Incredibly limited.
Even language, uh, the English language is a technology.
Uh, it's, uh, it's one that's been very internalized.
So you're right, there really.
..
The- the formulation of the problem is incorrect 'cause there really is no longer a
just a solo human.
We're already augmented in extremely complicated intricate ways
right?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So we're already like a collective intelligence.
Yes, yeah.
I guess.
Uh, so- so humanity plural has much more intelligence in principle
on its good days-  .
..
than- than- than the individual humans put together.
Uh, it can also have less, okay?
But, uh, um, yeah, so yeah
mathemat- method- the mathematical community plural is- is- is incredibly super intelligent
uh, entity, um, that, uh, no single human mathematician can- can come close to- to- to replicating.
You see it a little bit on these like question analysis sites
um, uh, so this MathOverflow which is the math version of StackOverflow.
Mm-hmm.
And like, sometimes you get like this very quick responses to very difficult questions from the community
um, and it's- it's- it's a pleasure to watch actually
as- as- as an expert.
I'm a fan-spectator of that, uh,  of that site
just seeing the brilliance of the different people there.
Um, the depth of knowledge that people have and the- the willingness to engage in the- in the rigor and the nuance over the particular question is pretty cool to watch.
It's fun, it's almost like just fun to watch.
Yeah.
Uh, what gives you hope about this whole thing we have going on with human civilization?
I think, uh, yeah, the, uh
the younger generation is always like- like really creative and enthusiastic and- and inventive.
Um, I- it's a pleasure working with- with- with
uh, with, uh, with young students.
Um, you know, the, uh, the progress of science tells us that the problems that used to be really difficult can become extremely
you know, can become like trivial to solve.
You know?
Um, I mean like it was s- like navigation
you know, just- just knowing where you were o- on the planet was this horrendous problem
peop- people died, um, you know, uh
or- or lost fortunes because they couldn't navigate
you know.
And we have devices in our pockets that do it automatically for us
like as a completely solved problem.
And also things that are- seem unfeasible for us now could be maybe just homework exercises for them .
Yeah, one of the things I find really sad about the finiteness of life is that I won't get to see all the cool things we create as a civilization
you know?
That, 'cause it, in the next 100 years
200 years just imagine showing- showing up in 200 years.
Yeah, well already plenty has happened, you know
like if- if you could go back in time and- and talk to your- your teenage self or something
you know what I mean?
Just- Yeah.
Just the internet and- and- and now AI
I mean that, uh, again they've- they've been in- they're beginning to internalize and say
"Yeah, of course, uh, an AI can understand our voice and- and give reasonable
uh, you know, slightly incorrect answers to- to any question.
" But yeah, like this- this was mind-blowing even two years ago.
And in the moment it's hilarious to watch on the internet and so on
the- the drama, uh, people take everything for granted very quickly and then they- we humans seem to entertain ourselves with drama.
Out of anything that's created, somebody needs to take one opinion and another person needs to take an opposite opinion and argue with each other about it.
But when you look at the arc of things
I mean, just even in re- progress of robotics- Yeah.
.
..
just to take a step back and be like
"Wow, this is beautiful that we humans are able to create this.
" Yeah, when the infrastructure and- and the culture is- is healthy
yeah, the community of humans can be so much more intelligent and mature and- and rational than the individuals within it.
Well, one place I can always count on rationality is the comments section of your blog
which I'm, uh,  a fan of.
There's a lot of really smart people there.
And thank you, uh, of course for- uh
for putting those ideas out on the blog.
And it's- I can't tell you how, uh
honored I am that you would spend your time with me today.
I was, uh, looking forward to this for a long time
Terence, I'm a huge fan.
Um, you inspire me, you inspire millions of people.
Thank you so much for Oh, thank you
it was a pleasure.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Terence Tao.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description or at lexfriedman.
com/sponsors.
And now, let me leave you with some words from Galileo Galilei
"Mathematics is the language with which God has written the universe.
" Thank you for listening, and hope to see you next time.