- Humans are by far the hardest part of computer graphics
because millions of years of evolution
have given us dedicated brain systems
to detect patterns and faces and infer emotions and intent
because cavemen had to,
when they see a stranger determine whether they were
likely friendly or they might be trying to kill them.
And so people in the world have extraordinarily
detailed expectations of a face
and we can notice imperfections,
especially perfect arising
from computer graphics limitations.
Okay, one part is capturing humans.
And so it involved really advanced, dedicated hardware
that puts a human in a capture sphere
with dozens of cameras in them, taking high resolution,
high frame rate video of them as they go
through a range of motions.
And then capturing the human face is complicated
because the nuance detail of our faces
and how all the muscles and sinews
and fat work together to give us different expressions.
So it's not only about the shape of a person's face,
but it's also about the entire range of motion
that they might go through.
So that's the data problem.
There's a lot of other problems with computer graphics.
You know, there's technology for rendering hair,
which is really hard 'cause you can't render every, again,
we know the laws of physics.
It would be easy to just render every hair.
It would just be a billion times too slow.
So you need approximations that capture the net effect
of hair on rendering and on pixels
without calculating every single interaction
of every light with every strand of hair.
That's one part of it.
There's detailed features for different parts of faces.
There's subsurface scattering
because we think of humans as opaque.
But really our skin is, we light travels through it.
It's not completely opaque.
And the way in which light travels
through skin has a huge impact on our appearance.
And this is why there's no way you can paint a mannequin
to look realistic for a human.
You know, it's just a solid surface
and we'll never have the sort of detail you see.
- That kind of blew my mind, like thinking through that.
I think I heard that sort of the oiliness of the skin
creates very specific, nuanced, complex reflections
and then some light is absorbed
and travels through the skin
and that creates textures that are humanized,
able to perceive and it creates the thing
that we consider human, whatever that is.
All of that, while considering all the muscles involved
in making the nuance expression, just the subtle squinting
of the eyes or the subtle formation of a smile,
it's a subtlety of human faces that you have to capture.
Like the difference between a real smile and a fake smile.
But the way to show like beginning of a formation of a smile
that actually reveals a deep sadness.
All of that, like when I watch a human face,
I can like read that.
I could see that.
You have to have the tools
that in real time can render something like that.
And that's incredibly difficult.
- That's right, getting faces right requires the interplay
of literally dozens of different systems
and aspects of computer graphics.
And if any one of them is wrong,
your eye is completely drawn to that
and you find it on the wrong side of uncanny valley.
- The following is a conversation with Tim Sweeney,
a legendary video game programmer,
Founder and CEO of Epic Games
that created many incredible games of technologies,
including the Unreal Engine and "Fortnite,"
which both revolutionized the video game industry
and the experience of playing and creating video games.
This is the Lex Fridman podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors
in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Tim Sweeney.
When did you first fall in love with computers
and maybe with programming?
- I had a brother, Steve Sweeney,
who 16 years older than me,
and at some point when I was a little kid,
he went off to work in California for a tech company
and he'd gotten one of the first IBM PCs.
And so for one summer, I think I was about 11,
I went to visit him in California.
It was my first like trip away from my family
just to hang out with him.
And he had this brand new IBM computer
and I learned to program over the course of a few days
in BASIC, I was just blown away with the capabilities
of computers at the time.
It was unbelievable what they could accomplish.
And I was hooked from that point onward
and very much wanted to be a programmer.
- Do you remember what you wrote in BASIC?
Is it a video game type thing?
Is it like for loop, some numerical thing?
Do you remember?
- Yeah, it's funny, I have a perfectly vivid memory
of all of the first things I learned to program. (laughs)
I have a hard time remembering people's names,
but like code really sticks with me.
Every step and every challenge there were lessons learned
and you know, some of which I've come to realize
were just like me getting over some learning hurdles.
But other things were actually shortcomings
of programming languages
and the realization that there are actually better ways than
what a programmer is learning to program for the first time.
You know, a lot of what they're facing
isn't the challenge of learning a new art.
It's friction introduced by failures
of programming language design.
And so I've constantly come back to those early lessons
there as I've progressed and done more
and more things including building programming languages.
- Yeah, the friction and the pain is the guide
to learning in programming.
Like if I were to describe programming journey
that would be marked by pain.
And that pain, you shouldn't escape the pain.
The pain is instructive for you
to understand programming languages.
But do you remember what kind of stuff you were writing
at that time?
Just the early programs?
- Yeah, in the early days
I wrote a little bit of everything.
I wrote some games.
The first game I wrote on the Apple II was...
Since I only knew how to program in text mode,
the computer would throw asterisks across the screen.
They'd flow from left to right
and you'd have a parentheses on the right hand side
of the screen and yeah, looks like a baseball mitt
and you're supposed to catch the asterisks.
That was my very first game.
It took about a couple hours to build
and tune and I went from there.
But I built a lot of things.
I built databases at different points.
I built a programming language
and a full compiler for a language like Pascal
'Cause I didn't know where you went to buy one of those.
So I made my own.
And you know, one of the fun things at that time
was Bulletin Boards.
Before we had the internet in the hands of consumers,
you used your modem and you dialed into a local phone number
and connected to whoever was running the computer there.
And every town or city
had hundreds of these Bulletin Boards
run by different people
with their own personalities and teams.
And so I spent a lot of time Bulletin Board program
and learning how to deal
with database management and user interface
and dealing with multiple users concurrently and things.
And so I don't know, I'd probably spend about 10,000
or 15,000 hours writing code just on my own as a kid
between like age 10 and you know, age 20
before I actually shipped a program to the outside world.
- 10,000 to 15,000 hours.
What was the value of the hours as a kid you put in,
in programming that led
to the success you've had in later life?
Maybe this is by way of advice to younger people
in terms of how they allocate the hours of their early life.
- Yeah, you know, it's not just hours.
It's really striving to learn to understand
what knowledge you have, what knowledge you lack,
and to continually do experiments
and work on projects that improve your knowledge base.
And I didn't do this with a great amount
of structure or planning.
I was rather just going from project to project,
doing things that I thought would be fun and cool.
And with each project I learned new things.
You know, learning about how to store and manage data,
learning how to deal with advanced data structures,
how to write complex programs
that have deeply nested data and control flow.
Each one of those, you know, provided a lesson
which were later essential, you know,
when in 1991 I released my first game
and over the course of that decade we went from,
you know, zero commercial releases
to the first generation Unreal Engine.
But you know, this was largely just using the knowledge
that I'd built up over the previous decade
just doing fun hobby projects.
And if I hadn't done all of that work,
there's no way I could have ever built
the things that came later.
- All the experimentation and all the exploration
somehow contributed, somehow made sense later on.
Like all of that is integrated
somehow in the stuff you build.
It's funny how life works,
the pieces kind of come together eventually.
- Yeah, you know, there are definitely "Karate Kid" moments.
'Cause you know,
all this time I was learning math in high school
and in college I studied mechanical engineering.
And so, you know, you learn all kinds of math,
calculus and vector math and matrices
and you know, all of these related fields,
physics and stress and strain and how to, you know,
deal with complex physical systems.
And yeah, I wasn't really sure
how engineers would actually make use of that knowledge.
Do you just like forget about it
when you actually go off to do work?
Or do you write down equations on paper?
It was actually not clear as an early engineering student
what you do.
But when I started writing the first generation
Unreal Engine and I was dealing with 3D math, I was like,
wait, I know this stuff, I learned this.
(Tim and Lex laughing)
And you know, suddenly like the "Karate Kid", you know,
you get to paint the fence and wax the car
and suddenly you put all the pieces together into, you know,
a 3D engine based on whole lot
of accumulated programming language
and math knowledge that
often knowledge gained without ever anticipating
that I might use it in that way.
- Also, I think what's useful
is over and over learning a hard thing
and then showing to yourself, you know, that you can do it.
That you can learn a hard thing.
So then when you come to having to write a 3D engine
that in ways that haven't been done before,
you're like, I've been here,
I've been here in this experience.
Like I don't know what to do, but we'll figure it out.
We'll learn, I'll learn all the necessary components.
So just not being afraid of something new.
- That's right, and constantly striving to make connections
between these fields and look for their applications.
Long after I chipped on Unreal Engine,
it was like going back through an engineering textbook
and looking at, oh yeah, I used that,
I used that, I use that.
And then I got to the section on eigenvalues,
I'm like, don't know what the hell this is.
But you know, it turns out eigenvectors
and eigenvalue were the critical breakthrough
that made the Google search engine technology work
and stand apart from the rest.
Because they found if you threw all the links
that exist in the web
and you know, links from in two different sites
and you put them in a giant matrix
and you conclude it, you found a dominant eigenvalues,
then those eigenvectors described the best search results
for different things.
And so constantly picking up knowledge
and looking for ways to put it together is the thing to do.
And if you aspire to be a programmer,
you've gotta write a lot of code
and you've gotta continually learn new things and improve.
And if you wanna be an artist, you've gotta continually
draw artwork all styles and all kinds
and constantly push yourself to learn more and more
because you never know exactly
what you're gonna end up doing in the long run.
But the more knowledge you have and the more skills,
the more chance you have putting it together
and being successful.
- And whether you're a programmer or an artist,
you should probably take linear algebra,
even though it doesn't make sense at the time.
- I found getting an engineering degree
and then never working in an engineering field, you know,
just being a computer programmer was immensely valuable.
You know, I went to University of Maryland,
which for some disciplines
it's kind of known as a party school,
but they worked the engineers to death,
worked really hard. (Lex laughing)
And if you learn any engineering discipline,
you learn massive amounts of math
and you learn the rigor of problem solving.
You know, not just what you find from the Wikipedia article,
but going through all the exercises
of solving complex problems
and building up series of solutions
to derive in an answer.
It's valuable and it embodies the knowledge
that you need as a programmer.
And you know, people often go to university
and think, okay, my goal here is to get good grades,
so I get a diploma and I prove
to an employer they're invaluable.
Like, no, that's just kind
of the superficial bookkeeping of the university.
The real purpose of all of this is to learn.
And whether you learn formally or you learn on your own,
it's the learnings that are really valuable in a career.
And especially if you're going to be entrepreneur anywhere,
it's really knowing the stuff that matters
and not having the diplomas is into, yeah,
there's ever more pressure to make rebuild society
more and more around credentials.
Do you have this certificate? Do you have that proof?
But like, you know, companies
that are focused on just building great products
and doing great things gravitate towards
people who do the great work.
- Yeah, one of the great things about youth
is there's more freedom.
There's just more time to learn.
And people, when they go to high school,
they sometimes think, "Wow, I can't wait to get out of this
and be an adult and be free."
But it's not quite freedom.
When you get a job and you start a family,
all wonderful things, you get more and more busy
and less and less time to learn in the general sense,
learn whatever the hell you want.
That is a wonderful time in life.
The teenage years, the early 20s.
The 20s when you could just learn random shit.
- Yeah, you know, I think this is something
that's kind of changing in America.
There's so much focus on grades and homework
and structure around kids' lives.
You know, when I was growing up, you know,
my mom would feed me and my neighbor's, you know,
my neighbor's moms would feed them breakfast
and they'd, you know, be like, "Well be back by dark."
(Lex laughing)
- And you know, we'd go out and we'd play
and we'd do all sorts of things.
We'd, you know, explore the woods, we'd build go-karts,
we'd, you know, salvage old pieces of electronics
and build you what we thought were
our spacecraft control panels for the, you know,
fake spaceships we were building as play.
And we'd have an enormous amount of freedom.
And you know, from basically being a little kid
through the time I went off to college,
it had an enormous amount of free time.
And some people just used that and waste it, and watched TV.
Some people socialized
and some people really got into serious projects.
So many people at all times were doing cool things.
You know, I was programming, I was learning to build things.
I was, you know, before I was releasing games to the world,
I'd be like, yeah, having neighborhood folks over
to play the things I was working on and check them out.
And sometimes they're impressed and sometimes they weren't
and they'd have their own projects
and often we'd have spare time jobs
and everybody was entrepreneurial.
Like everybody, you know, had a side gig.
Sometimes you go around and mow people's lawns
or you'd, you know, rake the leaves up
and, you know, earn money and do...
The freedom there,
and the organic learning that occurred there,
I think is something that is really critical
to the American experience.
I worry is increasingly going away
as society is ever more protective and sheltering
and makes it harder to get these experiences.
- So on the video game side,
when did you first fall in love with video games?
- I've had a funny relationship with games
because my real aspiration has always been
to program cool stuff.
I get more enjoyment of programming
than anything else in the world.
And so, you know, my first really two formative experience
with games were playing
this game called "Adventure" for the Atari 2600.
It was like you moved this dot around the screen
and picked up objects like swords and fought dragons
and invaded castles and solved puzzles.
Very, very simple iconic stuff, you know,
rather than realistic graphics.
And then the other game that really got immersed in
was "Zork," which was a text of adventure game.
It would tell you where you are and what you see
and you type in commands like "go north" or "pickup sword"
or "open door" and explore a world that way.
So the game didn't have any graphics,
but in your mind you had this elaborate picture
of what you're seeing there.
And it really brought inspired imagination
more than other things.
And playing those games led me to (indistinct)
and where I learn to program everything that I saw there
and that drove a lot of my programming.
I learned how to move a player around the screen.
I learned how to, you know, build a design tool
so I could build castles and save them off
and then play them in a game.
And I realized there was a separation between the tools
that you use to build a game and the game itself.
And that if the more powerful tools you had,
the more creativity you could unleash in yourself or others.
And you know, I learned all the programming techniques
that supported games, how to parse text, you know,
pick up sword and go north, how do you make that sentence
into an actual series of commands on the computer?
And that was really, really exciting.
I have to say, until the time that "Fortnite" came out,
I played video games primarily to learn what they were doing
so I could go off and do that myself.
You know, I'd sit down, you know,
when "Wolfenstein" tying came out
and then "Doom" came out, you know, I'd go through
and look at pixel by pixel, I'd move the mouse very slightly
and look exactly what was happening to figure out.
- That's great.
- What technique was being used there
and that was a puzzle solving at a grand scale.
And it was so fun.
- So, take me there in the early '90s.
So you launched Epic Games in 1991,
so the writing of your first big video game, "ZZT".
What was it like? What was the technical challenges?
What were the psychological challenges of building that?
- It was a funny project
because I didn't start out to build a video game.
I just moved from an Apple II that,
so my brother bought my family an Apple II
right after I'd visited him in California.
So I've been programming on that for a few years.
Learned a lot of techniques,
but weren't many Apple II users around still
by the time that cycle came to an end.
And so I'd just gotten an IBM PC of my own, I was learning
to program and I realized I needed to text editor.
So I started writing a text editor, you know,
a text editor is a program to edit text files.
You have logic to move the cursor around
and let people type things and backspace and delete
and do all of those, you know, mundane actions.
And you know, one night I was like, I finished it up
and I was like, well, okay,
I have a text editor, but this is pretty boring.
And so I made the cursor into a smiley face character
and I had the like different characters you could place
in this document, perform different gameplay actions.
Some would be walls and some would kill you
and some would be moving objects
that could fly around the screen.
And so this text editor that I made evolved
into little game editors.
So I was building these levels for a game.
I put a lot of time into like building an editor
and a primitive set of objects,
about 20 or 30 different objects,
enough to build a really cool and compelling game,
but not so many that players would lose track
of what they're seeing.
I started off just building different game levels.
You know, the idea is you'd be on a series of board,
they'd be connected by, you know, going north
passed the end of the current board would take you
to a new one if it was open
or maybe it was block and you couldn't go there.
I built the whole game world around that
and you know, this was the game that became "ZZT."
And I was having fun with it, building it and playing it,
but I didn't know if it would really work.
So I did this experiment.
I started inviting neighbors over, like some adults,
some kids of all different ages and sat them down from it
and said like, "Here's a game I made.
Figure it out." (Lex laughing)
And you know, I had to force myself not to tell them
what they need to do, right?
Because I really wanted to learn if they were able to,
you know, discover it all for themselves.
You know, today we would call this, you know,
user experience test
and there's a whole field to research
around user experience research,
but back then it was just inviting
some kids over to play the game.
I took notes about what they got stuck on
and what they enjoyed and where they felt bored
and just iteratively polished the game
until I felt it was good and I put it out
and released it on, well this was before the internet,
so there were Bulletin Boards.
I upload it to a bunch of local Bulletin Boards
and from there it started spreading
because, you know, the way to build up cred
for Bulletin Board users was to upload new files
and to claim that,
"Hey, I was the first that brought this to you."
And you know, so there was a natural tendency
of the software to spread.
I decided to use the sharer model, you know,
so I didn't just build this one game.
I built a trilogy of three games.
And I released the first one for free
and I said, "Hey, if you'd like this, buy the two sequels."
And yeah, I included my parents' mailing address
and said, you know, "Send us $30
and you can get the sequels to this game."
And the checks started coming in within a few days. (laughs)
And I was making like, getting three or four orders a day,
I was making like $100 a day.
I'm like, "Woo, I'm rich." (laughs)
Because, you know, being a 20-year-old,
that was like a pretty big deal.
- What did that feel like, just getting money
and probably feeling this immense success
from something you've created?
- Well, you know, I looked at money always just as a tool
to help you fund accomplishing cool things.
And you know, having enough
to do the things you wanna do is the critical thing.
It's always been just very utilitarian,
but the knowledge that other people all around the country
and all then, you know, and a month later,
all around the world were playing the game
that was mind-boggling.
You know, that me, like this little kid, who'd put out
a game on a local Bulletin Board
could be doing international business
and shipping discs all over the world to players,
you know, because the software was spreading on its own.
It was just magical.
And that was a new thing for software.
Like that did not happen with mechanical devices.
Like you manufactured one, you sold it to somebody
and they had it and that was it.
But software could spread.
That was just really cool to see.
And it made me realize there's really no upward limit
on the potential for business like that.
You know, we saw Microsoft as a big juggernaut company
at the time, but it was like, hey, you know,
if that Epic does games good enough, you know,
we could accomplish what they've accomplished
with operating systems.
And the sky was the limit.
And I think this is the age we live in now,
you don't have to be an industrialist
manufacturing physical products.
Anybody who builds anything digitally,
if it's good enough you can reach the entire world
and build the, you know, next Microsoft or Meta or Apple
or Google or Epic Games.
- It's such a cool origin story though.
You start out building a text editor,
so you're looking at this project,
you're playing around with it, you're building up the tools
and it's such an inspiring moment
'cause a lot of us start out building a project
and to allow yourself to see the potential pivots,
the potential trajectories that can go is really nice.
To sit back, allow yourself to be bored
and like, "Ah, I'm gonna go this way."
I mean, that's like a crossroads.
You came to a crossroads.
I mean, you built, you know, compilers,
you design your own programming language,
you built compilers, databases,
all this things you mentioned.
And you started building a text editor
and then here came to this crossroad,
I'm gonna make this fun.
And then from there, you know,
one of the most legendary gaming companies was created.
It's kind of cool,
like that's an inspiring thing for sort of developers.
Like be open to the possibility of creating something
you didn't plan to create and just go with it.
Right, that's cool.
- Yeah, and it was a bunch of learnings emerged
really quickly there.
The neat thing I did with "ZZT" was I didn't just release
the game, I also released the editor with it.
I built this tool so I could make these "ZZT" boards
that people could play, but I also gave it
to all of the players themselves.
And you know, like 30 years later I still run into people,
you know, when I go to a game industry event, it was like,
you know, "I grew up playing 'ZZT.'"
And you know, here's an adult who grew up playing my game.
(Tim laughing)
And it was because it enabled anybody
to become a creator too.
It had, you know, this old board editor
and it also had a little scripting language
so you could learn a little bit of programming in it too.
And it kind of impressed
and it really set a formative principle of Epic,
which was that, you know, the company's mission
is to make awesome entertainment, but also awesome tools
and to share those tools with everybody
so that they can build their own amazing things too.
And when we got into Unreal Engine a few years later,
the interplay between us building a game
and us building tools that were widely used
by others was a critical part of that.
And I think that's the sole reason
that Epic has been massively successful.
And actually the reason that we've survived
all of this time is that by serving both creators
and gamers, we've been able to weather
the ups and downs of the game industry.
It's a brutal place for companies.
We've been able to survive every financial downturn
and sometimes the Engine's been funding the business
because we didn't have a game.
And sometimes the games have been funding the business
and it really set a principle in our culture
that's persevered and is continually
bought to their forefront.
- But on the editor front,
that's such a fascinating philosophy
that you always allow people to create their own worlds.
You have an engine from which you simulate the world
that the game is in.
You have the actual game
and you also have the freedom for creators to create
various, you know, in "Fortnite" islands of their own.
It's like with everything you ship,
that freedom to create is always there.
That's really interesting.
- Yeah, and it's something we aim to do
more and more fully over time.
You know, in the course of building "Fortnite,"
we've built a lot of other tools,
they're useful for us too
because it's not just a game powered by Unreal Engine,
but it's also, you know, a social ecosystem
where people can make friends and voice chat
and get together and parties.
And we've opened up all of those social features
into Epic Online Services
and we give them away to all developers for free
because we all benefit from growth and that user base.
And, you know, our goal is ultimately
to build the company's products
and the same technology that we share with everybody else.
And to hope that foster a bigger and bigger ecosystem
over time where everybody benefits.
- If we could just linger on the '90s, (laughs)
so you said Bulletin Boards, maybe you can explain
what that's like and also explain the birth of the internet,
what that was like?
What was the internet like in the '90s?
- So the internet is a funny thing.
It started out as this Defense Department research project
called the ARPANET,
the Advanced Research Project Agency Network.
And it's kind of like this secret thing.
That became more and more open
as they connected universities.
Universities connected to the internet in the,
you know, mid 1980s.
And so if you're at a prestigious institution
with access to computers, you could get on there.
But as a consumer, back then we had these modems, you know,
this thing you plug into your phone line
and it dials up on phone number
and then, you know, it sends wild sound effects
over the telephone line
to send digital signals back and forth.
And these were really slow three, you know,
the first modem I had was 300 bauds.
That means 30 characters per second of data.
So you're like sitting there watching a sentence
like slowly emerge character by character
as you're going online.
But you know, that's how we got online
and we talked with each other.
So you dial up to a local Bulletin Board,
it'll be run by a person.
Usually they have a computer or two sitting in their kitchen
or something that's running the Bulletin Board
and they have a small community
of a few hundred users all competing
to connect to that one phone line.
It was often busy and you couldn't get in.
And the more popular Bulletin Boards were hardest to get to.
But you had all kinds of communities develop,
you know, and you could see like there was
the programming communities
where people talked about programming.
There was the news and events, you know, community.
I lived in the outskirts of Washington DC
so that was like a big thing.
But then there was like the pirate community
where they're sharing pirate at Apple II games
and you know, very different community ethos
and mantras out there.
But all, you know, all really nice and also very small.
These Bulletin Board couldn't grow to the size of Facebook
'cause your phone line couldn't take that many calls.
And, you know, then later in the 1990s,
the internet which had been fostered in these colleges,
that started opening up for the public
and anybody could connect to it.
And suddenly the world took on life of its own.
It became much, much easier to reach global audience faster.
- And you would start shipping games to the internet,
which is a bit of a crazy thing to do
because you're supposed to have like a, you know,
a physical copy,
but to post on the internet is pretty innovative.
Even shareware is pretty innovative.
- Yeah, yeah, it's been a funny transition
for the game business.
You know, Epic started out making shareware games
distributed digitally,
but you know, as the first 3D games took off,
like "Wolfenstein" and "Doom" from id Software
and then Unreal from us, took off, you know,
to reach a huge audience of billions of users,
we had to go into retail stores.
So we worked with a retail publisher and they made a box
and they put CD ROMs in the box .
And you know, then the world started transitioning
back to digitally, like,
and that transition didn't start well, right?
The initial transition of gaming to digital
was all but BitTorrent, all piracy.
And the other horror stories about games that would,
you know, sell like 100,000 copies
but have 2 million users
'cause most people pirated it.
And then, you know, Steam came along
and introduced digital distribution
and made digital distribution of legit games so convenient
that most players moved away from piracy towards that.
And you know, their practices followed by others
and the early digital industry took form.
- Yeah, it's fascinating.
I mean, pirates do lead the way for innovation. (laughs)
The same as the story of Spotify.
You basically, I think most people when they derive value
from things like video games,
want to pay for those video games,
they just want it to be easy.
And so the same thing with music with Spotify.
But maybe just staying on the '90s,
they're gonna be a lot of indie game developers
will listen to us talking today.
Can you go back to that mindset
and try to derive some wisdom
and advice to those folks when you were just
a solo developer, maybe just a small group of people
creating your early games
that eventually became this huge gaming company.
But in the early days,
what were you going through?
What were the ups and downs?
What did it take to sort of stay strong and persevere?
- Well, you know, one of the critical things
that Epic always worked hard to do was
to make something different that nobody else was doing.
And to try to satisfy a small audience
rather than competing globally
with the game juggernauts.
You know, back in the 1990s, Epic was new,
but Electronic Arts and Activision
and the other big publishers had been around for a decade.
And they were huge companies.
It had giant retail distribution networks.
You know, if I tried to make a game
and then convinced them to publish it,
I doubt I could have had a chance.
And I doubt even if I made a successful game,
that I would've made much money from it,
though they might have.
And you know, so the really unique angle to Epic
then was shareware.
And that was just the idea
that if we distribute our game differently,
then we can reach a much larger audience
than these bigger competitors
by virtue of this first episode of the game being free.
You know, it was kind of the advent of
what later became free to play.
And the logic of that is just as true now as it was then.
If the thing is free and anybody can get into it,
then it's kind of spread from friend to friend
as people bring, you know, their real world friends
into the games they're playing
and, you know, have the opportunity
to build up a community around that.
You know, so the other lesson there was just minimize
the friction of people getting into your game.
Make it easy to get into and make it fun.
And I think the other, well I was very fortunate,
"ZZT" was a funny game.
It was not like, much like any other game,
it was had much worse graphics
'cause it was all just text characters, smiley faces
and, you know, other Greek letters
and things participating in this game simulation.
They were kind of iconic representations of characters
rather than real ones.
And you know, this was decades into the age
of real graphical games with interesting graphics.
And so it wasn't even trying to compete in that area,
but it was able to compete in a different area,
which is that, you know,
it wasn't just the three games I'd made
and shipped as a trilogy that were successful
and drove the success of the product.
It was the fact I released an editor
and there's a whole community around it.
And you see that trend is repeated itself.
Like there was know "ZZT" was one of it.
Before that there was
"Bill Budge's Pinball Construction Set,"
that was a 1980s Apple game
that let users build their own pinball tables.
And since then you've had
some of the world's most successful games follow that path.
Like "Minecraft," you can build your own stuff.
"Roblox", now "Fortnite Creative"
and underwriter for "Fortnite."
You know, games that become platforms for other people
to build stuff was a real opportunity.
You know, I think the big thing to realize
as for indie developers right now is like there's massive,
massive competition in every major genre.
And it's very unlikely unless you just happen
to be the world's best at a particular thing,
that you're gonna release a game
in an existing highly competitive genre and win.
A much better chance of success
is in releasing something that hasn't been done before.
Being really unique and reaching an audience,
even if big or medium size or small, reaching an audience
and becoming really popular with that.
Making some money from it and being able to reinvest
and then expand towards your ultimate dream.
You know, I think the one shot go from idea
to commercial success at massive scale is a lot less likely
than the multi-step process of continually build better
and better stuff over time
until you get into a position of excellence.
- And constantly try to do something
that others aren't doing.
- Yeah, that's right.
'Cause if you look at every market,
there's a few markets where the current leader
came late to the space,
usually because the prior leader failed to horribly.
But most of the time the, you know, the company
that's succeeding and winning in a market is the first
or second entrant there.
They've just continually buoyed their success.
- Great advice and fascinating.
But on a human level, was it lonely?
Was it scary you sitting there as a developer?
- I'd say it was the opposite of lonely
because, you know, the thing that spurred me
to actually release this was seeing kids playing the game
in my neighborhood and having fun.
I mean like, this is really good.
And seeing them enjoying it and laughing
and pointing at the screen and, you know, getting together
and just wanting to play more.
- [Lex] That's awesome.
- Yeah, and the human element was always pervasive,
you know, because I did not only receive orders,
but people would actually write letters.
You know, we wrote letters back then in the 1990s.
People would say how much they're enjoying the game
and how their kids were playing the game
and so on and so on.
So, you know, they felt very connected.
And you know, I think a lot of businesses have
to make scary decisions
because you're spending, you know, potentially
all of the money you have to take a shot at something
that you're not sure will succeed.
I was very fortunate starting a business like this
because it didn't really need any capital.
The capital is, well,
the several thousand dollars in computers I'd bought
by mowing lawns. (laughs)
And it wasn't much risk if that hadn't succeeded,
I guess I could have figured out
how people get mechanical engineering jobs and pursued that.
But once it took off and once the orders started coming in
and people started writing letters saying
they're enjoying the game, I knew I was gonna go all out
and try to build a company there and succeed.
And that was like gonna be, you know, my big goal.
- So I'm sure people know,
but Epic Games was created in 1991
and went on to transform the gaming industry several times,
one of which is Unreal Engine.
So let's talk through the origin story of that.
You said that when "Wolfenstein" and "Doom" came out,
that changed everything.
So take me to that moment.
- Yeah, that was a very interesting time.
Epic had, after my first couple of games
that had recruited developers, you know,
usually college students, high school students
who are just working on their own, had real skills
but didn't have an outlet for their work.
Epic had been matchmaking the best artists
and programmers together from all over the world.
Like "Jazz Jackrabbit" was Cliff Bleszinski,
a high school kid in California,
who had made a really cool adventure game
together with Arjan Brussee,
a demo coder from Holland
who would make amazing graphical stuff
and had built a 2D game engine and connected them together
and a musician Robert Allen in California.
And they, you know, by telephone and modem and so on,
we were building these little 2D games
and having quite a lot of success.
You know, there were a bunch of people making
thousands of dollars a month while they were still students
and royalties from the games.
The Epic was kind of producing
and by coordinating people and publishing through shareware.
And that was all going great.
The company had a little office
and we were, you know, copying floppy disks
and mailing them out.
But when "Wolfenstein" came out, we realized like
the future of gaming is gonna be 3D.
There had been a lot of experiments in 3D before
that hadn't been great.
You know, there were 3D renderings of mazes
that were not in real time
and you're always looking north, south, east or west.
And then there were vector graphics
with little wire frames moving around and things.
But you know, "Wolfenstein" was the first game
that was fast enough, you know,
running at 30 frames per second.
It really felt immersive.
It felt like you were there,
like you were, you know,
in this castle Wolfenstein fighting Nazis.
And that was a really amazing and immersive experience.
3D graphics were pretty primitive then,
id Software followed shockingly fast with "Doom",
which was much, much more capable 3D engine,
which had, you know, stairs
and though it was still what we saw,
2.5D it was environments
that were very realistic textures that were very realistic.
You know, a form of lighting that was approximate
but incredibly realistic
and just such great artistry and sound effects.
It feeled completely visceral and real.
You know, you might look at it today from a,
you know, point of view of a modern, you know,
game player with, you know, 20 teraflops of computing power
in your device
and say, "Oh, that's not very impressive."
But it was amazing at the time.
- I mean, for me, just sorry to pause on that.
I think "Wolfenstein" was one of
the most amazing moments of my own life.
Just being able to, like you said,
in real time move about a three-dimensional world.
I just remember just moving around
just in like, what is that feeling like?
I mean, you feel transported into another world.
- You feel that you're there, yeah.
And especially when you turn the lights down in your room
and you turn the sound up on your speakers
and it'll scare you. (laughs)
and you'll feel like, you know,
that fireball that's coming at you is gonna kill you.
That was an amazing time
'cause we hadn't experienced that before.
There was nothing like that.
You know, you'd watch a movie,
a scary movie or whatever, you know,
it was just this thing that was happening.
This was you, this was you in a 3D world.
- So how did that change Epic,
this realization that the future of gaming
is going to be 3D?
- Well, at first I was really depressed, I think
(Lex laughing)
because the wizardry of "Doom" especially was so incredible
that I gave up on programming for like six months.
I was like, "I won't be able to compete with this.
I have no idea what we're gonna do."
We just keep making 2D games
and hope that the business goes on.
But like, that was the nature of Carmack's wizardry.
He had done things that were like,
not just one innovation leap ahead,
but like a dozen simultaneously,
interplaying in a way that you couldn't pick them apart
into their component pieces.
But funny thing happened,
Michael Abrash, long timer in computer graphics
that wrote a book on the techniques
for 3D graphics and texture mapping.
And he wrote some articles
in one of the programming magazines of the day
and explained it and showed assembly code
to do texture mapping, you know,
drawing these 3D graphics on the screen.
And it was actually really simple stuff.
I was like, "Oh, I can do that." (laughs)
And you know, so a bunch of us Epic independently went off
and started writing our own 3D graphics code
to figure it out.
And we found at one point we had a number of people
dabbling in this, doing different parts of it.
And at that point we decide, okay, this is 3D graphics
and 3D gaming is gonna completely change the world.
We need to go all in on this.
And so we took the best people
from our best 2D game development teams
and put them all together to make a 3D game.
We didn't really know what we were doing at the time.
None of us had ever shipped a 3D game
and most of us were still learning,
but everybody was like trying different disciplines
to see what they were best at.
And it was a combination of a bunch of people
who came together to make Unreal.
I'd initially volunteered to make the 3D editor
for the thing, and James Schmaltz
who had made "Epic Pinball."
"Epic Pinball," now that wasn't a crazy game.
This was one of the 2D shareware games.
He made it while he was in college
and he was making like $30,000 a month from, you know,
the royalties from this game
because everybody had wanted an awesome pinball game,
it was massively successful.
But he was a multidisciplinary person.
He wrote the code for the game, the art for the game,
and did basically everything.
And the code was 30,000 lines of assembly language.
(Tim and Lex laughing)
And so he was initially gonna write the 3D engine
and I was gonna write the editor
and he sent me his code
so I could integrate into the editor.
It was like just a giant pile of assembly code.
I was like, "Hmm, why don't I just write this myself?"
And so James instead started going off
and building 3D models
and 3D animations using the tools at the time.
And so Cliff, who had done a lot of design work
and built the level on "Jazz Jackrabbit" went off
and started learning basics of level design.
And so I was writing this editor
and Cliff Lesinski was customer number one for it,
starting to go off and build levels.
And James Schmaltz was drawing awesome creatures,
sending them to me.
I get them implemented in game.
And then we brought an animator to bring them into life
and we brought in, you know,
more and more people until
at the peak of Unreal 1 development
we had about 20 people working on,
which was a huge team for the time
and was really stretching Epic finances
nearly to the breaking point.
We barely survived
and almost ran out of money a number of times,
but somehow we always pulled through.
And it was a crazy project
because it was three and a half years of development
in a game that we always thought was six months
from shipping. (Tim and Lex laughing)
You know, it was like a, you know, three and a half years
of 70 or 80 hour weeks for most everybody
working on the project,
not even knowing what problems we'd need to solve next
because we were so immersed in the current ones.
- Were there moments when you were losing hope
that this might take too long
and the company will run outta money?
- We were always very financially stressed,
so I was continually worried about that.
I had total confidence
that we'd work out all the technical and artistic problems
'cause yeah, we knew the pieces
and it was largely a matter of typing code in
and solving some problems.
And kind of like we knew we could ship a version of it.
And the thing that was continually
really interesting was the ongoing discovery of
new techniques as we went.
You know, 'cause at the time "Quake" had shipped,
it had a little bit of dynamic lighting.
Unreal really pushed dynamic lighting much higher
than anybody else had done before.
Even colored dynamic lights
with some shadow casting capabilities,
statically or moving lights without shadows.
And figured out how to do volumetric fog
so you could have foggy areas that were full of lights
and you get the kind of glow of the lights
standing out in the fog
and affecting the appearance of the level.
A whole lot of amazing techniques came together to build
a game that, you know, made a number of leaps
ahead of the state of the art at the time.
Yeah, it was really crazy,
but like, I think most companies
wouldn't have survived that,
but the sheer talent of the people involved
made it possible.
Epic has often done things that
most companies would've failed at and we succeed.
Like, not because of awesome management or awesome planning
or awesome financing, but because of the sheer talent
and willpower of the people involved to make it happen.
- What about the interdisciplinary aspect of it?
Like you said, sort of artists, engineers
or programmers, designers, all of them working together.
What was that the 20 people,
What was the dynamic there, like working insane hours?
Like what was it like to sort of make a team like that
work together well as an orchestra
to actually deliver the game?
- Yeah, that's one of the really unique things
to exist in gaming.
Not in normal big tech companies, which are just engineering
and business driven,
but gaming really does require all the best people
across all the creative disciplines working together.
And, you know, Epic had grown organically
by recruiting people with awesome talent.
We always had a limited budget we could never pay to hire,
you know, bid up people's salaries
and hire them away by paying them more.
We just had to find awesome people who were
at the beginning of their career and put them together.
And, you know, so everybody was very new to this
and didn't have any assumptions about how companies worked.
And so, you know, you put all these people together
and, you know, it was really a constant interplay of talent
as people were learning how to work together as a team.
Nobody had management experience.
Most people hadn't chipped at a game
before they worked with Epic.
And we were figuring out as we went,
but it was a constant iterative cycle.
You know, we'd make several new versions
of the game every day.
Be a new compile, introduce a new feature
or fix some bugs, get to the artist,
artist improve their levels, continue building stuff,
and then we see what they're doing in their levels.
Like, ah, I see what you need now.
We'd constantly be improving the tools
and just the iterative process
and the speed at which that improves products
is the critical element to success in games.
The slower the iteration cycle,
if you make a build every week
and you go through one iteration every week,
you're gonna be way, way, way worse by the end
of your project than a game company
that makes, you know, new stuff every day.
And that was the magic that happened together.
And there was really nothing but passion
and everybody's individual dedication to it
that made it work.
- I heard you still program,
but how much programming were you doing back then?
You mentioned the hours, probably insane hours.
So like, it'd be almost fun to talk about your setup set up.
What a day in the life of Tim Sweeney in the '90s
when you were building Unreal look like?
- Well, we'd all gravitated towards
a work schedule that maximized productivity
and that usually meant waking up late.
I get to like, usually get to work around noon
and usually work till like 2:00 AM or so 3:00 AM sometimes.
And, you know, I didn't have anything else going on
in my life,
so usually just work and sleep and occasional eating
and yeah, I found I always needed eight or nine hours
of sleep a night.
Without good sleep, I would just become a zombie
and wouldn't be nearly at my best.
So I always needed to get sleep,
but I didn't need anything else going on.
So the programming itself was so energizing and drawing.
Yeah, so it was a, you know, three and a half years of that
during the project.
Mostly spent programming, I'd say probably 60 hours a week
of programming, five hours a week of coordinating
with other people and iterating
and you know, sitting down with them
and looking at what's going on and screen
and figuring out what they needed.
Maybe five hours of business stuff, you know,
there's a good division of labor then.
I didn't have a big executive team,
but it was like basically myself running the technical
and development part of the company
and Mark Rein running the business part of it,
doing deals and, you know, maxing out his credit card
and going around the world
bringing in sources of revenue to keep the company funded.
- What programming language, are we talking about C?
Because you mentioned there's this pile of assembly,
what was your decision in choosing
the programming language
that Unreal Engine would be written in?
- I'd grown up learning with Pascal as my favorite language.
In order to just get maximum performance
and get the latest operating system features
I had to move to C for my second game, "Joel of the Jungle,"
well, Nintendo style platformer.
And so when I started Unreal Engine, it was
on 16 bit Windows using the C programming language.
And over the course of the first year
it moved to 30 terabit one,
you know, 30 terabit, you know, using these Doss extenders
and then using Windows NT.
And I moved to the C++ language
and just because it simplified the code so much.
Went from a really complicated pile of code
to a much simpler one making that transition.
And so almost the entirety of Unreal Engine development,
about two and a half years of it was all on C++ 30 terabit,
completely stay of the art then,
like 30 terabit protected mode
was kind of a magical thing having come from the days
when computers were much less reliable
and crashed all the time.
- Yeah, and turned out to be a pretty good bet
'cause C++ out of all those languages
ended up being the dominant sort of
performance oriented language that survives to this day.
- Yeah, yeah, it's because it solves
all the problems at scale,
often through manual pain, but always solves them.
And yeah, a lot of other languages do better
and a lot of like theoretical aspects
and are better for some usage cases,
but you can't do everything
and that's really very limiting.
- All right, so ridiculous questions,
but like, did you have one monitor, two monitors?
Were you picky on the keyboard?
Were you picky on the chair?
What are we talking about?
Let's paint a picture.
- Okay, I went through a big transition there.
So I started out being pretty lazy.
I'd had a bunch of, like, I bought used computers
'cause you'd often get them at half the price of a new one.
They'd be good enough.
So I had this old 46 I was developing on,
I guess it was a 15 inch monitor at the time it was all,
it was a poor workstation set up,
but it was very economical.
And so as we started on Unreal, I realized that
like I had to write a ton of code.
I had to write absolute maximum productivity.
So I had to rearrange my entire life
around delivering maximum output.
And so at that point I realized like actually spending money
on getting good equipment was a good investment.
And we're not talking about millions of dollars here,
or billions if you're building a GPU farm.
We're just talking about buying some basic hardware.
And so I bought the biggest CRT you could buy at the time.
'Cause this was a CRT or it was 24 inches,
it weighed like a hundred pounds. (laughs)
I had back pain for a week after I installed it,
but it got me 1920 by 1200 view
- Wow, nice state of the art.
- In 1996, that was pretty cool.
So I'd upgraded to a 90 megahertz Pentium (indistinct)
programming on that.
It was on the 90 megahertz,
these were the main consumer computers at the time.
And I'd optimized the Unreal Engine software render on that,
which was, you know, the Pentium was
the first super scaler architecture in consumer computing.
It could run up to two instructions at a time.
And if you wrote your assembly code very carefully,
you could get absolute maximum throughput.
You know, so I'd gotten my texture mapping code down
to six CPU cycles, comprising 11 instructions.
And, you know, that was required
for every pixel on the screen.
And that was just enough performance to deliver that.
But Dell came out with these new workstations
and Intel I just launched the Pentium Pro,
the first out-of-order processor.
And so I like basically bought the absolute maximum
configuration that money can buy.
It costs $7,000.
I had a gigabyte of memory in 1996
and a 200 megahertz CPU. - [Lex] Wow.
- So it like tripled the speed of compiles
and just made me massively more productive.
So that's what I was using
throughout Unreal Engine development and chipped with that.
- By the way, people in the '90s would've been blown away
by this workstation. (Lex laughing)
I love it, yeah, yeah.
In writing, were you considering the hardware much?
Was there a sense like, so you know, for people
who don't know on Unreal Engine rendering,
I guess is all software doesn't use the hardware,
but were you trying to optimize, as I understand,
maybe you can correct me, but like were you trying
to optimize to the hardware at all?
- Well, at the time,
so we did most Unreal Engine development
before the first real GPUs came out.
And, you know, the 3D effects Voodoo 1.
The first GPU actually delivered serious performance
compared to software rendering.
The first GPU that was really gainful came
into the development and we supported it really quickly,
but it was not the target all along.
And so development was focused on just building,
there are two parts of the engine, right?
There's all of the gameplay systems
that manage the simulation and physics and so on.
That's all written in very high level C++ code
and maintainability is as much of a goal as performance.
You know, because we had to build massive amounts
of systems over time.
But one thing that was really bottleneck was graphics.
You know, the cost of rendering a single pixel
was really high.
And so you had to do everything you possibly could
to optimize the rendering of pixels on screen.
And you know, so we were talking about how many CPU cycles,
you know, and you say your CPU runs at a gigahertz
or whatever, it's a, you know,
a billion instructions per second.
How many instructions do you need to run
to get APIX on screen?
And so there was a constant challenge to optimize that down.
And you know, there was also competition
among all of the graphics programmers
who often send the emails,
you know, like bragging to each other about
what new technique they've discovered, you know,
to try to get the cost down.
And Abrash's original articles took like 12 CPU cycles
to render a pixel and you know,
everybody else had figured out how to get it to like
down to six or sometimes even four cycles.
And, you know, that involved lots of different trade-offs
of caching and memory hierarchy and so on.
It was just like a magical time
where a human could actually understand exactly
what the CPU was doing under the hood
and could write code that exactly targeted that.
And that's largely lost now.
When we talk about optimization and software now,
it's largely about heuristics
and statistically your, you know,
this memory access is likely to hit the cache
and you know, this algorithm is faster than that algorithm
because CPUs now have such advanced out-of-order execution
that you really can't micromanage what's happening
on an instruction by instruction basis,
you can only manage the aggregate performance of code.
And so there's kind of this lost art.
Some people miss it, some people don't,
in which the programmer had absolute control
over the machine and could work miracles
in special cases if you tried.
- It seems like there's still value to that art
when it comes to GPUs and ASICs.
So basically trying to understand
the nuances of the hardware
and how to truly, truly optimize it,
whether it's for machine learning applications
or for ultra realistic real-time graphics applications.
Is that true?
- Yeah, that's absolutely so.
You know, the optimization problems have just moved around.
In a system like Nanite,
the virtualized micro polygon geometry system
that Brian Karis, a brilliant engineer with Epic built,
was just one of those multi-year optimization efforts that,
you know, required him understanding everything
from the highest levels to the lowest levels of the hardware
to figure out how to,
you know, make this breakthrough technique work in a way
that was actually maximally performant on GPUs.
- And so Nanite is the system will jump around in time
that takes us to today with Unreal Engine 5.
It's the system that does the geometry?
- [Tim] Yeah. - So rendering
the world sort of geometric, there's many layers to this.
We'll probably sneak up to each of those,
but one, you have to actually create the geometry
of the world around you
and do that in real time and really efficiently.
And there's a bunch of different ways
to optimize that.
Can you just speak to it?
- Yeah, you know, with the advanced art tools we have today,
it's really easy to create a scene
with billions of polygons.
The hard part is how to render it efficiently
because you can't render billions of polygons in a frame.
Basically you wanna render an image
that's indistinguishable from the full detailed geometry
if you rendered it at ridiculous cost.
And so the challenge is how to simplify every component
of the rendering, you know, the geometry, the lighting
and so on down to real-time techniques.
They're efficient, they capture a realistic view
of what's around you.
And so when an object is up close to you,
you want to render it with a lot more polygons
than when it's far away.
But one of the cool principles of f max
is the Nyquist sampling theorem that says
if you're trying to reconstruct a signal, there's a limit
to the amount of data you need to bother capturing.
If you wanna render a texture at a certain resolution,
then you never need more than twice the pixels
than in the texture that you have on the screen.
And that, you know, that's called the Nyquist limit.
And so one of the challenges of computer graphics
is given the need to render objects
at extreme closeup distances and extreme faraway distances,
you always want to be able
to generate the right amount of geometry
so that you have enough to be indistinguishable
from reality, but not any more than necessary.
And you know, with geometry, the idea is that
if you render two triangles per pixel, you should get
an image that is indistinguishable
from thousands of triangles per pixel.
If you render less than two triangles per pixel,
you're going to start to see visible artifacts of the loss.
And GPUs have this amazing hardware
in a lot of different pipelines,
but it's all very fixed function.
There's pixel shader hardware,
there's geometry processing hardware,
and then there's triangle rasterization hardware.
And one of the limits of GPUs
is that the triangle rasterizers
are built for pretty large triangles.
If you're building a triangle
or rendering a triangle with 10 pixels,
that's pretty efficient.
But if you're building or rendering a triangle
with one pixel, it's very inefficient.
So one of the breakthroughs Brian made was
to design an entire pipeline
for avoiding the rasterization hardware in the GPU
and just going straight to pixels
and calculating what should be done with that pixel
as a result of some ray tracing
and geometry intersection calculations
done in a pixel shader.
So instead of using the triangle pipeline,
we're just using pixel pipeline
and... - Wow.
- [Tim] Getting a better result.
- Because of the limitations
of the triangle rasterizer in the GPUs, that's fascinating.
Because as you described, you need tiny triangles
for the detail, for the stuff that's up close.
I mean, this might seem obvious to people,
but it's not just stuff up close.
It's like, depends where you're looking,
like the human eye and the human focus
and the human attention mechanism
defines how much detail you wanna show
because the thing that the human is likely to be
giving attention to, you want that
to be super high resolution.
And everything else, including due to distance,
can have less geometry and less texture,
less information in it.
- Yeah, yeah, that's right.
But there's a lot of challenges like that.
It turns out it's a lot easier to render one frame
that looks perfect than it is to render a, you know,
a series of frames in motion that look perfect.
A lot of the problems with the earlier algorithms
that aspired to do the sort of things was popping.
You know, you'd be running some number of triangles
for a while and then you'd switch
to a different number of triangles
and you'd see a visible transition
and screen would look like it got shaken up.
You know, it's a disturbing artifact
that distracts you from the game.
And so one of the magical trade-offs of Nanite was how
to avoid all of the visible transitions
and get them down to a point
where though they exist statistically,
they're not really perceptible
to a person looking at it.
- You look at something like Nanite, I mean,
there's a nice blog post,
there's nice descriptions about the details,
but you can tell even under the details,
there's just incredible engineering that goes on.
It's so cool.
It's so cool how underneath this,
you know, the actual experience
of beautiful detailed scenery,
there's just incredible engineering
to bring to you simulation, ultra realistic simulation
of reality in real time.
Like lights changing everything.
And then, you know, it just takes you back to
that feeling I had with "Wolfenstein", but like more,
and you can completely lose yourself in that world
and you would forget that this real world exists.
What is the real world anyway, you know?
So it's that coupling of great engineering
and great storytelling
in terms of just feeling is super cool.
It's great to know, it's great to know
that these teams behind it.
And it's cool that you're also releasing
a bunch of details around it.
At least for folks like me.
It's inspiring to see.
So Unreal Engine is this fascinating creation.
It's a big, bold, crazy bet that you made.
Maybe it's good to actually explain what Unreal Engine is
for people sort of outside this world.
I would say it transformed the gaming industry,
but that was a big bet in 1995
that most of the effort would be on creating
the gaming engine, not the game.
- Yeah, Unreal Engine is a big bundle of code and tools,
a huge software package
that provides all the functions you need to build
any sort of a 3D graphics application.
Game developers use it to make games
and that's the predominant use.
But it's also used in Hollywood film
and television production to create 3D scenery in real time
for production sets to do pre-visualization.
It's used by car makers to visualize their cars
before they're constructed or manufactured.
It's used by architects to preview buildings
before they're made and industrial designers of all sorts.
And it provides, you know,
all of the 3D simulation features you need
both for creating highly realistic 3D graphics,
but also physics and interactions
between objects and making things happen
like you might see in the real world.
And supports a huge variety of styles
from Pixar stylized movies to cel shading to photorealism.
And it can be used for anything
that needs real-time 3D graphics.
- Including humans that populate
those three dimensional worlds.
And we'll probably talk a bunch of the details
involved in the process of creating ultra realistic humans
because we humans care about how other humans look
and how they convey emotion
and express how they speak, all that kind of stuff.
But so yes, it's the 3D objects that are static,
the 3D objects that are dynamic
and on the dynamic front,
including humans that are ultra dynamic.
So all of that, you have to create this engine
that simulates that world.
This beautiful world that we know and love.
Okay, but you know, you're early so
you see "Doom" and you're trying to create this world
and trying to create an engine
that would not just power "Unreal" the video game,
but future video games.
So how do you go about it?
What are you thinking and that,
I should sort of linger on that,
that is a crazy bet that we're going
to build an engine as a company.
- Yeah, well you know, the philosophy began with "ZZT"
and continued onward.
We're not just building a game for players to play,
we're also building tools that could be used
for building that game or any other game.
And catering to all the artists
and designers who had used the tool.
And so that philosophy started,
it's a very early parts of Unreal development.
I was building the tools for, you know,
level designers like Cliff Bleszinski
and artists like James Schwaltz.
And you know, as we began marketing the game
thinking it was six months away,
we were constantly releasing screenshots
and things like that.
Other companies started calling us
and saying they wanted to build 3D games too,
but they didn't have the expertise for that
and they wanted to license our 3D engine.
And this was one of the coolest pivots in Epic's history.
MicroProse called up Mark Rein, our, you know,
Vice President and longtime business guy
and said they wanted to license our engine.
And Mark Rein was like, "Oh, what?
You wanna license what?
An engine, what engine?"
And they explained to him what they wanted to license.
He's like, "Oh that engine.
Yeah, yeah, that's very expensive."
(Tim and Lex laughing)
But this was one of the critical things that kept Epic going
through that three and a half years.
We were starting to license our engine out
to other developers.
MicroProse took two licenses
and we got in half a million dollars from that
and company GT Interactive licensed our engine
to build another game and we got paid for that.
And so we had this revenue stream funding
the development of Unreal Engine from other games
that were being built by other developers.
And because they were the lifeline for the company,
we took the engine business very seriously from the start.
We set up, you know, mailing lists
so that our partners could ask us questions
and all the developers and artists working on our games
were participating in helping customers.
Everybody took that very seriously
'cause it was our funding source.
And you know, that's kind of set this dual spirit of Epic
of boning technology
and supporting game developers simultaneous
with building games and supporting gamers.
It's continued onward and just grown over time.
- Can you just go back to that, you programming,
what are some interesting technical challenges
you had to overcome?
You mentioned dynamic lighting, like create, you know,
create this three dimensional world
and try to figure out the puzzle of how you actually
do that at a time when nobody, Carmack and you (laughs)
doing this kind of thing.
It's a totally open wild west.
So what are some interesting technical challenges
you had to try to solve?
- There's a lot, some of them are visible on screen
and some are behind the scenes
and still require a lot of innovation.
All the graphical techniques
were really interesting challenges
and Unreal Engine in those early days
went a lot further than the quake engine
and building environments
using constructive solid geometry with a realtime editor.
And that was a really interesting technical challenge.
You know, the idea is building is extremely tedious
if you are only adding objects to the world.
If you wanna build a door, then you need
to add like a dozen different pieces of door frames
and add a bunch of different walls together
to fit together in the right shape.
It sure would be easier if you could just start
with a wall and subtract the door out.
And so we had this way of adding geometry to the world
and subtracting geometry and the engine would perform
all of the calculations on that.
And this is something
that I'd been anticipating was possible for a long time,
but when I finally got around to it,
it took this 30 hour coding session
to like figure out all the special cases of the code
that needed to be implemented to make that work.
But you know, in the course of 30 hours
I got constructive solid geometry up and running.
I started doing a, you know, like handed it
to James Schmaltz the next time we were together
and it's like, "Okay, I think you're cheating here."
So you create a giant Taurus
and then add another giant Taurus interlocked with it
and then subtracted a cylinder from it
and like created this really advanced composite object
with just three operations.
He was like, "Whoa, I can't believe this."
It's like, "Yeah, we figured it out."
And that was cool to see it for the first time,
but it was probably the first time somebody
had done constructive solid geometry in real time.
But it was also a really useful artist tool
that all the artists appreciated immediately,
began making use of.
- Can you actually speak to that, the 30 hour session?
I mean this is not, from everything I know about
computational geometry, doing this kind of thing
from your perspective, that's not easy.
That's, what is it?
The uncertainty, the open questions involved.
I mean even just on the algorithm front,
how to do that efficiently
and then plus the usual programming thing of debugging,
like suffering through the trickiness of it.
And we don't have really,
at that time you don't have the tooling
to really visualize everything that's going on really well.
And you probably like using some crappy editor.
I mean there's just a lot of like friction here.
So the 30 hour session is one that's probably rough.
It's a rough one.
- Your brain works in different ways
and depending on your state, right?
There are some things that require
really working on a problem fresh.
Where you've put together a bunch of logical pieces
and now you just need to write a whole lot of code
to make it all work together.
And, you know, plumb a whole lot of data
between a whole lot of different algorithms.
But, you know, I think our brains
have vastly more horsepower
than we're able to directly access
by thinking of what code to type next.
And you know, after you've been working
for a very long time,
you can get into a sleep deprived state
where you have much, much more direct access
to that low level knowledge.
(Lex laughing)
- That's great, yeah.
- You know, because you know their symptoms
that are well studied of sleep deprivation,
one of them is short-term memory loss.
And so you're working without like
the easy recall of the code you just typed,
but your brain is then freed to think about other problems.
And you know, I built up this intuition
over a very long period of time, you know.
So the foundation for the subject
is the binary space partitioning tree.
This data structure invaded by a computer.
Graphics researcher, Bruce Naylor.
Carmack had picked up on that and had used the technique
in "Doom" to really great effect.
And I'd picked up on that
and Unreal Engine was using this technique
for all of its graphics and rendering,
but it, yeah, it was just additive geometry everywhere
and it had a lot of overlapping polygons
and was pretty inefficient.
So I had the idea that if we had a BSP tree,
there was a really efficient way
to do constructive solid geometry.
And to do that you had to break down the ways
that different pieces of geometry can fit together.
I broke it down into like 14 different cases
and most of them are pretty simple, cranked them out.
Anyways, I got towards the end, you know,
there were some pretty complicated things like,
well how do you deal with coplanar polygons?
They're in the same plane
and pointing in the same direction
versus the other direction.
In what cases should you keep them?
What cases should you eliminate them?
And so on and so on
to create really efficient geometry output.
And you know, just plowing through it, eventually
through mostly deduction, but some trial and error too.
Like sometimes you just have to try the possibilities
and see what works.
Yeah, I cranked it out and it worked
and the next day I came in like kind of weary
and I was like, "Oh wow, this actually did work.
It wasn't just a dream."
- So you're considering the edge cases also.
I mean that's the problem with geometry is like
there's probably just gonna be all kinds of weird polygons
that you have to...
So you're like thinking through,
you're imagining the edge cases
and trying to see how do I not create inefficiencies
in this algorithm while still considering the edge cases,
allowing for the edge cases.
- Yeah, you know, it's pretty easy to write software
that's like 99% correct.
It's the 1% that's the really hard part
and where the devil lies in the details.
- What about like lighting?
Is there other interesting...
- Well the funny answer is like,
we know the laws of physics, so it's actually really easy
to do everything in computer graphics.
But the direct solution of the laws of physics
is immensely so.
And so what we're finding are approximations
rather than complete solutions.
'Cause you need something that's a million times faster
than the brute force answer.
- We should say that the physics of the scene
is you just take a bunch of photons,
bounce them around, that's how light works.
That's going to be very inefficient
because it's a lot of bouncing
and a lot of photons.
- Yeah, yeah, photon tracing is the subject matter
that does brute force calculation of pixels on a screen
from all of the light in the scene.
And it works and it's correct
and it just is an implementation of laws of physics
and it's millions or billions of times slower
than what we do.
But Carmack had figured out how to do
really cool lighting algorithms,
including real-time lighting with objects moving around.
And I hadn't taken it very far.
So with Unreal Engine I'd realized like
we don't have nearly enough computing performance
on our CPU to compute the light of every pixel on the screen
from all of the light sources that affect it.
Yeah, we were at a six cycle texture mapper
and we couldn't afford 30 more cycles for lighting.
And so the answer had to be some approximation.
And the one that Carmack had picked up on
in the "Quake" engine was light mapping.
Instead of calculating all the lighting on every pixel,
what if we like made a big texture
that we placed over all of the walls
in the scene that was like wallpaper.
And what if we say every foot,
we're gonna compute a lighting value
for just that one foot grid on the object
rather than computing it everywhere.
And then what if we just linear interpolate that
over the course of it?
You know, you get a lighting and solution
that actually works pretty well and is fast enough to work.
And so a lot of Unreal Engine's lighting techniques
were based on light mapping.
We introduced colored lighting
so you could have colored light sources.
Then we realized, oh, since we're doing this
and we're doing it on light maps,
we can actually do some pretty expensive calculations,
hundreds of cycles since we're only calculating it
for every one foot of world space rather than every pixel.
And so we introduced a whole bunch
of elaborate lighting effects like torch flickering
and you know, the caustic effects of water
bouncing off of a surface and so on.
And like pulsing lights
and blinking lights and everything else.
And I created a system for compositing them together.
So if you had an arbitrary number of light sources,
they could all do that.
And you know, then I implemented a shadowing algorithm.
You know, if you cast a ray from a point
from a light to a point on a surface
and see if whether it intersects in the other geometry,
if it doesn't intersect and the light hits the object
and if it does intersect
then the light hits something else first
and that pixel on the object should be dark.
So I built a real-time version of this
and it ran at about a half a frame a second.
(Tim and Lex laughing)
So I was running around at half a frame a second,
like shooting out light projectiles
and looking at dynamic lighting, it was like,
"Someday computers will be fast enough
for this, but not today."
So I made a non-real-time version
that precalculate all the lighting
and realized, oh wait, if you precalculated the shadowing
on an object, you can still apply the lighting dynamically
as long as the light's not moving.
So you could do torch flickering with shadows
and you know, figure it out all the cases of dynamic
and static lighting that were actually practical
on a computer at the time and exposed them to artists.
And this was the wonderful thing.
I was just like typing in these old features,
exposing them to artists
and every day they'd find like a dropdown
with some more lighting options available to them
and they'd start using them and they'd do things
that I never thought possible.
And this was always the coolest thing,
as a programmer building an engine,
you might think you know the implications
of the feature you're building, but artists are so clever
that you always find that you've built the capability
of doing vastly more than you ever anticipated as they start
to use combinations of features together
in concert to do ever more amazing things.
- That's the genius of artists is they're given constraints
and within those constraints they create something
you could have never possibly imagined
given the constraints.
That's such a beautiful coupling
between engineering and artistry and art.
- That's right, and it's timeless, you know,
what did the renaissance painters do with paints
and what do the early game artists do with early engines?
You know, everybody's figuring out the capabilities
of their medium and you're seeing a revolution.
- This is blowing my mind. This is so fun.
What about fog? You mentioned fog.
I don't even know, how do you even do fog?
So you mentioned "Unreal," so the first version had fog.
- Yeah, well it was a funny thing.
So this graphics hardware company had just started up
in Finland and they released a screenshot
of what their GPU was doing
and they showed a scene filled with volumetric fog.
She had a foggy room with some light sources in it.
And when that happens in the real world, what you see are
glows around the lights
as the light brightens the fog around it.
But the brightening of the fog diminishes over time
because the fog absorbs some lighting.
And so the further you get away from the light,
the more falloff there is.
And you know, you have a bunch of colored lights
overlapping together in a space like that.
The effect is just absolutely magical.
You know, like being out on a foggy light
with street lamps above.
It's something that's surreal and looked just beautiful.
So I was like, "Oh my God, they figured out
how to do realtime value metric fog.
I have to figure it out myself."
And so that was another like 30 hour coding section.
(Lex laughing) - Nice.
- But like at the core I realized, okay,
what's happening here is we have this lighting function
saying that light at a particular point in space
is like, you know,
falling off with the inverse square of the light,
light the distance from the light source, right?
The inverse square is all from Isaac Newton,
which applies to lighting.
What I had to realize was the way the fog interacted
with the light was that you calculate the view
from your eyes position to a point on the surface
in the world.
It's going through fog and you're accumulating more
and more light as a function of the amount
of light illuminating the fog at that point in time.
And so, well, you know, I'd studied that (laughs)
in mechanical engineering without even knowing it.
That's the line integral, you know,
you have an integral over a line of some function.
Well this is exactly what it's for.
It's for accumulating the values of a function
over a continuous space and time.
And you know, I did a bunch of math
and realized that oh wow, the integral,
and then I looked in a reference book
of all of the integrals and you know,
thankfully people had solved them all.
And I realized the integral of, you know,
this transformed one over R squared turns out
to be solved by the arc tangent of R.
And so, you know,
if you calculate some parameters
based on the position of the eye
and the position of the surface
point you're at ultimately seeing,
then you calculate exactly
how much fog you can accumulate from that.
But of course you can't do that per pixel
'cause that's hundreds of cycles of CPU time.
And so what we had to do is calculate volumetric fog
on something equivalent to a light map,
but calculating fog every square meter in the world.
And so, you know, we had enough performance for that,
built volumetric lighting and gave it to the artists
and they started building magically detailed levels
with volumetric fog and in real time.
And then, you know, decades later
I was talking to one of the engineers
who'd worked on that hardware
and asked about their volumetric fog
and told them how it inspired me to, you know,
figure out how to do it in real time myself.
And I was like, "Oh no, we cheated,
we just rendered it our 3D Studio Max."
- That's awesome. That is so awesome.
That is so inspiring on so many levels.
That you saw that maybe it's possible even if it was
kind of smoke and mirrors
and then you actually made it happen.
It's so inspiring to hear these kind of stories
when there's so much uncertainty
and so many constraints
and you figure out how to bring it to life in real time
and create this world that Unreal did.
Maybe if we could just pause,
since you mentioned John Carmack a few times.
As a fellow pioneer in the game industry at that time,
what do you admire about John?
- John singularly has this intense dedication
to getting the best result from his code
and having absolutely no attachment to passed code.
And some of the legendary things he did,
the end result was an absolute breakthrough
in real-time computer graphics.
Weren't his first try.
They were like his seventh or eighth try
after he'd done something time and time again,
tried it, found a better approach,
thrown out the old one, build it again
and continually re-wrote out his code
until he found the absolute best solution to a problem.
And you know, I think that stands as a lesson
for every programmer to pick up on.
When something is really, really important,
its performance is absolutely critical to the product
or its quality or its capabilities.
Just iterate on it until you've achieved perfection
and don't settle for the first
or second solution is good enough.
- And it's, you know, the result of that,
both you and him sort of define the future of gaming,
of gaming worlds.
It's so beautiful to see.
It's just fascinating.
It's inspiring because like under so much uncertainty,
under so many constraints, you figure out a way
and that, you know, actually continues to this day
because yes, the hardware is improved incredibly,
but in order to create an ultra realistic,
highly dynamic, real-time rendering of the world around us,
it's still really, really difficult.
And there's all these kinds of optimization,
like you mentioned.
Maybe you can speak to that
Unreal Engine 1 journey
from 1 to 5.5 or 0.6 now.
For 30 years you've been creating virtual worlds,
what's it like evolving a game engine
for those 30 years
when the hardware under you
is improving exponentially?
What are some things
that changed and what are some universal truths
that have not changed?
- It's been an astonishing experience.
Nobody 30 years ago had anticipated
that we'd see the performance gains in hardware
that we've actually seen in that timeframe.
It's something like a hundred thousand times
higher CPU performance
between multiple cores and higher clock rates
and more parallelism.
Like, you know, if we had that in aviation,
then we'd be like taking a trip to neighboring stars.
- [Lex] Alpha Centauri, yeah. - Exactly.
And in graphics it's been even more so.
It's something like literally 10 million times more
net usable GP performance
than we had back running on a Pentium 90 CPU
all in 30 years.
And you know, it's really made me appreciate
that over the generations,
some areas of our engine development
have absolutely kept up with technology.
And you know, the rendering team
that works on Unreal Engine
are the real miracle workers there.
Just about every generation of Unreal we've replaced
most of the rendering code and you know,
the different leaders and different points in times
and the different luminaries have built systems
that were absolutely rethought
and optimized for the latest generation of hardware.
You know, Unreal Engine 1 was built for software entering
and then the Voodoo 1 came along late in the cycle
and we had support for it,
but it wasn't fully capable and utilized.
Unreal Engine 2 was about bringing
all the latest GPU hardware acceleration features
to the engine and you know, keeping forward
and honing some new features like vehicles
and a few other capabilities.
And this was in the early GPU era
before GPU had really broken out of, you know,
everybody's expectations of Moore's Law.
But that breakout occurred with DirectX 9
and the capabilities of, you know,
programmable shaders.
Once you had control of writing code running on the GPU
that could color every pixel on the screen.
And that GPU code was literally a factor
of a hundred times faster than the equivalent code
I wrote a few years earlier in the Pentium 90.
And so that DirectX 9 generation was a godsend.
And Andrew Scheidecker,
a longtime Epic luminary wrote the core
of the Unreal Engine 3 render around
real-time pixel shading, real-time lighting,
being able to do dynamic shadows
using several different techniques
and multi-thread the render to support bits of, you know,
the early dual core CPUs that were starting
to show up at the time.
And it was a massive, massive graphical upgrade.
Unreal Engine 4 made a number of improvements
and just continued to add features to give artists
more and more options for lighting
and for geometry that created realism.
But then I think probably our biggest single level of leap
came with Unreal Engine 5
with a Nanite micropolygon geometry solution,
and with Lumen the global illumination lighting solution.
You know, which I think really bridged the gap
from, you know, game-ish computer graphics to,
you know, total observable photo realism
for artists who wanted to create that.
And so that's been the evolution
and the progress on the graphics side
is absolutely astonishing.
As it is on the audio side and a number of other areas.
But parts of the engine also haven't changed
all that much since the version I wrote and chipped in 1998.
You know, the a file management system
has been optimized a number of times,
but it hasn't been completely rethought.
And the networking system, the ways that clients
and servers talk together and negotiate game state
is still an evolution of the thing I wrote.
And you know, it's feeling kind of dated now.
You still see networking bugs in "Fortnite" where like
for some reason when you're spectating you're not seeing
some parameters update.
Well that's because of the lossful nature
of that networking model.
And the biggest limitation that's built up over time
is the single-threaded nature of game simulation
on Unreal Engine.
We run a single-threaded simulation.
You know, if you have a 16 core CPU, we're using one core
for game simulation
and running the rest of the complicated game logic
because single-thread programming is orders of magnitude
easier than multi-thread programming.
And we didn't want to burden either ourselves
or our partners or the community
with the complications of multi-threading.
And you know, over time
that becomes increasing limitation, you know,
so we're really thinking about
and working on the next generation of technology
and that, you know, being Unreal Engine 6
and that's the generation we're actually going to go
and address a number of the really core limitations
that have been with us over the history of Unreal Engine
and get those on the, you know, a better foundation
that, you know, the modern world deserves, given everything
that's been learned in the field of computing
in that timeframe,
- That's a terrifyingly challenging engineering problem.
And it seems like every version of Unreal Engine,
the amazing teams behind it are willing
to just throw away most of the code. (laughs)
And maybe I'm being a little bit too dramatic,
but basically throw away the old approaches
like you mentioned with Carmack
and start again, like with Nanite and Lumen,
just keep optimizing to the current hardware,
but even like rethinking how it's all done.
But going from single-threaded to multi-threaded.
Oh boy, that's terrifying.
And that's in part we'll talk about it,
why maybe you have to rethink
even the programming language that's being used
to rethink a lot of things.
That's fascinating. Can we just stick on Unreal Engine 5?
So I watched a bunch of stuff,
but the state of Unreal in GGC 2024.
(Lex laughing)
Thank you, I was just giggling
with excitement watching some of this stuff,
so just if we can talk about different things here
just to nerd out a little bit.
So people should go watch this video.
They talked about the dirt,
just the ultra realistic,
and this is for "Marvel 1943,"
which is kind of putting the Marvel universe
into Nazi occupied France in the winter.
So there's snow.
And you know, that's a moment in history,
that's a very intense moment in history
and it really creates a feeling and puts you there
and there's so much to that including the snow.
But just, you know, looking at the dirt is a really nice way
to show like how do you (sighs)
add a lot of details to the scene in real time
that like gives this experience
like infinite detail.
Like this is real, this is super real.
And then I think in the talk they describe
what's entailed in the generation of the geometry,
what's entailed in the lighting, all that kind of stuff.
Maybe can you speak about dirt? (laughs)
What are the components for people
who might not know in like creating this ultra realistic,
the texture, the lighting, the geometry, all of that.
Like how Nanite, how Lumen all come together
in this beautiful orchestra to paint in real time
the dirt in Nazi occupied France in 1943. (laughs)
- Yeah, there's a lot happening here on screen
and you know, the real hero of of this image isn't Epic,
it's the artists and technical artists
who work together to build this environment because it,
and the reason we showed it at GDC was it went way, way
beyond what we realized the system was capable of doing.
You know, largely because of their brilliance.
And this is the magic of computer graphics.
There's not one feature that makes this cool.
There's a dozen technical features that each interplay
and because of the ways that they interplay with each other,
it's hard to actually identify
the individual components of it.
One thing that's happening here that's really critical...
Oh yeah, now we're seeing it being turned off is
the lighting happening.
The Lumen lighting system
that's powering the scene is doing different
kinds of lighting calculations at different scales.
This was the work of Daniel Wright following a decade
of moving the state of the art of lighting forward.
But his theory, which was rather controversial at the time,
was that if you have enough levels of lighting calculation,
then you can get everything
global illumination working everywhere
from the absolute highest levels of a scene,
you know, that buildings are casting crack shadows,
all the way down to details like you see on the dirt here,
all working in concert
and without distinguishable boundaries.
So there is a good decade of foundational work there
to make the lighting work.
In particular when you see the very detailed shadows
interplaying between the, you know,
the ice and the dirt there, that's screen space lighting.
There's actually shadow calculation going on,
not based on the world but on the pixels on the screen
because that is the only way
that we could possibly do those calculations fast enough
running them on a pixel shader.
- Yeah, watch this,
watch when you add the objects, when you add the textures,
the different layering all the shadows
that have to be computed.
- Yeah, yeah. - Boy. (laughs)
- That shadowing is the amazing thing.
But you know, the reason that works is counterintuitive.
When somebody first explained it to me, I was like,
"That's really clever, but I don't think that will work."
But it does work
because if you observe the positions of incoming lights
and you know the z coordinates
of the different pixels on the screen, you can figure out
how, you know, geometry there is likely
to occlude other geometry.
And even though it's only an approximation
and not isn't perfect, it looks perfectly good
to the human eye and gives you the subtle shadowing
that you see in a scene like this
that it makes it look highly realistic
and the shadowing influences other things.
There's also, you know,
some really interesting things happening with the color here
and I'm not even sure what's causing, you know,
it looks like color is bleeding from some parts of the snow
onto other parts of the snow.
It looks like there's some subsurface scattering going on.
I'm not even sure if that's being used in the scene.
And then there's a material layering system for laying down,
you know, layers of material, dirt and snow
and other things all making that work.
And then there's the light bouncing off of the geometry,
which is another system for lighting
on top of the global illumination system.
- What about reflections too?
Is that count as the light balance?
So there's a light balancing off of stuff
to light it up in different interesting ways,
but then there's also actually literal reflections
in like we're looking at a puddle in the dirt.
- Yeah, yeah, that's right.
But the engine supports a number
of different reflection techniques.
One is calculating basically textures that reflect,
that capture all the lighting in the scene
and then bouncing that off of texture maps.
So you can see different lights bouncing off
of different pixels in different ways.
And then there's individual lighting
casting reflections off of things too.
And a lot of this is under the control of designers
and you know, one of the things that's yet to do problem
for the future is you don't just like press a few buttons
and this kind of scene magically appears.
This is a lot of work from some highly skilled people,
not only building out this particular scene,
but in setting up the material layers
so that you get the dirt with the ice layered on top
and all the reflections working
and they need to make a number of technical art decisions
to make this work.
And if a novice who hadn't, you know,
worked very hard built the kind of scene like this,
it wouldn't look nearly as good.
So one of the challenges we have is
to make building this kind of quality level
even easier and more seamless and automatic.
You'd like to just build a scene
and say, use this material here
and have this appearance come out of it.
- Yeah, and I mean once you create the scene
you could do things.
I remember where they said like,
"Can you turn off the headlights?"
I forget you could control the lighting.
I mean all of this we should say like, this is dynamic.
So you could change the position of the light,
you can turn on the lights and off the lights,
that's incredible.
So this is all real time.
The geometry, the lighting, the textures,
all of it, real time.
- This is the power of awesome technical art,
three decades of feature development,
and like you have to give credit
also to the 20 teraflops of graphics performance,
that NVIDIA's delivering.
- Thanks NVIDIA. (Tim and Lex laughing)
- 90 megahertz to this, 90 megahertz is 90 megaflops.
This is 20 teraflops. That's a big change.
- That's a lot.
So one of the other things
that they talk about in the presentation is about snow.
So you have to, if you're talking about 1943 Nazi Germany
in the winter, you know,
you have to create a feeling,
one of which is the season, the winter, the cold,
and you can control the, you know,
you have to cover everything in snow.
And here shown is the ability to control
how much snow covers the objects.
So the ability to do that for the artist is incredible.
Like just to control
how much snow is in the scene dynamically like that.
That's cool.
- Yeah, yeah. - That's really cool.
- It's a cool system for material layering
and a dozen pieces coming together here.
You also notice, you know, there's a fogginess
and there's some hot objects emanating fog.
You know, an artist did that,
that didn't just arise automatically.
- So that's called material layering.
So an artist creates the different materials
and are able to like layer the scene with it.
- Yeah, layer materials on top of each other
and see how much of each material should be protruding
in different places with the engine handling transitions
and things like that.
- And that's on top of the sort of the geometry
that creates the structure of the scene
and all the occlusions that have to be computed, man.
Okay, I gotta go to the other one
that was just blowing my mind, which is smoke.
Let me see that, look at that.
- Yeah. Yeah. (Lex laughing)
- Oh, there's a fire,
there's a fire in a trash can with the smoke
and the lighting and the shadows
interplaying on the smoke.
This is real time?
- Yeah, that's all real time.
- What the hell?
How do you do that? (laughs)
How do you do the smoke?
Well there's a really powerful particle system underneath,
it's providing the technological foundations
for this sort of thing.
But there's awesome artistry on top of that
and an awesome physics engine powering it.
It's hard to tell exactly which piece is doing what,
but you have several different particle systems there.
There's one for the fire
and then there's another one for the smoke coming out of it.
The really interesting thing happening
with the smoke here is that it's occluding light.
You know, there's calculation of
how the light should diminish as it travels through smoke.
And so you're seeing the lighting on the smoke
being the really interesting thing.
And there have been a lot of attempts,
but this was the first demo
where I felt like this kind of smoke had really,
it no longer looked like a video game.
It looked like just, you know, a burning trash can,
billowing out dark smoke.
And yeah, it's the artist sophistication.
It's a very, very, very large part of it.
- So yeah, again, it's the interplay between the tooling
and the artist.
But yeah, like I could watch that for a long time.
I mean there's something magical
sitting around a fire in real life
and just watching the fire and the smoke.
I mean humans have been doing that for, I don't know,
hundreds of thousands of years maybe.
And then that same, I was just staring at that
and I wish the people would just stop talking
and I could just watch the fire infinitely.
(Tim and Lex laughing)
And that, I mean that's immersion.
That's like I want to be in that.
I want to sit around that trash can with a fire
and the smoke and watch and maybe warm my...
'Cause I was also feeling cold because of the snow.
You're like, you really get immersed into the thing.
I mean it's so beautiful.
It's true art. It's true art.
It's just really wonderfully done. But, okay.
So I gotta ask you about the humans.
We talked about what's it like to create the scenes,
but you know, creating realistic humans is really tough.
Can you speak to that?
How to create ultra realistic humans?
So you have an actor behind this to convey emotion,
show the nuances and the details of the faces
and maybe this is a good opportunity
to also mention MetaHuman Creator
that's part of Unreal Engine.
- Yeah, that's right.
Humans are by far the hardest part of computer graphics
because millions of years of evolution
have given us dedicated brain systems
to detect patterns and faces and infer emotions and intent
because cavemen had to,
when they see a stranger determine whether they were likely
friendly or they might be trying to kill them.
And so humans, we people in the world
have extraordinarily detailed expectations of a face
and we can notice imperfections
especially perfections arising
from computer graphics limitations,
but it becomes by far the hardest problem.
So the MetaHumans effort is part of a decade long initiative
that Vlad Mastilovic,
the most talented digital humans visionary in the world
has been working on
for generations and generations of games.
You know, serving individual clients
around the game industry for a while
and then joining Epic as part of the three lateral team.
And leading now a worldwide effort to build
all of the technologies required
to make digital humans realistic.
Okay, one part is capturing humans.
And so we built really advanced dedicated hardware
that puts a human in a capture sphere
with dozens of cameras in them taking high resolution,
high frame rate video of them
as they go through a range of motions.
And then capturing the human face is complicated
because the nuanced detail of our faces
and how all the muscles and sinews and fat work together
to give us different expressions.
So it's not only about the shape of a person's face,
but it's also about the entire range of motion
that they might go through.
Capturing one human requires,
you know, a few hours of capture work
in a dedicated environment like that.
Then thousands of hours of processing work to capture
a precise and, you know, real time replicatable version
of that human in the environment.
And so one of the things that
that's done is just capturing an actor
or actress in the real world
and then using them in a video game.
But the much more interesting thing going on is capturing
thousands of humans to form a data set whose goal is
to encompass the entire range of faces in all of humanity.
So, you know, going around every culture, every continent,
every age and every face of variety
and capturing representative people
so the entire range of faces is represented.
And then being able to combine
and merge those together
to enable recreating an arbitrary face
that the system's never seen before.
So you know, one of the ideas is capture giant amounts
of this high precision data
and you use it to reconstruct a face at a consumer level.
Like maybe, you know, take an iPhone photo
of somebody's face and then capture a very accurate
depiction of that, not by synthesizing it then
and there on that device,
but by combining all the known details of human faces
to accurately capture
the most accurate representation of that.
So that's the data problem.
There's a lot of other problems with computer graphics.
You know, there's technology for rendering hair,
which is really hard 'cause you can't render every, again,
we know the laws of physics,
it would be easy to just render every hair.
It would just be a billion times too slow.
So you need approximations that capture the net effect
of hair on rendering and on pixels
without calculating every single interaction
of every light with every strand of hair.
That's one part of it.
There's detailed features for different parts of faces.
There's subsurface scattering
because we think of humans as opaque,
but really our skin is light travels through it,
it's not completely opaque.
And the way in which light travels through skin
has a huge impact on her appearance.
You know, this is why there's no way you can paint
a mannequin to look realistic for a human.
You know, it's just a solid surface
and we'll never have the sort of detail you see.
- We should actually just linger on that.
That kind of blew my mind like thinking through that.
I think I heard that sort of the oiliness of the skin
creates very specific nuanced,
complex reflections and then some light is absorbed
and travels through the skin and that creates,
would it be fair to say like micro shadows or something?
It creates like textures that our human eyes able
to perceive and it creates the thing
that we consider human, whatever that is.
And so like you have to compute both that, the reflection,
how light interacts with the oiliness of the skin
and how it is also absorbed in
and all of that while considering all the muscles
involved in making the nuance expression.
Just the subtle squinting of the eyes
or the subtle formation of a smile.
It's a stupid annoying subtlety of human faces
that you have to capture.
Like the difference between a real smile and a fake smile.
Man, I love human faces.
I love humans in general.
But the way to show like beginning of a formation of a smile
that actually reveals a deep sadness, all of that.
Like when I watch a human face, I can like read that.
I could see that.
Again, this is the engineering and the artist.
You have to have the tools
that in real time can render something like that.
And that's incredibly difficult. But anyway, sorry.
So yeah, so there's a lot of this kind of complexity
in even just the lighting of a face.
- That's right, getting faces right requires the interplay
of literally dozens of different systems
and aspects of computer graphics.
And if any one of them is wrong,
your eye is completely drawn to that
and you find it on the wrong side of uncanny valley.
So the level of perfection needed in this area is vastly,
vastly higher than, you know, world rendering or grass
or any of these other things.
You know, if the shadows on a work of architecture
are slightly wrong,
you're pretty forgiving with that actually.
Your brain doesn't really care that much.
But if anything wrong with the human
it's totally jarring.
- Can you speak more to the creation of digital humans
with MetaHuman, both on the editor side
and sort of bringing it to life side?
It seems like, 'cause I've watched a bunch of videos,
a bunch of individual developers doing it,
it's not too difficult to bring a human to life
using the tooling
that Unreal Engine editor provides.
- There are two main tools.
You know, compared to the old days
where every face was created by hand
by an artist from scratch.
One is a MetaHuman Creator tool for creating faces
where you have a huge number of parameters you can adjust
to create a unique human
by adjusting all the different capabilities of them.
And you can then get that MetaHuman Creator
into Unreal Engine,
and then you can add all kinds of computer graphics features
they're in the engine.
You could add clothing using the cloth simulation system
and you can adjust the hair
and all these other parameters on the thing.
And then there's Metahuman Animator,
a tool for animating a human based on a facial capture,
which can be done on a device as simple as like an iPhone.
And transfers the captured animation to the human you want,
which is not straightforward.
If the actor has one face shape
and the character on screen has another face shape,
the translation that needs to be done
from the actor to the face
is actually really sophisticated and non-obvious.
And if you just applied it literally,
then it would be completely wrong from your point of view.
So those are the main tools that people are using now.
And then when within the Unreal Engine,
then you have a face and you can do
absolutely anything you want to it.
And you could also, you know, if you decide to go outside
of the Metahuman geometry pipeline,
you could build your own face, like, you know, any creature
of any sort, and then use the animation tools to animate it.
But, you know, this is 30 years into a project
that's probably like 50 years in total
to get to absolute photo realism
and controllability for absolutely everything.
So there's vast amounts of work still to do.
And you know, we don't feel like we've solved
the problem at all.
We've just given artists a big productivity multiplier
and a quality multiplier.
But this is not in a state that we would say is done.
- But nevertheless,
I've seen people use it really effectively.
I saw it almost like plugins, maybe external services
where you can get the faces
to approximate the mouth movements
required to speak a thing.
So like that's a really useful feature.
- Yeah, that's right.
When you have an artist or actor in your studio
and you're recording a specific performance,
you can just capture their facial motion and apply it.
But if all you have is a voice recording
or you're generating a voice recording or it's parametric
or procedural or AI generated,
yeah, then you need the system to translate that speech,
not only to movement of the mouth and lips,
but also to facial expressions
and the whole intent.
You know, when we're speaking,
it's our whole face that's active
and emoting in different ways
and it's not just a mechanical motion of the pieces.
- So we spoke a bit about Nanite, so the magic behind
the virtualized geometry system.
But can you speak a little bit to Lumen
and in general what it takes
to dynamically light in all the complicated ways,
the faces, the scenes that we discussed?
Like what are some interesting things to you
that made the magic of it happen?
- Lumen is a system for global illumination.
Being, it's supposed to calculate the interaction of light
with the entire scene in a way that mimics reality.
The first generation of engines that did lighting just said,
well, the light casts light
and the surfaces that hits are lit
and the surfaces that doesn't directly hit are dark.
And that's just all the techniques we have.
So you'd have an area that wasn't hit by any light
being completely black,
but in reality, light bounces
around the entire scene dynamically.
When a light hits a red wall,
then most of the blue and green light is absorbed,
but the red light reflects off
and now is hitting other things.
And so if you have a red wall with a white floor,
light is bouncing off of the red wall into the floor,
and now the floor is being turned red.
And so the entire bouncing of light around the scene
through multiple bounces is the critical challenge
to solve here.
And again, laws of physics are known.
And so the complete solution to this,
it was written down in the 1950s, I think.
The real magic here in Lumen is this system
that Daniel Wright developed over the course
of many years based on ideas formed
over a longer period of time
to calculate the way lighting bounces
around at different scales, ranging from, you know,
the scale of miles or kilometers,
down to the scale of pixels and millimeters.
And to not only calculated at each level,
but integrate it seamlessly at each level
to give the appearance
of completely seamless and accurate lighting.
And previous techniques were highly specialized
and artist had to make a decision for each light
about exactly what it did.
And a lot of the practice with Nanite now
is you build a scene, you place lights in it,
and it just works to make it that much easier.
- Yeah, I mean, we're watching, so I recommend people go
through this blog post, like, look at that so dynamically.
I mean, we should say that,
so there's the indoors and the outdoors,
and to be able to dynamically compute the impact
of outdoor light.
Just look at that.
Look how gorgeous that is.
Just the lighting, like,
we're looking now at an image of a cave.
So external light lighting
the intricate complexity of insides of a cave.
Look at that.
- Light in the real world goes through a lot of bounces
and the effect of it are very, very subtle.
But when they're not there, you miss them.
Often a person can't point out why a scene is wrong,
but they know it looks wrong.
And it's the lack of the subtle lighting cues
that we're seeing here.
- And you know, for great,
'cause we mentioned for great video games,
but also for great films, lighting can make a film
and we're just looking at sort
of a very dramatic lighting of a scene.
Like imagine stepping into the scene,
it's exciting, it's terrifying.
And all of that has to do with light,
the interplay between light and darkness.
It's incredible, it's really, truly, truly incredible.
Like light is everything, and then to put the power
of the tooling in the hands of an artist
that is really special.
- Yeah, the industry's gone through a massive evolution
and there's so many supporting systems to make this awesome.
And always artists.
(Lex laughing)
- We're looking at reflections on smooth surfaces.
Oh boy, oh boy, look at how gorgeous that is.
- Yeah, that's right. - Wow.
- And you have to appreciate,
the algorithms are doing quite a lot here.
You can have a, you know, a scene with a huge number
of not just lights, but also bright objects
that reflect light off of them.
Every one of those has to be captured in the reflections
in order for it to be realistic.
And, you know, you can't calculate
every photon in the scene,
and so you need really detailed approximations.
And that's the field of computer graphics.
It's about increasingly effective approximations
of the laws of physics, which are just totally intractable.
- But the result of that graphics is the feelings
and experience by the viewer.
And it's just to me, as a fan of,
well, let's say beauty in the world,
it's exciting that we can create
that synthetically, artificially via graphics
and that just, it blows wide open
the possibilities of storytelling.
So outside of video games,
a lot of people are using Unreal Engine
for movies, for films.
And big congrats, I saw "Wars is Over" short film
that was made with Unreal Engine won an Oscar.
So you can add that to the resume. (laughs)
So that's huge, you know,
an Oscar winning film made with Unreal Engine.
So what do you see as the future of
the use of Unreal Engine
and creating stories in the film industry?
- Increasing capabilities and productivity.
You know, the limiting factor
in every one of these businesses is cost.
And the more the engine can make their jobs easier,
the more power that brings them.
One of the big revolutions we've seen in Hollywood
is that moving away from doing computer graphics integration
into a human scene with green screens,
to moving to these large LED wall panels,
they're displaying real-time computer graphics
powered by the Unreal Engine.
And that's a massive improvement in quality.
You can recognize the old green screen movies
because the lighting on the characters is just wrong.
And you know, as much as they try to fix it up,
it never really works.
When you're filming in front of a LED panel
with LED light emitters in front of you as well,
the actor not only picks up all the lighting
from the actual natural scene that they're supposed
to appear in the movie, but they also can look around
and see it, and they're aware of exactly
what set they're acting in.
And just the overall end result is that much higher.
It's as much because the actors are able
to do their jobs better seeing the scene they're in
because the technology is enabling
a better lighting calculation
and a better interplay of virtual light
and real world light to make the end result awesome.
- So there's a lot of excitement around generative AI.
What do you think is the future of the interplay
between what a human artist creates
and what an AI system can create in Unreal Engine?
- I think a lot of people in the industry
are overly optimistic about the rate of progress of AI
for video and other things like that.
The real problem is consistency,
like spurting out an image is really high quality,
but with video over the course of seeing, you know,
all the AI approaches have consistency issues
going from one place to another.
And I don't think that those will just be remedied.
Fundamentally AI just doesn't have anything resembling
an understanding of the entire scene they're in,
the entire arc of the movie or plot therein
and the entirety of the world around them
and how it might affect a scene.
Whereas game engines have that
exactly where they need to be.
And so I think what we're gonna see
in the space of world-class high quality productions
isn't just everybody moves to AI
and a large part of the human creatives contributing
to that are obsolete.
I think what we're gonna see is AI becoming
a multiplying force on the power of human creatives,
making them able to create better stuff more quickly
and with higher quality end results.
And I think unlike the fields of generative 2D art
and generative text, I think the future of AI
is much more complex and nuanced.
And I think your interview with Mark Zuckerberg
conducted in VR was a really
good first example of this.
So you did this VR discussion, it was capturing your faces
and then rendering a completely 3D
computer graphics model of your faces.
And then the end result was patched up
by an AI image enhancer that was able to add
an awful lot of the missing subtleties that are lost
by normal computer graphics rendering.
And that's the first step.
You know, you can imagine the output of Unreal Engine
being enhanced by an AI pixel shading post processor
is one thing.
You can imagine creation of objects being enhanced
and especially mashing up high quality objects
that have already been created.
Like Epic's Quixel team went around the world
and scanned tens of thousands of real world objects
at extremely high levels of quality.
They have everything from rocks to trees
to archeological finds and so on.
All captured there.
And we have an awesome library of them
on the Fab content site.
What it's missing is the ability
to create arbitrary amounts of new content.
And you know, I think using data like that
and AI to create completely new trees
that meet your specification from all of the knowledge
that has built up of high quality scanned trees
is gonna be a really valuable thing.
But you know, I don't see this reducing the need
for people or the role of people,
rather, I think it actually is probably an enhancer on that.
I can't help but think when I go on Amazon
and Netflix to watch a movie,
there's awful lot of linear content
and most of it isn't very good
because you know of the limitations of the media
and the budgets and of other things.
If we can use AI as an enhancer on that,
then, you know, everybody's gonna have
even more opportunity than they have now.
And every single technological revolution
has changed the way that people work,
but it's ultimately created more opportunity for people.
And you know, the (indistinct) its predicting
that this might be the last,
but I think just the opposite.
I'm an optimist on this
and an optimist that it's going
to create opportunity for everyone.
- Do you think it would be possible to generate,
so use generative AI to create
dynamic objects like you mentioned trees
in the Unreal Engine world, so create meshes and textures
and empower the creator
to create faster use meta knobs,
like hyper parameters versus very nuanced
where you can control much faster the look of a face,
the look of a tree, all that kind of stuff.
- Yeah, I think that's the central challenge
of the next decade of game engines and AI for,
you know, content creation of all sorts.
Because you have two very different models of the world
that are emerging.
There's the scene graph, the technical term we use
to describe the set of all of the objects in the world
in a 3D world maintained by Unreal Engine
or another engine, you know,
so in the videos you saw, it's the rocks and the trees
and the snow and the bridge
and the people and all of these things.
And each one has enormous amounts of data attached to it.
Some are like texture maps, some are sound files,
some are animation files
and enormous amounts of detail all stored there
in that procedural,
in this precise computer graphics representation
that enables rendering it from any perspective
with any settings and so on.
It's a completely general system
that has complete context
about the state of the world at any point.
And so you can always precisely reproduce it.
If you play the same scene 10 times in a row,
it's always the same.
It's never randomly changing.
You're like, "Oh no, why did it
that this character's face change midstream?"
But it's also, you know, rather limited
because you have to build everything manually
and it's costly and it's time consuming.
It requires expertise.
And then you have this other model of the world,
which is what AI sees or thinks.
You know, if we could peer into what's really happening
in its parameters,
there's something like the mushy connections of neurons
in a brain.
It has a vast amount of knowledge about the world
and about graphics and about images and about people
and about everything else.
It's stored in a human incomprehensible form,
but it can be extracted through queries
like asking it to produce an image from a prompt
or a video from a prompt or whoever.
But the huge problem with that is it's very mushy data.
We don't know how to give it a command
that will give us a precise result.
And if it produces one image one time
and we change our prompt slightly,
it might produce something completely different
and we were unable to art direct it.
And so it's this completely untamed tool.
And I think, you know, when we figure out more
and more ways to merge these
and connect these two together,
you can imagine AI enhancing the process of content creation
in a traditional scene representation.
You can re imagine the scene representation
being cured with AI.
So the AI not only sees a prompt,
but also here's a list of all of the objects in the world
and the characteristics and so on.
It can learn more about how those objects
should move and interact.
And so if you get a constant feedback cycle
going back and forth between an engine and AI,
and I think you can get the best of both worlds,
stable scenes, but also the higher productivity
of being able to get content out
and the ability to like select specific parts of it
and art direct those.
And to have those art directions stick
and be recognized
as part of this permanent scene representation.
- Yeah, I can't wait until AI can operate
not in the space of pixels,
but in the space of scene graphs.
Creating objects in the scene graph,
whether it's like you mentioned audio
or any of the things that you mentioned about
that empower the creator.
Yeah, that's a super exciting future.
I wonder if you could speak to a fear
that people have on this topic of artists,
engineers fear losing their jobs,
being replaced by AI.
Are there words of hope that you could offer them?
- This is certainly the most extreme example of it
because AI is just so far ahead of prior technologies,
but similar fears were had in every other industry.
There's a fear that digital music synthesis
would obsolete musicians.
And there's a very brief period of time
in which songs with digital music instruments,
like there are early mini mugs
and Yamaha synthesizers weren't allowed
to win certain music industry awards
because they weren't considered real music.
And then, you know, over time the people were educated
and realized, oh,
these are just instruments people are playing
and they're controlling them the same way they did before.
There's similar questions about is, you know,
computer art built in Photoshop really art,
or is it just, you know, goofy computer stuff?
And you know, I think nowadays digital artists
have gained respect and I think, you know,
if you look at just the tools that existed in Photoshop,
some of them are pretty sophisticated
and nowadays AI features,
but I think AI is ultimately gonna be another tool
in the artist's tool set.
And you know, I think it's gonna become
a more powerful directable
and human serving tool in the future.
And I think a lot of the alienation comes from the prompt
either being immensely powerful
at giving you an entire creation,
but then being completely unwilling
to let you control the nuances of it.
That feels alienating.
You give it an image, but you're like, you know,
replace this part of it with this thing
or make that object green.
And it just like, it can't do it.
Often it can't be convinced with any number of words
in the prompt.
And that makes it feel like the computer's taken
control away from us, you know, humans and artists
and is refusing to do what we want
and has its own opinions, right?
It feels like a competitor.
Or I think when we have much, much, much more nuanced
control of it and artists can join and just,
you know, like, yeah, let's enhance this object,
do this, do that, do that.
They'll feel it's a, you know, like some of the tools
that exist in Photoshop, which are in some ways compared
to a paintbrush or superpowers already,
AI will come to feel like that too.
And will increasingly serve creators creating
and enhancing a work in a way
that feels just a natural extension of their own, you know,
their own bodies and minds.
- And of course there is a real human pain to layoffs
and there is a hype around AI
and then companies might try to implement AI systems
and then so doing layoff a bunch of folks
and the pain that those folks feel is real.
I think there's always going to be pain
with these kinds of transformation that's happening.
And it's a terrible pain.
Pain in general in the human experience is terrible,
but I think I'm personally excited
by the human AI collaboration
as you've described in this whole process.
So I think if you just keep being open
to using the tools,
constantly trying the cutting edge tools,
how they can make you more productive,
how can they empower you as a creator, as an artist
or as an engineer, I think you're gonna just keep winning.
- Yeah, there's a lot of complicated trends underway
and it can be hard to break them down and distinguish.
And I think a lot of people like the theories
that get the biggest traction on social media
often don't capture the real underlying
mode of forces at play there.
But yeah, I think AI involved in code production
will probably create a net benefit for the need for humanity
to be involved in coding.
It may change parts of jobs,
but I don't think it's gonna obsolete anybody
who's willing to learn new ways of doing things.
And it's always been this way.
And I think that there's also a lot of over hype in AI.
AI is really great at spewing out code that does something
that a million GitHub repositories already do
because it's, you know,
kind of learned the underlying pattern.
It's notoriously hard to get to do something new,
it hasn't been done before,
especially when it's a complex task.
And you know, the bigger amount of code you ask AI for,
the more it leaves you
with just a massive code that sort of works, right?
And that's the problem with code it like 99% works,
but the 1%.
Might be harder to get to 100% with AI
than with hand coding.
And everybody who's looking at this topic should actually
try using the coding assistance on hard problems
and see how they do there.
- Yeah, I think it, for me personally, it makes it more fun
and faster to generate boiler plate code
so I can focus on the harder decisions,
harder big picture decisions
and harder innovative decisions and all that kind of stuff.
And just makes programming more fun for me
because I feel less lonely.
(Lex laughing)
I have like, even when it gives the wrong code,
I feel like, oh, okay, well that's a way to do it.
That's interesting, and then you could talk to it maybe.
Maybe that shows something about the programming experience
that it is in part sometimes a bit lonely.
- The topic of boiler plate code is an interesting one
because like the mere distance of boiler plate code
is a failure of programming language
and of the idea of creating software modules, right?
You know, you ask AI to create a sorting function, great,
now you have another sorting function
that might be buggy alongside the million others
that different people have written.
It would be better to have a sorting function
that's been written and tested and optimized
and everybody relies on it.
And more modular software,
I think will actually reduce the opportunity of AI
because, you know, people doing programming work
will largely be solving unique problems.
They're actually hard problems in themselves
and not just connecting other widgets.
- Yeah, I think as in many cases,
AI will just help improve the human systems
by shining a mirror to ourselves.
I have to apologize for the pothead question ahead of time,
but let's talk about the metaverse broadly.
You've been a big proponent of the idea of the metaverse.
We'll talk more specifically what that means today,
but we've been talking about simulating reality
better and better and better.
(Lex sighing)
So the pothead question is, what does it take
to simulate reality to the level
we see around us today?
How far away from that are we
to simulate this ultra realistic,
immersive fun reality that earth is?
What does it take?
- We're going to get shockingly close over the coming years,
certainly less than 20 years.
If you look at the progress, what areas
where we have achieved total photo realism
and what areas where we fall short?
We're getting very close in awe,
non-human interactions you see in the world,
walking through a jungle or a city,
all the lighting, it's very close.
And that might be just a few years away,
but then all of the problems that involve humans,
human dialogue and intent have a much, much, much higher bar
that they need to meet to satisfy our brains
and convince us that they're realistic and/or real.
And yeah, I think that's gonna be the primary challenge
of graphics development
and simulation development over the coming decade.
- So the realistic humans, that's gonna be the bottom line.
Yeah, so, and visual and behavior too, so everything?
- Yeah, I was asked about this about 10 years ago
and I said that even if you gave us an infinite amount
of computing power, we couldn't simulate realistic humans
because we simply don't have the algorithms,
we have no idea how to simulate human intelligence.
And that was absolutely the case then,
but it's not really true anymore.
You know, what we're seeing
with generative text AI is not only at a level
that you could say that it's actually doing
a pretty good job of simulating human, at least humans
at the text level, not at the emotional level yet,
but at least at the level of words spoken and find more
and more ways of training it on more and more scenarios
that, you know, you might have
a very, very compelling human simulation going on
in the next five years even.
I'm not saying it's a good idea,
but I like think the arc of the technology
is inextricably heading in that way
and it's heading at a shocking, shocking rate.
- You know, we don't say this enough,
but the current state of LLMs, I mean
if you put Alan Turing in conversation with ChatGPT,
I mean it really passes the Turing test
like almost definitively passes the Turing test.
Of course we like keep raising the bar.
Well, the Turing test is not a real test,
it's not a useful test, whatever.
We just keep raising the bar for AI where it's always going
to be lesser than.
But yeah, you have increasingly ultra realistic faces
and bodies combined with increasingly moving
and powerful full of emotion, speech, text.
You know, I work with this amazing company
called ElevenLabs that does text-to-speech well.
There's companies that specialize
in bringing text to life, right?
That's going to increase,
different companies do that very well.
And then all of a sudden you have
this synthetically created scene where human is speaking
and you're moved to the point of tears because of the scene.
Beautifully lit face in the full darkness, the emotion,
the drama of the scene.
Yeah, I think so you're saying five, 10 years maybe 20.
- Yeah, absolutely.
We'll definitely see it in our lifetimes.
- Increasing the level of potheadness in my question.
Do you think we might live in a simulation?
And if we do or don't,
how hard would it be to build such a simulation
where we're fully convinced we're in it?
- Well, I don't think
that these questions are necessarily unanswerable.
I think I'd like to see more actual effort
to ascertain like what is the underlying
mechanism of the universe.
And I don't think we're here for no reason at all.
I think the world's a pretty cool place
and the fact that we can exist
and, you know, the laws of physics
and especially a standard model of physics
and all of the parameters that lead to, you know,
these atoms and life evolving
and the presence of thermodynamic gradients,
that's really cool.
And I think it's a worthy field
to study more about that holistically.
I dunno, the question of are we living in a simulation
ourselves always boils down to, well,
if we are living in simulation, what are they living in?
Because at some point there has to be some base reality.
Or, you know, one of the philosophical theories
that was put forth seriously was
that there is no physical reality.
If you have a system of equations, you know,
such as the laws of physics, then all possible evolutions
of dynamical systems under those equations
kind of have a physical reality.
So we just are kind of a manifestation of laws of math
rather than needing an actual universe around us.
I dunno, I like dabbling into that philosophy.
And as we see AI becoming smarter and smarter
and we get closer and closer
to really capturing the full laws of physics,
these questions become quite a lot more compelling.
- You know, you start to think,
if we're not living in a simulation,
what are the things about this reality
that are not simulatable?
So what are the big mysteries around us?
It feels like the physics is simulatable.
It feels like a lot of the incredible stuff
that we talked about while super nice seems simulatable.
But then there's the flame of consciousness,
the feeling of it, whatever that is
that lights up in our eyes as humans.
Maybe that's not simulatable.
Maybe that is the thing.
Maybe that's a thread that connects to the explanation
of the mechanism, as you said, of the universe
that's really important to understand.
And we're completely clueless about that mechanism.
I mean, a lot of the religious texts sneak up on
what that mechanism is, but we're still mostly clueless.
We only have these like leaps of faith
in believing what that mechanism might be.
- So, you know, the whole idea
of nested simulations perhaps, you know,
given an sufficiently advanced technology is kind of mooted
such that if you wanted to simulate another reality,
you're kind of just actually creating the reality.
You're doing, you know, quantum mechanical operations
that would produce the same result anyway
and you're running them at full performance.
So it's not really a nested simulation,
it's just another thing that's happening in the universe.
So that would be interesting.
But I think it's ultimately a theological question
and because it's no longer cool to deal with theology
as part of science, there's not been much work on that.
You can't publish results on those topics
in a respected physics journal.
So I think it's kind of been set aside,
but it's interesting to note that the laws
of quantum mechanics themselves have a place for, you know,
god or souls or whatever external source of input you might
want to attach to such a thing.
And that, you know, that there's this idea
of quantum ways function collapse, that when we, you know,
look at a quantum system evolving
and perfect super position of many possibilities
and you go to observe it, you actually just see
a specific possibility.
In the multi-slit experiment,
the light ultimately ends up being observed
going through one slit or the other.
And that's a place where there's this random number
being injected into everything around us.
You know, trillions of trillions of trillions
of times per second and everything we're observing.
And if you want to ex attach some external input,
well there's a place. (Tim and Lex laughing)
- And it could be seriously accessible
to the rigors of science, but we just know so little there.
- Yeah, it's funny, and in that area,
we know nothing more than cavemen knew whatsoever.
We know than the laws of quantum mechanics.
And we have computers that maybe
soon more advanced than we are,
but we just don't have any answers
to the fundamental questions about life,
the universe and everything.
- Do you think sort of more practically,
do you think we'll create video game worlds
of the metaverse variety in which humans will want to stay?
So I mean, to me, this kind of discussion
of a simulated reality, the real test of immersion is like
not wanting to go back to the real world.
As a perfectly healthy, excited, normal human being,
choosing to stay in that world.
How hard is that, do you think?
- Well, I think the technology is coming
and then there's a human question
of should we go that far?
- [Lex] Should we? Yeah.
- And certainly as a game developer ourselves,
Epic doesn't aspire to that.
We make fun games.
And you know, the ultimate manifestation
that we found is fun games that people play together
to have fun in between, you know, work
and the other things in their real lives.
But as the simulations get more and more realistic
and the capabilities become more and more real,
I think we have to ask ourselves some hard questions
about how should humanity operate in that space?
What are the limits that we should go to
and what are the limits we should set?
- Yeah, I think there's gonna be some hard questions
and I think maybe I'm just being human-centric here,
but there should probably be some legal bounds
on two things,
sort of not creating a reality
in which humans would want to stay too long.
Sort of, yeah, focusing more on the game side.
And more importantly,
not creating simulations of humans
that could suffer.
To me, you know, as we talked about
creating ultra realistic humans,
eventually that means creating humans that can suffer,
that can fall in love and experience heartbreak and loss.
It can fear death.
And the more you simulate that to the full reality
of the human condition, the more you get to this place
where you have assimilated humans
that is able to suffer.
And I think legally speaking, I think you have to get
to a place where that's not allowed.
Like there is a line you can't cross.
And that's a hard thing for humans to deal with.
That's gonna be some interesting Supreme Court cases.
Once you create a human sufficiently realistic to
where they can suffer, means that human could be tortured
and you know, terrible things to that human
that's "artificial" quote unquote.
But boy, that still feels wrong.
I don't know what that is,
but you feel wrong
to torture a simulated human.
Now when you play a video game and it's a shooter
and everybody's having fun, that doesn't feel wrong,
but there's a line and that's gonna be a fascinating line
for the Supreme Court to explore. (laughs)
Oh man, what an exciting future we're living in, huh?
- Yeah, you know, I think the thing to appreciate
is like game developers have just generally
been on the good spirited side of things.
If you look at the worst things that people do
and in popular video games today, it's like what?
You rob a bank in "GTA."
Well, it's clearly fictional and awe and fun
and not serious and over the top.
Yeah, I think, yeah, as things get more realistic,
especially simulation of humans,
yeah, there are some hard questions
that will have to be answered there.
But I think the thing that all games developers
need to remember is we're here to make people's lives better
by entertaining them,
providing them with fun and a diversion from other things
and being a part of their lives
and not trying to be too big or being too much
and not trying to provide an alternate to reality,
but to just provide a fun source of entertainment
like the many other things that people do for fun.
- So you spoken,
like I mentioned about the metaverse for many years.
Let's step back, what is the metaverse?
And speaking of fun, you know, "Fortnite," (laughs)
you know, just hundreds of millions of people
just enjoying themselves in this huge scale social game.
You could call it a metaverse,
maybe you can describe the different flavors,
the layers of how you see what the metaverse is.
- You know, the metaverse is an idea whose stock price
goes up and down depending on who says what
on what day.
And some have an ability to drive it way down (laughs)
by opening their mouths.
But ultimately this is about
multiplayer social gaming experiences.
You and your friends getting together in a 3D world
and having fun together in any way you want.
You know, if you're playing "Fortnite: Battle Royale,"
in my view, that is capturing the essence of the metaverse.
And it's, especially in "Fortnite" when we got Sony on board
so that all players on all platforms in "Fortnite"
could play together, could voice chat together
and could be part of a single game experience.
It really took on a new nature,
which was not just like a multiplayer game in, you know,
with Heritage from "Doom",
but also a true social experience
between you and your friends.
And yeah, "Fortnite: Battle Royal"
is just one manifestation of that.
Another one is like "Rec Room VR", where you're standing
around in VR with friends playing billiards
or shooting hoops and we're doing other
like light entertainment things.
I think every game that has a huge number of players
who play together socially as part of their, you know,
entertainment lives.
Yeah, I think is really getting at the core essence
of the, you know, aspiration for the metaverse.
And, you know, we're still in the very early days of it.
You know, I was on the internet and like 1992 or so,
and you know, it was a pretty bare bones thing.
I think when we look back at the state of gaming today,
we'll realize that there's a lot further
to go to get to the ultimate version of it.
But, you know, I think it's all on track.
And I think it was the time we released
"Fortnite: Battle Royale" and started playing together,
all the people at Epic and Squads
and experiencing that world that we realized
that this trend was afoot and that we needed
to do everything we could
to bring in other creators so that anybody could, you know,
pile on to the work we were doing
by creating their own worlds, you know,
for through "Fortnite Creative" and UEFN
and creating more games
and more genres that people could play
and ever expanding the repertoire of fun.
- Yeah, I would love to sort of talk about
different aspects of that a little bit more
because, you know, Epic has created a lot of amazing games
"Unreal Tournament", "Gears of War,"
but the game that I think is fair to say
that transformed the gaming industry was "Fortnite,"
or "Fortnite: Battle Royale" especially.
Can you explain the origin story of "Fortnite"?
- Well, "Fortnite" has humble beginnings.
In 2011, we just been in the final days
of finishing one of the "Gears of War" games
and we wanted to explore ideas for new games
and we'd had a general idea that we would like to build,
you know, some smaller games, online games
or to learn more about, you know, that space
and not just have one single massive game in production
at all times and only one.
And so everybody in the company was given a week
to form a team and work with whichever coworkers they wanted
and build a game, you know, using Unreal Engine
so you can actually build something
pretty interesting in a week.
And one of the teams built
the very first version of what became "Fortnite."
The very first version of it had a different art style,
but it had the idea at the core that you're going
to build forts by day using this building system.
Then night would come
and you'd defend the forts against zombies.
And you know, the longer you could go,
the more elaborate forts you could build
and the more survival, you know, waves you could withstand
and it would get cooler and cooler with time.
And you know, that game was in development
for a very long time.
We always saw the potential, just the building aspect
of it was incredibly fun.
But we made different pivots at different times.
At one point we moved
to the current "Fortnite" art style,
away from kind of more of a realistic style.
Made it, you know, more in the Pixar vein of, you know,
cool stylized characters.
- What was that decision like?
'cause you mentioned "Gears of War" is this like incredible,
like shows off the graphics to the fullest,
different than the artistic style of "Fortnite."
It's amazing that the same company would make this like fun,
silly graphic style of "Fortnite," you know.
- People come to Epic because they wanna work
with the best people in the world
and artists bring a lot of different
personal art aspirations and style capabilities
and many of them are very multi-talented,
can produce photo reel content or highly stylized content.
And a lot of the best artists on "Fortnite"
were a lot of the best artists on "Gears of War"
to change styles,
but continue doing awesome work.
We'd realized that "Fortnite" could be mainstream
and it could be a game people play for a long time.
And so having a, you know, more visually pleasing art style
that's, you know, not as stressful as like a "Call of Duty"
game where you're constantly like pixel hunting,
you know, a dark scene for a, you know,
somebody's rifle scope. (Tim and Lex laughing)
That was the goal, so, you know, a few of the artists
got through into finding a new art style and we moved to it
and at different points it evolved towards being
kind of like a light MMO like "Destiny"
with rather complex RPG and stat systems.
And that evolved into a, you know, kind of an UMO like
tower defense game.
UMO only in that persistence of items and stats, you know,
which became "Fortnite: Save the World" mode,
which we launched in early 2017.
And it was a moderate success, you know,
it paid its budget and we'd come out ahead.
And then at the same time
the "Battle Royale" genre was booming.
"PubG" had just come out,
tons of people at Epic were playing that.
They're like, "Oh, this would be so cool
if it had 'Fortnite' building."
And so we assembled a team in a war room, you know,
like 30 people in one big room.
And you know, they worked insanely hard for four weeks
to build "Battle Royale."
So the nice thing is all the content for "Fortnite"
had been built over the previous seven years.
They had a huge library of content
but no gameplay of the type they wanted.
So they had to build it all in that four weeks and ship it.
And that put Epic on an exponential growth curve
where we went from 300 employees to, you know,
to thousands of employees
and went from about a hundred million dollars in revenue
to billions of dollars in revenue.
And, you know, kinda became the center of the gaming world
at the time.
- Can you actually speak to the technical challenge
of going from mostly not online
large scale gaming platform
to being able to support with "Battle Royale,"
a huge number of people playing with each other
at the same exact time?
Like what's the technical four weeks,
what's the technical challenges
there that had to be overcome?
- Since 2012, we've been building online backend system
to support player accounts and login
and you know, all of the different systems there
needed to make a multiplayer game.
And we've been building them to be scalable.
And by some miracle we built them stably enough
that they were able to scale up.
And you know, so the online team was responsible
for patching that code.
Spent a year of intense work getting it
to scale from like 40,000 concurrent users
to 15 million concurrent users.
Yeah, I mean they're scaling and there scaling,
that's a lot.
- That's immense, but they'd done such an awesome job
of building the foundations that it was tractable,
it was doable.
If they hadn't done that,
then the company would've died that, you know,
"Fortnite" just wouldn't have been playable
and the whole thing would've failed.
- I mean there's just so much detail there
that makes all the difference
because I mean that's what Spotify has talked about
that like the latency,
it's like how quickly you can deliver the song
changes the product from being this shitty thing
that I'd rather pirate the songs to like this is good enough
to where I really enjoy the experience, I want to use it.
And so like yeah, that's really important
to create an experience for 15 million concurrent users
to where it's not lagging
or it actually works, right?
Is there something you could say to the sort of like
how difficult that is to pull off?
- You know, the trend nowadays
for building online services is microservices.
There's not one big server that handles
all of the interactions with "Fortnite."
There's game servers running a hundred player game instances
for each Battle Royale session
and then there's an account server
and many instances of it all talking to a shared database
and there's hundreds of different microservices
talking to each other.
And so scaling is a matter of identifying
what are the bottlenecks in that system
and making sure that each one can scale
and has enough redundancy to be able to handle the load.
Thank God for Amazon Web Services and cloud hosting
because Epic went to 15 million concurrent users
without buying any server hardware.
We are able to just call up Amazon and say, "We need more."
And there was a period of time there
where "Fortnite" was undergoing this exponential growth
and we'd find like one week we ran out of servers in Brazil
during a heavy weekend of play
and next week we had an even heavier weekend of play
and there were servers to handle it.
Like somebody at Amazon had dropped shipped, you know,
millions of dollars of server hardware into Brazil
and turned it on just in time for "Fortnite" to need it.
And you know, there are a lot of unsung heroes
in that story, many of whom we've never heard of.
- Yeah, I mean behind AWS many unsung heroes.
It's like so much of those folks who run
the modern internet, all the incredible services, the games,
the services that we take for granted
are currently being run on AWS
or were originally and Google Cloud and so on.
Yeah, can you speak to how much money "Fortnite" made?
(Lex laughing)
So this is like one of the greatest successes
in the history of video games also.
- "Fortnite" makes billions of dollars a year
and that's the majority of Epic's revenue
that we have a robust business
around on Unreal Engine licensing, "Rocket League"
and "Fall Guys"
and some other tools like the Fab content marketplace.
But the majority of it is "Fortnite"
because we've chosen to reinvest heavily in building
what we think is the future of technology.
We're spending more every year than we're making.
And for a bit of time we were spending
over a billion dollars a year more than we were making
and we found that to be unsustainable
and we went through some painful layoffs at that time
and then we stabilize and now we're spending
several hundred million dollars a year
more than we're making,
which we can very well afford to do
because we have billions of dollars in the bank.
You know, thanks to a combination of the profits we made
when we were a very small company with a very big game.
And because of investment we've raised.
We're not an pumping oil out of the ground at
where we discovered oil.
We are growing to be a future technology powerhouse
and we think that 3D space
and the future of real-time 3D simulations is going
to be one of the major facets of technology for humanity.
And we're all investing in that.
- Yeah, it's exciting to see
that investing in a long-term future,
sort of taking the risk of doing the research
and defining the next chapter of Epic.
So using the successes of the day
to invest into the successes of tomorrow,
that might look very different, like completely different.
And part of that is investing in the developments,
the research and the innovation in the Unreal Engine.
- That's right, we're a company
that can start working on a project knowing
that we won't reach fruition or make any money
from it at all for three years, four years, five years.
We're totally okay with that.
And you know, that's the cycle
that's fueled our growth over time.
It's constantly investing in the future
and you know, being a serious company that's doing
serious R and D side by side
with shipping and maintaining products
and earning money from them.
- So can you speak to,
I mean there's several directions here.
So one of them sort of the future evolution
of this idea of the metaverse,
so potentially creating communities.
So "Fortnite" is this incredible,
huge community of humans interacting,
but your vision is to go outside of just one game.
So what is the kinds of standards
that you're thinking about building
such that people can sort of have an identity
to almost travel between games and that kind of thing?
- Lemme start with the present of gaming and why it sucks.
(Tim and Lex laughing)
- Like that's a good start, sure.
- "Fortnite" is an awesome thing.
You go into "Fortnite," there's, you know,
a hundred million monthly active users there,
a huge number of your own friends are there,
you can play with them,
go from experience to experience seamlessly
without leaving the app.
There a hundred thousand different islands you can play on.
And some of them are really awesome
and they're constant new ones coming out
and constant things to do.
If you wanna play "Roblox", all right, you quit
out of the "Fortnite" app, you launch the "Roblox" app,
different program, different friend system,
different account names, your username in "Fortnite"
and your username and "Roblox" are different names
and they're not connected to each other.
So you have to remake all of your friends
and then find different, you know, things to play.
And now the controls are different.
So you have to relearn how, you know,
the joystick, mouse, keyboard controller works in
that experience and you have to go from place to place.
And you buy some stuff in "Fortnite" and it's really cool
and you can use it anywhere in "Fortnite."
And then you go in "Roblox"
and you don't have that stuff,
you have to buy different stuff
and that stuff only works in "Roblox".
And same with "Call of Duty", it's another isolated place.
And same with "World of Warcraft",
and same with "League of Legends"
and every place you go is its own unique place,
different friends, different account names,
different people.
And there's no social cohesion between them at all.
And long time ago, console was set out to solve this problem
by creating their console-wide friend system in account.
So your friend on PlayStation in one game is your friends
on PlayStation in another game, but only on PlayStation.
If you're on Xbox you can't see PlayStation friends.
And so you have two basically orthogonal
and cross-cutting divisions of the world into fiefdoms,
you know, which were not created with bad intentions
but arose and are, you know, separated, isolated islands.
One is the platforms and their social services,
Xbox, PlayStation, Nintendo,
it's Steam, Epic if you add it to the list.
And the other is these different games people play
and you know, because of this weird historical artifact
where we're left in a world
where people can't seamlessly move from games to games,
bringing their friends and their stuff.
So the solution to this is to federate
and connect all of the systems together.
All of the players on all the different platforms
can be recognized by their name
and put the @ sign in it,
so your Xbox names and your "Fortnite" or Epic names
and your Steam names can all live together
and operate together in a single space.
So unifying the social ecosystems
is one thing that needs to happen.
The next and bigger challenge is to unify the economies too.
Now I'm not talking about like a sword you have in
"World of Warcraft" should work in "Fortnite".
(Lex laughing)
Every game's gonna have its own gameplay rules
and a lot of games are gonna have stuff
that only works in them.
But you know, there's a huge set of games
that have in common the idea of a cosmetic system
that does not affect gameplay outcomes
but is, you know, purely cool looks and cool appearances.
Most of the major multiplayer games have them
and you know,
if you look at games you could probably bundle it together
about 70% of them and say they're similar enough
that they could actually interoperate.
That you could own an outfit in "Fortnite,"
own an outfit in "Roblox",
and own the same outfit in maybe "Call of Duty"
and maybe, you know, a hundred or 200 other games
and actually expect they would work together.
And you find other kinds of items
are probably interoperable too.
Like "Fortnite" has car outfits so you can, you know,
buy different appearances of a car.
And when you find a physical car in the world of "Fortnite,"
if you're the first person to get into it in that session,
boom, it takes on your, you know, your chosen car cosmetic
and now you have a cool car that's identifiable as yours.
You know, we realized early on with "Fortnite" that the key
to making "Fortnite" work as a creator economy
was to open up the revenue from the item shop
to all of those sources of engagement, right?
There are two big things happening in "Fortnite"
that make it work as a product and as a business.
One is the game modes, "Fortnite: Battle Royale",
and all of the user modes and everything else
are sources of engagement.
People play there because it's super fun.
And because they're playing there, they're willing
to buy cool stuff to make their character look cooler.
And so you have all of these sources of engagement,
but the sources of engagement don't make money directly.
You can't spend money in "Fortnite: Battle Royale"
to buy a game item like everything's, you know,
the gameplay is not pay to win and it's all just a game.
So we make money from the item shop
and the item shop only exists
because of the sources of engagement.
If you weren't playing "Battle Royale," trust me,
nobody would wanna buy a "Fortnite" outfit.
If you weren't playing any "Fortnite" games,
why would you buy "Fortnite" outfits?
And so you have all the revenue in this item shop economy
and all of the engagement in this engagement economy.
And the thing that magically makes the "Fortnite" creator
economy works is revenue sharing.
Item shop spending according to sources of engagement,
buy engagement, if you buy an item
and you've played, you know, 40% of your time
in Battle Royale and 60% of your time in these user modes,
the amount you spent, the portion of that
that's profit can be separated out
and paid out to all the different creators
who participate in that economy.
And that's why "Fortnite" scaled up
to a $400 million creator economy so far and is growing.
- It's amazing.
- One of the really critical things we aim
to do in designing that is ensure it's a creator economy
that could scale to other companies, other ecosystems.
And say, you know, right now we have
many industry standards bodies,
so one standardized game ratings, you know,
age ratings of games, another standardized file formats
for the web, another style, you know,
standardizing file formats for 3D
like Khronos Groups in the Metaverse standards form.
If we had a standards body standardize
what are portable outfits in games, you know,
game outfits you could buy in one game that work in another.
What are their, you know, dimensions
and what are their capabilities
and what can you do
and what can't you do and so on.
Then you could have an item economy where every game agrees
to respect each other's item purchases of that sort.
And revenue is shared between ecosystems as well.
- That would be incredible.
That would be so amazing.
Is there, first of all, just it seems silly maybe
for people who don't play video games,
but an outfit is an important...
If an outfit can be persistent across video games,
I mean, I don't know what's the purpose of life?
Like, why do we wear clothing?
Clothing is a part of our identity.
It's how we present ourselves to the world.
It's, you know, I wear the stupid suit and tie.
It feels good.
It feels good when I put it on.
And even like the other outfit, I have two outfits,
this and then a black t-shirt and jeans.
And it feels good to wear that.
It feels like me when I look in the mirror.
Okay, I know that guy.
And to be able to have that outfit go from game to game
to game maybe across years, that would be wonderful.
I wonder if you could just even comment,
could there also be another standardization about the value?
So for more complicated items, so, you know,
take a sword from "Diablo"
and transfer to a gun in "Fortnite."
But based on the value some, you know,
some generic concept of money.
So the value of a thing in one game
versus the value of a thing in another game
where you're almost operating in a space of value
versus the actual items.
Or is that already getting too general?
- I think this can be done, yeah.
We did a lot of analysis of the "Fortnite" economy
and found that some "Fortnite" experiences
lead to or correlate with higher spending than others.
And you know, "Battle Royale" is relatively strong
in that area because you see your character from behind
and see all of your other characters from the front,
and you have lots of opportunities to really see who you are
and to emote and to interact with other players.
And a lot of games have that characteristic.
One funny anomaly stood out.
There was this game
that was one of the big breakthroughs
in "Fortnite," "Only Up."
It's a game where you're just climbing up in the up
by following pads of stacks of objects and things.
It was just stupid fun. (Lex laughing)
Everybody loved, okay, but we found people weren't spending
a lot of money on outfits
when they were playing "Only Up".
It's kind of intuitive actually.
Like you're not seeing other players,
like if you see anything, like you're seeing their butt
as you're like trying to catch up to them,
jumping from object to object and they're above you.
And so, you know, it wasn't a mode
that shut off outfits very much,
but you could, you know,
you can determine the economic correlation
between a game mode and spending.
- That's so fascinating.
I mean, "Fortnite" is this gigantic economy
where you could do those kinds of studies,
you can understand markets, the digital markets
as they emerge amongst humans and what they value.
And from that value, you can probably have a very stable
kind of money that emerges.
- Yeah, I think so.
You don't need like an alternate currency system,
you know, unfortunately, a bunch of ideas have conflated
because people were trying to hype up different things.
But you know, this idea of large scale multiplayer
social gaming, you know, that notion of the metaverse,
you know, there's 600 to 800 million people playing
that kind of game every month.
So like, you know, that's real and that's happening
and it's, you know, very much underway.
VR has a much smaller audience.
I don't think you need VR to have anything like this.
Like VR is hardware that may or may not enhance
the experience for some usage cases.
For some it'll probably be better
and for some it'll probably be worse,
but certainly there's not any set
of "Battle Royale" players flocking to VR.
And the other thing is NFT is it's like you trying
to equate digital or cryptocurrency to the metaverse.
It's just a way of denoting money or value exchange.
You can do that with money or you can do it with NFTs
or whatever, but there's nothing about this future digital
economy that fundamentally requires
cryptocurrency or whatever.
What you need is interoperability.
Interoperability can happen through a blockchain,
it can happen through a database,
it can happen through standards bodies
with defining standards and protocols.
And we've been doing it for hundreds of years
since the railroads were standardized.
And you know, it's not something
that totally requires a novel technological solution.
- Yeah, I mean even on the topic of cryptocurrency,
it's very frustrating.
You know, blockchain and crypto is a really powerful
technology that I think can enable
a lot of the things that we're talking about.
But so many people use it to try to make money
to create these bubbles.
And the hype and the meme coins and the so on and so forth,
that becomes much less about
that drifts far away and rapidly
from things that are actually of value,
which is the experience of playing "Fortnite"
and how you look when you play "Battle Royale."
I mean, it sounds ridiculous to say, but it's true.
But that's valuable.
That's like, you know,
you have like gold in the physical space.
We know that holds value.
How your outfit looks like in "Fortnite" that,
as you're saying, provably holds value.
And so you want to connect
like a standard definition of money value
to that and not let it become this hype thing which NFTs
that you mentioned are just become that.
Like quickly drifts away
into the land of people trying to buy
and sell and try to make money versus like staying close
to the thing that people actually value.
Forget the money, it's more about exchanging
valuable experiences or things of value.
So you can play "Fortnite"
and then go to another video game
and continue the valuable experience
and then come back to "Fortnite" and do that kind of thing.
So you're saying there might be a way to do that
and to basically create standards
the way the web has different standards
for displaying websites and all this kind of stuff
or the communication
that's required on the networking side.
So all the different standards that make the web work,
there need to be those kinds of standards.
Like what would those standards look like
to enable the metaverse?
- We need a lot of different things.
The one area where the standards bodies
have been very successful in creating working standards
implemented by all the major engines today
is in low level file formats for data interchange.
You know, the web has PNG files for 2D images
and in MP3 files for audio.
And 3D has the Pixar USD file format,
the universal scene description, which is a description
of the scene graph, the entire set of objects in the scene
and all of their parameters so that any engine
that supports those features could import that
and then render the same scene as the engine they came from.
You know, large parts of this work across Unreal Engine
and Unity and Blender
and all of these 3D packages of different sorts.
Then there's the GLTF texture format, which stores textures
and geometry and other low level data for 3D objects.
You know, when you see a "Fortnite" character
that file format together with the image file formats
can store their static appearance,
you know, the shape of their body,
even their animations and their different poses
and the appearance of them,
the different standard file formats could store
all of the sounds they make in their emotes.
But we're still missing a bunch of pieces.
The biggest missing piece is the programming language
that's at the center of standardizing the metaverse.
Now if you look at the web, the web is a combination
of a bunch of different technologies.
The two biggest ones are HTML,
which describes the 2D scene graph or the, you know,
2D layout of controls and objects on the webpage.
But that's just static data.
It's just a non-moving, non animating webpage.
And then you have the JavaScript programming language,
which is used to manipulate that to display things
to the user and to implement anything
you could implement in code.
So it's a little programming language
that runs in your web browser.
And the Metaverse needs something
that performs that similar role.
But the Metaverse and 3D gaming in general needs something
that's rather more powerful, more safe, more scalable,
and more capable than JavaScript
because the metaverse is actually more difficult
technical problem than a webpage.
A webpage like an app is just a single bundle of code
and content that somebody, a company, has prepared
and they release it and it stays exactly what it is
until they release a new version
and it's upgraded from version to version as it goes.
But the metaverse needs to be a composite of code
and content built by millions of different people
that could potentially form a seamless world together.
- Yeah, it's fully distributed collaborative.
First of all, also the amount of data,
I mean it doesn't have to be that way,
but websites are showing very little information.
The metaverse, even when it looks like something like
"Fortnite," just the amount of information
that's conveyed in the scene graph
as the individual players are collaborating is a huge,
huge, huge amount.
- Yeah, the highest detail of "Fortnite" updates
amount to about 60 gigabytes of data.
And you know, that's just a small part of
what exists in the "Fortnite" creative economy.
And if you look at what this might be in a decade
as standards emerge, you might have exabytes
of data out there.
"Fortnite: Battle Royale" is I don't think
the ultimate manifestation of gameplay that will,
you know, ever be invented.
What we've seen time and time again is that
as we gain more technical capabilities,
graphics gets more capable, CPUs become more performant.
You know, web services become ever more scalable.
We've seen new genres of games that emerge
that weren't possible before
and you know, "Doom" ushered in the era of Death Match
and the first time 3D multiplayer game
was even possible at all.
You know, the early "Battle Royale" games
starting about 10 years or 15 years ago
only became possible back then.
You couldn't have built one 20 years ago
because you just couldn't have rendered an environment
that's as large as a VR game with that many players,
with that level of interaction and performance.
It was just not possible to run it.
So you got a certain level of technical capabilities
and a genre came out that proved to be
by far the best shooter genre ever invented.
But I think there are numerous, numerous more genres,
some of which are better than any of the existing ones
that will be invented as we get more and more capabilities.
You know, some of the capabilities we're lacking now
are the ability to build environments and game simulations
that span more work than a single company
can possibly create.
And you know, you see kind of the birth
of that idea in "Fortnite" and "Roblox"
where there are tens of thousands creators,
each building content.
And users are playing meaningful amounts of it all.
And so there's an ecosystem
that's scaled larger than company,
but it's still very much you go into one island
and you play that creator's work.
The other direction of its scalability is putting more
and more of people's work together in a seamless continuous
play space for games where that makes sense.
You know, you can imagine a game taking place
in an environment that is the size of a continent
or earth in which you can like go from place to place
and then see different areas
which are maintained by different people.
So you go into different spaces,
the game rules are customized according to that
and you can go from experience to experience
and instead of having just one company's authorship
ever present wherever you are,
yeah you'd see you'd be driving a car built
by one person, carrying weapons built by 20 other people
and you know, taking place in a simulation in an environment
that's built by thousands of other people, you know,
and working for separate companies or their own,
you know, entrepreneurs or indies or enthusiasts
all working together simultaneously.
And we totally lack the programming foundations for that.
You know, the kinds of code you would need
to write now to make that happen are just not practical.
And so we're investing massively in building
new programming language technologies around Verse
and our proposed standards for, you know,
future metaverse programming
that we hope will solve those kinds of problems
and make that kind of world possible.
- So first of all, that's a super exciting future where,
you know, it's not hundreds or thousands,
it's millions of creators that can just create
different small or big elements of a world as big as earth.
Just if you sort of close your eyes and imagine that world,
that's really exciting.
Where it's not a centralized company controlling
the release of a particular island or so on.
It's people constantly dynamically modifying
all the islands of reality in this digital world.
So if you could speak to some of the technology
that can enable that,
you mentioned the Verse programming language.
First of all also, how legit is it for you CEO of Epic Games
to be a co-author?
The programming language theorists are losing their mind.
(Tim and Lex laughing)
So co-author in a paper that's describing
some of the sort of nuance details
of a programming language.
So maybe you could speak
to this programming language called Verse,
it's a functional logic language.
What is it?
What are some cool features of Verse?
- Verse is a programming language that we're building
for large scale simulation programming.
It's designed to make it easy to write code
that can scale up to
not only you building a "Fortnite" island
but you building modules
or components that can be used by millions
of other programmers and coexist in a huge environment
and also can scale up to a huge scale simulation.
Some games will be small "Battle Royale" might find
that, you know, a hundred players is actually optimal.
It might be the a thousand player version of "Battle Royale"
would be worse,
but I bet there are a thousand, million
and tens of million player experiences,
they're even better than that
that will yet to be discovered.
And so... - Wait, wait a minute,
tens of millions of players together.
- Sure we've had "Fortnite" events
that have attracted 15 million concurrent users
but you know, the fact that they're all divided up
into servers with a hundred players each
for those events isn't really a positive.
It's just a limitation of the technology.
Tracing back to Unreal Engine 1
and its single threading decisions.
You know, if we could build a concert
where all the concert participants,
potentially tens of millions of them,
could participate together simultaneously
and see that there's that massive a crowd
and they could all do interesting things
and interact with each other, that would be way cooler.
- Just if we just, sorry I'm just loading it in,
just imagining together
in one scene graph, 10 million people interacting,
what a cool world that is.
- Sure, well, you know, 10 million people,
you have less than 10 million pixels on your screen.
So what does the Nyquist sampling theorem say?
It says that you don't need full overhead for every player,
you need to render the players around you
in some approximation of everything else.
- Yeah, too, but there's also a networking component
like yeah you're speaking to the rendering but like, oh boy.
(Lex laughing)
- There's a lot of work that has to happen there
but you know, this is what we do for a living,
we solve hard problems. - [Lex] I understand
- 'Cause if they're easy then other people
could have solved them already.
- That's really cool though.
Just sort of the possibility,
the vision of that is really cool.
Even just, you know, even a hundred thousand people
were like bring 10,000 together just to...
I mean there's a reason in the physical world
when you go to a concert
and you have all those people around you,
that energy or you go to a football game,
that energy is unlike anything else.
And if you can bring that energy to the digital world,
that's amazing.
Yeah, but anyway, so sorry.
So on the technology side of bringing that to life
on the programming language side,
can you continue, as I rudely interrupt you
talking about Verse.
- Versus the functional logic language
because we think that's the way to make the most simple
and powerful language simultaneously.
Back in the 1970s, the programming language designer
who built Pascal, one of the early programming languages,
Niklaus Wirth or Nicholas Wirth,
as Americans might call him, stated this principle
that programming language should achieve
a high degree of power not by having a lot of features
but having by having a small number of features
that work together and can be composed together arbitrarily.
So that you have to learn a relatively small set of things
and then the real knowledge comes as you learn ways
to combine them to achieve bigger and bigger programs.
And so, you know, there's long history
to the field of programming languages,
but in the 1950s the first programming language designers
got together and built the first standardized language
called ALGOL.
And there was this meeting in 1956,
very few people even know about,
but it's where all the major foundations
of modern programming languages were decided on.
That the C family of languages inherited.
And so we're very much living in a world
that was defined by them.
And thankfully they got a whole lot of things right.
They defined how functions should work,
how variable should work and how recursion should work.
And you know, thank God they got those things right
but they got a few things wrong
and Verse is trying to fix those.
And that's the functional logic part of it.
The interesting thing about functional logic language
is that in an old school language
an expression produces a value.
In a functional logic language,
an expression can produce zero, one or multiple values.
If it produces zero values, we might say it fails.
If it produces one value, we say it succeeds.
And if it produces multiple values, it's kind
providing a set of values you could iterate over.
And so there are a bunch of features
in today's programming languages that were defined
in an ad hoc way without really thinking this through
this zero, one or many values way.
And that's the problem
that functional logic languages address.
The most basic example,
an if statement in a programming language.
If some condition holds, then do this thing,
otherwise do that thing.
And in the language today this is done with variables
of type boolean or expressions that produce booleans.
We have boolean variables that are either true or false.
We have expressions that evaluate to boolens.
And so you can express a condition
as a bunch of these features together,
but you've lost any computation you've done
in doing that boolen expression evaluation.
So in a functional logic language,
your condition wouldn't do that.
It would either succeed
and produce a value or it would fail.
If it succeeds, it goes to then branch,
your operation succeeded. now you're operating, you know,
running this one batch of code.
And if your expression failed
then you go to the else branch.
But the exciting thing about that is your expression
that succeeds or fails can produce values
and bind variables that are then accessed
by the then branch.
So you can write a conditional where you can only get
to the inside of the condition the then
if a bunch of variables have successfully
been bound to variables.
So it lets you test if some conditions hold
and then use the results of those tests.
And that gives you a much higher level of reliability.
And then a for loop in a traditional language,
it's just a bunch of imperative code that's woven together
to produce a bunch of values iteratively.
It's rather awkward to do complicated things in for loops.
And so you often end up with either ever more complicated
constructs built to work around that,
like iterators and other things.
The idea of functional logic languages
is your for loop can just produce multiple values
and if it produces zero values
you got to reiterate zero iterations.
And it produces a bunch of values,
you got all of those as your iterations.
Rather than having a bunch of nested loops,
you can write arbitrary things
that look like SQL queries in a condition
or in a for loop that bind a bunch of variables,
do a bunch of tests, produce a series of results
and in some order that you're iterating over
and then you can handle all of them and produce a result.
So you kind of gain the power of SQL queries,
you know, large complex queries over data structures
in a language that is much simpler
in which your code is just performing
simple iterative operations.
And so it kind of gives you the best of databases
and of regular programming in a much more uniform way.
And the power of this is now users can write functions
that not only produce a value,
you can write functions that might fail.
And so you can write a function that answers a question.
The answer can be either a yes and my value is this or no.
And you can combine these together into arbitrary queries.
And if you like, the funny thing
is that this is not how C++ works.
And so when we have Epic programmers moving over from C++
and writing their first Verse code,
they try to write C++ code and versatile
and it actually ends up being convoluted code
that's worse than good C++ or good Verse.
But after a few months they get up to speed
and they're writing really awesome code that's tighter
and more compact than before
and with users who've never programmed before
but are learning programming for the first time
in the context of "Fortnite," it's really fascinating.
You see these users are learning this kind of as
it becomes their intuition.
They just assume programming works this way
and they're writing way more advanced
and interesting for loops and conditions
than we're often writing internally
because they've kind of rocked the core concept.
- Yeah, I mean you said a lot of really interesting stuff.
First of all, it's very interesting
that there's a bunch of people,
a lot of people learning programming
for the first time with Verse,
which is a very different way to look at programming
and some deep sense as you're saying,
a very intuitive way to learn programming.
But there's a lot of properties about this being
a logical language,
one of which will maybe speak also about confluence
but also correctness.
So being able to prove the correctness of a code
is basically easier to write bug free code.
Can you just speak to that
and the importance of that
when you're building the metaverse?
- Yeah, right, so the challenge with the metaverse
is first of all that it's a huge base of code
that's evolving over time and written by many authors.
So you might see every second a new module is updated
somewhere and you expect in this live ever running
simulation that never shuts down for everything
to upgrade live in place.
And so one critical component that is the ability to
release an update to something you've already published
and be sure that it's backwards compatible with the one
that you've already released.
And that's essentially a type checking problem,
checking that your new interface is backwards compatible
with your old one.
And that comes down to the type system of the language.
There's been a lot of very interesting research
on type systems over the years, most of which
hasn't ever made it
into the C++ programming language unfortunately.
But you see several branches of that whole field.
One of the really interesting things that Java
and C# did in the early days and then later abandoned
and didn't bother update was defining a very rigorous
set of rules for if you publish a module
with one set of types today,
then what changes can you make to that module
for your future updates to it
that don't break backwards compatibility.
And that's a problem for type checking.
You know like say you have a function that promises
to return some integer, when in the future you could say
that returns some natural number
'cause every natural number is an integer.
So that's a backwards compatible change.
But you can't say it returns a rational number
'cause some rational numbers are not integers.
So the, you know, system ought
to reject that kind of change.
But the much, much, much more interesting thing
about type checking, it was the realization
it was actually made in the 1930s
that if you design a programming language type system
in a very particular way, then it becomes not only useful
for expressing types of variables.
A traditional thing every type system does is say
like variable X is of type integer.
But if you design a type system in a certain way,
then your types can express theorems
like mathematical theorems.
You know the Pythagorean theorem is a cool one.
But one theorem you might set of
in a program is like the theorem
that this function takes an array of integers
and returns an array of the same integers
but the result is sorted.
If you express that as a theorem
and you follow this system of type theory,
then you can actually require that anybody who writes
that sorting function to prove
that it has actually sorted its result.
And so you have types or theorems
and values constructed a certain way
can be proofs of those theorems.
And, you know, nowadays in mathematical literature
you see more and more theorems
are being proven mechanically.
Mathematicians are proving theorems in a way
that is verified by computer to be a correct proof.
In the old days of math, people would write down
like language.
If you look at all of Euclid's theorems,
it was just language.
It was just writing an ancient Greek
to say the steps of the proof
to convince the reader that the thing is true.
Starting in the 1930s,
mathematicians move towards rigorous formal proofs
in which there's a series of steps
that can be mechanically verified, they're proving things.
And when mathematicians say
they've done a computer proof of a theorem,
what they really mean is they've written
the program in a proof language.
Like Lean is theorem prover
a Coq is theorem prover and there are several others.
It means they've written a mechanical proof in that language
that a computer is checked so that it's impossible to lie.
If you say that you've proven a thing
and the computer verifies it, then it's definitely true.
And you know, this is a feature
of mathematical proof languages
but it's also I think an idea
that's making its way into programming language
is gradually over time.
And our aim for Verse is
to be the first mainstream programming language
that fully adopts that approach and that technique
and not only adopts it
but adopts it in a way that's really user friendly.
So you don't have to do that.
And the idea of this is
that you want gradually more information
to be incorporated in the types of variables.
The property you want of a programming language is
that if your compiler accepts your program and doesn't beep
and tell you there is an error,
then your program should work.
Now there are all kinds of ways humans
can make mistakes there
so that we'll never achieve that ideal,
but we can get closer and closer to it by having more
and more language features that enable the compiler
to catch more human coding errors
and tell the user what went wrong.
And you know, that becomes extremely important
in the metaverse, the cost of fixing a bug
that's made it through to a runtime and is in users' hands.
The cost of fixing a bug in a shipping program is
hundreds of times higher
than fixing a bug that you've just observed
as you're running your code yourself.
When it's running on your computer,
you just fix a line of code and your bugs fixed.
When you have to fix it live, you have to release a patch,
you have to release patch notes,
you have to test the patch, you have to check
for all the other bugs that might have been introduced
and everything becomes vastly, vastly more expensive.
So you know, the real aim of the Verse program
and approach is to catch all of these errors at compile time
and make the metaverse a very reliable place.
- Do you see a world where like at compile time
you could prove that the program is correct
in some sense of correctness?
- Proving things becomes commentorially harder
as they get larger, right?
And so the really important thing
about this whole field is that you should be able
to adopt these capabilities gradually
and apply it where you really need it.
Like if you're writing something
like a cryptography algorithm,
that's a good place to prove stuff.
If you're writing a data decompressor that's gonna be used
by an entire ecosystem, like proving that
that doesn't overrun memory, it's actually really important.
And a lot of the reason
that security vulnerabilities happen today
is because in a different language a compiler
could have caught, we're not caught in C
because it just doesn't have this feature.
But yet we shouldn't see this as scary.
Everybody working in a type language like C
or C # or Java is proving theorems all the time.
If you have a variable of type integer
and you assign some value to it, you've proven
to the compiler that value was an integer
'cause otherwise it would've rejected it.
And so, you know, as we add more and more advanced proofs,
we'll get compositional properties flying out of our systems
that they're easy to use and you know, people prefer to use.
And we might think in a future
where we have AI helping us write certain kinds of code.
The big problem with AI is you ask it to do something
and ask you to write a fragment of code that does something,
it might give you a perfectly valid fragment of code
that compiles but does the wrong thing.
And if we had languages where you could say,
write a function that sorts these disarray
and prove that it did that it could actually write the proof
and you could, if the compiler didn't beep with it,
you could trust it was actually sorting the array
and otherwise you could go back to the AI
and say, well that didn't work.
But you know, getting to the point where we know
that our programs do what we say they're going to do
or think they're going to do is a very important thing.
- And by the way, I should mention that you sent me a note
about Curry-Howard correspondence,
which I went down a rabbit hole
and that's a whole fascinating field which shows
the mathematical relationship between programs and proofs.
- That's right, this is a result from the 1930s.
It's one of the most important results of computer science
that almost nobody knows about.
But they did this rigorous breakdown of type systems
and the 1930s formulation of programming
and established that everything you can prove
in mathematical logic you can prove within a type system
if it has certain features.
And you know, if you break down what is a proof,
well a proof that integer exist as some integer,
like five is a proof that integer exist.
So when you have, you know, something like var xn
and you say X equals five, well you're proving
to the compiler that five is an integer, you know,
that comes as secondhand nature.
But you can prove more advanced things.
You know, if you wanna prove that a pair of things are true,
that like theorem A is true and theorem B is true,
then you need to provide a pair of values,
one that proves theorem A and one that proves theorem B
and that's the conjunctive law of proofs.
And there's a disjunctive law too.
And then there's an implication law for proofs.
And it turns out that's really satisfied by functions.
When you write a function of programming language,
you're saying if you give me this thing,
I will give you that thing.
If you give me a parameter of type something,
then I'll give you a result of some other type.
And by writing that function,
you're proving that given one of these things
you can produce another thing.
And that's a proof of an implication.
And with only like seven laws, you can construct
all of mathematical logic in a type system.
And you know, one of the important thing
for programming language is hasn't been given
enough attention is some aspects of programming languages
are just subjective.
They're just machinations
of the programming language designer, you know.
And Guido van Rossum decided
that Python should support indentation a certain way.
And you know, as long as you're dealing
with things like human notation and naming of things,
there's always going to be that subjective layer.
But there are other parts of programming languages
that are not subjective but should be fundamental.
And when you look at type systems,
there is a way to do type systems
that gives you mathematical proofs.
And every other way of type systems
that doesn't give you mathematical proofs is just worse
and should ultimately be rejected.
And so I think one of the jobs of computing is to identify
what have we actually done right in the past
and what have we done wrong
and for everything we've done wrong
actually going back and fixing it
otherwise we just keep accumulating so much croft
that our systems eventually are crushed
under their own complexity.
And you know, there've been massive announcements
of horrible vulnerabilities in software
and services over the past year.
You know, turns out like some nation state backdoored
a bunch of Teleco's surveillance systems for wiretaps,
like huge problem there.
But you know, ultimately when you break it down
it's probably because of some buffer overrun
in some C program.
Like these decisions about programming languages
have long-term implications.
- It's really fascinating that in building these systems
that hundreds of millions of people use,
you're rethinking about like
how do you actually build it from first principles?
So I should mention that Verse's primary design goals,
it should be simple enough to learn
as a first time programmer,
general enough for writing any kind of code and data.
Productive in the context of building, iterating
and shipping a project in a team setting.
Statically verified to catch as many categories
of runtime problems as possible at compile time
as we were talking about.
Performant for real-time, open-world multiplayer games.
We didn't really quite talk about performance,
maybe I could ask you about that in a second.
Complete so that every feature
of the language support program are abstraction
over that feature.
Timeless, built for the needs of today
and for foreseeable future needs, yeah.
And then there's some design goals
that we talked about that is strongly typed.
Multi-paradigm to use the best of functional programming,
object-oriented programming and imperative programming.
So it's as deterministic as possible.
You know if you run it over and over,
it runs in exact same way.
You know, failable expressions as you talked about.
It's super fascinating.
There's so many cool features in this,
speculative execution, concurrency.
Maybe can you talk about concurrency?
Like what is it about Verse that allows for concurrency
at the scale that you need?
- This is the one biggest technical problem
that we're working to solve in this generation
and that is taming concurrency
so that any ordinary programmer can achieve it
by just writing ordinary code.
- It's hard.
- Programming on a single threaded computer
is hard enough but it is completely predictable.
If you have a language that's deterministic
and you're on the same code over and over,
it's always gonna do exactly the same thing
and there's no unpredictability
about what might happen, right?
You're reading and writing variables in some order
and you're always gonna see it behave the same.
The problem is when you introduce multiple threads
or multiple nodes in a data center all working together
on a single problem, is that they each want to read
and write different pieces of data
and change the state of the world as they go.
And still almost all concurrency
and real world programs today is achieved manually.
Programmers are writing this code
that might run in multiple threads very, very carefully
so that they are negotiating among each thread to get access
to data in a way that's going
to give them predictable results.
And it's incredibly hard.
It's so hard that in five generations of Unreal Engine,
every single generation decided we're not
going to try to scale up all of our gameplay code
to multiple threads manually.
It's just much, much, much too likely to go wrong.
Not only for ourselves, but for every partner company
who licenses Unreal Engine
and tries to use it for building a game,
it's just a massive foot gun.
There's a variety of solutions to concurrency
that are all rather suboptimal.
One attempted solution was like,
"Oh, just don't try to solve this problem at all.
Let's break our program down into microservices.
And almost all online websites have massive scale
like amazon.com work with the hundreds of microservices
where different servers negotiate with each other
by sending messages to each other.
And by programmers writing those things very carefully,
they eventually get to being able to take your orders
and not make a mess of them reliably.
But you know, this is totally not scalable to the metaverse
where you have millions of programmers
who are like mostly not gonna be computer scientists,
they're mostly gonna be hobbyists and enthusiasts
and first time programmers doing stuff for fun.
That's never gonna work for them
because they'll never be able to envision
all the different dependencies
between different computations they're running in parallel.
But it turns out that there was amazing foundational work
done in the 1980s
that was made very real by paper on Haskell concurrency
"Composable Memory Transactions" is the name of the paper.
And it describes the system for
transactional updates to programs.
And the idea of a transaction is
a transaction is a block of code that does a bunch
of operations on memory, might read, might write,
it might process an order, it might accept an order
and/or reject an order.
It might transfer money
between one bank account and another.
It might make conditional decisions like,
oh you asked to transfer $100 from your account
to this guy's account, we're gonna see if you
have $100.
If you don't, we're gonna reject it
and if you have $100,
we're gonna take $100 out of your account
and add it to this other guy's account.
Without transactions, if everybody's just randomly adding
and subtracting each other's bank balances,
then you might have somebody read a bank balance,
subtract a hundred and write it out.
But in the meantime somebody has out written something else
in the meantime.
And so you might get inconsistent bank balances
arising if you don't have a way of ensuring
that these all run in a specific order.
So the idea of transactions is,
it's a way of dividing an entire program into updates,
you know, self-contained updates that do an arbitrary amount
of computation but must run in a single threaded manner.
And in the case of a game engine,
that's a gameplay object update.
When you're playing "Fortnite," you see a gameplay object.
Every other player is a gameplay object.
Every enemy is in a gameplay object.
Every rocket and projectile and car
and thing you see moving around and interacting.
It's not just a fixed static part of the world,
that's a separate game object.
And each of those objects is updated at, you know,
a rate of one update per frame at 60 frames per second.
And so then in the course
of "Fortnite: Battle Royale" gameplay,
you have tens of thousands of object updates
happening every frame with a hundred players.
In a simulation with billions of players,
you'd have a whole lot more than that.
So right now that's done single threaded.
Yeah that's done single threaded in each game session.
This is why "Fortnite" is a hundred players limitation.
If you absolutely maxed out a server,
maybe today you could get up to 140 or something,
but, you know, it's not going to thousands
or millions or billions.
And so what we need is a technique
for magically automatically scaling our code to that.
And transactions are the idea.
And the idea is a transaction is a granule of code
that runs its entirety.
And so the idea of this transactional memory concept
is that we're gonna have programmers
write completely ordinary code,
that reads and writes variables in a completely ordinary way
and they're not gonna have to worry
about concurrency at all.
And then the system, like today a program,
a computer just runs your program.
There's no amount of speculation going on
at the programming language level.
Value of transactions is,
since we have a bunch of operations we need to know,
we apply a large set of them concurrently,
but instead of each one reading and writing
from global memory shared by all,
in which case they might be reading and writing
and contending with each other for the same data
and might be doing contradictory things to it.
We're gonna track all of our rights locally.
We're not gonna write changes out to global memory.
We're gonna keep track of it in a buffer.
It's just for that one transaction.
So it's gonna look to that code exactly
as if it's running on the global system
affecting global game state,
but it's gonna be isolated to just that one transaction
and it's gonna be set aside
and buffered up for consideration later.
We're gonna run tens or hundreds or thousands
of the updates concurrently.
We're gonna see which ones had read-write conflicts
because if two transactions don't read and write
any of the same data, then you could have run them in
either order or simultaneously
and it wouldn't have changed the end result.
- Yeah, the order doesn't matter.
This is so fascinating to imagine this kind of system
arbitrarily concurrent
running millions of updates
in parallel of gameplay objects.
That's the thing that enables the thing
that we're talking about, which is, you know,
tens of millions of people together in one scene.
- Yeah, exactly, and the key is
that you're running these updates speculatively
and you're not committing their changes to memory
until you're sure that they're free of conflict.
So you might update 10,000 objects,
you might find 9,000 of them were conflict free.
So you apply those 9,000 updates to memory
and they could have run in any order
and it wouldn't have changed the result.
- [Lex] That's so cool.
- Now there's a thousand objects left over.
Now you have to run those again.
Try them, maybe interleave in a different way to get them
to eventually commit to memory.
And in the meantime you just throw
all their computations away and redo them later.
And by doing this, like we're moving this
from being a programming problem
for the programmer to deal with,
to being a language problem
for us language designers to deal with.
And we're moving a vast amount of pain
that would be imposed on a million people instead
to a vast amount of pain
imposed on a small number of people
to have to actually make this work.
- That's amazing, that's really incredible.
So what's the state of things with Verse
and I guess what you're outlining is if,
and hopefully it is successful, this would be a big part
of Unreal Engine 6.
So what's the timeline?
Where do we stand today?
- Well there's a lot going on in parallel.
The key thing with Verse
is that we have been specifying like
what we think is the ultimate version of the language
with all the features we want.
Whereas we've been shipping more modest
versions of language over time
and we've released dozens of updates
to it over the past year and a half.
And the idea is that the shipping version gains
more and more features over time,
but each maintaining backwards compatibility
with old versions and each continuing to improve
and approach the ultimate version of it as we go.
And we've been doing this experiment entirely
within the world of Unreal Editor for "Fortnite" for now.
We wanna test this and iterate
with "Fortnite" creators in just the metaverse usage case
before we make it available to all of our partners
using Unreal Engine for all of their projects.
And the idea is to iteratively improve it and build it out.
'Cause right now UEFN has relatively
few features for programming.
It needs a lot more and everything we add makes the world
a much better place for "Fortnite" creators
and we're adding major, major new APIs every few months
throughout the course of this year.
Whereas Unreal Engine licensees
who are building standalone games
already have access to the full engine through C++.
They have massive, massive expectations of an API.
And so we can't release this to them
until we've built up all of the essential features
that they'll need for building
their game play in the future.
And so, you know,
we have these two different tendrils of progress.
There's Unreal Engine 5 for game developers
and there's Unreal Engine 5
targeting the "Fortnite" community.
And there's different bits of development
that are only in one area of it,
there aren't applied to both.
Like not all of the Unreal Engine 5 features
are actually available in "Fortnite"
because some of them we haven't figured out
or haven't gotten to the point where we can deploy them
to all seven platforms in a platform independent way.
And so the place where all of these different
threads of development come together is Unreal Engine 6.
And it's a few years away.
We don't have an exact timeframe
but you know, we could be seeing preview versions of it
perhaps two to three years from now
and we're making continuous progress towards it.
- So that's really nice.
So there's this ultimate version of a language
that you're constantly working on and thinking through.
Then there's the shipped version of the language
that's used by a large number of people
but still in the constrained environment
of the Unreal Editor for "Fortnite."
So for the "Fortnite" game.
And then there awaits the more general
Unreal Editor, Unreal Engine
for the lessons learned in the "Fortnite" context
to be integrated in the more general context
of creating simulated worlds for all kinds of games,
including "Fortnite."
It's a really nice setup
'cause it's a testing ground of the language in "Fortnite"
and you're keeping an eye on
what the ultimate thing will look like also,
necessary to deliver all the features
that we mentioned, brilliant.
- You know the aim for UE 6 is to bring
the best of both worlds together.
A much easier gameplay programming
for the "Fortnite" community and for licensees,
more scalability to large scale simulations of all sorts.
Greater ease of use, meaning it'll be easier
to hire programmers who are familiar with
and experienced with the thing,
but also ensure that every game developer
has the full deployment capabilities
so that it can build a game once
and then ship it anywhere.
Like the Autumn version of this enables a game developer
to build a game of any sort
or simultaneously both ship it into "Fortnite"
as a "Fortnite" island that players can go into,
bring their "Fortnite" items and cosmetics
and interoperate properly
or ship as a standalone game or both.
And if they ship as a standalone game,
they shouldn't be missing out on the, you know,
open economy either
because in this timeframe we'll have opened up
the "Fortnite" item economy
to third party developers of all sort.
Hopefully there is standards body,
but there might be multiple phases of it
so that if you choose to ship a standalone game
you can still choose to, you know,
have "Fortnite" items work in your game
and have your game items work in "Fortnite"
and have your item economy integrated
with the overall metaverse economy
and solve the really core problem of the game industry
that Matthew Ball has been documenting
over the past few years.
- Yeah, by the way, Matthew Ball has been really helpful.
He wrote a really great book
that I recommend people check out.
There's an updated version.
Let me just ask for, 'cause again, there's a bunch
of indie developers listening to this.
I saw that a lot of solo developers out there,
they're using Unreal Engine
that they're basically creating video games solo.
I can highly recommend it's great, "Choo-Choo Charles,"
it's a great video game. (laughs)
Gavin Eisenbeisz, a great guy.
He's solo created this game that's I think quite popular.
I believe he says he used visual,
he didn't even use C++.
He used visual scripting, he used blueprints to create it.
Okay, so I mean all that to say
people should go check it out,
support indie developer, support Gavin,
support everybody like that.
I think it's important to say
'cause there's so much genius and artistry out there
that we wanna support the crazy dreamers out there.
Anyway, all that to say, what are the ways you think Epic
can support indie developers like that?
People like Gavin, like give them superpowers
to create games from which they can make at the very least
enough money that they can keep doing their art.
- Yeah, well that's really about productivity
because to be successful with a game,
you have to have a great game.
If you're building a type of game
that nobody's ever built before, you might be able
to build a smaller, simpler game than if you're competing
in a massive genre that has huge expectations.
But it's all about enabling somebody to do that
in a reasonable amount of time that they can spend
and to be able to finish it and chip it
and maintain it successfully.
The tools are a big part of that.
Having the tools be as productive as possible.
But there are a lot of other facets as well.
Like having a content marketplace is a big thing.
You know, just off the shelf piles of content, some free,
some paid built by other creators
can enable a small indie team to build a big game
and just be able to focus on the unique content of the game.
Being able to write their gameplay
and lay out their environments the way they want,
but not have to build every tree and rock.
Yeah, because somebody's already built one
and there's is probably like, you know, perfectly suitable
for your game.
And over time there'll be more and more.
You know, there's also a lot of indie developers
living as content creators.
They'll be releasing content on Fab marketplace
or the Unity Asset Store and earn living for that.
But specialization of labor
is a really, really valuable thing.
In the early days,
pretty much one person would build one game.
Like that's how a lot of the games were built in the 1980s.
Over time you had a separation
where artists became specialized and then programmers
and then gameplay programmers and engine programmers.
Now you have technical artists
and you have, you know, dozens of different specialties
contributing to a AAA 3D game now.
And the more we can modularize those bits of content
so you could get something off the shelf
rather than having to build it or have to com,
you know, engine synthesize it for you,
the more we can enable creators
to create stuff fast and successfully.
- So we should talk about the fact
that amongst many other things you've been
philosophically and spiritually battling monopolies
in general.
Sort of one of which is sort of the Apple marketplace
that charges 30% from developers.
Can you speak about this idea
that you believe that Apple
and other companies valves should not be charging
that kind of revenue cut?
- Sure, well let's start
from a very basic principle of computing.
The first computer I owned was an Apple II +, you know,
designed by Steve Wozniak and marketed by Apple
and then an IBM PC.
And in those days anybody could write code.
Your computer literally turned on
with a programming language prompt in front of you.
You had to actually do work to not write a program
and to instead run somebody else's program.
That was incredibly empowering.
And anybody could write a program,
anybody could put it on a floppy desk,
anybody could share it with their friends.
Anybody could make copies of that, put it in a store,
they could sell it, they could build a business around it.
And they were completely able to,
without seeking any big tech corporation's permission,
do whoever they want.
Even from IBM, remember IBM
was the dominant computer company on Earth at the time
that they released IBM PC as an open platform.
And you know, so it's really been firmly implanted
in my mind that this was a magical
and wonderful time of unmatched economic progress
for technology in the entire world.
And you know, over time the big companies have realized
that they could shut down
and just block software makers from releasing software
on their own and block software makers from doing business
with customers directly.
And yeah, I've always viewed this practice
as terribly abusive
because when you buy a computer or a phone,
you spend good money on it,
it's your money you spend on that phone
and now you own that phone.
And there's absolutely no reason that Apple should block you
from installing apps
from other developers directly if you want,
going to their webpage or writing your own apps
without their permission and running them yourself
without having to get a developer account,
without having to go through their bureaucracy.
And there's no reason that any consumer
who gets an app shouldn't be able to do business directly
with the developer of the consumer.
You already bought that phone.
Why should Apple be adding a 30% junk fee
to all commerce you do.
And why do they selectively apply it
to some things and not others?
I've always viewed this as deeply abusive
and that it shuts down the competitive engine
that once fueled the app and software economy.
It's still a vibrant competitive engine on Windows
and on the internet, but it's no longer with mobile apps
because these stores have popped up
and they don't provide any useful value to the user.
Yes, they're a search function to find software,
but there's no reason other companies
couldn't build a better one.
And I bet if you had Steam
or if you had Valve build Steam for iPhone,
I bet Steam for iPhone would be a much better app store
than the iOS App Store.
And a lot of people would use it.
And that Apple would be forced
to build a better app store in competition
and everybody would improve their products as a result.
But you know, Apple and Google shutting down
the competitive engine that drives the software economy
has massive implications for everything.
And you know, one of them is reshaping
the nature of mobile apps to be really offensive
to gamer sensibilities.
You know, if you go on console,
the best console games you see listed in the store,
on the storefronts, the best console games
that you see reviewed are awesome games
that really have a lot of creative merit.
The ones that sell the best are really enormous values
for their money
or their product of an immense amount of work.
You don't see that on iPhone.
The top apps on iPhone or the top games on iPhone
at almost all times are these ridiculously greedy,
high monetizing, you know, whale games,
which are pervaded with pay to win and loot box practices,
you know, they have a sort of a legalized a form of gambling
and you know, these games are not driven by fun,
they're driven by manipulation
of the players to greedy ends.
And you know, it's very hard for the fun-based games
to actually succeed there.
And you know, the cost of operating these online games
now are enormously high.
So you have a game that's based on fun,
it's not loot box heavy, you know, you have to pay 30%
of your revenue to Apple
in order to just get access to the platform.
And 30% is way, way, way more than most gaming companies
make in profits right now.
And so if the that fee is more than the profit
from a natural company,
then they can only stay in business by raising prices.
So these 30% fees are raising prices of all digital goods.
It's just inflationary as a force in the economy.
That's just the first drag text.
But then to reach users, when a user searches for like,
before Apple blocked "Fortnite" on iOS,
when a user searched for "Fortnite,"
the first result was always some competing game.
Like it's utterly anti-user.
Like you search for Steam for a game
and if that game's on Steam, it's the first result always.
'Cause Steam's not getting in inshitified
with advertising, Apple is.
And you know, they do that
so they can make even more than 30%.
So if you wanna be the first search result
for your game, you're probably paying more like 45%.
If you wanna reach users on social media,
you're paying another 20%.
So literally something like 70% of the revenue
for your game is just going into junk fees
to acquire users and get them in your game.
And the money that's left over is only enough to fund these,
you know, games with rather abusive practices
that do not look to normal gamers like games
for the most part.
Now there are some exceptions.
There are some great games on iOS
and there's some games with good practices,
but you know, the engine has been really corrupted in a way
that competition would fix.
If you unleashed lots of competing stores on iOS,
then you'd have lots of awesome options
and you'd have much better deals and much better prices.
- I had a quick chat with Matthew.
He asked me to ask you this question of
why don't more companies fight Apple in the way openly
and totally as Epic has been.
What makes you, what makes Epic
so unique in this regard?
And I should say, I think everything you said
I agree with fully.
I think what Apple is doing is just wrong.
I think Apple in many dimensions is an incredible company.
They have brought so much good for the world.
In this regard,
I just think it's straight up wrong what they're doing.
That they're not providing the value of 30%.
And even if they were the monopolization,
the centralized control without competition is wrong.
Anyway, why are you fearlessly fighting Apple on this?
And other companies don't seem to wanna step up?
- All companies are terrified of Apple
because Apple can destroy their business.
Epic was in a unique position with "Fortnite,"
first of all having the, you know,
the biggest game in the world at the time
we started the fight with Apple.
And second of all, having a majority of our users
playing on PC and console
meant that if we lost access to iOS during a fight,
then we would still be able to survive.
That a bigger part,
Spotify, Facebook, you name the top 10 mobile apps,
I think none of them would be able to survive without Apple.
Like literally their business would be destroyed
if Apple blocked access to them.
And Apple is incredibly clear with developers
that they're willing to deprive all users of access
to any app if they get in a fight.
And they've, you know, if you look at how they dealt
with Epic, they were not just legally maneuvering
with the intent of winning the court case against us,
they were also sending a message
to all developers in the world.
We will destroy your business
or we will try our best if you fight us.
And a very small number of vocal developers
have been willing to speak up
and Apple was actually refrained from crushing
their businesses when they weren't violating
any Apple policies.
And that took a bit of discipline,
which I think is also amount of calculation by Apple
that they couldn't survive being seen as the company killer,
that if you criticize us will crush your company.
But you know, the other thing that Apple has,
that they can and will readily deploy
against every developer is soft power.
When they take 30% and advertising is so expensive,
soft power by Apple, like approving your updates faster
or slowing down all of your updates
by a couple weeks can also have a dramatic effect
on your ability to compete successfully.
And Apple, it's a very long history of playing
cat and mouse games with developers.
It's like a developer isn't in Apple's good graces,
so just slow down the updates.
So they've been slowing down updates
for several major tech companies, sometimes for weeks,
sometimes for months without all going under the radar
because everybody's afraid to challenge them publicly.
And so Apple's wielding a soft power can change
a company's economics for the worse,
enough to deter almost any public company.
And you know, Epic is in the fight
because I firmly believe
that something like the metaverse will only arise,
it's something like a billion plus user, you know,
real-time 3D social ecosystem that grows to encompass
potentially all or most major games
by all major developers tied together into an open economy
where they all participate as peers
and they all compete to give users the best deals
and they grow and, you know, do business
with their customers directly.
That thing can only exist if the Apple
and Google gatekeeping monopolies are lifted.
And it's not just the 30% fees.
30% fees are economically ruin us,
but they impose other levels of control.
Apple prevents all web browsers on iOS from implementing
web standards better than Apple does.
So Apple has really limited data storage capabilities
and 3D graphics capabilities on, you know, the iOS web APIs.
So APIs you can access from web apps
running within a web browser.
And you know, that's to eventually cripple those apps
to ensure that they can't possibly compete with native apps.
And by depriving web apps of those features,
they prevent web apps from competing with native apps.
Well, you know, Apple,
if they treat the Metaverse the way they treat the web,
they'll say you can only use Apple's metaverse engine.
Unreal Engine is disallowed.
And then they can impose all of their own limitations
on the metaverse to force all commerce through Apple
or force it to be so uncompetitive
and lousy that it can't compete.
And you know, they have this giant array
of these anti-competitive techniques that they use
to disadvantage other app developers, you know,
saying only Apple can build certain kinds of apps
or only Apple can integrate certain features.
In Europe, even where the DMA law requires Apple
to allow competing stores,
they say a store can only be a store.
You can't build a store into Facebook,
you can't build a social network into a store.
A store must only be a store
because a store that's more than a store might be able
to compete with us more effectively.
It's just a giant, you know, to use the Soviet term,
it's a defense in depth strategy
where they've constructed a massive series of barriers,
each are fatal to any attempt to compete
so that even if one barrier is overcome,
the others remain in place and shut down the whole scheme.
And that's playing out in Europe where Apple has enabled us
to launch the Epic Game Store, but has made it so difficult
and uncompetitive both for Epic
and for clients who we want to do business with that,
you know, it has no chance of success
until the European Union
and starts to really enforce the DMA law and impose harsh
and serious penalties on Apple to force compliance.
- I think it should be said, once again, I think it's wrong
what they're doing there and I hope there's public pressure
and government pressure for them to open up the platform.
And I believe as a person
who loves Apple, I believe this is also good for Apple.
There's the natural thing in companies to want to close
and control and crush competition.
But like Apple is full of brilliant engineers,
open it up and win, it's going to create the right
kind of competitive incentive to make the Apple Store better
to make, you know,
'cause they're great at creating great interfaces,
but competition will sharpen the sword.
I mean, it's just gonna make everything much better.
So I do hope there's a lot of public pressure
and I deeply appreciate
that you're speaking out in this way, sort of putting
that pressure and letting people know
like it's okay to say that this is wrong.
- Thanks, competition makes everybody better.
You have a monopoly that's forced to compete,
suddenly the monopolies products get much better,
the offerings to consumers get much better.
You see so many areas where Apple could be the best,
but what they have is just really, really lousy.
And it's this old guard of leadership who is clinging
to these old policies, turning themselves into the enemy
of every developer, every regulator.
And I think it's ultimately massively to their detriment.
And I can't wait for a new generation to come in
and, you know, paint a bright path to the future.
Epic was an awesome partner to Apple
for more than a decade of demos and partnership
and technology usage together.
And we did amazing things together.
Love nothing more than to have that Apple, you know,
bringing back Steve Wozniak's original views.
Just the Apple II was such an amazing thing.
It's a completely open platform.
The manual to the Apple II included a listing
for all the ROMs, the source code to the ROMs,
so you could understand exactly what was happening there
and you could learn from it.
It included a hardware schematic of the entire computer
so you could learn how to make a peripheral and plug it in
and an open ecosystem.
And that's the awesome Apple,
that company would be the best company in the world.
Again, I think the current one is just
on the wrong side of history and needs to change.
- Well I hope Epic and Apple find a path forward together
and flourishing together
and Apple embraces competition better.
One of the things I admire about this conversation
that you mentioned Steam a bunch, with kind words,
supportive and basically never mentioned Epic Game Store.
I love that.
So I really love that.
It really embodies the fact that you want variety,
you want freedom for people to choose the best thing
and in so doing, create this large network
of humans interacting freely with each other.
Okay, that said, one of the competitive pressures
that Epic has created a few years ago
was by launching the Epic Game Store.
And instead of Steam's 30% revenue cut,
you went with 12% revenue cut
creating the competitive pressure saying, you know,
"Listen, this shouldn't be that high of a cut."
Which I thought was like amazing.
This is a brilliant idea
and I think it still is a brilliant idea, it's wonderful.
Now in preparing for this conversation,
I looked on the internet and I saw
there's a lot of criticism of EGS at Big Game Store.
First of all, I should say the internet, (laughs)
it's full of drama and criticism.
Like there's not enough celebrating of awesome shit,
that let's get...
If I can ask the internet as a blob one request,
can we just celebrate awesome and also criticize.
But just like there's not enough celebration.
Anyway, the two directions of criticism
is just straight up the Launcher interface is clunky
and lacks a lot of the features of Steam.
And then the second set of criticism
is the exclusive contracts
which were made with some of the games
that are on Epic Game Store.
So first huge props on the 12%.
Maybe you could speak to the vision of that.
And second, can you comment on those two criticisms?
- Sure, yeah, I think, one of the reasons that people
characterize the Epic Games launcher is clunky
is because like the Epic Games launcher is clunky
and we need to improve this. (laughs)
You know, there's a lot of work going on there
and you know, I wish we'd gotten better
at addressing quality of life features
and prioritize them above all of the other features.
You know, because Steam has 15 years of built up work
by many of the best programmers in the whole industry
working on that.
A much larger team working on Steam
and a lot more time working on it.
And so we've had to make a lot of prioritization decisions
about what do we support with the Epic Game Store and when.
A lot of the time it's been supporting commercial features
like merchandising, offering multiple versions of a game
for sale and offering upgrades from the regular edition
to the deluxe edition and other things that partners work.
And you know, other priorities have been quality of life
and launcher load times and other things.
And we've not put enough emphasis
on the quality of life features.
We've recognized this very clearly multiple times
and we've gone through multiple refactorings.
But you know, that's definitely been a disappointment to us
and to a lot of users.
And I think one thing it took us a while to realize
was it's not in uniform.
Depending on your proximity to a CDN
and the size of your game collection,
it can be either awesome or really clunky.
And the users for whom it's really clunky
are the people like I think
are a large part of the complaints.
- They're gonna speak up.
And I should also say that the Steam launcher
for a long time, from my memory,
but also just looking online was also very clunky
in the beginning.
- Yeah and you know, one of the criticisms of Epic Game
Store from the beginning was you don't have
all of the features of Steam,
but we very much don't want
to have all of the features of Steam.
Like Steam has forums to get to your game
and like we decide we don't wanna create forums
and our partners when we talk to them,
generally didn't want us to create Epic Game Store forums
for their games
because there's already, you know,
channels that they prefer to them.
There's social media and a number of platforms
and there's Reddit and there's lots of places for gamers
to discuss their game
and they preferred those discussions to be there.
And so it's very much not our goal to mimic everything
of Steam, but we do wanna have
all of the convenience features that makes it as easy
and fun to use as Steam.
So there's a long journey ahead,
but you know, we continue to reinvest in
and you know, we're working
to build a multi-billion dollar business there
and think we'll succeed.
Already at the Epic Game Store,
yeah, supports an immense amount of Epic games commerce
in "Fortnite," on PC, now on Android and iOS
and the European Union too.
So it's a forever facet of the industry
and we are never losing heart in it.
And we think at some point, you know,
I really feel that the benefits of the Epic Games approach
are gonna outweigh the benefits of this Steam approach,
especially as gaming becomes multi-platform.
One of the things that really sucks for all gamers is that,
you know, you have a lot of friends in the real world,
everyone has different platforms.
Your Steam friends aren't connected to your Xbox friends
and they're not connected to your PlayStation friends,
or your Nintendo friends.
And so you're very much bottling up PC gaming
into a kind of a hard core group of PC only folks
and making all of the other aspects of it difficult.
You know, a lot of games have flocked towards Discord,
which is a mess in itself.
Can now your Steam name is not your Discord name
and that's not your PlayStation name.
And so now you have two people in a game
and they have four different identities and that sucks.
You know, our aim for that is, you know,
with Epic Online Services and the social systems
that we built for "Fortnite" opened up
to all developers to have cross kept platform social
features be super easy and free for all developers.
This is not something we're trying to gatekeep
or rent seek on or lock people into.
It's just a way that we're making social gaming easier
for everybody.
As more and more games follow the "Fortnite" approach
of being multi-platform, especially multi-player games.
You know, Metcalfe's law is a very real phenomena
in the industry.
It's the thing that's upending some games
and causing growth in other games.
It is the number one trend
for pervading the world of gaming today.
And it says that, you know, your game is
quadratic more valuable the more percentage
of a user's real world friends they can connect to.
Your game vastly benefits by connecting
all of its players together and not, you know,
segregating them off into different online platform
populations and so on.
And so, you know, I think the future trend
is in that direction.
I wish Velvet opened up Steam Works
to just work on all platforms.
They could have easily done it, we did it,
but you know, they seem to be using it as a lever
to keep people locked into the Steam PC game store.
And you know, that's gonna be a long long running battle
because there's always a very toxic group of Steam users
who, like, they even created an entire subreddit dedicated
to criticizing Epic on our store.
And they create, you know, basically harassment campaigns
at times against developers who use Epic Online Services.
You know, developers do that
so they can connect their players across platforms
and have friends across platform
and voices across platforms.
But, you know, suddenly that's trying
to be turned into a negative.
- It's clear that Epic wants developers to win,
wants gamers to win
and wants Steam to do awesome also.
And in the competition between Steam and Epic Game Store,
like create awesome stuff together.
I mean there's just, it's obvious to me
if you don't read this stuff online,
but online it's like there is this just negativity
that I don't think is constructive in general.
I give a big sort of positive
thank you and props for the push to multi-platform
that was always there with for "Fortnite."
Perhaps before the pressure
that Epic created on breaking the barriers of Xbox
and PlayStation and PC and be being multi-platform.
Like I got a chance to play with "Fortnite" a little bit
with you and all the people in the group...
By the way awesome interface audio chat, really fun.
But you could see like a couple of PC folks,
a PlayStation person, Xbox person all together.
You can't really tell what they're using
except for a little icon.
And it's nice, it's like all these barriers
that we've created with these platforms are gone
and you creating the pressure with Epic Game Store
and just everything you're doing with "Fortnite" platform,
it's really nice.
There's no reason to create these silos
'cause ultimately you should put the gamer first
and let everybody interact
with actual real life friends
and make new friends across the entire network of humans.
So anyway, thank you for that.
Thank you for creating that pressure.
- Thanks, yeah, that was an interesting time.
Sony had a long running policy
preventing cross-platform play
and we had a long series of conversations
which got pretty harsh towards the end,
but Sony ultimately came around
and they opened up PlayStation
and you know, through a series of private conversations
they did the right thing.
And not only that, our partnership with Sony has increased,
you know, since that argument back in 2018.
And we've gotten closer and closer
and done ever more things with, you know, Sony, you know,
brand IP like the characters from "God of War"
and other games coming into "Fortnite"
and you know, all kinds of crossovers.
Massive Unreal Engine adoption
and Sony for making games,
for making movies at Sony Pictures,
music partnerships with Sony Music.
That's been an absolutely wonderful relationship.
And I think, you know, that stands as an awesome example
of a company that, you know,
because of historic reasons got, you know,
stuck with a policy that no longer made sense for the future
and you know, following a serious discussion
with a close partner, righted it and did an awesome thing
and now Sony's much better off and Epic's better off
and all game developers are better off
and the whole console industry
I think it's a lot stronger now than it would've been if,
you know, these silos had continue to be playing out.
And despite the kind of potential concern
that like maybe blocking platform play
with Xbox gave Sony advantage, you know.
Sony's actually grown in market share
relative to Xbox since that time.
And so you can't say that anything
but goodness came of that time.
And I think a better version of Apple would've received
the email I sent to Senior Apple Management
and been like, "Huh, there's an issue here.
We should have a discussion,
we should reconsider this, we should listen."
And you know, they didn't and that's why we're in the midst
of a five-year battle with Apple
and in, you know, hopefully they're,
still the early days of a 15 plus year partnership
with Sony.
- Come on Apple, we love you Apple,
do a little bit better.
The second line of criticism that I mentioned,
the exclusive contracts with some of the games.
Can you just speak to that
because in so much of the journey of Epic
you've been sort of against exclusivity.
- Let's back up and talk about the principles at work here.
Apple forcing other companies
to use their payment service is a cursive decision by Apple.
- But if Apple convinced other developers
to use their payment service by offering benefits
or a better deal or funding
or any other positive incentive,
then that would be perfectly fine.
One is preventing competition
and the other is actual competition.
Epic has never forced any developer
into any sort of exclusivity relationship.
Rather we've offered developers payment or incentives
or marketing or any number of things of value to them
in exchange for coming to our store exclusively.
And it's their game.
So it's entirely rightfully up to them
to decide how to distribute it
and to make the decisions about their business.
It's their game.
If they wanna distribute it through Steam, they can.
If they wanna distribute it
through Epic exclusively, they can.
If they wanna distribute it through both,
then they could do that as well.
And if we pay them money
or other things of value in exchange
for them coming exclusively to the Epic Game Store,
I think that's their right.
And this is an example of Epic, an underdog
with a tiny fraction of Steam's market share,
working to proactively compete with Steam
by offering a better supply of games.
And some consumers who prefer Steam might prefer
that the game be on Steam,
but the developer in each case has decided
that they believe they would benefit more
by doing this exclusive deal in exchange for benefits
than by being on Steam.
And you know, like one of the key exhibits
in the Epic-Google trial was it's opening exhibit,
which was trying to point out to the jury in the trial
the benefits of exclusives.
Like imagine a new store popping up.
The store has a big sign outside of it,
"We're the new store store, we have everything
that the other store has and it's at the same price."
Are you gonna go to the new store? No.
You know, nobody's gonna switch from Steam
if Steam has all of the same games as the competing store
and everything's priced just the same.
And so we looked at initially two ways
of competing with Steam strongly.
We wanted to sell BET games at a better price than Steam
by agreeing on the amount of money
we pay each game developer, you know,
if the game's gonna sell for $50 and we take 12%,
we'd actually lower the price
and potentially even lose some money to offer a better deal.
Well, you know, we tried to pursue this,
but very quickly every developer told us
that they wouldn't agree to better pricing
because if they did then Steam would stop giving them,
you know, marketing featuring and benefits
and the console makers would be mad
and all their relationships would be harmed,
you know, so there's an undercurrent of powerful platforms
and ecosystems encouraging developers
not to compete on price.
So not being able to compete on price,
we decided to compete on supply by doing exclusive deals
and we signed a lot of them,
paid developers lots and lots of money.
I think we distributed over a billion dollars
in net expenditures to developers beyond
the revenue we actually made from games
in order to get a whole lot of exclusive games.
Some are successful, some weren't.
"Borderlands" did awesomely on the Epic Games tour
and Gearbox felt that it did just as well through Epic
as it would've done on Steam
because you know, the players who wanted "Borderlands"
wanted "Borderlands" and they came and got it.
Whereas a lot of other games, you know,
some smaller games especially
that didn't have a dedicated audience
that was absolutely gonna play the game
typically benefited from exposure on Steam.
They were reaching an audience
that wouldn't have reached organically.
And so some of them in the end we
and they concluded that they did worse
by being on the Epic Game Store exclusively
in terms of, you know, reaching fewer customers.
And so, you know,
we had these limited time exclusives,
when they ran out, they put their games on Steam
and you know, lots of data was gathered
to understand what worked.
And so this worked well for some games,
didn't work for other games.
But you know, companies
seeking to compete,
especially underdogs seeking to compete,
have to offer some unique value, have to offer something
that's not available through their competitors.
And I get that Steam users who just prefer using Steam
and buying games on Steam and wanna have their library
in one place don't like this.
But you're never gonna have competition
for better deals if you don't support
the competitive mechanisms
that allow competitors to come about.
And I think if Valve were forced
through Epic Game Store's success to compete
with Epic Game Store, then developers would be getting
a better deal, consumers would be getting a better deal
and these 30% fees would be driven down
quite a lot towards the actual costs
that are required to support the stores.
- Yeah, I mean there's a lot to be said there.
You know, I've gotten to watch Spotify
try to do this with podcasts, you know,
enter as the underdog into the space
and try to attract, you know, they made exclusive deals
with, for example, for Joe Rogan
where the podcast would only be published on Spotify.
I personally think long term what I would love to see
for EGS for Epic Game Store is to not do any exclusivity.
Similar to what Spotify's doing now.
Even with Joe Rogan, they let go, it's wide open.
And instead compete on the space of just
the non-clunkiness of the interface
because the foundation of what
Epic games still represent with 12%,
it's just philosophically.
So you're also competing on the sort of spiritual realm
of like what it stands for, ethically.
That's also a really powerful way to win.
So now that there's enough number of people
using at the Epic Game Store, like to drift away,
to move away from exclusivity.
It's understandable that it's needed for the competition
for the underdog to enter the scene.
But it goes against the sort of the freedom,
the free spirit of choice that I think you represent
in a lot of the decisions you've made,
which is making the games cross platform.
And just yes, giving freedom to the developers,
giving freedom to the gamers to choose.
So in that way I think exclusivity a little bit
goes against that.
- Well here's the conundrum, the exercise of soft power
by all of the competing stores
has made it intractable for almost any developer
to offer a better price
through the Epic Game Store than through Steam.
You can imagine that if the effective Epic revenue
sharing 12% to developers was
that games just cost 22% less on Epic Games,
sorry 18% less on Epic Game Store.
That would actually start
to reshape consumer behavior significantly.
People would start coming here for the better deals.
But I feel like Steam, you know,
giving developers nasty phone calls
and so on, when they propose to do that
prevents developers from passing on savings to consumer,
then what's the mechanism that drives users away
from the incumbent store to the store
that offers a better deal.
If basically developers are fearful of competing on price
through stores, you know,
what can possibly be done to get a dominant store with,
you know, something like 90% of revenue share from,
you know, multi publisher stores,
you know, in line so that a much,
much smaller store can compete.
I think some answers required there.
A better UI is great.
Like Steam is super polished.
Epic Game Store and you know,
time will hopefully be as polished.
You know, how does that overcome the fact
that your entire library over the past 15 years is there.
If developers have been afraid
to exercise their own economic interest
because there's own developer's interest to sell on Epic
and you know, 18% more of the revenue.
You know, I think there's a real power to incumbents.
It's very hard to overcome through just being there
and being as good.
- Ultimately, where I hope it converges to
is less exclusivity.
And where the competition can be the kind I love the most,
which is on the UI,
on the experience, on the just...
And then on the Steam side, on the 12%.
So it can go from 30%
and start to support the developer
by lowering it from 30% closer to 12%.
So anyway, I'm a big supporter
and I don't like the criticism of Epic Game Store,
but I also have to say that I don't love the exclusivity
but I understand.
I understand the reality of the world is
that you have to have some mechanism to get people
to switch or not to switch
but to at least get some of their games to try out,
to experience, to allocate some of their library
to the underdog.
So I totally understand.
And hope the UI keeps improving.
(Tim laughing)
- Thanks, one more bit on that exclusivity point
is that when we told Google that we were going
to launch "Fortnite" outside of Google Play
and go into competition with them, they viewed exclusivity
as such a powerful competitive force
that they went around to the top 30 publishers
and paid out hundreds of millions of dollars to them
in order to agree not to do exclusive deals
with competitors.
And that was called Project HUG, H-U-G
Hold developers Close.
And that was one of the major pieces of evidence
on which the jury found their practices
to be illegal and anti-competitive.
And the one more data point on that,
you know, we talk about 30%
and there's always a lot of people defending Steam.
Well of course they have more costs
because they have more features than Epic.
We have data on that's very detailed.
The all in cost of operating the Google Play store,
stocking it, maintaining it, the software,
the entire ecosystem is around 6% of revenue.
So you know, in a competitive market,
what a company whose cost is 6%,
people to charge 30%, like absolutely not.
And Apple's costs are similar.
Apple runs an even more efficient
and lean operation than Google.
So their costs are also likely in the range of 6% all in.
They mark it up from 6% to 30%.
Like only a monopoly can do that.
Look at competitive businesses,
they have a margin of a few percentage.
The numbers there are strikingly supportive
of just outright anti-competitive distortions.
- Okay, what do you think
is the future of the gaming industry?
So we've said to me a bunch of exciting stuff
about indie developers so, you know,
do what are called AAA video game companies,
so these big gaming companies, do they have a future?
What is their role?
How do you see like in the next 5, 10, 20 years
the evolution of these big companies and indie developers?
- Yeah, there's one constant in gaming
that I think the industry manages to lose sight of
from time to time astonishingly and that's fun
and people play games for fun.
Our whole job is to deliver fun.
And when you look at a lot of the games
that failed recently, they just didn't deliver fun
or they didn't deliver fun in a manner
that was nearly competitive
with the other sources of fun just in people's lives.
And so, you know,
at a basic level we don't need a terribly complicated theory
to explain a lot of the malas in the game industry.
There's just been a degradation of the capabilities
of a lot of publishers,
partly because of competition for talent.
You know, companies like really vibrant game businesses
like Epic or Riot or others are hiring the best developers
and accumulating them and big tech companies are hiring
the best game developers 'cause there's super talent there.
And so in some cases the companies aren't competing
robustly or getting worse.
They're making games that are less fun.
And you know, I think everything else
that's happened is kind of a side show to that.
You know, there's always political drama and so,
and I think the core is of failure to deliver fun.
And you know, the nature of fun is changing.
It turns out that playing a game together
with your friends in a really socially
and engaging way with voice chat is just way more fun
than playing a solitary game for the most part.
And there are exceptions to that,
but I think we're seeing much, much play time
shifting towards games you're playing
together with your friends.
And not just random internet strangers who happen to play
that game too, but the people actually
you know in the real world.
And that's certainly been the case with me
and with almost everybody I know who's playing
"Fortnite" or similar games.
And that has really significant effect in reshaping
the whole game business.
Because like a single player game,
if you have 20 people with 20 different opinions
of which game to play, each one might buy
a different single player game.
But in a multiplayer game, if there are 20 games out
and each one might have their own completely individual
preference and each one or independently choosing
which game to play, each one might buy a different game.
But they're all realizing that they wanna play together.
And so what players are doing increasingly is playing
a game they like and accept together with their friends,
even if it's not the game that every one of them
might be preferring to play themselves.
Like if you have, and you know,
that's certainly the case in, you know,
different "Fortnite" groups I play with from time to time.
It's like, you know, one player might have been preferring
to play "COD", one might have been
preferring "League of Legends,"
somebody else, something completely random,
but it's just so fun to play together, we're doing that.
And that means that there's really strong
Metcalfe's law effect in games
which are able to attract a large percentage
of your friends are more able to attract you
and not only attract, but also retain.
And so, you know, I think Matthew Ball's analysis
of this over the years has really documented
the trend towards, you know, you can call it the metaverse
or you can call it large scale multiplayer social gaming.
He is really documented this trend
and you know, over the past year or so it's taken a really,
really strong turn towards increasing rate of change,
increasing numbers of players coming to "Fortnite."
You know, we hit an all time high
of 110 million monthly active users about a year ago.
(Lex laughing)
- That's crazy. - And another
like close to peak this time.
"Roblox" is bigger than ever.
And you know, this trend is players consolidating
into multi-player experiences of play together.
And we're seeing another trend overlaid with that,
which is like when an awesome single player game comes out
or a small multi-player game comes out,
people often will like treat it as a vacation.
They'll go off and play that game for a while,
then come back.
And I think "Wukong" was an awesome example of
that wonderful game from a brilliant team.
In China they made a game that's like,
no western players had really seen
that type of thing done before.
And it was awesome and it did well,
but most players play it for a while and move back on.
And that could be lucrative.
But a business that's building that kind of game,
it's gonna have to build a new one every few years
and build a business around that while the other games
continue to accrete users.
But you know, when you have a large number of gamers
migrating to a small number of games,
the effect of that is increasing revenue for those games,
increasing reinvestment.
And you know, there are things that Epic can do
with a team of thousands of people building "Fortnite."
Internally and tens of thousands contributing to "Fortnite"
as independent creators.
You know, there are just things that can happen
with that level of investment
that can't happen in a smaller game.
And so there's somewhat of an increasing
winner take all dynamic
where the biggest games reinvest more
to make their games more fun,
to gain fun at a faster rate than other games.
And you know, the industry is changing around that.
And you know, so I think the lesson for the game industry
now is that there are really two big opportunities
being pursued.
There's big games or games that have the potential
to be really big multiplayer experiences
that keep players around, you know, indefinitely
for very long periods of time.
And then there are just really good single player
and small scale games
that people are taking a break from their big games for.
And you know, the trend there is going
to be towards efficiently developing those games.
You can't build one of those games
with a $300 million budget,
but if you can do it with a $40 million budget,
you can make a lot of money.
So I think that's the main reshaping going on
and I think that it creates a rather bleak outlook
for a lot of the category of like single player games
that don't have a huge audience to reach.
But this is just one of the really trends
of restructuring the business around
the technology and changes of the day.
- Okay, this is gonna be a ridiculous question,
but aside from the games you've created,
what are some of the greatest video games
ever created to you?
Like what video games have been like
either impactful to you in your life
or maybe you've seen created
and you're like, "Huh, that's a beautiful art piece."
Like it could be in a totally different realm.
Like obviously for me, I returned too often
to the single player domain of role playing games.
Of the "Elder Scroll" series, "Skyrim",
that was like a world that they created.
A recent game, "Baldurs Gate 3",
that was really incredible piece of work and art
and doing a lot of innovative stuff
again in the single player domain.
Is there games like that outside the ones you've created?
- I'm most impressed with the games that have created
what appears to be a full living, breathing world.
You know, games that give you the sense that
you're just a part of it and there's a lot more happening
and there's, you know, always more.
And you know, gives you the sense that you could go anywhere
and do anything.
Even though these games really do have finite limitations
and there are places you can't go.
It really creating that sense of wonder
is just a magical thing.
Like "Zelda: Breath of the Wild,"
yeah "Skyrim," "Red Dead Redemption"
- [Lex] "Red Dead" is great, yeah.
- It's like there's an entire ecology simulator in there.
I have a high school classmate
that got into studying river ecology
and he was commenting on like
"This is one of the very few games
that's hydrologically sound."
The way, like they actually went to the effort
of shaping the rivers
to follow like erosion dynamics and so on.
It is the attention to detail.
There's something there, it's big,
and it's been funny through the industry.
Like I last designed a game in 1992,
I'm not a game designer.
Yeah, I have a very open-minded
like the best game genre that will ever exist
has not yet been invented.
And as we get more technological capabilities
and creatives, people use that to,
and you know, hopefully empowered
by higher productivity tools and so on that will see more
and more cool things emerge
that we'd never dreamed possible.
And you know, the idea of a world simulator
is actually really interesting there.
It's been tried a lot.
It's, you know, usually extremely slow
and expensive to create,
but over time maybe we'll get better at that
and that will be a thing too.
- You said so many interesting things there.
New city builders. - [Tim] Yeah.
"Civilization," it's a mind boggling
they built a game with that depth that can evolve
so dependent on your actions.
- To do that scale of world,
but to where you can step into it
and be in it, you know.
I think "Red Dead" is a great example,
but to do "Red Dead" redemption in a way
where you can walk around with friends at a large scale.
And I guess what you have given
so many years to is creating the tools
that enable the artists to give that attention to detail
that "Red Dead" does on several of the things.
And once you do, there's something magical about that.
Like once you give that attention to detail,
like, I don't know what it is,
but the love of the artist comes through somehow
and you could feel the care that they put into it.
- That's right, the best games of a soul.
You can really sense it.
You know, like "Call of Duty" has a very different soul
than "Fortnite" and it just kind of exudes not only
in what you see in the game,
but also in how players interact with it
and interact with each other online.
And that's a really fascinating thing
I wish would be studied more.
(Lex laughing)
- I think we talked about the soul on several fronts, right?
I wish it would be studied more.
- Yeah, yeah, all game design decisions
the designers make have a profound impact on what players
think of the game and seeing the game.
You know, "Fortnite: Battle Royale"
always had a sense of mystery to it.
You're on this island but you're not sure
exactly what's happening here.
There are all these houses, they're abandoned, why?
And you know, I'm not the secret holder,
you know, I'm not on the design team.
I experienced "Fortnite" as a player,
but it really exudes a lot of that
and a good spiritedness as well
'cause even when you're eliminated in "Fortnite," you know,
there's not like blood spurts and there's not jibs.
You're just, you know, teleported out of the simulation
and often, you know, you end up losing the game in a way
that's hilarious enough to like,
actually you're laughing at it
or you're like, respect to that player
who just won because that was clever.
And you know, it creates a very different dynamic
than these other games where players
tend to be very, very positive towards each other.
One of the things I like to do in "Fortnite,"
just to kind of gauge how the game is going
is I play full squads
so you get match made with the, you know,
three other random players and play a game together.
Sometimes they have voice chat, sometimes they don't.
And you know, back when our matchmaking regions were bigger,
I learned a little bit of like battlefield Spanish
so I could speak with the people who were down.
- [Lex] Battlefield Spanish - As far south as, yeah.
Mexico City, and you know, the positivity
of the interactions there among just every kind of person
you might ever meet online were really quite impressive
and completely unlike what you would see in a game
like "Call of Duty",
where it's always, you know,
everybody's gotta be an Edge Lord.
(Lex laughing)
- Ah, I love online gaming culture.
I have to ask it 'cause it's kind of like one of
the legendary games is "Grand Theft Auto,"
speaking of the worlds that are just like...
I mean that's a whole, it's that's its own thing, right?
That's that world, the characters,
the style, the edginess, all of that.
But the interesting thing about "Grand Theft Auto 6" to me
that I want to ask you about is they took forever.
It's the six month thing that you mentioned before.
You know, there's some games like that just take years
to bring to the conclusion.
What can you say about that process that, you know,
you eventually were able to take Unreal to completion.
If you were to look from the outside,
why does it take Grand Theft Auto that long
or other companies
to take the games to the conclusion
and I mean, just insight into what that process is like.
- Making games is very hard
and especially when you're pushing
the boundaries of something.
You know, with "Grand Theft Auto,"
it's just the realism
and feeling that you're in this huge city
and anything can happen and it's all living
and breathing in you're just a part of it.
The level with which Rockstar has brought quality
to that genre is astonishing.
And when you're building something at a level of quality
and detail that's never been achieved before,
you can't predict how long it will take.
Whatever problems you're solving today to get to, you know,
the next iteration of quality on it,
you don't know what new problems that will unlock.
And often, you know, you fix one thing
and make it super realistic
and that just highlights the unrealism of other things
that you then need to fix.
And I think the, you know, the thing that always
comes to mind is that shipping a game is easy
if you don't have a high quality standard,
we also won't have much success.
What we've seen from Rockstar is they take a long time,
but they ship amazing games and it's worth it in the end.
Right, a bad game is bad forever.
The late good game is eventually game is released
and is good.
- Do you ever feel, like Rockstar is a good example of that,
the pressure of delivering quality.
You know, Epic has not missed recently
that I'm aware of in terms of delivering quality.
Do you feel the pressure of that,
that you're not allowed misses?
- We certainly do.
Everybody's often working very much to the last minute
to make something excellent.
And it's really hard with these fast delivery timeframes
because you really have to get a lot of stuff up and running
before you can judge it,
like a new "Fortnite" season holistically.
You know, it's not until like the last month or so
that you really know what you've built
and you really understand it.
And if any late breaking problems emerge in like balance
or anything else, it's usually towards the end
and that usually leads to a rapid push to fix it.
And then other lessons you can only learn live.
And you know, from experience
and that means accepting a game that like
it's a live experience and it's also an experiment
and it's gonna continually be improving.
And anytime there's some things that some people don't like
and you learn from it and you improve it and you move on.
- Let me ask you a big philosophical question.
So you've created these gigantic worlds
that bring so much fun to humanity,
but you also get to learn about humanity.
What gives you hope about us humans,
about the future of humans, the future of humanity?
- You know, I see two contrasting worlds that, you know,
have been brought about in the digital age.
One is the world of social networks
and people typing at each other
and just, you know, massive negativity and politics
and, you know, hucksterism
and, you know, curation by engagement
often promoting negativity and toxicity.
That's a harsh world, I think is a step
backwards in many ways.
Like, I think that the foundation of the world
is actually a little bit shaky
because of just the social dynamic
that those platforms have have brought on.
But then I compare that with the good spiritedness
of what's happening online when you're connected
to real people, like actually playing "Fortnite."
Playing "Fortnite," full squads with people
you've never met before, never talked to,
and just judging what, you know,
human connections develop there
and whether they're positive.
I found those to be really, really excellent and endearing.
I think the lesson from all of that is that humans talking
to humans and being together in the real world
or virtual world is
a naturally empathetic medium at which naturally leads
to bonding and though conflict sometimes occurs,
it's just generally so much more promoting
of our social norms
and good interactions between people
and positivity promoting.
Whereas kind of the, you know,
typing angry message is thing at each other
as a self-reinforcing negative dynamic that's negative.
And then I think you though, you look at social media
and you look at gaming that is increasingly social
and I couldn't see a bigger divide between any two medium
as I see there in terms of the actual social dynamics.
One super positive, one super toxic at times.
- Yeah, that's actually really the text-based medium.
Now that could even be around gaming.
You could look at Discord, it could be a real toxic in text,
but you place humans together
in the real world, here in the room.
I literally have never, like,
I very rarely see humans not get along
in the physical space.
And the degree to which you can create a digital space,
like a metaverse type of space
where it's sufficiently immersive,
where you feel the other person, the empathy comes out
and then the joy that's derived from the empathy comes out.
And it's just a reminder that humans like,
I don't know that humans are good
and they wanna see the good in others,
they wanna share the goodness.
And then, you know, like when they get in
that group together, there's love there.
Now they might talk shit about some other group,
this is the dark side of humans, (laughs)
but together in terms of the dynamics
of that group, is joyful.
So yeah, that gives me hope as well.
And the more degree which we can create those worlds
online that make it super easy for us to connect
in that empathic way, the better.
And I am grateful that you are pushing the boundaries
of what's possible in creating such worlds.
And I'm grateful that you would talk with me today, Tim.
This was amazing and it's an honor to talk to you.
- Oh, thank you very much, it's been fun.
- Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Tim Sweeney.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you some words from Benjamin Franklin.
"We do not stop playing because we grow old,
we grow old because we stop playing."
Thank you for listening, I hope to see you next time.