- He said very specifically,
"Depending on the questions you ask Putin,
you could be arrested or not."
And I said, "Listen to what you're saying.
You're saying the US government
has like control over my questions
and they'll arrest me if I ask the wrong question.
Like, how are we better than Putin if that's true?"
Killing Navalny during the Munich Security Conference
in the middle of a debate
over $60 billion in Ukraine funding,
maybe the Russians are dumb.
I didn't get that vibe at all.
I don't think we kill people in other countries
to affect election outcomes.
Oh wait, no, we do it a lot, and have for 80 years.
- The following is a conversation
with Tucker Carlson, a highly influential
and often controversial political commentator.
When he was at, Fox, Time Magazine called him
the most powerful conservative in America.
After Fox, he has continued to host big,
impactful interviews and shows on X,
on the, "Tucker Carlson Podcast" and on, tuckercarlson.com.
I recommend subscribing, even if you disagree
with his views, it is always good
to explore a diversity of perspectives.
Most recently, he interviewed the President
of Russia, Vladimir Putin.
We discussed this, the topic of Russia, Putin, Navalny,
and the war in Ukraine at length in this conversation.
Please allow me to say a few words about the very fact
that I did this interview.
I have received a lot of criticism publicly
and privately when I announced
that I'll be talking with Tucker.
For people who think I shouldn't do the conversation
with Tucker or generally think that there are certain people
I should never talk to.
I'm sorry, but I disagree.
I will talk to everyone as long as they're willing
to talk genuinely in long form.
for two, three, four or more hours.
I will talk to Putin and to Zelensky,
to Trump, and to Biden, to Tucker
and to Jon Stewart, AOC, Obama,
and many more people with very different views on the world.
I want to understand people and ideas.
That's what long form conversations
are supposed to be all about.
Now for people who criticize me
for not asking tough questions, I hear you,
but again, I disagree.
I do often ask tough questions, but I try to do it in a way
that doesn't shut down the other person,
putting them into a defensive state
where they give only shallow talking points.
Instead, I'm looking always for the expression
of genuinely held ideas and the deep roots of those ideas.
When done well, this gives us a chance
to really hear out the guest
and to begin to understand what and how they think.
And I trust the intelligence of you, the listener,
to make up your own mind, to see through the bullshit,
to the degree there's bullshit
and to see to the heart of the person.
Sometimes I fail at this,
but I'll continue working my ass off to improve.
All that said, I find that this no tough questions criticism
often happens when the guest is a person
the listener simply hates and wants to see them grilled
into embarrassment, called a liar, a greedy egomaniac,
a killer, maybe even an evil human being and so on.
If you are such a listener,
what you want is drama, not wisdom.
In this case, this show is not for you.
There are many shows you can go to for that
with hosts that are way more charismatic
and entertaining than I'll ever be.
If you do stick around, please know I will work hard
to do this well and to keep improving.
Thank you for your patience and thank you for your support.
I love you all.
This is the, "Lex Fridman Podcast."
To support it, please check out
our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Tucker Carlson.
What was your first impression
when you met Vladimir Putin for the interview?
- I thought he seemed nervous
and I was very surprised by that.
And I thought he seemed like someone
who'd overthought it a little bit, who had a plan.
And I don't think that's the right way
to go into any interview.
My strong sense, having done a lot of them for a long time,
is that it's better to know what you think,
to say as much as you can honestly,
so you don't get confused by your own lies
and just to be yourself.
And I thought that he went into it
like an over-prepared student.
And I kept thinking, "Why is he nervous?"
But I guess because he thought
a lot of people were gonna see it.
- But he was also probably prepared
to give you a full lesson in history as he did.
- (chuckles) Well, I was totally shocked by that
and very annoyed because I thought he was filibustering.
I thought he would, I mean, I asked him as I usually do,
the most obvious dumbest question ever,
which is, why'd you do this?
And he had said in a speech that I think is worth reading.
I don't speak Russian,
so I haven't heard it in the original,
but he had said at the moment of the beginning of the war,
he had given this address to Russians,
in which he explained to the fullest extent
we have seen so far why he was doing this.
And he said in that speech, I fear that NATO, the West,
the United States, the Biden administration
will preemptively attack us.
And I thought, "Well, that's interesting."
I mean, I can't evaluate whether that's a fear
rooted in reality or one rooted in paranoia.
But I thought, "Well, that's an answer right there."
And so I alluded to that in my question
and rather than answering it, he went off on this long,
from my perspective, kind of tiresome,
sort of greatest hits of Russian history.
And the implication I thought was, "Well,
Ukraine is ours, or Eastern Ukraine is ours already."
And I thought he was doing that
to avoid answering the question.
So, the last thing you want
when you're interviewing someone is to get rolled.
And I didn't wanna be rolled.
So, a couple of times interrupted him, politely I thought,
but he wasn't having it.
And then I thought, "You know what?
I'm not here to prove that I'm a great interviewer."
It's kind of not about me, I want to know who this guy is.
I think a Western audience, a global audience,
has a right to know more about the guy,
and so just let him talk.
'Cause it's not, you know, I don't feel
like my reputation's on the line.
People have already drawn conclusions about me,
I suppose to the extent they have.
I'm not interested really in those conclusions anyway,
so just let him talk.
And so I calmed down and just let him talk.
And in retrospect,
I thought that was really, really interesting.
Whether you agree with it or not,
or whether you think it's relevant
to the war in Ukraine or not, that was his answer,
and so it's inherently significant.
- Well, you said he was nervous.
Were you nervous?
Were you afraid that says Vladimir Putin?
- I wasn't afraid at all, and I wasn't nervous at all.
- Did you drink tea beforehand?
- (chuckles) No, I did my normal regimen
of nicotine pouches and coffee.
No, I'm not a tea drinker.
I try not to eat all the sweets they put in front of us,
which is that is my weakness is eating crap.
But you eat a lot of sugar,
as you know before an interview, and it does dull you,
so I successfully resisted that.
But no, I wasn't nervous.
I wasn't nervous the whole time I was there.
Why would I be?
I'm 54, my kids are grown, I believe in God.
I'm almost never nervous.
But no, I wasn't nervous, I was just interested.
I mean, I couldn't.
I'm interested in Soviet history, I studied it in college.
I've read about it my entire life.
My dad worked in the Cold War.
It was a constant topic of conversation.
And so to be in the Kremlin in a room
where Stalin made decisions, either wartime decisions
or decisions about murdering his own population,
I just couldn't get over it.
We were in Molotov's old office.
So for me that was, I was just blown away by that.
I thought I knew a lot about Russia.
It turns out I knew a lot about the Soviet period,
the 1937 purge trials, the famine in Ukraine.
Like I knew a fair amount about that,
but I really knew nothing about contemporary Russia,
less than I thought I did it turned out.
But yeah, I was just blown away by where we were.
And that's kind of one of the main drivers
at this stage in my life of, you know,
that that's why I do what I do
is 'cause I'm interested in stuff
and I wanna see as much as I can and try
and draw conclusions from it to the extent I can,
so I was very much caught up in that.
But no, I wasn't nervous.
I didn't think he was gonna like, kill me or something.
And I'm not particularly afraid of that anyway.
- Not afraid of dying?
- Not really, no.
I mean, again, it's an age and stage in life thing.
I mean, I have four children,
so there were times when they were little
where I was terrified of dying,
'cause if I died it would have huge consequences.
But no, I mean, at this point, I don't want to die,
I'm really enjoying my life.
But I've been with the same girl for 40 years
and I have four children who I'm extremely close to.
Well now five, a daughter-in-law.
And I love them all, I'm really close to them.
I tell 'em I love them every day.
I've had a really interesting life.
- What was the goal?
Just linger on that.
What was the goal for the interview?
Like, how were you thinking about it?
What would success be like in your head leading into it.
- To bring more information. - [Lex] Just information?
- To the public, yeah, that's it.
I mean, I have really strong feelings about
what's happening not just in Ukraine or Russia,
but around the world.
I think the world is resetting
to the grave disadvantage of the United States.
I don't think most Americans are aware of that at all.
And so, that's my view.
And I've stated it many times because it's sincere,
but my goal was to have more information brought to the West
so people could make their own decisions
about whether this is a good idea.
I mean, I guess I reject the whole premise
of the war in Ukraine from the American perspective,
which is a tiny group of dumb people in Washington
has decided to do this
for reasons they won't really explain.
And you don't have a role in it at all
as an American citizen, as the person who's paying for it,
whose children might be drafted to fight it,
to shut up and obey.
I just reject that completely.
I think, I guess I'm a child of a different era.
I'm a child of participatory democracy to some extent,
where your opinion as a citizen is not irrelevant.
And I guess the level of lying about it
was starting to drive me crazy.
And I've said, and I will say again,
I'm not an expert on the regional,
really any region other than say Western Maine.
I just don't, you know, I'm not Russian.
But it was obvious to me that we were being lied to
in ways that were just, it was crazy the scale of lies.
And I'll just give you one example.
The idea that Ukraine would inevitably win this war.
Now victory was never, as it never is defined precisely,
nothing's ever defined precisely, which is always to tell
that there's deception at the heart of the claim.
But Ukraine's on the verge of winning, well, I don't know.
I mean, I'm hardly a tactician or a military expert.
For the fifth time, I'm not an expert on Russia or Ukraine.
I just look at Wikipedia.
Russia has a hundred million more people than Ukraine.
A hundred million.
It has much deeper industrial capacity,
war material capacity than all of NATO combined.
For example, Russia is turning out artillery shells,
which are significant in a ground war
at a ratio of seven to one
compared to all NATO countries combined.
That's all of Europe.
Russia is producing seven times the artillery shells
as all of Europe combined.
What, that's an amazing fact.
And it turns out to be a really significant fact.
In fact, the significant fact.
But if you ask your average person in this country,
even a fairly well informed person of good faith
who's just trying to understand what's going on,
who's gonna win this war?
Well, Ukraine's gonna win.
They're on the right side.
And they think that because our media,
who really just do serve the interest of the US government,
period, they are state media in that sense,
have told him that for over two years.
And I was in Hungary last summer
talking to the prime minister, Viktor Orban,
who's a, you know, whatever you think of,
he's a very smart guy, very smart guy.
Like smart on a scale that we're not used to in our leaders.
And I said to him off camera, so is Ukraine gonna win?
And he looked at me like I was deranged,
like, or I was congenitally, deficient, are they gonna win?
No, of course they can't win.
It's tiny compared to Russia.
Russia has a wartime economy.
Ukraine doesn't really have an economy.
No, look at the populations.
He was like, looked at me like I was stupid.
And I said to him, I think most Americans believe
that because NBC News and CNN and all the news channels,
all of them tell them that because it's framed exclusively
in moral terms and it's Churchill versus Hitler.
And of course Churchill's gonna prevail in the end.
And it's just so dishonest that even, it doesn't even matter
what I want to happen or what I think ought to happen.
That's a distortion of what is happening.
And if I have any job at all,
which I sort of don't actually at this point,
but if I do have a job, it's to just try to be honest.
And that's a lie.
- There is a more nuanced discussion
about what winning might look like.
- For sure.
- A nuanced discussion is not being had,
but it is possible for Ukraine to, quote, unquote, "win"
with the help of the United States.
- I guess that conversation needs
to begin by defining terms.
And the key term is win.
What does that mean?
- Peace, a ceasefire, who owns which land.
- Yes. - Coming to the table
with as you call the parent, the United States.
- Yes.
- Putting leverage on the negotiation
to make sure there's a fairness.
- Amen, well, of course, and I should just restate this,
I am not emotionally involved in this.
I'm American in every sense.
And my only interest is in America.
I'm not leaving ever.
And so I'm looking at this purely from our perspective,
what's good for us.
But I also as a human being, as a Christian,
I mean, I hate war.
And anybody who doesn't hate war
shouldn't have power, in my opinion.
So I agree with those, that definition vehemently.
A victory is like not killing an entire generation
of your population.
It's not being completely destroyed to be eaten up
by BlackRock or whatever comes next for them.
So yeah, we were close to that a year and a half ago.
And the Biden administration dispatched Boris Johnson,
the briefly prime minister of the UK to stop it
and to say to Zelensky, who I feel sorry for, by the way,
'cause he's caught between these forces
that are bigger than he is to say, no,
you cannot come to any terms with Russia.
And the result of that has not been a Ukrainian victory.
It's just been more dead Ukrainians
and a lot of profit for the West.
It's a moral crime in my opinion.
And I tried to ask Boris Johnson about it
because why wouldn't I, after he denounced me
as a tool of the Kremlin or something,
and he demanded a million dollars to talk to me.
- [Lex] Oh wow.
- And this just happened last week.
And by the way, in writing too,
I'm not making this.
- Just for the record,
you demanded a million dollars from me
to talk to me today. - (chuckles) I did.
And you paid.
No, I'm of course kidding.
And I said to his guy, I said,
I just interviewed Putin who was widely recognized
as a bad guy, and he did it for free.
He didn't demand a million dollars,
he wasn't in this for profit.
Like, are you telling me that Boris Johnson
is sleazier than Vladimir Putin?
And of course that is the message.
And so, I guess these are really,
it's not just about Boris Johnson
being a sad rapacious fraud, which he is obviously,
but it's about like the future of the west
and the future of Ukraine, this country that purportedly
we care so much about all these people are dying
and like what is the end game?
It's also deranged that I didn't imagine and don't imagine
that I could like add anything very meaningful
to the conversation because I'm not a genius, okay?
But I felt like I could at the very least,
puncture some of the lies.
And that's an inherent good.
- Vladimir Putin, after the interview
said that he wasn't fully satisfied
because you weren't aggressive enough.
(Tucker laughing)
You didn't ask sharp enough questions.
First of all, what do you think about him saying that?
- I don't even understand it.
I guess it does seem like the one Putin statement
that Western media ticket face value,
everything else Putin says is a lie
except his criticism of me, which is true.
But I mean, I have no idea what he meant by that.
I can only tell you what my goal was, as I've suggested,
was not to make it about me.
I watched, you know, he hasn't done any interviews
of any kind for years, but the last interview he did
with an English speaking reporter, Western media reporter,
was like many of the other interviews
he'd done with Western media reporters,
Mike Wallace's son did an interview with him
that was of the same variety.
And it was all about him.
I'm a good person, you're a bad person.
And I just feel like that's the most tiresome,
fruitless kind of interview.
It's not about me.
I don't think I'm an especially good person.
I've definitely never claimed to be,
but people can make their own judgements.
And again, the only judgements
that I care about are my wife and children and God.
So I'm just not interested in proving I'm a good person.
And I just wanna hear from him.
And I had a lot of...
I mean, you should see.
I almost never write questions down, but I did in this case
because I had months to, well I had three years
to think about it as I was trying to book the interview,
which I did myself.
But they were all, it was all about
internal Russian politics and Navalny.
And I had a lot of, I thought really good questions.
And then at the last second, and you make these decisions,
as you know since you interview people a lot,
often you make them on the fly.
And I thought, no, I want to talk about the things
that haven't been talked about
and that I think matter in a world historic sense.
And the number one among those, of course, is the war
and what it means for the world.
And so, I stuck to that.
I mean, I could have asked.
I did ask about Gershkovich,
who I felt sorry for, and I wanted Putin
to release him to me.
And I was offended that he didn't.
I thought his rationale was absurd.
Well, we wanna trade him for someone.
I said, well that doesn't that make him a hostage?
You know, which of course it does.
But other than that, I really wanted to keep it
to the things that I think matter most.
People can judge whether I did a good job or not,
but that was my decision.
- In the moment, what was your gut,
did you wanna ask some tough questions
as follow ups on certain topics?
- I dunno what it would mean to ask a tough question.
- Clarifying questions, I suppose they would-
- I guess.
I just wanted him to talk.
I just wanted to hear his perspective.
Again, I've probably asked more asshole questions
than like any living American.
- [Lex] Sure.
- I'm has been noted correctly,
I'm a dick by my nature.
And so I don't, I just feel at this stage of my life,
I didn't need to prove that I could,
like, "Vladimir Putin answer the question." (laughs)
- Sure, for sure.
- You know, I think if I had been, 34 instead of 54,
I definitely would've done that,
'cause I would've thought, this is really about me
and I need to prove myself and all stuff.
No, there's a war going on
that is wrecking the US economy in a way
and at scale people do not understand.
The US dollars going away.
That was of course, inevitable ultimately
because everything dies, including currencies.
But that death, that process of death
has been accelerated exponentially by the behavior
of the Biden administration and the US Congress,
particularly the sanctions.
And peoples don't understand
what the ramifications of that are.
Ramifications are poverty in the United States, okay?
So, I just wanted to get to that
because I'm coming at this from not a global perspective,
I'm coming at it from an American perspective.
- So, you mentioned Navalny.
After you left, Navalny died in prison.
- [Tucker] Yes.
- What are your thoughts on,
just at a high-level first about his death?
- Well, it's awful.
I mean, imagine dying in prison.
I've thought about it a lot.
I've known a lot of people in prison a lot,
including some very good friends of mine,
so I felt instantly sad about it.
From a geopolitical perspective,
I don't know any more than that.
And I laugh at and sort of resent,
but mostly find amusing the claims by American politicians
who really are the dumbest politicians
in the world actually.
This happened and here's what it means.
And it's like, actually as a factual matter,
we don't know what happened.
We don't know what happened.
We have no freaking idea what happened.
We can say, and I did say, and I will say again, I think,
I don't think you should put opposition figures in prison.
I really don't.
I don't, period.
It happens a lot around the world.
Happens in this country as you know,
and I'm against all of it.
But do we know how we died?
The short answer, no, we don't.
Now, if I had to guess, I would say killing Navalny
during the Munich Security Conference
in the middle of a debate
over $60 billion in Ukraine funding.
Maybe the Russians are dumb.
I didn't get that vibe at all.
I don't see it.
But maybe they killed him.
I mean, they certainly put him in prison, which I'm against,
but here's what I do know is that we don't know.
And so when Chuck Schumer stands up and rah,
Joe Biden reads some card in front of him
with lines about Navalny, it's like,
I'm allowed to laugh at that because it's absurd.
You don't know.
- There's a lot of interesting ideas about
if he was killed, who killed him.
- [Tucker] Yeah.
- Because it could be Putin,
it could be somebody in Russia who's not Putin.
- Yeah. - It could be Ukrainians
'cause it would benefit the war.
- They killed Dugin's daughter in Moscow.
So yeah, it's possible.
- And it could be, I mean, the United States
could also be involved.
- I don't think we kill people in other countries
to affect election outcomes.
Oh wait, no, we do it a lot and have for 80 years.
And it's shameful.
I can say that as an American,
'cause it's my money in my name.
Yeah. I'm really offended by that.
And I never thought that was true.
And I spent, again, I'm much older than you.
And so I spent my worldview was defined by the Cold War.
And very much in the house I lived
in Georgetown, Washington, DC,
that's what we talked about.
And yeah, and the left at the time,
I don't know the wacko MIT professor
who I never had any respect for,
who I know you've interviewed, et cetera.
Like the hard left was always saying,
well, the United States government
is interfering in other elections.
And I just dismissed that completely out of hand as stupid
and actually a slander against my country.
But it turned out to all be true
or substantially true anyway.
And that's been a real shock for me
in middle age to understand that.
But anyway, as to Navalny, look, I don't know,
but we should always proceed on the basis
of what we do know, which is to say on the basis
of truth, knowable truth.
And if you have an entire policymaking apparatus
that is making the biggest decisions
on the face of the planet, on the basis of things
that are bullshit or lies,
you're gonna get bad outcomes every time.
Every time.
And that's why we are where we are.
- Does it bother you
that basically the most famous opposition figure
in Russia is sitting in prison?
- Well, of course it does.
Of course it bothers me.
I mean, it bothered me when I got there.
It bothers me now.
I was sad when he died.
Yeah, I mean that's one of the measures of,
it's one of the basic measures of political freedom.
Are you imprisoning people who oppose you?
Are you imprisoning people who pose a physical risk to you?
I mean, there's some subjective decision making
involved in these things, however, big picture.
Yeah, do you have opposition leaders in jail?
It's not a politically free society,
and Russia isn't, obviously.
And as I said, a friend of mine from childhood,
an American actually was a wonderful person
lives in Russia with his Russian, Moscow,
with his Russian wife.
And I had dinner with him.
He's a very balanced guy, totally non-political person
and speaks Russian and loves his many Russian children,
and loves the culture.
And there's a lot to love.
The culture that produced Tolstoy.
It's not a gas station with nuclear weapons.
Sorry, only an a moron would say
that it's a very deep culture.
I don't fully understand it, of course, but I admire it.
Who wouldn't?
But I asked him like, what's it like living here?
And he goes, "It's great."
Moscow is a great city indisputably.
He said, "You don't wanna get involved in Russian politics."
And I said, "What?"
He said, "Well, you could get hurt,
you could wind up like Navalny if you did."
But also, it's just too complicated.
The Russian mind is not exactly the same.
It's a Western, it's a European city,
but it's not quite European.
And the way they think is very, very complex. Very complex.
It's just, it's too complicated, just don't get involved.
And I would just say two things.
One, I'm not sure, I mean like, I don't know,
but my strong sense is that Navalny death, whoever did it,
probably didn't have a lot to do
with the coming election in Russia.
My sense from talking to Putin and the people around him
is they're not really focused on that.
I mean, in fact, I asked one of his top advisors,
when's the election?
And she looked at me completely confused.
She didn't know the date of the election, okay? (chuckles)
She's like, March. Okay.
And I asked a bunch of other people just in Moscow,
who's Putin running against, like nobody knew.
So it's not a real election, right?
In the sense that we would recognize at all.
Second, I was really struck by so many things in Moscow
and really bothered by, deeply bothered
by a lot of things that I saw there.
But one thing I noticed was the total absence of cult
of personality propaganda, which I expected to see
and have seen around the world.
Jordan, for example, I dunno if you've been to Jordan,
but go to Jordan in every building
there are pictures of the king and his extended family.
And that's a sign of political insecurity.
You don't create a cult of personality
unless you're personally insecure.
And also unless you're worried about
losing your grip on power, none of that.
It's interesting and I expected to see a lot of it,
like statues of Putin.
Yeah, there are no statues of anybody
other than like Christian saints.
So that was like, I'm not quite sure.
I'm just reporting what I saw.
So yes, in a political sense, it's not a free country.
It's not a democracy in the way
that we would understand it or want.
I don't wanna live there, okay?
'Cause I like to say what I think.
In fact I make my living doing it.
But it's not Stalinist in a recognizable way.
And anyone who says it is should go there and tell me how.
- I mean this question about the freedom of the press
is underlying the very fact
of the interview you're having with him.
So you might not need to ask the Navalny question,
but did you feel like, are there things I shouldn't say?
- I mean, how honest do you want me to be?
I mean it, when I say I felt not one twinge of concern
for the eight days that I was there.
Maybe I just didn't.
And I feel like I've got a pretty strong
gut sense of things.
I rely on it.
I make all my decisions based on how I feel, my instincts.
And I didn't feel it at all.
My lawyers before I left.
And these are people who work for a big law firm.
This is not Bob's law firm, this is one
of the biggest law firms in the world, said,
"You're gonna get arrested if you do this
by the US government on sanctioned violations."
And I said, well, I don't recognize
the legitimacy of that actually,
'cause I'm American and I've lived here my whole life.
And that's so outrageous that I'm happy to face that risk
because I so reject the premise, okay?
I'm an American, I should be able
to talk to anyone I want to."
And I plan to exercise that freedom,
which I think I was born with.
And I gave them this long lecture.
They're like, "We're just lawyers."
But that was, it was a, lemme put it this way,
I dunno how much you've dealt with lawyers,
but it costs many thousands of dollars
to get a conclusion like that.
Like they sent a whole bunch of their summer associates
or whatever they sent, they put a lot of people
on this question, checked a lot of precedent and I think,
and they sent me a 10 page memo on it
and their sincere conclusion was do not do this.
And of course it made me mad.
So I was lecturing on the phone
and I had another call with a head lawyer and he said,
"Well look, a lot will depend on the questions
that you ask Putin.
If you're seen as too nice to him,
you could get arrested when you come back."
And I was like, "You're describing a fascist country, okay?
You're saying that the US government will arrest me
if I don't ask the questions they want asked
is that's what you're saying?"
"Well, we just think based on what's happened,
that that's possible."
And so I'm just telling you what happened.
- So, you were okay being arrested in Moscow.
and arrested back in-
- I didn't think for a second.
I mean maybe, look, I don't speak Russian,
I'd never been there before.
Everything about the culture was brand new to me.
Ignorance does protect you sort of,
when you have no freaking idea what's going on,
you're not worried about it.
Like this has happened to me many times.
There's a principle there that extends throughout life.
So it's completely possible that I was in grave peril
and didn't know it, 'cause like how would I know it?
I'm like a bumbling English speaker from California,
but I didn't feel it at all.
- But the lawyers did.
- Yeah, I mean it scared the crap out of people.
And look, and you have to pay in cash.
They don't take credit cards because of sanctions.
And you have to go through all these hoops,
just procedural hoops to go to Russia.
Which I was willing to do
because I wanted to interview Putin
because they told me I couldn't.
But then there's another fact,
which is that I was being surveilled by the US government,
intensely surveilled by the US government.
And this came out, they admitted it,
the NSA admitted it a couple of years ago
that they were up in my Signal account,
and then they leaked it to, The New York Times.
They did that again before I left.
And I know that because two New York Times reporters,
one of whom I actually like a lot, said,
"Oh, you're going and called other people,
Oh, he's going to interview Putin."
I hadn't told anybody that, like anybody.
My wife, two producers, that's it.
So, they got that from the government.
Then I'm over there and of course I wanna see Snowden,
who I admire.
And so, we have a mutual friend,
so I got his text and come on over
and Snowden does not want publicity at all.
And so, but I really wanted to have dinner with him.
So we had dinner in my hotel room
at the Four Seasons in Moscow.
And I tried to convince him,
I'd love to do an interview, shoot it on my iPhone,
I'd love to take a picture together
and put it on the internet
because I just wanna show support.
'Cause I think he's been railroaded.
He had no interest in living in Russia,
no intention of being in Russia.
The whole thing is a lie.
But anyway, whatever, all this stuff.
And he just said respectfully,
I'd rather not anyone know that we met.
Great.
The only reason I'm telling you this is because,
and I didn't tell anybody and I didn't text it to anybody.
Okay, except him.
Semafor, Semafor runs this piece
saying reporting information
they got from the US Intel agencies
leaking against me using my money in my name
in a supposedly free country.
They run this piece saying I'd met with Snowden
like it was a crime or something.
So again, my interest is in the United States
and preserving freedoms here, the ones that I grew up with.
And if you have a media establishment
that acts as an auxiliary of,
or acts as employees of the national security state,
you don't have a free country.
And that's where we are.
And I'm not guessing,
'cause I spent my entire life in that world.
33 years I worked in big news companies,
and so I know how it works,
I know the people involved in it.
I could name them.
Ben Smith of Semafor among many others.
And I find that really objectionable,
not just on principle either, in effect, in practice,
I don't wanna live in that kind of country.
And people are like, they externalize
all of their anxiety about this, I have noticed.
So, it's like Russia's not free.
Yeah, I know.
Neither's Burkina Faso.
Like most countries aren't free actually, but we are.
We're the United States, we're different.
And that's my concern.
Preserving that is my concern.
And so they get so exercised about what's happening
in other parts of the world,
places they've never been know nothing about.
It's almost a way of ignoring what's happening
in their own country right around them.
I find it so strange and sad and weird.
- So the NSA was tracking you, as do you think CIA was?
Is people still tracking you?
- Look, one of the things I did before I went,
just because of the business I'm in,
all of us are in and just 'cause we live here,
we all have theories about secure communications channels.
Like Signal is secure, Telegraph isn't,
or WhatsApp is owned by Mark Zuckerberg.
You can't trust, okay?
So I thought, before I go over here,
I was getting all this,
we're having all these conversations,
my producers and I about this,
and I decide, I'm just gonna actually find out
like what's really going on.
So, I talked to two people who would know,
trust me, and it's all I can say.
And I hate to be like, "Oh, I talked to people
who would know by kentu there,"
but I mean it, they would know.
And both of them said exactly the same thing,
which is, are you joking?
Nothing is secure.
Everything is monitored all the time.
If state actors are involved,.
I mean you can keep the, you know,
whatever, the Malaysian mafia
from reading your texts probably you cannot keep
the big intel services from reading your texts.
It's not possible.
Any of them.
Or listening to your calls.
And that was the firm conclusion of people
who've been involved in it for a long time.
Decades, in both cases.
So I just thought, "You know what?
I don't care, I don't care.
I'm not sending a ton of naked pictures
of myself to anybody."
- Not a ton, just a little. - (laughs) A ton.
I'm 54, dude, probably not too many.
- [Lex] All right.
- But you, so I'm like, I'm just,
so the guys I travel with,
three people I work with who I love,
who I've been around the world with for many years,
and I know them really, really well.
And they all got separate phones
and I'm leaving my other phone back in New York or whatever.
And I just decided I don't care actually.
And I resent having to no privacy
because privacy is a prerequisite for freedom,
but I can't change it,
and so I have the same surveilled cell phone.
And I do switch them out because there it is.
Because if you have too much spyware on your phone,
this is true.
It wrecks the battery. (Lex chuckling)
No, I'm serious.
It does.
And we got, it was, I don't know,
five or six years ago we went to North Korea
and my phone started acting crazy.
And so I talked to someone on the National Security Council
who called me about this,
somehow knew that your phone is being surveilled
by the South Korean government.
I was like, why the, I like the South Korean government.
Why would they do that?
Because they want more information.
They thought I was talking to Trump or whatever.
So, but I could tell because all of a sudden
the thing would just drain in like 45 minutes.
So, that's the downside.
- So you keep switching phones,
getting new phones for the battery life.
That's good.
- Yeah. I mean, I try not to do it,
I'm kind of flinty Yankee type in some ways,
so I don't like to spend a thousand dollars
with a freaking Apple corporation too often,
but yeah, I do.
- I mean, you say it lightly,
but it's really troublesome
that you as a journalist would be tracked.
- Well, they leaked it to Semafor,
and they leaked it to The New York Times.
Look, I would even put up, well there's nothing I can do,
so I have to put up with everything, okay?
But I would probably not be actively angry
about being surveilled because I'm just so old
and I actually do pay my taxes.
I'm not sleeping with the makeup artist or whatever,
so I don't care that much.
The fact that they are leaking against me,
that the intel services in the United States
are actively engaged in US politics and media.
That's so unacceptable.
That makes democracy impossible.
There's no defense of that.
And yet NBC News, Ken Dilanian and the rest will defend it.
And it's like, and not just on NBC news, by the way,
on the supposedly conservative channels too.
They will defend it.
And there's no defending that you can't have democracy
if the intel services are tampering in elections
and information, period.
- So, you had no fear.
Your lawyer said, be careful which questions he asked
you said, I don't have-
- Well, the lawyer said no, he said very specifically
"Depending on the questions you ask Putin,
you could be arrested or not."
And I said, "Listen to what you're saying.
You're saying the US government has like control
over my questions and they'll arrest me
if I ask the wrong question.
Like, how are we better than Putin if that's true?"
And by the way, that's just what the lawyer said,
but I can't overstate one of the biggest law firms
in the United States, smart lawyers we've used for years.
So, I was really shocked by it.
- You said leaders kill, leaders lie.
- Yeah, I don't believe in leaders very much
like this whole like Zelensky's Jesus and Putin's Satan.
It's like, no, they're all leaders of countries, okay?
Like grow up a little bit, you child.
Have you ever met a leader?
Like all of the, first of all, anyone who seeks power
is damaged morally, in my opinion.
You shouldn't be seeking power.
You can't seek power or wealth for its own sake
and remain a decent person.
That's just true.
So there aren't any like really virtuous billionaires
and there aren't any really virtuous world leaders.
You have grades of virtue.
Some are better than others for sure.
But I mean, in other words,
Zelensky may be better than Putin.
I'm open to that possibility.
But to claim that one is evil and the other is virtuous,
it's like you're revealing that you're a child.
You don't know anything about
how the world actually is or what reality is.
- That's quite a realist perspective.
But there is a spectrum.
- There is a spectrum, absolutely.
I'm not saying they're all the same, they're not.
- And our task is to figure out
where on the spectrum they lie,
and the leader's task is to confuse us
and convince us they're one of the good guys.
- Of course, of course.
But I actually reject even that formulation.
I don't think it's always about the leaders.
I mean, of course the leaders make the difference.
A good leader has a healthy country
and a bad leader has a decaying country,
which is something to think about.
But it's about the ideas and the policies
and the practical effect of things.
So we're very much caught up in the personalities
of various leaders, not just our political leaders,
but our business leaders, our cultural leaders.
Are they good people?
Do they have the right thoughts?
It's like, no, I ask a much more basic question.
What are the fruits of their behavior?
And I always make it personal
because I think everything is personal.
Does his wife respect him?
Do his children respect him?
How are they doing?
Is the country he runs thriving or is it falling apart?
If your life expectancy is going down,
if your suicide rate is going up,
if your standard of living is tanking,
you're not a good leader.
I don't care what you tell me.
I don't care what you claim you represent.
I don't care about the ideas
or the systems that you say you embody.
It's dogs barking to me.
How's your life expectancy?
How's your suicide rate?
What's drug use like?
Are people having children?
Are people's children more likely to live in a free
or more prosperous society than than you did
and their grandparents did?
Like those are the only measures that matter to me.
The rest is a lie.
But anyway, the point is we just get so obsessed
with like the theater around people or people
and we miss the bigger things that are happening
and we allow ourselves to be deceived into thinking that
what doesn't matter at all matters.
That moral victories are all that matters.
No actually facts in the ground victories
matter more than anything.
I mean you certainly see it in this country.
Black Lives Matter for example.
How many black people did that help?
It hurt a lot of black people,
but in the end we should be able to measure it.
Like how many black people have died by gunfire
in the four years since George Floyd died?
Well the number's gone way, way up.
And that was a Black Lives Matter operation,
defund the police.
So I think we can say as a factual matter,
data-based matter, Black Lives Matter
didn't help black people.
And if it did tell me how.
Well, these are important moral victories, I'm over that.
That's just another lie, long litany of lies.
So I try to see the rest of the world that way,
but more than anything I try to see world events
through the lens of an American because I am one.
And what does this mean for us?
And it's not even the war,
it's the sanctions that will forever change
the United States, our standard of living,
the way our government operates.
That more than any single thing in my lifetime
screwed the United States.
Levying those sanctions in the way that we did was crazy.
For me the main takeaway from my eight days
in Moscow was not Putin.
He's a leader with, whatever.
None of them are that different actually
in my pretty extensive experience.
No, it was Moscow that blew my mind.
I was not prepared for that at all.
And I thought I knew a lot about Moscow.
My dad worked there on and off in the 80s and 90s
'cause US government employee
and he was always coming back,
"Moscow, it's a nightmare."
And all this stuff, no electricity.
I got there almost exactly two years
after sanctions totally cut off
from Western financial systems, kicked outta Swift,
can't use US dollars, no banking, no credit cards.
And that city is just factually,
I'm not endorsing the system.
I'm not endorsing the whole country.
I didn't go to Lake Baikal, I didn't go to Turkmenistan.
I just went to Moscow,
largest city in Europe, 13 million people.
I drove all around it.
And that city is way nicer outwardly anyway,
I don't live there, than any city we have by a lot.
And by nicer, let me be specific.
No graffiti, no homeless,
no people using drugs in the street, totally tidy,
no garbage on the ground and no forest of steel
and concrete soul destroying buildings.
None of the postmodern architecture
that oppresses us without even our knowledge.
None of that crap.
It's a truly beautiful city.
And that's not an endorsement of Putin.
And by the way, it didn't make me love Putin.
It made me hate my own leaders
because I grew up in a country
that had cities kind of like that,
that were nice cities that were safe.
And we don't have that anymore.
And how did that happen?
Did Putin do that?
I don't think Putin did that actually.
I think the people in charge of it, the mayors,
the governors, the president, they did that
and they should be held accountable for it.
- So, I think cleanliness and architectural design
is not the entirety of the metrics
that matter When you measure a city.
- They're the main metrics that matter.
They're the main metrics that matter.
The main metrics that matter are cleanliness,
safety, and beauty in my opinion.
And one of the big lies that we are told in our world
is that no, something you can't measure
that has no actual effect on your life matters most.
Bullshit, what matters most, to say it again.
Beauty, safety, cleanliness,
lots of other things matter too.
A whole bunch of things matter.
But if I were to put them in order,
it's not some like theoretical.
Well actually I don't know if you know
that the Duma has no power.
It's okay, I get that.
Freedom of speech matters enormously to me.
They have less freedom of speech in Russia
than we do in the United States.
We are superior to them in that way.
But you can't tell me that living in a city
where your 6-year-old daughter can walk to the bus stop
and ride on a clean bus or ride in a beautiful subway car
that's on time and not get assaulted, that doesn't matter.
No, that matters almost more than anything actually.
And we can have both.
And like the normal regime defenders and morons,
Jon Stewart or whatever he is calling himself, they're like,
"Whoa, that's the price of freedom."
Like people shitting on the sidewalk
is the price of freedom.
It's like you can't fool me
because I've lived here for 54 years.
I know that it's not the price of freedom,
'cause I lived in a country
that was both free and clean and orderly.
So, that's not a trade off I think I have to make.
That is the beauty of being a little bit older
because you're like, no, I remember that actually.
It wasn't what you're saying.
We didn't have racial segregation in 1985.
It was a really nice country that kind of respected itself.
I was here and I think with younger people
you can tell 'em that and they're like,
well 1985 you were selling slaves in Madison Square Garden.
It's like no, they weren't.
You're going to Madison Square Garden
and not stepping over a single fentanyl addict.
- It is true.
There doesn't have to be a trade off
between cleanliness and freedom of speech.
But it is also true that in dictatorships, cleanliness is,
and architectural design is easier to achieve
and perfect and often is done, so you can show off,
look how great our cities are while you're suppressing.
- Worse, of course, I agree with that vehemently.
This is not a defense of the Russian system at all.
And if I felt that way, I would not only move there,
but I would announce I was moving there.
I'm not ashamed of my views.
I never have been.
And for all the people who are trying
to impute secret motives to my words,
I'm like the one person in America
you don't need to do that with.
If you think I'm a racist, ask me and I'll tell you.
- Are you a racist?
- No, I'm a sexist though. (laughs)
- All right, great.
- Anyway, no, but if I was like
a defender of Vladimir Putin,
I would just say I'm defending Vladimir Putin now, I'm not.
I am attacking our leaders
and I'm grieving over the low expectations of our people.
You don't need to put up with this, you don't need to put up
with foreign invaders stealing from you,
occupying your kids' school.
Your kids can't get an education
because people from foreign countries broke our laws
and showed up here and they've taken over the school.
That's not a feature of freedom actually,
that's the opposite.
That's what enslavement looks like.
And so I'm just saying raise your expectations a little bit.
You can have a clean, functional, safe country.
Crime is totally optional.
Crime is something our leaders decide to have or not have.
It's not something that just appears organically.
I wrote a book about crime 30 years ago.
I thought a lot about this.
You have as much crime as you put up with, period.
And it doesn't make you less free to not tolerate murder.
In fact, it makes you unfree to have a lot of murders.
And so I just, but it makes me sad that people are like,
"Well, you know, I guess this is,
I can't like live in New York City anymore
'cause of inflation and filth and illegal aliens
and people shooting each other,"
but I'm glad because this is vibrant and strong and free."
It's like that's not freedom actually at all.
- Your point is well taken.
You can have both, but do you regret-
- We had both. - [Lex] Yes.
- That's the point.
We had both, I saw it.
- Do you regret to a degree using the Moscow subway
and the grocery store as a mechanism
by which to make that point?
- No, I mean I thought, I mean look, I'm one
of the more unselfaware people you will ever interview.
So to ask me how will this be perceived?
(laughs) I mean, I literally have no idea
and kind of limited interest.
But I was so shocked by it.
I was so shocked by it.
And there were two.
And to the extent I regret anything
and am to blame for anything, it would be not.
And I've done this a lot, not giving it context,
not fully explaining why are we doing this?
The grocery store, I was shocked by the prices
and yes, I'm familiar with exchange rates,
but very familiar with exchange rates, but those don't,
and I adjusted them for exchange rates.
And this is two years into sanctions,
total isolation from the West.
So I would expect, in fact, I did expect until I got there
that the supply chains would be crushed.
How do you get good stuff
if you don't have access to Western markets?
And I didn't fully get the answer
'cause I was occupied doing other things when I was there.
But somehow they have, and that's the point.
And they haven't had the supply chains problems
that I predicted.
In other words, sanctions haven't made the country
noticeably worse, okay?
So again, this is commentary
in the United States and our policymakers.
Why are we doing this?
It's forcing the rest of the world
into a block against us called BRICS.
They're getting off the US dollar.
That will mean a lot of dollars are gonna come back here
and destroy our economy and impoverish this country.
So the consequences, the stakes were really high,
they're huge.
And we're not even hurting Russia.
It's like, what the hell are we doing?
One, on the subway.
That Subway was built by Joseph Stalin
right before the Second World War.
I'm not endorsing Stalin obviously.
Stalinism is the thing that I hate
and I don't want to come to my country.
I'm making the obvious point that for over 80 years
you've had these frescoes and chandeliers.
Maybe they've been redone or whatever,
but like somehow the society has been able to not destroy
what its ancestors built.
The things that are worth having.
And they're a lot.
And that, like why don't we have that?
And even on a much more terrestrial plane,
like, why can't I have a subway station like that?
Why can't my children
who live in New York City ride the subway?
A lot of people I know who live in New York City
are afraid to ride the subway.
Young women especially.
That's freedom?
No, again, it's slavery.
And how can, if Putin can do this, why can't we?
Like what?
In other words, I mean this is like so obvious.
I'm a traitor.
Okay, so if I'm calling for American citizens
to demand more from their government
and higher standards for their own society,
and remember that just 30 years ago we had a much different
and much happier and cleaner and healthier society
where everyone wasn't fat with diabetes at 40
from poisoned food.
Like how is the, I'm not a traitor to my country.
I'm a defender of my country.
And by the way, the people calling me a traitor,
they're all like, you know, whatever.
They're not, I would not say they're people
who put America's interest first. (chuckles)
To put it mildly.
- There's many elements.
Like you said, you don't like Stalinism.
You're a student of history.
Central planning is good at building subways
in a way that's really nice.
The thing that accounts for New York subways, by the way,
there's a lot of really positive things
about New York subways, not cleanliness,
but the efficiency, like the accessibility
of how wide it spreads.
Now the New York network is incredible.
But Moscow under different metrics,
results of a capitalist system.
And you actually said that you don't think US
is quite a capitalist system,
which is an interesting question itself.
- That's true.
We have more central planning here than they do in Russia.
- No, that's not true.
- Of course it is.
- You think that's true.
- The climate agenda, of course.
They're telling the US government
has in league with a couple of big companies,
decided to change the way we produce and consume energy.
There's no popular outcry for that.
There's never been any mass movement
of Americans who's like, I just,
I hate my gasoline powered engine.
No more diesel.
That has been central planning.
That is central planning.
And you see it up and down our economy.
There's no free market in the United States.
You get crossways with the government, you're done.
If you're at scale.
I mean maybe if you've got a barber shop
or a liquor store or something,
but even then you're regulated by politicians.
And so no, I actually am for free markets.
I hate monopolies.
Our economy is dominated by monopolies.
Completely dominated-
- Like, what do you mean?
- Google, what percentage of search does Google have? 90.
Google's a monopoly by any definition.
And Google is just rich enough
to continue doing whatever it wants in violation of US law.
So there's no monopoly in Russia as big as Google.
I'm not, again, defending the Russian system.
I'm calling for return to our old system, which was sensible
and moderate and put the needs of Americans
at least somewhere in the top 10, (laughs)
somewhere in the top 10.
I'm not saying that Standard Oil
was like interested in the welfare of average Americans,
but I am saying that there was a constituency
in our political system, in the Congress for example,
different presidential candidates were like,
"No, wait a second, what is this doing to people?
Is it good for people or not?"
There's not even a conversation about that.
It's like, shut up and submit to AI and no offense,
and so I'm just- - Offense taken.
(Tucker laughing)
I'll write, we will get you.
When it's stronger enough. - Yeah.
I have no doubt.
- You'll be the first one to go.
- As a white man, I just won't even exist anymore.
- Right, so much to say on that one.
- I bet when you google my picture 20 years from now,
it'll be a black chick.
(Lex chuckling)
- A hundred percent.
- Well, I hope she's attractive.
- I hope so too.
It'd probably be an upgrade. (laughs)
- So, well, the central planning point
is really interesting, but I just don't,
I don't know where you're coming from.
There's a capitalist system.
I mean the United States is one
of the most successful capitalist system
in the history of earth, so to say-
- What's the most successful,
I'm just saying that I think it's changed a lot
in the last 15 years and that we need to update
our assumptions about what we're seeing.
- [Lex] Sure.
- And that's true up and down.
That's true with everything.
It's true with your neighbor's children
who you haven't seen in three years
and they come home from Wesleyan and you're like,
"Oh, you've grown."
That is true for the world around us as well.
And most of our assumptions about immigration,
about our economy, about our tax system
are completely outdated if you compare them
to the current reality.
And so I'm just for updating my files
and I have a big advantage over you
because I am middle aged and so I don't-
- You've called yourself old so many times
throughout this time.
- I don't trust my perceptions of things.
So I'm constantly trying to be like, is that true?
I should go there, I should see it.
And I guess just in the end, I trust direct perceptions.
Like I don't trust the internet actually.
Wikipedia is a joke.
Wikipedia could not be more dishonest.
It's certainly in the political categories
or things that I know a lot about.
Occasionally I'll read an entry written about something
that I saw or know the people involved and I'm like,
well, that's a complete liar.
You left out the most important fact.
And it's like, it's not a reliable guide
to reality or history.
And that will accelerate with AI
where history or perception of the past
is completely controlled and distorted.
So I think just getting out there and seeing stuff
and seeing that Moscow was not what I thought it would be,
which was a smoldering ruin.
Rats in a garbage dump.
It was nicer than New York.
What the hell?
- Direct data is good, but it's challenging.
For example, if you talk to a lot of people in Moscow
or in Russia and you ask 'em is there a censorship?
They will usually say yes, there is.
- Oh yeah, of course there is.
Well, I agree.
I mean, just to be clear, I'm not,
I have no plans to move to Russia.
I think I would probably be arrested if I moved to Russia.
Ed Snowden, who is the most famous sort of openness,
transparency, advocate in the world,
I would say along with Assange doesn't wanna live in Russia.
He's had problems with the Putin government.
He's attacked Putin.
They don't like it.
I mean, I get it, I get it.
I'm just saying, what are the lessons for us?
And the main lesson is we are being lied to
like in a way that's bewildering and very upsetting.
I was mad about it all eight days I was there,
'cause I feel like I'm better informed than most people,
'cause it's my job to be informed
and I'm skeptical of everything.
And yet I was completely hoodwinked by it.
I would just recommend to everyone watching this
like you think like if you're really interested,
if you're one of those people and I'm not one,
but who's like waking up every day
and you've got a Ukrainian flag on your mailbox or whatever,
you're Ukrainian lapel pen or it's like absurd theater.
But if you like sincerely care about Ukraine or Russia
or whatever, why don't you just hop on a plane
for 800 bucks and go see it, okay?
That doesn't occur to anyone to do that.
And I know it's time consuming and kind of expensive
sort of, not really, but you benefit so much.
I mean I could bore you for like eight hours.
And I know you've had this experience
where you think you know what something is
or you think you know who someone is
and then you have direct experience of that place or person
and you realize all your preconceptions were totally wrong.
They were controlled by somebody else.
Like you'd know, in fact, I won't betray confidences,
but off the air we're talking about somebody
and you said, I couldn't believe the person
was not at all like what I thought.
Well, that's happened to me-
- In the positive direction.
By the way, for me it's almost always in that direction.
Most people I meet and I've had the great privilege
of meeting a lot of people over all this time,
they're way better than you think
or they're more complicated or whatever.
But the point is a direct experience unmediated by liars.
There's no substitute for that.
- Well, on that point, direct experience in Ukraine.
So I visited Ukraine and witnessed a lot
of the same things you witnessed in Moscow.
So first of all, beautiful architecture.
- [Tucker] Yes.
- And this is a country that's really in war,
so it's not- - Oh for real.
- Like for real where most of the men
are either volunteering or fighting in the war
and there's actual tanks in the streets
that are going into your major city of Kyiv,
and still the supply chains are working.
- [Tucker] Yes.
- The handful of months after the start of the war
everything is working.
The restaurants are amazing.
The most of the people are able to do some kind of job like,
like the life goes on.
Cleanliness, like you mentioned.
- I love that. - Security.
Like it's incredible.
Like there's the crime went to zero.
They gave all guns to everybody.
The Texas strategy. - It does work.
- Yeah, when you witness it, you realize,
okay, there's something to these people.
There's something to this country
that they're not as corrupt as you might hear.
You hear that Russia is corrupt, Ukraine is corrupt.
You assume it's just all gonna go to shit.
- Well, so that's been, and I haven't been to Ukraine
and I've certainly tried and they put me
on some kill him immediately list.
So I can't, I've tried to interview Zelensky.
He keeps denouncing me.
I just want an interview with him.
He won't unfortunately. - [Lex] Yeah.
- I would love to do it.
- I hope you do. - I hope I do too.
But one of the things that bothers me most,
I love to hear that what you just said about Kyiv,
but I'm not really surprised.
One of the things that I'm most ashamed of is the bigotry
that I felt towards Slavic people, also toward Muslims.
I'll just be totally honest because I lived
through decades of propaganda from NBC News
and CNN where I worked about this or that group of people
and they're horrible or whatever.
And then you wind...
And I kind of believed it, and I see it now.
Like we can't even put the word Russia
at Wimbledon 'cause it's so offensive.
Well what does the tennis player have to do with it?
Did he invade Ukraine?
I don't think he did.
Stealing all these business guys yachts
and denouncing with oligarchs.
Like what do they have to do with it?
You know, whatever.
Here's my point.
The idea that like a whole group of people is just evil
because of their blood.
I just don't believe that.
I think it's immoral to think that.
And I can just tell you my own experience
after eight days there.
I think it's a really interesting culture, Slavic culture,
which is shared by the way, by Russia and Ukraine of course.
They're first cousins at the most distant
and I found 'em really smart and interesting and informed.
I didn't understand a lot of what they're saying
and don't understand the way their minds work,
'cause I'm American but it wasn't a thin culture,
it's a thick culture, you know?
And I admire that.
And I wish I could go to Ukraine.
I would go tomorrow.
- So I think after you did the interview with Putin,
you put a clip I think on, "TCN"
where like your sort of analysis afterwards.
- Yeah, it wasn't much of an analysis.
- No, but what stood out to me
is you were kind of talking shit about Putin a little bit.
- Yeah.
- Like you were criticizing him.
- Why wouldn't I?
- It spoke to the thing that you mentioned,
which is you weren't afraid.
Now the question I want to ask is,
it'd be pretty badass if you went to the supermarket
and made the point you were making,
but also criticize Putin, right?
Criticize that there is a lack of a freedom of speech
and freedom of the press.
- In the supermarket?
- Yes.
- Oh, you mean if I also said that.
Well, yeah, I mean I of course I think that, I'm not.
So I guess part of it is that I'm a little,
because I have such a low opinion
of the commentariat in the United States
and the news organizations which really do
just work for the US government.
I mean I really see them as I did
Izvestia and Pravda in the 80s.
Like they're just organs of the government
and I think they're contemptible.
And I think the people who work there are contemptible.
And I say that as someone
who knows them really well personally.
I think they're disgusting.
That I'm a little bit cut off kind of
from what people are saying about me
'cause I'm not interested.
So, I try not to be defensive.
Like see I'm not a tool of Putin.
But the idea that I'd be flaking for Putin
when you know my relatives fought in the Revolutionary War,
like I'm as American as you could be.
It's like crazy to me.
And Applebaum calls me a traitor.
I'm like, "Okay, right."
It's just like so dumb.
But no, of course they don't have...
No country has freedom of speech other than us.
Canada doesn't have it.
Great Britain definitely doesn't have it.
France, Netherlands, these are countries
I spend a lot of time in.
And Russia certainly doesn't have it.
So, that's why I don't live there.
I'm just saying our sanctions don't work.
That's all I was saying.
And we don't have to live like animals.
We can live with dignity.
Even the Russians can do it.
That's kind of what I was saying.
Even the Russians under Vladimir freaking Putin
can live like this.
And no, it's not a feature of dictatorship.
That's the most, I think discouraging
and most dishonest line by people like Jon Stewart
who really are trying to prepare the population
for accepting a lot less.
He is really a tool of the regime in a sinister way.
It always has been.
Like, how dare you expect that?
What are you a Stalinist?
It's like, no, I'm an American.
I'm like a decent person.
I just wanna be able to walk
to the grocery store without being murdered.
Is that too much to...
Shut up then, you don't believe in freedom.
It's really dark if you think about it.
- So there is a fundamental way
which you wanted Americans to expect more.
- You don't have to live like this.
We don't have to live like this.
You don't have to accept it, you don't.
And everyone's afraid in this country,
they're gonna be shut down by the tech oligarchs
or have the FBI show up at their houses or go to jail.
And people are legit afraid of that in the United States.
And my feeling is so like show a little courage.
Like what is it worth to you for your grandchildren
to live in a free prosperous country?
It should be worth more than your comfort.
That's how I feel.
- We should make clear that by many measures,
you look at the world press freedom index, you're right,
US is not at the top, Norway is, US scores 71.
Same as Gambia in West Africa.
- Really.
So let me just ask- - Hold on, hold on,
hold on a second, hold on a second,
hold on a second.
- [Tucker] (laughs) Now you're making me laugh.
- Ukraine is 61 and Russia is 35.
The lower it is the worst.
Close to China at 23 and North Korea at the very bottom, 22.
- Didn't Ukraine put Gonzalo Lira in jail till he died
for criticizing the government.
How can they have a high press?
- Yes, that's why there are 61 out of zero.
- But I'm saying look, I don't know what the criteria are
they're using to arrive at that.
But I know press freedom when I see it,
I try to practice it, which is saying
what you think is true,
correcting yourself when you've been shown to be wrong,
as I have many times, being as honest
as you can be all the time and not being afraid.
And those are wholly absent in my country, wholly absent.
People are afraid in the news business.
I would know since I've spent my life work in there
and they're afraid to tell the truth.
They're under an enormous amount of pressure
and a lot of them have little kids and mortgages.
I've been there, so I have sympathy.
But they go along with things like you would,
you are not allowed if you stand up at any cable channel,
any cable channel in the United States
and say, wait a second, how did the Ukrainian government
throw a US citizen into prison until he died
for criticizing the Ukrainian government?
And we're paying for that.
That's why it's offensive to me.
We're paying for it.
And that happens all the time around the world of course.
But this is a US citizen
and we're paying the pensions of Ukrainian bureaucrats.
Like, we are the Ukrainian government at this point.
And like if you said that on TV on any channel,
well, you'd lose your job for that.
So like that's not, I don't care.
Or Norway is at the top, really Norway.
If I went to nor Norwegian television
and said NATO blew up Nord Stream, which it did,
NATO blew up Nord Stream, the United States government
with the help of other governments blew up,
committed the largest act
of industrial terrorism in history.
And by the way, the largest environmental crime,
the largest emission of CO2, methane.
Could I keep my job? No.
So how is that a free-
- We don't know that.
I mean the whole point of-
- In Norway? - [Lex] Yes.
- Well as a Scandinavian I can tell you
they would not put up with that in Norway for a second.
- [Lex] It's been a while.
- You deviating for the majority? No. (laughs)
- Well, but in it's deviating maybe is frowned upon, but-
- [Tucker] Frowned upon, yeah.
- But do you have the freedom to say it if you do deviate?
That's the question.
- Can you keep your job?
That's one measurement of it.
- [Lex] You can keep your job, yeah.
- Yeah, it's not the only measurement.
Obviously being thrown into prison
is much worse than losing your job.
I've been fired a number of times
for saying what I think, by the way.
And it's fine. I've enjoyed it.
I don't mind being fired.
I've always become a better person after it happened.
But it is one measurement of freedom.
If you have the theoretical right to do something,
but no practical ability to do it,
do you have the right to do it?
And the answer is not really actually.
- You mentioned Jon Stewart,
the two of you have a bit of a history,
I don't know if you've seen it,
but he kind of grilled your supermarket and subway videos,
have you got a chance to see it?
- I haven't seen it, but someone characterized it to me,
which is why I pivoted against it early in our conversation
about how the price of freedom is living in filth and chaos.
- Yeah, that was essentially it.
So in 2004, that's 20 years ago,
Jon Stewart appeared on, "Crossfire," a show he hosted.
And that was kind of a memorable moment.
Can you tell the saga of that as you remember it?
- I mean for me, you know, as I was saying to you before
about how it takes a long time to digest
and process and understand what happens to you,
or at least it does for me.
I didn't understand that as a particularly significant
moment while it was happening.
I just got off a plane from Hawaii.
I mean I was out of it as usual
and I was very literal as usual.
And so from my perspective, his criticism of me,
to the extent I remember it, was that I was a partisan.
Well, he had two criticisms.
One that, "Crossfire," was stupid,
which it certainly was.
In fact, I'd already given my notice
and I was moving on to another company by that point.
"Crossfire" was stupid.
Crossfire didn't help, Crossfire framed everything
as Republican versus Democrat, whatever.
It was not helpful to the public discourse.
I couldn't agree more, and that's why I left.
So that was part of his critique, fair.
I'm not sure I would've admitted it at the time
'cause I worked there and it's sort of hard
to admit you're engaged in an enterprise
that's like fundamentally worthless, which it was.
But his other point was
that I was somehow a partisan or a mindless partisan,
which is definitely not true.
It is true of him.
He is a mindless partisan.
But I'm not, and I haven't been for,
I really haven't been since I got back from Baghdad
at the beginning of the Iraq war
and I realized that the Republican party,
which I'd voted for my whole life to that point
and had supported in general
was like pushing this really horrible thing
that was gonna hurt the United States
which in time it really did.
The Iraq War really hurt the United States.
And I realized that I had been on the wrong side of that.
I said so publicly, immediately from Baghdad,
I said that to, The New York Times and I really meant it.
I mean it now.
And so to call me partisan,
you could call me stupid, you could call me wrong.
I certainly have been wrong, but partisan,
I just didn't think it was a meaningful,
I mean it's like that's just not true.
It's the opposite of true.
So I didn't really take it seriously at all.
And I never thought much of him.
So I was like, whatever, some buffoon
jumping around on my show grandstanding.
But I do think it was recorded.
And by the way that happened right at the moment
that YouTube began, I think that was one
of the first big YouTube video.
It was one of the first big YouTube videos.
So it had a virality that, if that's a word,
it went everywhere in a way
that didn't used to happen in cable news.
I mean, by that point I had, that was 20 years ago.
As you point out, I've been in cable news for nine years.
So in the before 2004, we would say something on television
and then it would kind of, it would be lost.
Like people could claim they heard it.
But you'd have to go to the,
I think the University of Tennessee at Knoxville
archives to get it.
Suddenly everything we said would live forever
on the internet, which is good by the way.
That's not bad.
But it was a big change for me.
And I just couldn't believe how widely
that was discussed at the time,
'cause I thought he was not an interesting person.
I think he is obviously a very unhappy person.
I just didn't take him seriously then and I don't now.
But, so anyway, that was it.
It was a smaller thing in my life at the time
than other people imagined.
- Okay, you said a lot of words that will make it sound
like you're a bit bitter even if you're not.
So you said unhappy person, partisan person.
- Well, I think he's an unhappy guy.
Well, he's definitely partisan for sure.
- So, can you elaborate why you think he's partisan?
- Well, so I think that,
and I see this a lot, not only on the left,
but people who believe
that whatever political debate they're engaged in
is the most important debate in the world.
And so they bring an emotional intensity to those debates
and they're inevitably disappointed
because no eternal question is solved politically.
So they're kind of on the wrong path, right?
And they're doomed to frustration,
if they believe that, and many do.
He certainly does. that whatever the issue is.
So, "Clarence Thomas should not be Supreme Court justice."
And the implication is, well,
if someone else's Supreme Court justice
we'll live in a fair and happy society.
But that's just not, it's a false promise.
So I think that people who bring that level of intensity
to politics are by definition bitter,
by definition disappointed,
bitter in the way the disappointed people are.
And that the real questions are like,
what happens when you die?
And how do the people around you feel about you?
Those are not the only questions in life,
but they're certainly the most important ones.
And if we're spending a disproportionate amount of time
on who gets elected to some office,
not that it's irrelevant, it is relevant,
but it's not the eternal question.
And so I feel like he's not the only kind of bitter,
silly person in Washington or in its orbit.
There are many, and a lot of them are Republicans.
But I just thought it was ironic.
I mean, everything's ironic to me,
but like being called a Russia sympathizer
by a guy who calls himself Boris,
like, it just made me laugh. (chuckles)
No one else has ever laughed at that.
Boris Johnson's real name is not Boris as you know.
He calls himself Boris, it's his middle name.
And so like if you call yourself Boris,
you don't really have standing to attack anyone else
as a Russia defender, right?
That's my, I think that's funny.
No one else, as I noted does.
But Jon Stewart, like, you know,
if there are a lot of things
you could say about me,
but he's much more partisan than I am,
so to call me a partisan, it's like what?
- He would probably say that he's not a partisan,
that he's a comedian who's looking for the humor
and the absurdity of the system.
That's a dumb- - On both sides.
He's a very serious person in this, I will say this.
And he shares this quality with a lot of comedians.
I know a lot of comedians.
I know a cross sectioned people
just having done this job for a long time.
And a lot of 'em are very serious, like about their views
and they have a lot of emotional intensity
and he certainly is in that category.
He's not, that's like the silliest thing.
Yeah, he's a comedian for sure.
He can be very funny for sure.
He has talent, no doubt about it.
I've never denied that.
But he's motivated by his moral views,
this is right, that is wrong.
And I just think that's, it's a misapplied passion.
- Well, do you think I'm just a comedian, is-
- I don't think any serious person thinks that.
I mean, if you're just a comedian, be.
And look, I'm not trying to claim, I couldn't claim
that I haven't said a lot of dumb things.
And one of the dumbest things I ever said
was when he was on our set lecturing me, he's a moralizer,
which I also just don't really care for
as an aesthetic matter.
But he was lecturing me about something
and I said, "I thought you were here to tell jokes,"
which I shouldn't have said
because he wasn't there to tell jokes.
He was there to lecture me.
And I should have just engaged it directly
rather than trying to diminish him
by like, you're just a little comedian.
Well, he doesn't see himself that way.
But I would just say this,
Jon Stewart's a defender of power.
Like Jon Stewart has never criticized.
Like, what's Jon Stewart's view
on the aid we've sent to Ukraine,
the a hundred billion dollars or whatever.
Like, what happened to that money?
What happened to the weapons that have bought?
He doesn't care.
He has the exact same priorities
as the people permanently in charge in Washington.
So whatever, he doesn't, he's not alone in that.
So does Mika Brzezinski and her husband
and all the rest of the cast of dummies.
But if you're gonna pretend to be the guy
who's giving the finger to entrenched power,
you should do it once in a while.
And he never has.
There's not one time when he said something
that would be deeply unpopular on, "Morning Joe."
That's all I'm saying.
And so don't call yourself a truth teller.
You're a court comedian or a flatterer of power.
Okay, that's fine, there's a role for that,
but don't pretend to be something else.
- I'll just be honest that I watched it just recently,
that video- - From 20 years ago.
- From 20 years ago.
I watched it initially and I remember very differently.
I remembered that Jon Stewart
completely destroyed you in that conversation.
And I watched it and you asked a very good question of him,
which was, and there was no destruction, first of all.
And you asked a very good question of him,
why, when you got a chance to interview John Kerry,
did you ask a bunch of softball questions?
- [Tucker] Yeah.
- I thought that was a really fair question.
And then his defense was, "Well, I'm just a comedian."
- So, I thought that was disingenuous.
And I haven't watched it,
I never have watched a clip one time in my life
and I don't like to watch myself on television.
I never have.
And that's my fault.
And I probably should force myself to watch it though,
of course I never will.
But I think the takeaway for me,
which was really interesting and life changing
was I agree with your assessment.
I'm not just, I've lost a lot of debates.
I've been humiliated on television, I'm not above that.
It certainly happened to me, it will happen again.
But I didn't feel like it was a clear win for him at all.
Maybe a TKO, but it was not a knockout at all.
And yet it was recorded that way.
And I remember thinking, "Well, that's kind of weird.
That's not what I remember."
And then I realized, no,
Jon Stewart was more popular than I was,
therefore he was recorded as the winner.
And that was hard for me to accept
because that struck me as unfair.
You should rate any contest on points.
Like here are the rules, we're gonna judge the contest
in the basis of those rules.
And no, in the end it's just like the more popular guy wins.
Every TV critic liked Jon Stewart,
every one of 'em hated me, therefore he won.
And I was like, wow, that, I guess
I have to accept that reality.
And you do like the reality of the sunrise,
you're not in charge of it,
so that's just what it is.
- Unfortunately, it's a bit darker I think.
The reason he's seen as the winner
and the reason at the time I saw
as the quote, unquote, "winner,"
is because he was basically shitting on you,
like personal attacks versus engaging ideas.
And it was funny in a dark way
and like making fun of the bow tie
and all this kind of stuff. - [Tucker] Fair.
Bow ties are-
- I understand.
- And it was fair to call me a dick.
I remember he called me a dick.
And I remember even when he said that, I was like,
"Yeah, I'm definitely a dick."
Yeah, and that's not my best quality, trust me.
- I think but also to be kind of,
I thought Jon Stewart came off as a giant dick at that time
and I'm a big fan of his and I think he has improved a lot.
- That may be true.
- We should also say that like people grow, people like-
- Well, I certainly have or change anyway.
You hope it's growth, you hope it's not shrinkage.
- It is cold outside.
- Yeah, I mean look, I haven't followed
Jon Stewart's career at all.
I don't have a television.
Like I'm pretty cut off from all that stuff,
so I wouldn't really know.
But the measure to me is, are you taking positions
that are unpopular with the most powerful people
in the world, and how often are you doing it?
It's super simple.
Not for its own sake, but do you feel free enough
to say to the consensus, I disagree.
And if you don't, then you're just another toady.
That's my view.
- Well, I think he probably feels free enough to do it,
but you're saying he doesn't do it.
- On the big things.
Look, the big things, this is my estimation of it,
others may disagree.
The big things are the economy and war, okay?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- The big things government does can be,
I mean there are a lot of things government does.
Government does everything at this point.
But where we kill people and how, and for what purpose
and how we organize the economic engine
that keeps the country afloat.
Those are the two big questions.
And I hear almost no debate
about either one of them in the media.
And I have dissenting views on both of them.
I mean, I'm mad about the tax code, which I think is unfair.
I don't think we should be...
The fact we've a carried interest loophole in the tax code
and people are claiming that their income
is investment income and they're paying half the tax rate
as someone who just goes to work every day.
It discourages work, it encourages lending at interest,
which I think is gross personally
I'm against it, sorry.
And the fact that we're creating chaos around the world,
like is the saddest thing that's happening right now.
And nobody feels free to say that, so that's not good.
- How do you hope the war on Ukraine ends?
- With a settlement.
With a reasonable settlement.
And what a reasonable settlement is, which is a settlement,
where both sides feel like they're giving a little,
but can live with it.
And I mean I was really struck in my conversation
with Putin by how he basically refused
to criticize Joe Biden and to criticize NATO.
And it is, I will just be honest as an American,
it would be a little weird to be like pissing on Joe Biden
with a foreign leader, any foreign leader,
even though I don't think Joe Biden
is a real person or really president.
I mean the whole thing is ridiculous.
But still, he is the American president technically.
And I don't want to beat up on the American president
with a foreigner.
I just don't, maybe I'm old fashioned.
So, that's how I feel.
So I didn't push it,
but I thought it was really interesting.
And 'cause of course Putin knows my views on Joe Biden.
He knew I applied to the CIA,
so they've done some digging on me.
but he didn't mention it and he didn't attack NATO.
And the reason is I know for a fact
'cause he wants a settlement.
And he wants a settlement
not because Russia's about to collapse
despite the lying of our media.
That's just not true.
And no one is even saying it anymore 'cause it's so dumb.
He wants it 'cause it's just bad to have a war.
And it changes the world
in ways you can't predict, people die.
Everything about it is sad.
And if you can avoid it, you should.
So I would like to see a settlement where,
look, the thing that Russia wants
and I think probably has a right to,
is not to have NATO missiles on this border.
Like, I don't know why we would do that.
I dunno what we get out of it.
I just don't even understand it.
I don't understand the purpose of NATO.
I don't think NATO is good for the United States.
I think it's an attack on our sovereignty.
I would pull out of NATO immediately
if I were the US president
because I don't think it helps the US.
I know a lot of people
are getting their bread buttered by NATO,
but anyway that's my view as an American.
If I'm a Russian or a Ukrainian,
let's just be sovereign countries now.
We're not run by the US State Department,
we're just our own countries.
Like that's, I believe in sovereignty, okay?
So, that's my view.
And I also wanna say one thing about Zelensky.
I attacked him before because I was so offended
by his cavalier talk about nuclear exchange
because it would kill my family,
so I'm really offended by that.
Anyone who talks that way, I'm offended by.
But I do feel for Zelensky, I do.
That he didn't run for president to have this happen.
I think Zelensky, he's been completely misused
by the State department, by Toria Nuland,
by our secretary of state,
by the policymakers in the US who've used Ukraine
as a vessel for their ambitions,
their geopolitical ambitions.
But also the many American businesses who've used Ukraine
as a way to fleece the American taxpayer.
And then by just independent ghouls like Boris Johnson
are hoping to get rich from interviews on it.
Like the whole thing, Zelensky is at the center of this.
He's not driving history.
NATO in the United States is driving history.
Putin is driving history.
There's this guy Zelensky.
So, I do feel for him and I think he's in a perilous place.
- Do you think Zelensky is a hero for staying in Kyiv?
Because I do.
To me, you can criticize a lot of things.
You should call out things that are obviously positive.
- Well, I just tried to a second ago.
I don't know the extent that he is in Kyiv.
He seems to be in the United States an awful lot.
Like way too much.
You can do a satellite interview.
You don't have to speak to my Congress,
you're not an American, please leave.
- [Lex] Yeah. - That's my opinion.
- You got many zingers, Tucker.
- No, no, no, it's just heartfelt.
It's just bubbling up from the wellspring
that never turns off.
But I would say this about Zelensky.
Yeah, to the extent he's in Ukraine, good man.
George W. Bush fled Washington on 9/11.
I lived there with three kids and he ran away
to some Air force base in South Dakota.
And I thought that was cowardly,
and I said so at the time.
And man was I attacked for saying that.
And I wrote a column about it in, New York Magazine
where I then had a column.
Hard to believe.
But I felt that, I felt that.
I think the prerequisites of leadership are really basic.
The first is caring about the people you lead.
That's number one.
A deep, in the way a father cares for his children
or an officer cares for his troops,
a president should care for his people.
And that leads inexorably to the next requirement,
which is bravery, physical courage.
And I believe in that.
And I'm not like some tough guy,
but I just think it's obvious.
If you're in charge.
I'm at my house and I feel like someone broke in,
I'm not gonna say to my wife, "Hey, baby,
go deal with the home invasion."
I'm gonna deal with it 'cause I'm dad, okay?
So if you're the president of a country
and your capital city is attacked
as ours was at the Pentagon and you run away.
And the Secret Service told me to.
Bitch, are you in charge?
(Lex chuckling)
Like, who's daddy here?
The Secret Service.
Do you know what I mean?
I found that totally contemptible.
And I said so, and man, did I get a lecture.
Not just from Republicans but from Democrats.
Oh you don't know, put yourself in that position.
I was like, "Okay, I don't know what I would do
under that kind of stress."
Enormous stress, I get it.
I know one thing I wouldn't do is run away,
'cause you can't do that.
And if you're not willing to die for your country,
then you shouldn't be leading it.
So yes, to the extent if Zelensky
really is in Ukraine most of the time, amen.
- Well, hold on a second, let's clarify.
It's not about what is in Ukraine most of the time or not.
- Well, I thought that was the whole premise
of the- (laughs) - No, no,
at the beginning of the war, when the tank,
when Kyiv, when a lot of people thought
that the second biggest military in the world
is pointing its guns in Kyiv is gonna be taken.
And a man, a leader who stays in that city
and says, fuck it, when everybody around him says flee,
says everybody around him believes the city
will be taken or at least destroyed.
Leveled, artillery, bombs, all of this.
He chooses to stay.
You know a lot of leaders,
how many leaders would choose to stay?
- Well, the leader of Afghanistan, the US backed leader,
when the Taliban came, got in a US plane
with US dollars and ran away.
And of course is living on those dollars now.
So yeah, there's a lot of cowardly behavior.
Good for him.
I mean, I guess I'm looking at it slightly differently,
which is what's the option?
You're the leader of the country, you can't leave.
Like Stalin never left Moscow during the war.
It was surrounded by the Germans, as you know, for a year.
And he didn't leave.
And when I was in Russia, they're like, Stalin never left.
It's like how he's the leader of the country.
You can't, I mean like that's just table stakes of course.
I would say, but you raised
an interesting by implication question,
which is what about Kyiv?
Like you think the Russians couldn't level Kyiv?
Of course, obviously they could, why haven't they?
They could, but they haven't.
- Well, there's military answers to that,
which is urban warfare is extremely difficult.
- Do you think that Putin wants to take Kyiv?
- No, I do think he expected Zelensky to flee
and somebody else to come into power.
- Yeah, that may be totally, I don't know.
I don't think, I have no idea what Putin was thinking
when he did that about Zelensky.
I didn't ask him.
But it's a mistake to imagine this is a contest
between Putin and Zelensky.
This is Putin versus the US State Department.
I mean Zelensky, and that's why I said
I felt sorry for him.
I mean, as I said, we're literally paying the pensions
of Ukrainian bureaucrats.
So there is no Ukrainian government
independent of the US government.
And maybe therefore that maybe you're against it,
but you can't endorse that in the same sentence
that you use the term democracy,
'cause that's not a democracy, right? Obviously.
- Well, that's why it's interesting
that he didn't really bring up NATO extensively.
- He wants a settlement, he wants a settlement
and he doesn't wanna fight with them rhetorically.
And he just wants to get this done.
And he made a bunch of offers at the peace deal.
And we wouldn't even know this happened
if the Israelis hadn't told us.
And I'm so grateful that they did
that Johnson was dispatched
by the State Department to stop it.
And it's like, I mean I think Boris Johnson
is a husk of a man.
But imagine if you were Boris Johnson
and you spend your whole life with Ukraine flag pen,
I'm for Ukraine, and then all those kids died
because of what you did.
And the lines haven't really moved.
It hasn't been a victory for Ukraine.
It's not gonna be a victory for Ukraine.
And it's like, how do you feel about yourself
if you did that?
I mean I've done a lot of shitty things in my life.
I feel bad about them,
but I've never extended a war for no reason.
Like that's a pretty grave sin in my opinion.
- Yes, that was a failure.
But it doesn't mean you can't have a success over and over
and over keep having negotiations between leaders.
- Well, the US government is not allowing negotiations.
And so, that for me is the most upsetting part.
It's like in the end what Russia does
I'm not implicated in that.
What Ukraine does, I'm not implicated in that.
I'm not Russian or Ukraine.
I'm an American who grew up really believing in my country.
I'm supporting my country through my tax dollars.
And it's like I really care about
what the US government does
'cause they're doing it in my name
and I care a lot 'cause I'm American
and we are the impediment to peace,
which is another way of saying we are responsible
for all these innocent people
getting dragooned outta public parks in Kyiv
and sent to go die.
Like what?
That is not good.
I'm ashamed of it.
- What do you think of Putin saying that justification
for continuing the war is denazification?
- I thought it was one of the dumbest things I'd ever heard.
I didn't understand what it meant, denazification.
- It literally means what it sounds like.
- Yeah, I mean I have a lot of thoughts on this.
I hate that whole conversation because it's not real,
it's just ad hominem.
It's a way of associating someone with an evil regime
that doesn't exist anymore.
But in point of fact, Nazism, whatever it was,
is inseparable from the German nation.
It was a nationalist movement in Germany.
There were no other Nazis, right?
There's no book of Nazism.
I'm like, I wanna be a Nazi.
What does it mean to be a Nazi?
There's no idea, there's no...
I mean there's no, "Mein Kampf,"
is not, "Das Kapital," right?
"Mein Kampf," is like, to the extent I understand it,
it's like he's about the Treaty of Versailles.
Whatever, I'm very anti-Nazi.
I'm merely saying there isn't a Nazi movement in 2024.
It's a way of calling people evil.
Okay, Putin doesn't like nationalist Ukrainians.
Putin hates nationalism in general, which is interesting.
And of course he does.
He's got 80 whatever republics
and he's afraid of nationalist movements.
He fought a war in Chechnya over this.
So I understand it, but I have a different,
I'm for national, I'm for American nationalism,
so like I disagree with Putin on that,
but calling them Nazis, it's like,
I thought it was childish.
- Well, I do believe that he believes it.
- I agree with that.
'Cause I was listening to this
because in the United States everyone's
always calling everyone else a Nazi.
You're a Nazi.
Okay.
But I was listening to this and I was like,
"This is the dumbest sort of not convincing line
you could take."
And I sat there and listened to him
talk about Nazis for like eight minutes.
And I'm like, "I think he believes this."
- Yeah, and I actually having had a bunch of conversations
with people who are living in Russia, they also believe it.
Now there's technicalities here, which the word Nazi,
the World War II is deeply in the blood
of a lot of Russians and Ukrainians.
- [Tucker] I get it, I get it.
- So you're using it as almost a political term,
the way it's used in the United States also,
like racism and all this kind of stuff.
So, you can really touch people if you use the Nazi.
- [Tucker] I think that's totally right.
- But it's also to me a really like disgusting thing to do.
- [Tucker] I agree.
- Because, and also to clarify,
there is neo-Nazi movements in Ukraine,
which is, they're very small.
You're saying that there's this distinction
between Nazi and neo-Nazi, sure.
But it's a small percentage of the population,
a tiny percentage that have no power in government
as far I have seen no data to show
they have any influence on Zelensky
and Zelensky government at all.
So really, when Putin says denazification,
I think he means nationalist movements.
- I think you're right.
And I agree with everything you said,
and I do think that the war,
the Second World War occupies a place in Slavic society,
Polish society, central Eastern Europe
that it does not occupy in the United States.
And you can just look at the death totals.
Tens of millions versus less than half a million.
So it's like this eliminated
a lot of the male population of these countries,
so of course it's still resonant in those countries.
I get it.
I just, I think I've watched,
I don't think I know I've watched the misuse of words,
weaponization of words for political reasons
for so long that I just don't like,
and though I do engage in it sometime, I'm sorry,
I don't like just dismissing people in a word.
Oh, he's a Nazi, he's a liberal or whatever.
It's like, tell me what you mean,
what don't you like about what they're doing or saying?
And a Nazi especially, it's like,
I don't even know what the hell you're talking about.
- What troubled me about that is because he said
that that's the primary objective currently for the war.
And that because it's not grounded in reality,
it makes it difficult to then negotiate peace
because like what, what does it mean to get rid
of the Nazis in Ukraine?
So like he'll come to the table and say,
"Well, okay, I will agree to do ceasefire
once the Nazis are gone."
Okay, so can you list the Nazis?
- I totally agree.
Plus can you negotiate with a Nazi?
- [Lex] Right, exactly, exactly.
- No, I totally agree with you.
- It was very strange.
But maybe it was perhaps had to do
with speaking to his own population
and also probably trying to avoid the use of the word NATO
as the justification for the war.
- Yeah, yes, that's all...
Of course, I don't know,
but I suspect you're right on both counts.
But I would say it points to something
that I've thought more and more since I did that interview,
which was like two weeks ago, I guess.
I didn't think he was like,
as a PR guy, not very good.
Like he's not good at telling his own story.
The story of the current war in Ukraine
is the eastward expansion of NATO
and scaring the outta the Russians with NATO expansion,
which is totally necessary.
Doesn't help the United States.
NATO itself doesn't help the United States.
And so I'm not pro-Russian for saying
that I'm pro-American for saying that.
And I think that's a really compelling story,
'cause it's true.
He did not tell that story.
He told some other story that I didn't fully understand.
Again, I'm not Russian.
He's speaking to multiple audiences around the world.
I'm not sure what he hoped to achieve by that interview.
I will never know.
But I did think that like this guy
is not good at telling his story.
And I also think honestly on the base of a lot,
I mean I know this, very isolated during COVID, very.
We keep hearing that he's dying of this or that disease.
He's got ALS.
I mean I don't know, I'm not his doctor.
There's a ton of lying about it.
I know that.
But one thing that's not a lie
is that he was cloistered away during COVID.
I know this.
And only dealing with two or three people.
And that makes you weird.
It's so important to deal with a lot of people
to have your views challenged.
And you see this with leaders who stay in power too long.
He's been in power 24 years, effectively.
He's done a, you know, there's been upsides
I think for Russia, the Russian economy,
Russian life expectancy.
But there are definitely downsides.
And one of them is you get weird and you get autocratic.
Like this is why we have term limits.
Very few kings don't get crazy in old age.
- Yeah, and you said some of this also in your,
whilst in your post Kremlin discussion
while you're in Moscow still,
which was very impressive to me
that you can just openly criticize.
This is great.
- Well, I don't care.
- I understand this.
I just wish you did some more of that
also with the supermarket video
and perhaps some more of that with Putin in front of you.
- Putin in front of me. - [Lex] I understand.
- I'm such a good person.
- I know you see it as virtue signaling.
- Yeah, it is.
- Have you seen some of the interview
he did with some NBC news child?
- Yes, I understand.
So I think you're just so annoyed by how bad journalists are
that you just didn't want to be them.
- Yeah, that's probably right actually. (laughs)
- Some great conversations will involve some challenging,
like you were confused about denazification.
- Well first of all, I accept your criticism
and I accept it as true that in some way
I'm probably pivoting against what I dislike.
And I have such contempt for American journalists
on the basis of so much knowledge
that I probably was like, I don't wanna be like that, fair.
That is a kind of defensiveness and dumb.
So, you're right.
As for the Nazi thing, I was like,
I really felt like we were just speaking
so far past each other that we would never like come to,
I was like, I don't even know
what the hell you're talking about.
And especially when I decided
or concluded that he really meant it, I was like,
that's just too freaking weird to me.
It's almost like, yeah, I can think of many other examples.
We were interviewing someone else,
say something that's like, I was interviewing a guy one time
and he started talking about the black Israelites,
and we're the real Jews.
And I was like, and it wasn't on camera,
but I was like, I don't, that was so,
it was so far out to me that I was like,
we'll never kind of understand common terms on that.
- So you mentioned there's a bunch of conspiracy theories
about Putin's health.
How was he in person?
Like what did he feel like?
Did he look healthy?
- I'm not a health person myself, so I mean,
I can easily gain 30 pounds and not know it.
So like, I'm probably not a great person to ask.
But no, he seemed fine.
He seemed, he had his arm hooked through a chair
and I heard people say, well, he's got Parkinson's.
And Parkinson's can be controlled,
I know for periods with drugs.
So, it's hard to assess.
I'm just not...
One of the tells of Parkinson's is gait.
How a person walks, I think.
And his walking seemed fine.
I walked around with him and talked to him off camera.
He's had some work done for sure.
He's 71 or two.
- [Lex] You mean like visual purposes?
- Yeah, I'm 54.
He's like almost 20 years older than me.
He looked younger than me.
- What was that like, the conversation off camera,
like you walking around with him.
What was the content of the conversation?
- I mean, I can't, you know, I feel bad even with Putin
or anybody like talking about stuff that is off the record.
But I'll just say that when I said that
he didn't wanna fight with NATO
or with the US State Department or with Joe Biden
because he wants a settlement,
that's a very informed perspective.
He doesn't.
Say whatever you want about that,
believe it or not, but that is true.
- So, he's open for peace. For peace and negotiation.
Russia tried to join NATO in 2000.
That's a fact.
Okay, they tried to join NATO
So just think about this,
NATO exists to keep Russia contained.
It exists as a bulwark
against Russian territorial expansion.
And whether or not Russia
has any territorial ambitions is another question.
Like why would it, it's the largest land mass
in the world, whatever.
But that's why it exists.
So if Russia seeks to join NATO,
it is by definition a sign that NATO's job is done here
we can declare victory and go home.
The fact that they turned him down
is like so shocking to me.
But it's true.
Then he approaches the next president,
George W. Bush, that was with Bill Clinton
at the end of his term in 2000.
He approaches the next president and said,
let's, in our next missile deal,
let's align on this and we will designate Iran
as our common enemy.
Iran which is now effectively league with Russia,
thanks to our insane policies.
And George W. Bush to his credit's like,
well, that seems like kind of an innovative good idea.
And Condi Rice, who's like one of the stupidest people ever
to hold power in the United States, if I can say,
who's like monomaniacally anti-Russia versus,
'cause she had an advisor at Stanford
who was or something during the Cold War.
No, we can't do that.
And Bush is just weak, and so he agreed.
It's like, what?
That is crazy.
If you're fighting with someone and the person says,
you know what, actually our interests align
and you've spent 80% of your mental disc space
on hating me and opposing me or whatever,
but actually we can be on the same team.
If you don't at least see that as progress.
Like what, why would you...
If your interest is in helping your country,
what would be the, what's the counterargument?
I don't even understand it.
And no one has even addressed any of this.
The war of Russian aggression.
Yeah, it was a war of Russian aggression for sure.
But how did we get there?
We got there because Joe Biden
and Tony Blinken dispatched Kamala Harris,
who does not freelance this stuff, okay?
Fair to say.
To the Munich Security Conference
two years ago this month, February, 2022,
and said, in a press conference to Zelensky,
poor Zelensky, we want you to join NATO.
This was not in a back room.
Things was in public at a press conference knowing,
because he said it like 4,000 times,
we don't want nuclear weapons from the United States
or NATO on our Western border.
Duh. And days later he invaded.
So like, what is that?
And if you even, I raised that question in my previous job,
and I was denounced as you,
of course a traitor or something.
But okay, great, I'm a traitor.
What's the answer?
These are not into...
Toria Nuland who I know, not dumb,
hasn't helped the US in any way.
An architect of the Iraq war, architect of this disaster,
one of the people who destroyed the US dollar,
okay, fine, but you're not stupid.
So, like you're trying to get a war by acting that way.
What's the other explanation.
By the way, NATO didn't want Ukraine
'cause it didn't meet the criteria.
So, for admission.
So, why would you say that?
Because you want a war. That's why.
And that war has enriched a lot of people
to the tune of billions.
So I don't care if I sound like some kind
of left-wing conspiracy nut
because I'm neither left-wing nor a conspiracy nut.
Tell me how I'm wrong.
- Who do you think is behind it?
If you are to analyze, like zoom out
looking at the entirety of human history,
the military industrial complex, you said Kamala Harris.
Is it individuals?
Is it like this collective flock
that people are just pro-war as a collective?
- It's the hive mind.
And I spent my whole life in DC
from '85 to 2020, so 35 years.
And again, I grew up around it in that world.
And I do think that conspiracies,
of course there are conspiracies.
But in general, the hive mind
is responsible for the worst decisions.
It's a bunch of people with the same views, totally.
Views that have not been updated in decades.
Putin said something that I thought was true.
Absolutely true.
I don't know how he would know this, but it is true,
'cause I lived among them.
So the Soviet Union dissolves in August of '91
on my honeymoon in Bermuda.
I'll never forget it.
And it was a big thing, if you lived in DC,
I mean, the receptionist in my office in 1991
was getting a master's in Russian from Georgetown.
He was gonna be a sovietologists.
And he was among thousands of people in Washington
on that same track.
And so the Soviet Union collapses.
Well, so does the rationale for like a good portion
of the US government has been dedicated for over 40 years
to opposing this thing that no longer exists.
So, there's a lot of forward momentum.
There's a huge amount of money.
The bulk of the money in the richest country in the world
aimed in this direction.
And it's very hard for people to readjust, to reassess.
And you see this in life all the time.
I love my wife.
All of a sudden she ran off with my best friend.
Holy shit, I didn't expect that this morning.
Now, it's a reality.
Like how do I deal with that?
Well, I got stage four cancer diagnosis, okay?
And it's all bad.
But I'm just saying like, that's the nature of life.
Things that you did not anticipate,
never thought you'd have to face happen out of nowhere.
And you have to adjust your expectations and your goals.
And people have a hard time with that.
Very hard time with that.
So, that's a lot of it.
People, if you're Condi Rice,
sort of like highly ambitious mid wit
who gets this degree from Stanford,
and you read Tolstoy in the original.
Sure, you did.
And you spent your whole life like thinking
that Russia is the center of evil in the world.
It's kind of hard to be like,
well actually there's a new threat
and it's coming from farther east.
It's primarily an economic threat.
And maybe all the threats aren't reduced to tank battles.
That's the other thing, is these people
are so inelastic in their thinking, so lacking imagination
and flexibility that they can't sort
of imagine like a new framework.
And the new framework is not that you're gonna go to war
with China over Formosa, Taiwan.
No, the framework is that all of a sudden
all the infrastructure in Tijuana
is gonna be built by China.
And like that's a different kind of threat,
but they can't kind of get there
because they're not that impressive.
- So you actually have mentioned this,
it's not just the Cold War, it's World War II
that populates most of their thinking in Washington.
You mentioned Churchill, Chamberlain and Hitler.
And they kind of seeing the World War II
as the kind of the good war and the successful role
the United States played in that war,
they're kind of seeing that dynamic,
that geopolitical dynamic
and applying it everywhere else still.
- Yeah, it's a template for everything.
And I think it's of huge significance
to the development of the West,
to the civilization we live in now
to world history was a world war.
And so I think it's worth knowing a lot about
and being honest about and all the rest,
but it's hardly the sum total of human history.
Yeah, it's a snapshot.
And so you keep hearing people refer to not even the war,
no one ever talks about the war.
Like what, how much does Tony Blinken
know about the battle of Stalingrad?
Hmm, probably zero.
He doesn't know anything.
Largest battle in human history.
But everybody, he knows nothing.
But he knows a lot about the cliches
surrounding the '38 to '40 period, 1938 to 1940.
And everything is kind of expressed through that formula
and not everything is that formula.
That's all I'm saying.
And the Republicans have a strange weakness for it,
particularly the closeted ones,
the weird ones who were like have no life
other than like starting more wars.
Everything to them, the most vulnerable, I would say
among them, emotionally, psychologically vulnerable,
the dumbest,
they will always say the same thing.
And it appeals to Republican voters, unfortunately,
that every problem is the result of weakness.
Everyone's Chamberlain.
Like Germany never would've gone in
to Poland, Czechoslovakia if England had been stronger.
That's the argument.
Is that true?
I don't know, actually.
Maybe it might be totally true.
It might not be true at all.
I really don't know.
But not everything is that, that's not always true.
If I go up to you in a bar and I say, I hate your neck tie.
I'm being pretty aggressive with you, pretty strong.
you might beat the outta me actually,
or shoot me if I do that.
Like an aggressive posture doesn't always get you
the outcome that you want.
Sometimes it requires
a more sophisticated Mediterranean posture.
I mean, it kind of depends.
It's a time and place thing.
And they don't acknowledge that.
It's like everything is this same template.
And that's not the road to good decision making at all.
- Since we're on the time period,
let me ask you kind of almost cliche question,
but it applies to you,
which you've interviewed a lot of world leaders.
- [Tucker] Yep.
- If you had the chance to interview Hitler
in '39, '40, '41.
First of all, would you do it?
And how would you do it?
I assume you would do it given who you are.
- Man, it would be a massive cost for doing it.
It may destroy my life to interview Putin, though.
I can tell you as much as I want
that I'm not a Putin defender,
I only care about the United States.
That's a hundred percent true.
Anyone who knows me will tell you what's true,
I keep saying it.
But history may record me to the extent
it records me at all as a tool of Putin, a hater of America.
That seems absurd to me, but absurd things happen.
So, what would I ask Hitler?
I don't even know.
I guess that I would probably ask him, what I asked Putin,
which is what I ask everybody, like, what's your motive?
Why did you do, I mean, if he'd already gone into Poland,
like, why are you doing that?
what's your goal?
And then the question is, is he gonna answer honestly.
I don't know.
You can't make someone answer a question honestly.
You can only sort of shut up while they talk
and then let people decide what they think of the answer.
- Well, just like in the bar fight,
there's different ways.
You could- - There are different ways.
That's exactly right.
That's exactly, man, is that true.
That is absolutely right.
- I mean, your energy with Putin, for example,
was such that it felt like he could trust you.
I felt like he could tell you a lot.
- I just wanted to get it on the record.
- [Lex] Yes. - That's all I wanted.
- I think it was extremely like,
we have to acknowledge how important that interview was
for the record and for opening the door for conversation.
Like opening the door to conversation literally is the path
to like more conversations and peace, peace talks.
- Well, I would flip it around and say anyone who seeks
to shut that down by focusing on a supermarket video
of four minutes versus a two hour
and 15 minute long interview with a world leader.
Anyone who doesn't want more conversation,
who wants fewer facts, fewer perspectives is totalitarian,
probably doesn't have good intent.
I mean, I can honestly say for all my many manifold faults,
I've never tried to like, make people shut up.
I just, it's not in me.
I don't believe in that.
- So Putin's folks have shown interest
of quite a while to speaking with me.
So, you've spoken with him.
What advice would you give?
- Oh, do it immediately.
How's your Russian, by the way?
- [Lex] Fluent. - Have you kept up With it?
- Yeah, fluent.
So it would most likely be in Russian.
So like that's the other thing
is I do have a question about language barrier.
Oh, like, did you feel was annoying?
- It's horrible. - [Lex] Yeah.
- It's horrible.
I mean the, I don't have much of a technique
as an interviewer other than listen really carefully.
That's my only skill.
I don't have the best questions.
I certainly don't have the best questions.
All I do that I'm proud of
and that I think works is I just listen super carefully.
I never let a word go by that I'm not paying attention.
It exhausts me, actually.
But you can't do that in a foreign language
because there's a delay.
Here I'm just whining, but it's real.
- Well, it's not whining.
Like can you actually describe
the technical details of that?
Are you hearing concurrently, like at the same time?
- Yes, but there's a massive lag.
So what's happening is, so the translators,
so we were of course extremely uptight
about the logistical details,
so we brought our own cameraman
who I've been around the world with,
who worked at Fox, came with me now.
Amazing.
And he did, I mean, it was our cameras, lighting everything.
Like we had full control over that
and we had control of the tape.
The Russians also had their own cameras,
and I don't know what they did with it.
But we had full control of that,
and we brought our own translator.
We got our own translator
because I don't trust anyone, right?
So, I think we had a good translator.
We had two of them actually, 'cause they get exhausted.
But the problem is, from my perspective,
as someone who's like trying to think of a follow up
and listen to the answer, Putin will talk
and in part of your ear hear the Slavic sounds
and then over that is a guy
with a Slavic accent speaking English.
And then you can hear Putin stop talking
and then this guy's answer goes on
for another 15, 20 seconds.
So, it's super disconcerting and it's really hard.
And the other thing is, it doesn't matter
how good your translators are.
I'm interested in language,
I speak only English fluently,
but I'm really interested in language.
And I work in language.
It doesn't matter how good your translator is.
In literature and in conversation, you miss so much
if the language is moving for you.
I mean, you see this in Bible study,
you see it in Dostoevsk, you see it everywhere.
If you don't speak Aramaic, Hebrew, Russian,
you're not really getting.
I mean, even in romance languages.
I like Balzak, okay?
Who's obviously wrote in French.
You read, "Pere Goriot," it's amazing novel, hilarious.
And it's like, you're not really getting it.
And it's not that French and English
are not that far apart.
Russian, like what?
- Plus conversation.
So the chemistry of conversation, the humor, the wit,
the play with words, all this stuff.
- Exactly.
And my understanding of Russian as a lover
of Russian literature in English
is that it's not a simple language at all.
The grammar's complex.
There's a lot that's expressed
that will be lost in the translation.
So yes, I mean the fact that you speak Native Russian,
I mean I would run that walk to that interview,
'cause I think it would just be amazing.
You would get so much more out of it than I did.
- And we should say that you've met a lot of world leaders,
both Zelensky and Putin are intelligent, witty, even funny.
- [Tucker] Yes.
- So like there's a depth to the person
that can be explored throughout conversation
just on that element, the linguistic element.
- For sure, and Putin speaks decent English.
I spoke to him in English, so I know that.
But he's not comfortable with it at all.
- [Lex] Right. - But Zelensky is, I think.
- No, well he's better than Putin in English,
but he's still, the humor, the like, the intelligence,
all of that is not quite there in English.
He says simple points.
But the guy's a comedian.
And he's a comedian primarily in Russian,
the Russian language.
So the Ukrainian language is now used mostly,
primarily as a kind of symbol.
of independence. - [Tucker] I'm aware of that.
It's a political decision.
No, I know.
- And he is, you know, his really,
his native language is Russian language.
- [Tucker] Of course, as a lot of people in Ukraine.
- But you can also understand his position
that he might not want to be speaking Russian publicly.
That's something-
- I don't think they're allowed to speak
in Russia in some places in Ukraine, right?
That's one of the reasons that Russia was so mad,
is that they were attacking language.
And that's a fair complaint.
Like, what?
And by the way, if you haven't been to Moscow in a while,
you should see it and you will pick up a million things
that were invisible to me.
And you should assess it for yourself.
And my strong advice would be,
even if you don't interview Putin, go over there,
spend a week there and assess what you think.
I mean, how restricted does the society feel?
I mean, it would take a lot of balls to do this
because I mean, whatever you decide,
you'll be sucked into conversations
that have nothing to do with you.
Political conversations. - [Lex] Yeah.
- You're obviously not a political activist, right?
You're an interviewer.
But I think it would be so interesting.
- But for interview itself, is there advice
you have about how to carry an interview?
It is fundamentally different when you do it
in the native language.
- Yes, I mean, I think I approached...
And maybe I did it incorrectly,
but this was the product of a lot of thought.
I was coming into that interview aware
that he hadn't given an interview at all
with anybody since the war started,
so I had a million different questions.
And as noted, I didn't ask them
because I just wanted to focus on the war.
But I mean, there's so many,
I'll send you my notes that I wrote.
I was like a diligent little girl. (chuckles)
- That would be amazing.
But I think- - (laughs) My interview.
All these questions, and some of them
I thought were pretty funny.
- In your case, I think the very fact of the interview
was the most important thing.
- Yeah, that's probably right.
The question that I really wanted
to ask that I was almost gonna ask,
'cause it made me laugh out loud.
I was sitting having drinking coffee beforehand
with my producers and I was like, "I'm gonna go in there.
My first question's gonna be, Mr. President.
I've been here in the Kremlin for two days preparing,
and I haven't seen a single African American
in a position of power in the Kremlin."
- [Lex] Sure.
- (laughs) I thought that's too.
- [Lex] Yeah. - Culturally specific and dry.
And he'd be like, "This guy's freaking crazy."
- Yeah, yeah, you don't wanna open with a crazy.
with humor. - No, I know.
I know. - [Lex] All right.
- That's probably, doesn't translate.
- It doesn't.
Oh yeah, and there'll be a small delay
where you have to wait for the-
- (laughs) Like what?
- [Lex] To see if it lands or not.
- This is not America.
- At Fox, you were for a time, the most popular host.
After Fox, you've garnered a huge amount
of attention as well.
Same, probably more.
Do you worry that popularity and just that attention
gets to your head is a kind of drug
that clouds your thinking?
- You think?
I live in a spiritual graveyard
of people killed by the quest for fame.
Yes, I have lived in it.
I mean, I would say the one advantage,
the two advantages I have.
And one, I have a happy family and a stable family
and a stable group of friends,
which is just the greatest blessing
and a strong love of nature and that my family share.
So, I'm in nature every day.
And I have a whole series of rituals
designed to keep me from becoming the asshole
that I could easily become.
But no, of course.
And I don't want to beat up on, I'm grateful to Elon
who gave me a platform, and I mean that sincerely,
but I definitely don't spend a lot of time on social media
or on the internet for that exact reason.
Well, first of all, I think it's, as I've said,
a much more controlled environment than we acknowledge.
And I don't want lies in my head,
but I also don't want to become the sort of person
who's seeking the adulation of strangers.
I think that's soul poison.
And I said earlier that I think that the desire
for power and money will kill you.
And I believe that, and I've seen it a lot.
But I also think the desire for the love of people
you don't know is every bit as poisonous maybe more so.
And so, yes, and it's not just because
I've obviously spent most of my life in public.
And in fact I don't spend my life in public
and I'm completely private person.
But professionally I've spent my life in public.
But it's not just that.
It's like social media makes everybody
into a cable news host.
And we were talking off the air, my new, I just,
I'm obsessed with this, but I don't know enough about it,
but here's what I do know.
South Korea, amazing country, great people.
I grew up around Koreans, probably no group,
if I can generalize about a group
that I like more than Koreans,
are just smart, funny, honest, brave.
I really like Koreans, I always have.
My whole life growing up
in southern California with Koreans.
South Korea is like dying.
It's literally dying.
It's way below replacement rate in fertility.
Its suicide rate is astronomical.
Why is that?
It's a rich country.
But of course, I dunno the answer,
but I suspect it has something to do
with the penetration of technology
into South Korean society is I think one of the highest,
certainly one of the highest in the world.
People live online there.
And there was a belief in,
for a bunch of reasons in South Korea
that Western technology would be
a liberating progressive force.
And I think it's been the opposite.
It's my sense, strong sense.
And I think it's true in this country too.
And I don't understand how people can ignore the decline
in life expectancy or the rise in fentanyl use.
Like, it's not just about China shipping
precursor chemicals to Mexico.
It's like, why would you take that shit?
- I hope those two things aren't coupled.
Technological advancement and the erosion.
- Well, let me ask you, and I know you're a technologist,
and I respect it.
And there's a lot about technology that I like
and it benefited from.
I had back surgery and it worked okay,
so I'm not against all technology.
But can you name a technology,
a big technology in the last 20 years
that we can say conclusively has improved people's lives?
- Well, conclusive is a tough thing.
- [Tucker] Pretty conclusively.
That we can brag about.
- Well you've criticized Google search recently,
but I think making the world knowledge accessible to anyone
anywhere across the world through Google search.
- Well, I love that, I love that idea.
Are people better informed?
Are they more superstitious and misled
than they were 20 years ago? (laughs)
It's not close.
- Well, no, I don't know.
I think they are more informed.
It is just revealing the ignorance.
The internet has revealed the ignorance that people have.
But I think the ignorance has been decreasing gradually.
And like, if you look even,
you can criticize places like Wikipedia a lot
and very many aspects of Wikipedia are very biased.
But when you, most of it are actually topics
that don't have any bias in them
because they're not political,
so there's no battle over those topics.
- [Tucker] Right.
- And most of Wikipedia.
- [Tucker] I think that's true.
- Is like the fastest way to learn about a thing.
- I couldn't agree more.
You can very quickly imagine you're an expert.
And that may be the problem, I think.
No, it's true.
I just experienced it in Moscow.
It's like, again, I feel like I'm in the top 1%
for information, certainly intake because it's my job.
And I had literally...
And I'm always outta the country.
I've been around the world many times.
Like I feel like I know a lot about the rest of the world
or I thought I did.
And how did I not know any of that?
And maybe I'm just like unusually ignorant or something,
or reading the wrong things.
I don't know what it was.
But all I know is the digital information sources
that I used to understand.
Just something as simple as what's the city of Moscow like.
We're completely inadequate.
And anyway, look, I just am worried
that we're missing the obvious signs.
And the obvious signs are reproduction,
life expectancy, sobriety.
If you have a society where people just can't deal
with being sober, don't want to have children
and are dying younger, you have an extremely sick,
you have a suicidal society, okay?
And I'm not even blaming anyone for,
I'm just saying objectively that is true.
And the measure of a health of your society
is the number of children that you have
and how well they do.
It's super simple.
That's the next generation.
We all die.
And what replaces us.
And if you don't care, then you're suicidal.
And maybe other things too.
But that's all I'm saying.
So, what happened to South Korea?
Like, why can't anyone answer the question?
They're great people, they're rich,
they have all these advantages.
They're on the cutting edge of every American.
For a foreign country, they're more American
than maybe any other country other than Canada.
And like what happened?
- And I mean, your fundamental war
is the same kind of thing might be happening
or will happen in the United States.
- Well, lemme just ask you this.
I think North Korea seems like the most dystopian,
horrible place in the world, right?
Obviously.
It's a by word for dystopia, right?
North Korean.
I use it all the time, and I mean it.
If in a hundred years
there are more North Koreans still alive
than there are South Koreans, what does that tell us?
- [Lex] Yeah, that's something to worry about.
- But like, how did it happen?
Like why?
I'm interested in the why.
This is a question I asked Putin.
Sometimes we don't know why, but why does no one ask why.
- I've seen a lot of increased distrust in science,
which is deserved in many places.
It just worries me because some of the greatest inventions
of humanity come from science and technological innovation.
- Okay, then let me ask you a couple quick questions
and perhaps you have the answer.
And I've always assumed that was true.
And I should say that when I was a kid,
I lived in La Jolla, California,
next to the Salk Institute named after Jonas Salk,
a resident of La Jolla, California,
who created the polio vaccine and saved untold millions.
And so my belief, which is still my belief actually,
that's a great thing.
It's one of the great additions to human flourishing ever.
But if technology is so great,
why is life expectancy going down
and why are fewer people having kids,
and why would anybody who has internet access
every use fentanyl?
What is that, what is going on?
And until we can answer that question,
I think we have to assume the question
of whether technology is a net good
or net bad is unresolved, like at best, right?
- At best, perhaps.
But technology is the very tool that which will allow us
to have that kind of discourse to figure out
to do science better.
- I mean, I want that to be true.
And when you said that the internet allows people
to escape the darkness of ignorance.
Man, that resonated with me,
'cause I felt that way in 1993, 4
when it was first starting and I first got on it.
And I thought, "Man, this is amazing."
You can talk for free to anyone around the world.
This is gonna be great.
But lemme just ask you this.
This is something I've never gotten over
or gotten a straight answer to.
Why is it that in any European city,
the greatest buildings indisputably
were built before electricity and the machine age?
Why has no one ever built a medieval cathedral
in the modern era ever?
What is that? - Well, indisputably
you're have a presumption
we have a good definition of what beauty is.
There's a lot of people-
- Right, let's be specific.
Pick a European city or any city in the world
and tell me that there's a prettier building
than say Notre Dame before it was set fire to.
- There's other sources of prettiness and beauty.
- That it's purely in architecture.
Of course, of course.
Trees are prettier than any building in my opinion, right,
so I agree with you there. - But also there could be,
I mean I grew up in the pre-internet age.
- [Tucker] Good, good.
- But if you grew up in the internet age,
I think your eyes would be more open
to beauty that's digital, that is in a digital.
- I'm not discounting the possibility
of digital beauty at all.
And the Ted Kaczynski in me wants to.
But that's too close-minded, I agree.
I'm completely willing to believe
there is such a thing as digital beauty.
I mean I have digital pictures of my phone,
of my dogs and kids, so I know that there is.
But purely in the realm of architecture,
'cause it's like limited.
And it is one of the pure expressions of human creativity.
We need places to live and work and worship and eat,
and so we build buildings and every civilization has.
But the machine age, the industrial age
seemed to have decreased the quality
and the beauty in that one expression
of human creativity architecture.
And why is that?
- Well, I could also argue
that I'm a big sucker for bridges.
And modern bridges can give older bridges
that run for their money.
- I like bridges too.
So I agree with you sort of.
But like the Brooklyn Bridge, I don't know
that there's any modern bridges
that was built in late 19th century.
Very much in the industrial age.
But I'm just saying like the great cathedrals of Europe.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Even the pyramids, whoever built them, it doesn't,
it seems like if you, it's like super obvious.
I'm just like, I'm dealing on the autism level here.
Just like, well why is that?
But that's a good way to start.
If all of a sudden you have electricity and hydraulics
and you have access to, I mean,
I have machines in my wood shop at home
that are so much more advanced in anything
than any cathedral builder in 15th century Europe had.
And yet there's neither I nor anyone know
could even begin to understand
how a flying buttress was built, right?
And so, what is that?
- And the other question is also consider
that whatever is creating this technology is unstoppable.
- And well there's that, yeah.
- And the question is like, how do you steer it then?
You have to look in a realist way at the world
and say that if you don't, somebody else will.
And you want to do it in a safe way.
I mean, this is the Manhattan project.
- Was the Manhattan project a good idea
to create nuclear weapons?
That's an easy call, no.
- For me it's an easy call in retrospect.
In retrospect, yes.
Because it seems like it stopped world wars.
So the mutually assure destruction
seems to have ended wars, ended major military.
- Well it's been what, 80 years?
Not even 80 years. 79.
And so we haven't had a world war in 79 years.
But one nuclear exchange would of course
kill more people than all wars in human history combined.
- You're saying '79 makes it sound like you're counting.
- I'm counting, 'cause I think it obviously
it's like completely demonic
and everyone pretends like it's great.
Nuclear weapons are evil.
- [Lex] Yeah, no, absolutely.
- The use of them is evil and the technology itself is evil.
And in my opinion, I mean it's like,
if you can't, that's just so obvious.
And that's what what I'm saying is like,
I'm not against all technology.
I took a shower this morning.
It was powered by an electric pump.
- [Lex] Yep. - Heated by a water heater.
Like I loved it.
I sat in an electric sauna.
Like I'm not against all technology obviously,
but the mindless worship of technology.
- Sure.
Mindless worship of anything is pretty bad.
- But I'm just saying, so you said,
let's approach this from a realist perspective.
Okay, if we think that there is a reasonable,
or even a potential chance
it could happen maybe on the margins,
let's assign it a 15% chance that AI, for example,
gets away from us and we are now ruled by machines
that may actually hate us.
Who knows what they want.
Why wouldn't we use force to stop that from happening?
So you're walking down the street in midtown Manhattan,
it's midnight, you've had a few drinks,
you're coming from dinner,
you're walking back to your apartment.
A guy, a very thuggish looking,
guy young man approaches you.
He's 50 feet away.
He pulls out a handgun, he lifts it up to you.
You also are armed.
Do you shoot him or do you wait to get shot
because all the data, look, he hasn't shot you.
He's not committed a crime
other than carrying a weapon in New York City.
But maybe he's got a license you don't know.
Could be legal.
But he's pointing a gun at you.
Is it fair to kill him before he kills you?
Even though you can't prove that he will kill you.
- If I knew my skills with a gun
because he already has the gun off.
- Right, but it turns out
that you have some confidence in your ability
to stop the threat by force. - [Lex] Okay, okay, yeah.
- Are you justified in doing that?
- I just like this picture.
Am I wearing a cowboy hat?
- No, no, but you are wearing cowboy boots
and they're clicking on the cobblestone,
actually you're wearing the meat packing,
okay? - Okay, great.
I like this picture. - [Tucker] Yeah.
- I think about this a lot actually, no.
Yeah, I understand your point.
But also, I think that metaphor falls apart
if there's other nations at play here.
So, if the same as with the nuclear bomb.
If US doesn't build it, will other nations build it?
The Soviet Union build it, China or Nazi Germany.
- We faced this, I mean, we faced this
and the last president to try and keep in a meaningful way
nuclear proliferation under control was John F. Kennedy.
And look what happened to him.
- What's your suggestion?
Wasn't it inevitable? - But hold on.
Well, their position in 1962
was no, it's absolutely not inevitable.
Or perhaps it's inevitable in the sense
that our death is inevitable, but as human beings.
But we fight against the dying of the light anyway,
because that's the right thing to do.
No, we were willing to use force
to prevent other countries from getting the bomb
because we thought that would be really terrible.
'cause we acknowledged that while there were upsides
to nuclear weapons, just like there were upsides to AI,
the downside was terrifying in the hands of...
I mean, that's the thing that I kind of don't get.
It's like the applications of that technology
in the hands of people who mean to do harm and destroy.
It's like so obviously terrifying.
- It's not so obvious to me.
What I'm terrified about is probably a similar thing
that you're terrified about, is using that technology
to manipulate people's minds.
That's much more reasonable to me as an expectation.
A real threat that's possible in the next few years.
- But what matters more than that?
- Well, I think that could lead to like
destruction of human civilization through other humans,
for example, starting nuclear wars.
- Yeah, well, I mean this is one of the reasons
I wasn't afraid in the Vladimir Putin interview,
'cause it's like it's all ending anyway.
You know what I mean? - [Lex] Yeah.
- Might as well dance on the deck of the Titanic.
Don't be a pussy, enjoy it.
- I think we will forever fight against
the dying of the light as the entirety of the civil.
- Someone the other day said that Biden
ascribed that to Churchill.
That was a Churchill quote. - Hmm.
- That's kind of what I'm saying.
It's like if you live in a society
where people don't read anymore,
like people are by definition much more ignorant,
but they don't know it.
It's like, I do think the Wikipedia culture,
and I think there are cool things about Wikipedia,
certainly it's ease of use is like high and that's great.
But people get the sense that like,
oh, I know a lot about you know,
this or that or the other thing.
And it's like the key to wisdom.
Again, the key to wise decision making
is knowing what you don't know.
And it's just so important to be reminded
of what a dummy you are
and how ignorant you are all the time.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- That's why I like having daughters.
It's like it's never far from mind how flawed I am.
And that's important.
- Yeah, in the same way I hope to be a dad one day.
- You should have a ton of kids.
Are you gonna have a ton of pups?
- Five, oh pup.
You mean like kids? - Children.
- Yes, five.
But also I've been thinking of getting a dog,
but unrelated.
I would love to have like five or six kids.
Yeah, for sure.
- Have you found a victim yet?
- (chuckles) You make it sound so romantic, Tucker.
- (laughs) Just joking, I love it.
No, you should totally do that.
- Yeah, 100%.
But also in terms of being humble,
I do jiu-jitsu, it's in martial art
where you get your ass kicked all the time.
- [Tucker] Yeah, I love that.
- It's nice to get your ass kicked.
Physical humbling is unlike anything else I think,
'cause we're kind of monkeys at heart
and just getting your ass kicked just really helpful.
- I agree, I've had it happen to me twice.
- (chuckles) Twice is enough.
- It got me to quit drinking.
I was good at starting fights, not good at winning them.
But no, I completely agree with that.
- Let me ask you, you've been pretty close
with Donald Trump.
Your private texts about him around the 2020 election
were made public.
In one of them you said that you passionately hate Trump.
When that came out,
you said that you actually know you love him.
So, how do you explain the difference?
- My texts reflect a lot of things,
including how I feel at the moment that I sent them.
That specific text, I happened to know
since I had to go through it forensically
during my deposition in a case I was not named in.
I had nothing to do with whatsoever.
It's crazy how civil suits can like be used
to hurt people you disagree with politically.
But I was mad at a very specific,
I mean really what that...
I mean, you're asking me,
I'll tell you exactly what that was.
It was the second the election ended
and they stopped voting,
stopped the vote counting on election night.
I was like, well this is,
and it's all now mail-in ballots
and electronic voting machines.
I was like, that's a rigged election.
I thought that then, I think it now.
Now, it's obvious that it was.
But at the time I was like, I feel like there's,
that was like crazy what just happened.
I want, but I don't wanna go on TV
and say that's a rigged election
because I don't have any evidence as a recollection.
You can't do that.
It's irresponsible and it's wrong.
So I was like, I want...
The Trump campaign was making all these claims
about this or that fraud,
so I was trying my best to substantiate them,
to follow up on it.
Everyone else was like, "Shut up, Trump, you lost.
Go away. We're gonna indict you."
But I felt like my job was to be like,
"No, the guy's, he's president,
he's claiming the election just got stolen
and he's making these claims.
Let's see if we can."
Well, the people around him were like so incompetent.
It was just absolutely crazy.
And so, I called a couple of times.
I finally give up, but I'd call him be like,
all right, you guys claim that these inconsistencies
and this, you know, whatever this happened,
gimme evidence and I'll put it on TV.
It's my job to bring stuff
that is not gonna be aired anywhere else to the public.
I couldn't, it was like, it was insane
how incompetent and unserious.
- So, they weren't able to provide like-
- Well, here's the point of the story and of that text.
So then they come out and they say, well, dead people voted.
Well, that's just an easy call.
Okay, if a dead person voted, we can prove someone's dead,
'cause like being dead is one of the few things
we're good at like verifying,
'cause you start to smell, okay?
And there's a record of it.
It's called a death certificate.
So it was like, gimme the names of people who are dead,
who voted, and then we can get their registration
and we can show they voted.
Five names.
So I go on TV and I say this,
Caroline Johnson, 79 of Waukegan, Illinois voted,
here's her death certificate, she died.
And the campaign sends me this stuff.
Now I in general don't take stuff directly
from campaigns 'cause they all lie
'cause their job is to get elected or whatever.
So, I'm very wary of campaigns
having been around it for 30 years.
So like, but I made an exception to my rule
and I got a bunch of stuff from them.
Well, like of the six names, two of 'em were still alive.
What?
I was so, well, I immediately corrected it the next night.
CNN did a whole segment
on how I was spreading disinformation,
which I was by the way.
In this one case they were right.
I was so mad.
I was like, "I hate you.
I'm not talking about you, I'm so mad."
Anyway, that's the answer if that's what that was.
- Who were you texting to?
- My producer.
And I was like, venting.
It's like a producer I was really close to.
And I've known him for a long time.
He's really smart.
And he's like, he was someone I could like be honest with.
And I was like, "Rah."
And by the way, it was so funny.
I mean now I'm doing what was me,
which I will keep to a minimum,
but it's like stealing someone's text.
And by the way, I was an idiot.
I should have said, come and arrest me.
I'm not giving you my freaking text messages,
okay? - [Lex] Yeah.
- But I got bullied into it by a lawyer.
I didn't get bullied into it.
I was weak enough to agree with a lawyer.
It was my fault.
Never should have done that.
Fuck you, they're my texts.
I'm not even named in this case.
That's what I should have said, but I didn't.
I said I was mad on the air the next day,
but not in language that colorful.
But whatever, whatever.
I try to be transparent.
I mean, I also think, by the way,
if you watch someone over time,
you don't always know what they really think,
but you can tell if someone's lying.
You can sort of feel it in people.
And I have lied.
I'm sure I'll lie again.
I don't wanna lie.
I don't think I'm a liar.
I try not to be a liar.
I don't wanna be a liar.
I think it's like really important not to be a liar.
- You said nice things about me earlier.
I'm starting to question.
I have questions. (Tucker laughing)
I have a lot of questions, Tucker.
- I hate Lex Fridman. (laughs)
- Yeah, I am gonna have to see your texts after this.
- My texts are so uninteresting now.
It's like crazy how uninteresting they are.
- [Lex] Emojis and gifs.
- Yeah, lots of dog pictures.
- Nice.
You said some degree the election was rigged.
Was it stolen?
- It was a hundred percent stolen.
Are you joking?
- [Lex] Like it was rigged to that large of a degree.
- Yeah, they completely change the way people vote
right before the election on the basis of COVID,
which had nothing to do with-
- In that way it was rigged,
meaning like manipulated. - 100%.
And you censor the information people are allowed to get.
Anyone who complains about COVID,
which is like, by the way, it might have hurt Trump.
But I mean it's like whatever.
I mean you could play it many different ways.
You can't have censorship in a democracy by definition.
Here's how it works.
The people rule.
They vote for representatives to carry their agenda
to the capital city and get it enacted.
That's how they're in charge.
And then every few years
they get to reassess the performance
of those people in an election.
In order to do that, they need access,
unfettered access to information.
And no one, particularly not people
who are already in power is allowed to tell them
what information they can have.
They have to have all information that they want.
Whether the people in charge want it or don't want it
or think it's true or think it's false, it doesn't matter.
And the second you don't have that,
you don't have a democracy.
It's not a free election, period.
And that's very clear in other countries, I guess.
But it's not clear here.
So, but I would say it's this election that,
I mean it took me a while to come to this,
but it's this election that's the referendum on democracy.
Biden is senile.
He's literally senile.
He can't talk, he can't walk.
The whole world knows that.
Leave our borders, people are, you know,
everybody in the world knows it.
A senile man is not gonna get elected
in the most powerful country in the world
unless there's fraud, period.
Like who would vote for a senile man?
He literally can't talk.
And nobody I've ever met
thinks he's running the US government 'cause he's not.
And so I think the world is looking on
at this coming election and saying,
and a lot of the world hates Trump.
Okay, it's not an endorsement of Trump, but it's just true.
If Joe Biden gets reelected, democracy's a freaking joke.
It's just true.
- I think half the country doesn't think he's senile,
just thinks he's speaking-
- Do you really think that?
They don't think he's senile?
- Yeah, I think he just has difficulty speaking.
It's like-
- [Tucker] Why do they think he has difficulty speaking?
- Like gradual degradation, just getting old.
So, cognitive ability is a degrading.
- What's the difference between degraded
cognitive ability and senility?
- Well, senility has a threshold of like a,
it's beyond a threshold
to where he could be a functioning leader.
- Okay, okay, that may be a term of art
that I don't fully understand
and maybe there's like an IQ threshold or something,
but I'm happy to go with degraded cognitive ability.
- Sure, but that's an age thing.
- But he's the leader of the United States
with the world's second largest nuclear arsenal.
- And I'm with you.
I'm a sucker for great speeches
and for speaking abilities of leaders
and Biden with two wars going on and potentially more,
the importance of a leader to speak eloquently,
both privately in a room with other leaders
and publicly is really important.
- I agree with you that rhetorical ability really matters.
Convincing people if that your program is right,
telling them what we're for, national identity,
national unity, all come from words.
I agree with all of that.
But at this stage, even someone
who grunted at the microphone would be more reassuring
that a guy who clearly doesn't know where he is.
And I think everyone knows that.
And like, I can't imagine there's an honest person
in Washington which is gonna vote for Biden
by 90% obviously, 'cause they're all dependent
on the federal government for their income.
But is there any person who could say like,
out of 350 million Americans,
like that's the most qualified to lead,
or even in the top 80%, like what?
That's so embarrassing that that guy is our president.
And with wars going on, it's scary.
- But it's complicated to understand
why those are the choices we have.
- Well, I agree.
Well, it's a failure of the system.
Clearly it's not working.
If you've got one guy over 80, the guy,
other guy almost at 80,
like people that he should not be running any.
- So why you have on the democratic side,
you have Dean Phillips, you have RFK Jr.
until recently, I guess he's independent.
And then you have Vivek who are all younger people.
- [Tucker] Yeah.
- Why did they not connect to a degree to where people-
- It's such an interesting,
I mean I think it's a really interesting,
there are a million different answers.
And of course I don't fully understand it
even though I feel like I've watched it pretty carefully.
But I would say the bottom line
is there's so much money vested in the federal apparatus,
in the parties, in the government.
As I said a minute ago,
our economies dominated by monopolies,
but the greatest all monopolies is the federal monopoly
which oversees and controls all the other monopolies.
So it's like, it's really substantially about the money.
It's not ideological, it's about the money.
And if someone controls the federal government,
I mean at this point it's the most powerful
organization in human history.
Like, it's kind of hard to fight that.
And in the case of Trump, I know the answer there.
They raided Mar-a-Lago,
they indicted him on bullshit charges.
Like, and I felt that in myself too.
Even I was like, come on, come on.
Like whatever you think of Trump.
And I agreed with his immigration views
and I really liked Trump personally.
I think he's hilarious and interesting, which he is.
But it's like, okay,
there are a lot of people in this country.
At very least like let's have a real debate.
The second...
Messed up your cameras there,
sorry, I'm getting excited.
But the second they rated Mar-a-Lago on a documents charge
as someone from DC I was like,
I know a lot about classification
and all that stuff and been around it a lot.
That's so absurd that I was like, now it's not about Trump,
it's about our system continuing.
Like if you can take out a presidential candidate
on a fake charge, use the justice system
to take the guy outta the race,
then we don't have a representative democracy anymore.
And I think a lot of Republican voters felt that way.
If they hadn't indicted him,
I'm not sure he would be the nominee.
I really don't think he would be.
- So, now a vote for Trump is a kind of
fuck you to the system
- Or an expression of your desire
to keep the system that we had.
Which is one where voters get to decide.
Prosecutors don't get to decide.
Look, they told us for four years
that Trump was like a super criminal or something.
I've actually been friends with some super criminals.
I'm a little less judgey than most.
So I didn't discount the possibility
that he had, I don't know.
He is in the real estate business
in New York in the 70s.
Like, did he kill someone?
I don't know. - [Lex] Yeah.
- No, I'm not joking and I'm not for killing people,
but like anything's possible.
- It's good that you took a stand on that.
(Tucker laughing)
- Yeah, no, I'm not joking. - [Lex] Yeah.
- I was like, well who knows, you know,
and I didn't know. - [Lex] Yeah, real estate.
- And what they came up with was a documents charge.
Are you joking?
And then the sitting president
has the same documents violation, but he's fine.
It's like, it's crazy this is happening
in front of all of us.
And then it becomes like at that point,
it's not about Joe Biden, it's not about Donald Trump.
It's about preserving a system
which has worked not perfectly,
but pretty freaking well for 250 years.
I know you don't like Trump. I get it.
Let's not destroy that system.
Like we can handle in the four years of Trump.
I think we can, so I'll calm down.
What we can't handle is a country whose political system
is run by the Justice Department.
Like that is just,
you're freaking Ecuador at that point, no.
- So speaking of the Justice department,
CIA and intelligence agencies of that nature,
which you've been traveling quite a bit,
probably tracked by everybody,
which is the most powerful intelligence agency do you think?
CIA, Mossad, MI6, SVR.
I can keep going.
(chuckles) The Chinese.
- It depends what you mean by powerful.
Which one bats above its weight we know,
which one is-
- Mossad just to be clear, I guess is what you-
- Well, of course, tiny country,
very sophisticated intel service.
Which one has the greatest global reach in comms?
Which one is most able to read your text?
I assume the NSA, but Chinese are clearly pretty good.
Israel's pretty good.
The French actually are surprisingly good
for kind of a declining country.
Their intel services are pretty, seem pretty impressive.
No, I love France, but you know what I mean, and all that.
So but the question,
I mean I grew up around all that stuff.
That's all totally fine.
Like a strong country should have a strong
and capable intel service, so its policy makers
can make informed decisions.
Like that's what they're for.
As Vladimir Putin himself noted.
And I don't talk about it very much, but it's true.
I applied to the CIA when I was in college
'cause I was familiar with it
because of where I lived and had grown up and everything.
And I was like, seemed interesting.
That's honestly the only reason.
I was like live in foreign countries, see history happen.
Like I'm for that.
I applied to the operations directorate,
they turned me down on the basis of drug use actually.
True.
But anyhow, whatever, I was unsuited for it,
so I'm glad they turned me down.
But the point is I didn't see CIA as a threat,
partly because I was bathing in propaganda about CIA
and I didn't really understand what it was
and didn't want to know.
But second, because my impression at the time
was it was outwardly focused.
It was focused on our enemies.
I don't have a problem with that as much.
The fact that CIA is playing in domestic politics
and actually has for a long time,
was involved in the Kennedy assassination.
That's not speculation, that's a fact.
And I confirmed that from someone
who had read their documents that are still not public.
It's shocking.
Like you can't have that.
And the reason I'm so mad is I really believe
in the idea of representative government
acknowledging its imperfections,
but like I should have some say, I live here,
I'm a citizen, I pay all your freaking taxes.
So the fact that they would be tampering
with American democracy is so outrageous to me.
And I don't know why, "Morning Joe" is not outraged.
This parade of dummies, highly credentialed dummies
they have on, "Morning Joe" every day.
They don't seem to, that doesn't bother them at all.
How could that not bother you?
Why is only Glenn Greenwald mad about it?
I mean, it's confirmed it's not like a fever dream,
it's real.
They played in the last election domestically.
And I guess it shows how dumb I am
because they've been doing that for many years.
I mean, the guy who took out Mossadegh lived on my street.
One of the Roosevelt, CIA officer.
So I mean, again, I grew up around this stuff,
but I never really thought,
I never reached the obvious conclusion,
which is that if the US government
subverts democracy in other countries
in the name of democracy, it will over time
subvert democracy in my country.
Why wouldn't it?
The corruption is like core.
It's at the root of it.
The purpose of the CIA was envisioned,
at least publicly envisioned
as an intel gathering apparatus for the executive,
so the president could make wise foreign policy decisions.
What the hell is happening in Country X? I don't know.
Let me call the agency in charge of finding out.
The point wasn't to freaking guarantee
the outcome of elections.
- I'm doing a Israel-Palestine debate next week.
But I have to ask you just your thoughts,
maybe even from a US perspective,
what do you think about Hamas attacks on Israel?
What would be the right thing for Israel to do
and what's the right thing for US to do in this
if you looking at the geopolitics of it.
- I mean, it's not a topic that I get into a lot
because I'm a non-expert.
And because I'm not, unlike every other American,
I'm not emotionally invested in other countries,
just in general.
I mean I admire them or not and I love visiting them.
I love Jerusalem, probably my favorite city in the world.
But I don't have an emotional attachment to it.
So maybe I've got more clarity.
I don't know, maybe less.
Here's my view.
I believe in sovereignty as mentioned.
And I think each country has to make decisions
based on its own interest,
but also with reference to its own capabilities
and its own long-term interest.
And it's very unwise for, I'm not a huge fan of treaties.
Some are fine, too many bad,
but I think US aid, military aid to Israel
and the implied security guarantees some explicit,
but many implied security guarantees of the United States
to Israel probably haven't helped Israel
that much long term.
It's a rich country with a highly capable population.
Like every other country,
it's probably best if it makes its decisions
based on what it can do by itself.
So I would definitely be concerned if I lived in Israel
because I think fair or unfair,
and really this is another product of technology,
social media.
Public sentiment in that area is boiling over.
And I think it's gonna be hard for some
of the governments in the region, Jordan, Egypt, Turkey,
to contain their own.
They don't want conflict with Israel at all.
They were all pretty psyched actually
for the trend in progress.
The Saudi peace deal, which was never signed,
but would've been great for everybody,
'cause like trade peace, normal relations,
like that's good, okay, let's just say.
I know John Bolton doesn't like it, but it's good.
And it's kind of what we should be looking for.
But now it's not possible.
And if you had like a coalition of countries against Israel,
I know Israel's nuclear weapons
and has a capable military and all that
and the backing of the United States,
but like you don't, it's a small country,
I think I'd be very worried.
So, there's that.
And I don't see any advantage in to the United States.
I mean, I think it's important for each country
to make its own decisions.
- But it also is a place, like you said,
where things are boiling over
and it could spread across multiple nations
into a major military conflict.
- Yeah, well I think very easily could happen.
In fact, probably right after Ramadan, if I had to guess.
And yeah, I pray it doesn't.
But again, I don't think you can overstate
the lack of wisdom, weakness, short-term thinking
of American foreign policy leadership.
These are the architects of the Iraq war,
of the totally pointless destruction of Libya,
totally pointless destruction of Syria
and the 20 year occupation of Afghanistan
that resulted in a return to the status quo.
So like their, of the Vietnam War, their track record
of the Korean War, even going back 80 years
is uninterrupted failures one after the other.
So I just don't have any confidence in those leaders,
when was the last time they improved another country?
Can you think of the, oh, the Marshall plan.
Well, you look at Europe now and you're like,
"I don't know if that worked."
But even if it did work, again 80 years ago,
so when was the last country
American foreign policy makers improved?
So if I were...
Netanyahu's in a very difficult place,
politically impossible I mean.
I'm glad I'm not Netanyahu.
And I'm not sure he's capable
of making wise long-term decisions anyway.
But if I was just like an Israeli, I'd be like,
I don't know if I want like all this help and guidance.
So yeah, I actually think it's worse
than just having just returned from the Middle East
and talking to a lot of pretty open-minded,
sort of pro-Israeli Arabs who want stability above all.
The merchant class always wants stability,
so I'm on their side, I guess.
And they're like,
"Man, this could get super ugly super fast."
American leadership is completely absent.
It's all posturing.
It's like people like Nikki Haley.
You just wonder like how does an advanced civilization
promote someone like Nikki Haley to a position of authority?
It's like what?
Shh, shh, like adults are talking, adults are talking.
Nikki Haley, please go away.
Like that would be the appropriate response.
But everyone's so intimidated to be like,
oh, she's a strong woman.
She's so transparently weak and sort of ridiculous
and doesn't know anything and is just like,
thinks that jumping up and down
and making these absurd blanket statements,
repeating bumper stickers is like leadership,
so it's like a self-confident advanced society
would never allow Nikki Haley to advance.
I mean, she's really not impressive, sorry.
- I just feel like you hold back too much
and don't tell us what you really think.
- (laughs) Sorry.
- I think you just speak your mind more often.
- Well, by the way, these are not,
I mean you can completely disagree with my opinions,
but in the case of Nikki Haley,
it's not like an opinion formed
just from watching television, which I don't watch.
It's an opinion formed from knowing Nikki Haley.
- So, strong words from Tucker.
- Well felt too. (chuckles) (Lex chuckling)
Well the world's in the balance.
I mean it's not just-
- [Lex] Yes, this is important stuff.
- Yeah, it's not just like, well, you know,
what should the capital gains rate be?
It's like, do we live or die?
I don't know, let's consult Nikki Haley. (laughs)
So if you're asking should we live or die
in consulting Nikki Haley,
clearly you don't care about the lives of your children.
That's how I feel.
- Not to try to get a preview or anything,
but do you have interest of interviewing Xi Jinping?
And if you do, how will you approach that?
- I have enormous interest in doing that, enormous.
And a couple other people, and we're working on it.
- Yeah, I should also say like, it's been refreshing
you interviewing world leaders.
I think when I've started seeing you do that,
it made me realize how much that's lacking.
- Well, yeah, it's just interesting, I mean-
- From even a historical perspective is interesting,
but it's also important from a geopolitics perspective.
- Well, it's really changed my perspective
and I've been going on about how American I am.
And I think that's a great thing.
I love America.
But it's also we're so physically geographically isolated
from the world.
Even though I traveled a ton as a kid a lot
more than most people.
But even now I'm like, I'm so parochial.
I see everything through this lens and getting out
and seeing the rest of the world
to which we really are connected,
like that's real is vitally important.
So, yeah, I mean at this stage
I don't kind of need to do it,
but I really want to just motivated by curiosity
and trying to expand my own mind and not be close-minded
and really see the fullest perspective I possibly can
in order to render wise judgments.
I mean that's like the whole journey of life.
- I was just hanging out with Rogan yesterday, Joe Rogan,
and I mentioned to him that it's me being a fan of his show,
that I would love for him to talk with you.
And he said he's up for it.
Any reason you guys haven't done it already?
- I don't know, I would.
I've only met Rogan once and I liked him.
I met him at the UFC in New York.
He was with somebody, a mutual friend of ours.
And Rogan changed media.
I mean maybe more than anybody.
And he did it.
What I love about what I admire about Rogan
without knowing him, beyond meeting him that one time,
I mean, I'm still in media, but I've always been in media,
it's like not a great surprise.
I'm doing what I've always done, just a different format.
But Rogan, like he's got one of those resumes that I admire.
I like the guy who was like, I was a longshoreman,
I was a short order cook, I was an astrophysicist.
I mean, he was like, he used a man of parts.
And this guy was a fighter, a standup comic,
he hosted some, "Fear Factor."
Like how did he wind up at the vanguard
of like the deepest conversations in the country?
Like how did that happen?
So, I definitely respect that and I think it's cool.
And he, Rogan is one of those people
who just kind of came out of nowhere.
Like no one helped him, you know what I mean?
- And he was doing the thing that he loves doing
and it somehow keeps accidentally
being exceptionally successful.
- Yeah, and he's curious.
So, that's like the main thing.
And there was a guy without getting boring,
but there was a guy I worked with years ago
who like kind of dominated cable news, Larry King,
and everyone would always beat up
on Larry King for being dumb.
Well, I got to know Larry King well,
and I was his fill-in host for a while,
and Larry King was just intensely curious.
He'd be like, "Why do you wear a black tie, Lex?"
I'd be like, "Because I like black tie."
"Why do you like a black tie?"
No one, everyone else wears a stripe type.
You wear a black one, why?
And he would like, he was like really interested.
- [Lex] Yeah, genuinely so,
yeah. - Totally.
And I want to be like that.
I don't want to think I know everything.
That's so boorish and also false.
You don't know everything.
But I see that in Rogan.
Rogan's like, "Rah, how does that work?"
And people will, and it's so funny
how that's threatening to people.
It's like Rogan will just sit there while someone else
is free balling on some far out topic,
which by the way might be true,
probably true than the conventional explanation.
People are like, I don't know, how can he stand that?
He had someone say the pyramids
weren't built 3,000 years ago,
but 8,000 years ago, and that's wrong.
It's like, first of all,
how do you know when the pyramids were built?
Second, why do you care if someone disagrees with you?
Like, what is that?
This weird kind of like groupthink.
It's almost like fourth grade,
there's always like some little girl in the front row
who's like acting as the kinda the teacher's enforcer,
like whip around and be like, "Sit down.
Didn't you hear what Mrs. Johnson said, sit down."
(laughs) That's like the whole American media.
How dare you ask that question.
And Rogan just seems like completely on his own trip.
Like he doesn't even hear it.
He's like, "Well, really when were the pyramids built?"
And I'm just like, "Oh, I love that."
- [Lex] Yeah, curiosity, open-mindedness.
- Yes.
- The thing I admire about him most honestly,
is that he's a good father.
He's a good husband.
He's a good family man for many years.
And like, that's his place
where he escapes from the world too.
And it's just beautiful.
- Without that, man, you're destroyed.
- [Lex] Yeah. - If I had a wife
who was interested at all in any way in what I did,
I think I would've gone crazy by now.
When we get home, we don't.
She's like, how was your day?
It was great.
Oh, I'm so proud of you.
That's the end of our conversation
about what I do for a living.
And that is such a wonderful
and essential respite from you said,
how do I not become an asshole to the extent I haven't,
I kind of have, but how have I not been transformed
into a totally insufferable megalomaniac
who like checking his Twitter replies
every day or every minute.
It's that, yeah, you gotta have,
the core of your life has to be solid and enduring
and not just ephemeral and silly.
- So, the two of you have known each other
for what, 40 years?
- We've been together 40 years.
- [Lex] Together 40 years. - 40 years.
Yeah, 1984.
He was the hottest 15-year-old in Newport, Rhode Island.
- Wow. - [Tucker] Sounds dirty.
But I'm talking about myself.
I was the hottest person. (laughs)
- Yeah, you were just looking in the mirror.
- [Tucker] Yeah. - Very nice.
So, what's the secret to a successful relationship,
successful marriage?
- I don't even know.
I mean, no, I'm serious. - [Lex] Yeah.
- I got married in August '91, so that's,
well, it's our 33rd year of being married fall.
- At the collapse of the Soviet Union.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah as noted, yeah.
So, you hear these people,
it's actually changed my theology a little bit.
Not that I have deep theology,
but like, I grew up in a society in Southern California
when I was little, that was like
a totally self-created society.
I mean, Southern California was,
it was the root of libertarianism for a reason.
It was like, that's where you went to recreate yourself.
And so, the operative assumption there
is that you are the sum total of your choices,
and that free will is everything.
And we never consider questions like,
well, why do children get cancer?
Like, what do they do to deserve it?
Well, of course, nothing, right?
Because that would suggest
that maybe you're not the sum total.
Your choices matter.
If I smoke a lot, I get lung cancer.
If I use fentanyl, I may OD, got it.
If I don't exercise, I might get fat, okay.
But like on a bigger scale,
you're not only the sum total of your choices.
Like things happen to you
that you didn't deserve, good and bad.
And marriage is, and I'll speak for myself
in my case, just one of 'em.
I mean, I could say, I mean, clearly spending time
with the person you're married to,
talking, enjoying each other.
I have a lot of rituals.
We have a lot of rituals that ensure that.
But in 40 years, like you change,
you're like a different person.
I like did drugs, I was drinking all the time when we met.
It's been a long time since I've been done that.
I'm very different and so is she.
But we're different in ways
that are complimentary and happy.
Never been happier.
So, like how do we pull that off?
Just kind of good luck, honestly.
And then I see other people.
No, I'm not kidding.
But that's true.
I think it's so important not to flatter yourself
if you've been successful at something.
The thing I've been most successful at is marriage,
but it's not really me.
I mean, I haven't-
- So I think what you indirectly communicating is,
it's like humility, I think.
- It's not even humility.
Humility is the result of a reality based worldview.
- [Lex] Sure, okay, right, reality.
- Once you see things clearly,
then you know that you are not the author
of all your successes or failures.
And I hate the implication otherwise
because it suggests powers that people don't have.
It's one of the reasons I always hated
the smoking debate or the COVID debate.
Someone die of COVID, did you not have the vaccine?
They'd be like, "See, this is what you get.
You smoke cigarettes, you die."
Well, shit I've, you know...
Yeah, if you smoke cigarettes,
you more likely to get lung cancer.
If you don't, if you get, whatever.
Cause and effect is real.
I'm not denying its existence, it's obvious.
But it's not the whole story.
There are larger forces acting on us, unseen forces.
That's just a fact.
You don't need to be some kind of religious nut.
And they act on AI too.
And you should keep that in mind.
The idea that all-
- Convincing way you said that.
- No, it's true.
It's demonstrably true.
We're the only society
that hasn't acknowledged the truth of that.
And the idea that the only things
that are real are the things
that we can see or measure in a lab.
Like that's insane, that's just dumb.
- In the religious context, you have this two categories
that I really like that of the two kinds of people
who believe they're God and people who know they're not,
which is a really interesting division
that speaks to humility and a kind of realist worldview
of where we are in the world.
- Oh.
- Can atheists being in the latter category?
- No, there are very few atheists
I've never actually met one.
There are people who pose this atheists,
but no one's purely rational.
And everyone, I mean, this is a cliche for a reason.
Everyone under extreme stress appeals to a power
higher than himself because everyone knows
that there is a power higher than himself.
So really it's just people who are gripped
with the delusion that they're God.
No one actually believes that.
If you're God jump off the roof of your garage
and see what happens.
You know what I mean?
No one actually thinks that,
but people behave as if it's true.
And those people are dangerous.
And I will say by contrast, the only people I trust
are the people who know their limits.
And I was thinking actually this morning in my sauna.
Of all the people I've interviewed or met,
this is someone I've never interviewed,
but I have talked to him a couple of times.
The greatest leader I've ever met in the world
is literally a king.
It's MBZ, Sheikh Mohamed of Abu Dhabi, who is Muslim.
I'm definitely not Muslim.
I'm Christian, Protestant Christian,
and so I don't agree with his religion
and I don't agree with monarchies.
But he's the best leader in the world that I've ever met.
And by far it's like not even close.
And why is that?
Well there, I could bore you for an hour on the subject,
but the reason that he's such a good leader
is because he's guided by an ever present knowledge
of his limitations and of the limits of his power
and of his foresight.
And when you start there, when you start with reality,
it's not even humility.
Humility can be opposed.
Like, oh, I'm so humble.
Okay, humble brag is a phrase for a reason.
It's like way deeper than that's just like, no.
Do I have magical powers?
Can I see the future?
No, okay, that's just a fact, so I'm not God.
But I've never seen anybody
more at ease with admitting that than MBZ,
just a remarkable person.
And for that reason, he is like treated as an oracle.
I don't think people understand the number of world leaders
who trapes through his house or palace to seek his counsel.
I'm not sure that there is parallel since,
I don't wanna get too hyperbolic here,
but honestly since like Solomon,
where people come from like around the world
to ask what he thinks.
Now, why would they be doing that?
Because Abu Dhabi's military is so powerful.
I mean, he's rich, okay?
Massive oil and gas deposits.
But like for a lot of, you know, so is Canada.
You know what I mean?
And no one is coming to Ottawa
to ask Justin Trudeau what he thinks.
No, it's humility.
That's where wisdom comes from.
You start to think like, I spent my whole life like mad
at America's leadership class, 'cause it's not just Biden
or the people in official positions,
it's the whole constellation of advisors
and throne sniffers around them.
And it's not that even that I disagree with them.
I'm not impressed by them.
I'm just not impressed.
They're not that capable, right?
So that's what I was saying about Nikki Haley.
I don't think Nikki Haley's
the most evil person in the world.
I think she's ridiculous, obviously.
And everyone's like, "Oh, Nikki Haley or Mike Pompeo," what?
- Great leaders are so rare that when you see one,
you know it right away.
- It blows your mind.
And what blows my mind about Sheikh Mohamed in Abu Dhabi
is that everyone in the world knows it.
And I've never seen a story on this.
And I'm not guessing, I know this is true
'cause I've seen it.
Everyone in the world knows it.
And so if there's a conflict,
he's the only person that people call.
Like everybody calls the same guy.
And it's like he runs this tiny little country, the UAE,
I mean, he's in Abu Dhabi.
There are a bunch of Emirates,
but he's the president of the country, but still.
And it's got a ton of energy
and all that wealth and all that.
And Dubai's got great real estate and restaurants,
but really it's a tiny little country
that wasn't even a country 50 years ago.
So, how did that happen?
Purely on the basis of his humility
and the wisdom that results from that humility.
That's it.
- What advice would you give to young people?
You got four, you somehow made them into great human beings.
What advice would you give to people in high school?
- Have children immediately including in high school, yes.
I think that, that's all that matters.
Like in the end, again, these aren't even cliches anymore
because no one says them.
But when I was a kid, people always say on your deathbed,
you never wish you spent more time at work.
And I mean, everyone said
that it was like one of these things.
And now I don't think Google allows you to say that.
It's like, no, you're gonna wish
you spent more time at work, get back to your cube.
But I can't overstate from my vantage how true that is.
Nothing else matters, but your family.
And if you have the opportunity,
and a lot of people are being denied
the opportunity to have children.
And this messing with the gender rules,
and I'm not even talking about the tranny stuff.
I mean, feminism has so destroyed people's brains
and the ability of young people to connect with each other
and stay together and have fruitful lives.
It's like nothing's been more destructive than that.
It's such a lie, it's so dumb.
It's counter to human nature.
And nothing counter to human nature can endure.
It can only cause suffering.
And that's what it's done.
But fight that, stop complaining about it.
Find someone, by the way, everyone gets together
or most people get together on the basis in a free,
in a Western society where there's no arranged marriages.
They get together on a basis of sexual attraction.
Totally natural.
Get off your birth control and have children.
Oh, I can't afford that.
Well, yeah, you'll figure out a way
to afford it once you have kids.
It's like it's chicken in the egg, but it's actually not.
When you have responsibility, when you have no choice.
This is true of men.
I'm not sure of true of women,
but it's definitely true of men.
You will not achieve until you have no choice.
As I always think of men,
men do nothing until they have to.
But once they have to, they will do anything.
That is true.
Men will do nothing unless they have to.
But once they have to, they will do anything.
I really believe that from watching and from being one.
And I would never have done anything if I didn't have to,
but I had to and I would just recommend it.
But by the way, even if you don't succeed,
and even if you're poor.
Having spent my life among rich people,
I grew up among rich people.
I am a rich person.
Boy, are they unhappy.
Well, that's clearly not the road to happiness.
You don't want to be a debt slave
or starved to death or anything like that.
But like making a billion dollars, that's not worth doing.
Don't do that.
Don't even try to do that.
If you create something that's beautiful and worth having
and you make a billion dollars, okay,
then you have to deal with your billion dollars,
which will be the worst part of your life, trust me.
But seeking money for its own sake is a dead end.
What you should seek for its own sake is children.
Talk about a creative act.
Last thing I'll say the whole point of life
is to create, okay?
The act of creation, which is like dying in the west,
in the arts and in its most pure expression,
which is children.
That's all that's worth doing while you're alive
is creating something beautiful.
And creating children, by the way, it's super fun.
It's not hard.
I can get more technical off the air if you want.
- [Lex] Yeah, please.
- I have a lot of thoughts on it.
- Do you have documents or something?
- (chuckles) No, I can draw you a schematic.
- [Lex] Oh, thank you.
- But yeah, that's the greatest thing.
And the fact that corporate America denies,
oh, freeze your eggs, have an abortion.
What? You're evil.
Are you kidding?
Because you're taking from people the only thing
that can possibly give them enduring joy.
And they are successfully taking it from people
and I hate them for it.
- You founded, TCN, Tucker Carlson Network.
- [Tucker] Yeah.
- [Lex] What's your vision for it?
- [Tucker] I have no vision for myself, for my career,
and I never have, so I'm like the last person to explain,
- Just roll with it.
- Yeah, I'm an instincts guy, a hundred percent.
I have a vision for the world,
but I don't have a vision for my life, for my career.
So really my vision extended precisely this far.
I just want to keep doing what I'm doing.
And there was a five hour period
where I wondered if I would be able to,
'cause I feel pretty spry and like alert
and I'm certainly deeply enjoying what I'm doing,
which is talking to people and saying what I think
and learning, constantly learning,
but I just wanted to keep doing that.
And I also wanted to employ the people
who I worked with at Fox.
I've worked with the same people for years and I love them.
And so, I had all these people
and I wanted to bring them with me.
So, we had to build a structure for that.
- But this feels like one of the first times
you're really working for yourself,
like there's an extra level of freedom here.
- Totally, totally.
And the good, I'm not, you don't want me doing your taxes.
Like I'm good at some things,
but I'm really not good at others.
And more of them would be like running a business,
like no idea.
I'm not interested, not a commerce guy,
so I don't buy anything.
So it's like the whole thing I'm not good at.
But luckily I'm really blessed to have friends
who are involved in this, who are good at that.
So I feel positive about it,
but mostly I'm totally committed to only doing the things
that I am good at and enjoy and not doing anything else,
'cause I don't wanna waste my time.
And so I'm just getting to do what I wanna do
and I'm really loving it.
- What hope, positive hope do you have for the future
of human civilization in say 50 years, 100 years, 200 years?
- People are great just by their nature.
I mean, they're super complicated, but I like people.
I always have liked people.
If I was sitting here with Nikki Haley,
who I guess I've been pretty clear,
I'm not like a mega fan of Nikki Haley's.
I would enjoy it.
I've never met anybody I couldn't enjoy
on some level given enough time.
So as long as nobody tampers with the human recipe,
the human nature itself, I will always feel blessed
by being around other people.
And that's true around the world.
Like, I've never been to a country.
And I've been to scores of countries
where I didn't given a week really like it.
And like the people.
So yeah, bad leaders are like a recurring theme
in human history.
Like, they're mostly bad.
And we've got an unusually bad set right now,
but we'll have better ones at some point.
I just don't wanna, I don't...
The one thing I don't like
more than nuclear weapons and more than AI,
the one thing that really, really bothers me
is the idea of using technology
to change the human brain permanently.
Because you're tampering with the secret sauce.
You're tampering with God's creation and totally evil.
I mean, I literally sat there the other day
with Klaus Schwab, I was with Klaus Schwab,
it was like a total moron.
I'm like a hundred years old
and like has no idea what's going on in the world.
But he's like one of these guys who, speaking of mediocre,
everyone's so afraid of Klaus Schwab.
I don't think Klaus Schwab is gonna be organizing anything.
Again, he's just like a total figurehead, like a douchebag.
But anyway, but he was talking
and he's reading all these talking points,
like all what the cool kids are talking about at Davos
and whatever, and he starts talking about it.
In his way and his accent, he was saying,
I think it's so important that we follow in an ethical way,
always in an ethical way, of course very ethical.
I'm a very ethical man.
That we follow using technology to improve your human mind
and implant the chips in the brain.
And I'm like, okay, you have no idea
what you're talking about.
You're like as senile as Joe Biden.
But what was so striking
is that no one in the room is like, Wait what?
You're fucking with people's brains.
(laughs) Like what are you even talking about?"
Who do you think you are?
- It's like, I mean, you're right, the secret sauce.
The human mind is really special.
Like, we should not mess with it.
It's all be very careful and whatever special thing it does,
it seems like it's a good thing.
Like human beings are fundamentally good
and like these sources of creativity,
a creative force in the universe we don't wanna mess with.
- Oh, I mean, what else matters?
I don't understand.
I mean, I guess look, I don't wanna seem
like the Unabomber and I'm not,
- We are in a cabin in the woods.
- No, well I'm sympathetic to some of his ideas,
but not of course sending mail bombs to people,
'cause I like people,
and I don't believe in violence at all.
But I think the problem with technology,
one of the problems with technology
is the way that people approach it
in a very kind of mindless, heedless way.
And I think it's important, this idea that it's inexorable
and we can't control it.
And if we don't do it, someone else will.
And there's some truth in that,
but it's not the whole story.
We do have free will
and we are creating these things intentionally.
And I think it's incumbent on us.
It's a requirement of a moral requirement of us
that we ask like, is this a net gain or a net loss?
To the extent we can foresee them,
will the effects be, et cetera, et cetera.
It's like, it's not super complicated.
So I just, I prize long-term thinking.
I don't always apply to my own life, obviously,
I want to, but I prize it.
And I think that people with power should think
about future generations.
And I don't see that kind of thinking at all.
They all seem like children to me.
And like, don't give children handguns
'cause they can hurt people.
- Yeah, fundamentally, you want people in power
to be pro humanity.
- By the way, you don't want people
who are 81 who are gonna die anyway.
Why do they care?
And by the way, if your track record
with your own family is miserable,
why would I give you my family to oversee?
I just don't.
Like, again, these are artistic level questions
that someone should answer.
- Well, thank you for asking those questions first of all,
and thank you for this conversation.
Thank you for welcoming me to the cabin in the woods.
- Thank you.
- Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Tucker Carlson.
To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now let me leave you
with some words from Mahatma Gandhi,
"When I despair, I remember that all through history,
the way of truth and love has always won.
There have been tyrants and murderers
and for a time they can seem invincible,
but in the end they always fall.
Think of it, always."
Thank you for listening,
and I hope to see you next time.